<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0034.001">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Rebecca v. Lloyd Pumphrey. Civil Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Bryant, Samantha M." xml:id="smb">Samantha M. Bryant</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0034.001</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0366</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Civil and Criminal in the United States Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, from 1801 to 1841</title>
<author n="Cranch, William, 1769-1855">William Cranch</author>
<publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume II</biblScope>
<date when="1852">1852</date>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Petition for Freedom</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1824-12">December 1824</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people"> 
<term xml:id="per.000003">Brent, William, 1774-1848</term>
<term>Morgan, Jacob</term>
<term xml:id="per.000064">Thruston, Buckner, 1763-1845</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Alexandria County (Va.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="outcome">
<term>Verdict for Plaintiff</term>
</keywords> 

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Ann</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Margaret</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Rebecca</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>William</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Pumphrey, Lloyd</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000640">
<persName>Turner, Thomas</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000496">
<persName>Coxe, Richard S. (Richard Smith), 1792-1865</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000830">
<persName>Marbury, John</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>             
<change when="2016-02-04" who="#kln">reviewed, edited</change>
<change when="2016-02-01" who="#smb">transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.report.0034.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption"> 

<p>Negro Rebecca and Children v. Lloyd Pumphrey</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus"> 

<p>Upon a petition for freedom, suggesting an apprehension that the defendant will sell and remove the petitioners from the jurisdiction of the Court, supported by affidavit, a judge of this Court, in vacation, will order an injunction without security; and upon further affidavit that the defendant had attempted to carry the petitioners away after notice of the filing of their petition, the judge will order the marshal to take them into his custody for safe keeping until the defendant shall give the security required by law for their forthcoming to prosecute their petition; and if the defendant shall refuse to give such security, and if judgment shall be rendered against him, the marshal's fees for keeping them shall be taxed in the bill of costs against the defendant.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
     
<p>Petition for freedom. The petition stated that the said Rebecca and her three children, William, Ann, and Margarett, are     

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.report.0034.001.jpg"/>

entitled to their freedom, but are held in slavery and bondage by a certain Lloyd Pumphrey; she therefore prays for a subpoena to him, commanding him to appear and answer the petition. "She also, having reason to apprehend a sale and removal immediately from the jurisdiction of your honorable Court, prays a writ of injunction, enjoining and forbidding the said Lloyd and his agents from removing her and her children as aforesaid; hoping such other relief as may be meet in the premises; thus ever prays. Thomas Turner, Solicitor for petitioners.</p> 

<p>"District of Columbia, Alexandria county, ss. On this 24th of November, 1824, personally appears before me, justice of peace in and for the county aforesaid, Thomas Turner, and makes oath on the holy evangels of Almighty God that he believes that Lloyd Pumphrey meditates the sale and removal from the district, of the within named petitioner and children, as stated in the petition. Sworn before me, Jacob Morgan. Let an injunction issue as prayed. B. Thruston. William Brent, Esq. clerk,&amp;c., &amp;c., 25th November, 1824."</p> 

<p>Afterwards, upon an affidavit that the defendant had attempted to carry the petitioners away, after notice of their having filed their petition for freedom, the judge, upon the urgency of the case, directed the marshal to take them into custody. The defendant refused to give the security required by law for the forthcoming of the petitioners to prosecute their petition, and they were kept in prison until the trial; viz. from November 26, 1824, to January 8th, 1825, forty-four days, at an expense of thirty-five cents a day for each, and one dollar each for commitment and release; making $63.84. Verdict for the petitioners.</p> 

<p>The Court, on the motion of Mr. Turner, ordered this expense to be taxed in the bill of costs against the defendant.</p> 

<p>Mr. Turner, for the petitioners.</p> 

<p>Mr. Marbury and Mr. R.S. Coxe, for the defendant.</p> 

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
