<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0341.008">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Rebecca v. Lloyd Pumphrey. Deed of Trust</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0341.008</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0366</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Deed of Trust</title>
<date when="1821-01-01">January 1, 1821</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<idno>Box 337, Folder 880</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Exhibit</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1824-12">December 1824</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Baker, John W.</term>
<term xml:id="per.000003">Brent, William, 1774-1848</term>
<term xml:id="per.000001">Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</term>
<term>Spalding, Bernard</term> <!--occupation Jusitce of the Peace-->
<term>Sparling, Thomas</term> <!--alternate spelling Spurling-->
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Washington County (D.C)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Ann</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Margaret</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Rebecca</persName> <!--alternate name Becky-->
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>William</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Pumphrey, Lloyd</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015-12-11" who="#snc">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>
           
<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0341.008.001.jpg"/>
                
<div1 type="case">

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Thomas Spurling<lb/>
to<lb/>
baker &#38; Pumphrey</p>

<p>Deed of Trust<lb/>
Recorded 5th March 1828</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Whereas I have this 1st day of January A.D 1821 passed my note to Misters Baker &#38; Pumphrey dated this day for the payment of one hundred dollars with interest on or before the 13th day of February A.D. 1828</p>

<p>Now this Indenture witness that in consider action of the paid sum of money so due as aforesaid &#38; to secure the payment thereof I Thomas Spurling do hereby assign and transfer unto the said Baker &#38; Pumphrey all my right and title to a certain negro woman called Becky about thirty years old and her three children William aged seven years Anne aged four years and Margaret aged one year- Which said negroes are to serve as follows Becky fifteen years and the children to the age of forty years respectively, &#38; any increase of Becky &#38; of the said female children during their terms of servitude to serve also till 40, &#38; so also as to the increase of such increase.-</p>

<p>To Have and To Hold the said negroes to them <del>the</del> as security for the payment of said note with power to sell the same for the terms above specified if the said note should not be paid when due &#38; to be returned and conveyed to me on my Exes. admrs. or assigns upon the payment of the said note.</p>

<p>Witness my hand and seal this first day of January A.D. 1821.</p>

<p>Signed, Sealed &#38; Delivered in presence of F. S. Key</p>

<p>Thomas Spurling   seal</p>

<p>It is hereby agreed that Baker and Pumphrey to whom the said woman &#38; children are delivered shall keep and maintain the same until the note within mentioned is due &#38; shall be paid therefor at the time when the said note is paid, at the note of two hundred dollars a year and if the

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0341.008.002.jpg"/>

said <del>note</del> Spurling shall be then willing to sell the said woman and children for the term herein specified, then the said Baker and Pumphrey engage to pay him the sum of one hundred and fifty dollars cash &#38; to give up the aforesaid note &#38; all claim for keeping and maintaining said negroes.</p>

<p>Witness our hands &#38; seals this 1st day of Jany A.D 1821.<lb/>
Thomas Spurling  seal<lb/>
John W. Baker    seal<lb/>
Lloyd Pumphrey   seal<lb/>
Witness F.S. Key</p>

<p>I do hereby assign over to Lloyd Pumphrey all my right title claim &#38; interest of the within negroes as mentioned.</p>

<p>Apl 21st 1821</p>

<p>John W. Baker</p>

<p>Whereas I did on the first day of January A.D. 1821 assign &#38; transfer unto Mister Baker and Pumphrey a certain negro woman called Becky and her three children, William, Anne and Margaret, upon the terms and conditions and for the negroes hereunto annexed, And whereas the said Baker afterwards assigned his interest in and to the same negroes unto the said Pumphrey as appears by an endorsement on the said assignment. And whereas I have this day borrowed of the said Lloyd Pumphrey the further sum of twenty one dollars which it is my desire to secure to him on the said negroes. Now this Indenture Witnesseth that <del>the</del> in consideration of the said sum of twenty one dollars paid to me by the said Lloyd Pumphrey and for the consideration expressed in the assignment hereunto annexed I Thomas Spurling do hereby assign and transfer the said negroes above mentioned and particularly described in the said assignment hereunto annexed unto the said Lloyd Pumphrey his executors, administrators,

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0341.008.003.jpg"/>

and assigns for the purpose expressed in the said assignment, and for the further purpose of securing the sum of money above expressed to have been this day advanced and I do notify and confirm in every respect the said Lloyd Pumphrey his exors" admors" and assigns for the trust and purposes aforesaid and in the said assignment declared.</p>

<p>In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand and seal this second day of March in the year 1822.</p>

<p>Signed, Sealed and delivered in the presence of Bernard Spalding</p>

<p>Thomas Spurling  T.S</p>

<p>District of Columbia, Washington County to wit,</p>

<p>On this second day of March in the year 1822 Thomas Spurling appeared personally before me the subscriber a Justice of the Peace for the County above named and acknowledged the above written Instrument of writing to be his act and deed.</p>

<p>Bernard Spalding</p>

<p>Copy Test</p>

<p>Wm Brent Clk</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0341.008.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Copy</p>

<p>Thomas Spurling<lb/>
To<lb/>
Baker &#38; Pumphrey</p>

<p>Deed of Trust</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>