<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.mdcase.0006.012">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Robert Thomas v. Henry Pile. Leonard Boarman's Answers to Defendant's Interrogatories</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.mdcase.0006.012</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0342</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Leonard Boarman's Answers to Defendant's Interrogatories</title>
<date when="1792-05-22">May 22, 1792</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Maryland State Archives</repository>
<collection>General Court of Western Shore (Judgments)</collection>
<idno>MSA S498-343</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Deposition</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1794-10">October 1794</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term xml:id="per.002077">Boarman, Leonard</term>
<term xml:id="per.001946">Briscoe, William D.</term>
<term xml:id="per.001964">Mingo, Betty</term>
<term xml:id="per.002055">Semple, John</term>
<term xml:id="per.002059">Stone, David</term>
<term xml:id="per.002062">Stone, John</term>
<term xml:id="per.002074">Wharton, Henry</term>
<term xml:id="per.002016">Thomas, Peg</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Charles County (Md.)</term>
<term>Saint Mary's County (Md.)</term>
<term>Port Tobacco (Md.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.001950">
<persName>Thomas, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.001943">
<persName>Pile, Henry</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.001393">
<persName>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.001495">
<persName>Key, Philip Barton, 1757-1815</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>Maryland. General Court of the Western Shore</orgName>
<placeName>Annapolis (Md.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>       
<change when="2015-12-23" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>     
<change when="2015-12-09" who="#lkw">added xml:ids; transcription</change>     
<change when="2015-06-11" who="#ea">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.012.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Petition for freedom in the Genl Court</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
     
<p>Interrogatories contained in a piece of paper signed Philip B. Key for defts, and proposed to Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>1st In: Did you know Betty commonly called (Mingo) who died in the possession of Mrs. Pile?</p>

<p>Answer I did know Betty commonly called (Mingo) who died in the possession of Mrs. Pile.</p>

<p>2d In: Did she formerly belong to Mr. Wharton who removed from Charles to St Mary's County and how long since, did she formerly belong to John Stone Father of David Stone of Charles County and sold or exchanged for another negro to said Wharton?</p>

<p>Answer She formerly belonged to Mr. Wharton who lived in St. Mary's County but do not know how long since neither do I know that she was belonged to John Stone Father of David Stone of Charles County or that she was sold or exchanged for another Negro to said Wharton.</p>

<p>3d In: In what year did Betty Mingo die and how old was she reputed to be when she died?</p>

<p>Answer I do not know what year she died in. She was upwards of Eighty years old.</p>

<p>4th In: did she have a number of Children, Grandchildren and great grand Children and among them a great number of men and women grown?</p>

<p>Answer I have heard that she left a number of Children Grand Children and Great Grand Children and I knew several of them myself that were grown up.</p>

<p>5th In: Do you know or have you heard that Betty Mingo had any Children while she belonged to John Stone and what were their Names?</p>

<p>Answer. I do not know neither have I heard that Betty Mingo had any Children while she belonged to John Stone.</p>

<p>6th In. Did you know Margaret commonly called Peg who died in the possession of John Sample?</p>

<p>Answer. I did not know her.</p>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.012.002.jpg"/>

<p>7th In: When Peg belonged to Semple was she his Cook and House Keeper, intrusted with the care of his House. A Woman who was acquainted with and conversed freely and boldly and was noted by most people of All Ranks who frequented Port Tobacco Town?</p>

<p>Answer I have heard that Semple had a Negro Woman named Peg and that she was the Daughter of Betty Mingo, and that the sd. Peg was Semples Cook. and intrusted with the Care of his House.</p>

<p>8th In: are you acquainted with the Characters of the Family of the petitioner and of those to whome she respectively belonged, if so, have you not heard that these Negroes were remarkable <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> for their <unclear reason="illegible">Intrepidity</unclear>, Independence and understanding, and that their owners were Industrious fed and Cloathed them well and made them work and gave them as much Liberty as usual?</p>

<p>Answer. I was Overlooker for Mrs. Pile's for 13 years who had several of the family of the petitioner and <del>that</del> during that Time the behaved and conducted themselves very well. they were made to work they were fed and Cloathed well and had as much Liberty as usual.</p>

<p>9th In: Have you ever Heard that the Petitioner or any of his family claimed freedom or that they were intitled to it, at what Time did you first hear <gap extent="one or two words" reason="strikethrough"/> such Conversation</p>

<p>Answer I have heard that some of the Family of the Petitioner Claimed their Freedom upwards of forty years ago and while I lived with Mrs. Pile Betty Mingo sold a Horse belonging to her, and gave a Hhd of Tobacco to a Lawer who visited at Mrs. Piles to plead for her Freedom.</p>

<p>10th In: Did you ever hear that this Family Claimed their freedom in any other Way than that set up?</p>

<p>Answer: I have never heard that this Family Claimed their Freedom in any other Way than that set up.</p>

<p>11th In: Has the Petitioner been held in slavery and reputed a Slave were his ancestors by the female side held in slavery and reputed to be slaves and for what length of time.</p>

<p>Answer. The Petitioner and his Ancestors by the female side has been Held in Slavery and 

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.012.003.jpg"/>

reputed to be Slaves ever since I knew them.</p>

<p>Charles County Set: May 22d 1792 I hereby Certify that the foregoing Interrogatories and answers thereto given on Oath have been attentively considered by the Deponant and he declares the said Answers to be just and true and these Answers to the <del>questions</del> Interrogatories to which the severally relate according to the best of his recollection and Belief which he further confirms by subscribing his Name thereto.<lb/>
Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>Sworn &amp; Subscribed Before<lb/>
Wm. D. Briscoe</p>

<p>Admitted to be read in Evidence<lb/>
G Duvall for petr.<lb/>
Philip B Key for Defdt.</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.012.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>7<hi rend="super">3</hi>&#8260;<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> sid</p>

<p>Interrogatories &amp; Deposition of Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>7<hi rend="super">3</hi>&#8260;<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> sid</p>

<p>Interrogatories &amp; Deposition of Leonard Boarman.</p>

<p>No. 4. Entered</p>

<p>7<hi rend="super">3</hi>&#8260;<hi rend="subscript">4</hi></p>

<p>Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>4.</p>

<p>7<hi rend="super">3</hi>&#8260;<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> sid</p>

<p>Thomas<lb/>
v<lb/>
Pile.</p>

<p>Depo. Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>filed 31. Octo 1794</p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
