<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0296.018">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Ellen Johnson v. Morris Adler. Defendant's Statement of Facts</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Stephanie N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0296.018</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0298</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Defendant's Statement of Facts</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 772, Folder 48</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Statement of Facts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1853-10">October 1853</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Johnson, John</term>
<term>Johnson, Phoebe</term>
<term>Johnson, Rachel</term>
<term>Turner, Thomas</term>
<term>Turner Jr., Thomas</term>
<term>Tyler, Trueman</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Virginia</term>
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
<term>Frederick (Md.)</term>
<term>Georgetown (Washington, D.C.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Johnson, Ellen</persName>
<persName>Johnson, John Thomas</persName>
<persName>Johnson, Louisa</persName>
<persName>Johnson, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Adler, Morris</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>             
<change when="2015-07-07" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>
<change when="2015-03-26" who="#snc">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0296.018.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Ellen Johnson<lb/>
v<lb/>
Morris Adler admr of Tho Turner Decd</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Thereupon the Defendant to support the issue on his part offered evidence to the Jury tending to prove &#8212; that the petitioner was a slave of Tho Turner Senr in his lifetime &amp; at the time of his death; that after his death the Petitioner came to the possession of Trueman Tyler one of the executives of the Estate of said Turner, &amp; was by him returned in the inventory of his Estate to the Orphans Court of Washington County in this District as the property said Turner; that the said Executor settled his first account of his said admr in the year 1817 (here insert it) &amp; in the year 1821 his second account (here insert it) leaving the petitioner <gap extent="one or two words" reason="illegible"/> of, &amp; still a part of the property of his said Testators Estate; that Testator left five children two sons &amp; three daughters who continued to occupy the dwelling of their deceased Father, the same being part of his real Estate &amp; lived together as one family until the removal of one of the sons to Virginia &amp; the marriage of one of the daughters. that the <del>said</del> Tho Turner Junr one of the said five children &amp; two of his sisters <del>continued</del> occupied the same dwelling &amp; lived together as one family

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0296.018.002.jpg"/>

up to the year 1840 when they removed to Frederick. That <del>in the year 1831</del> this Petitioner lived with them &amp; served in their family up to the year 1831. &amp; had in that year two twin female children respectively named Phebe &amp; Rachel &amp; in that year was at her own request permitted by the said Turner to leave his house &amp; service that &amp; to live with her husband a free negro man then living &amp; keeping house in Georgetown aforesaid, on condition that she would maintain herself &amp; children without charge to &amp; for the use of the said Estate:.</p> 

<p>That when the said Turner removed with his family to Frederick he took possession of the twin child Phebe &amp; after wards while so living in Frederick in the year 1842 to took possession of the other twin child called Rachel &amp; held them as slaves in his family in Frederick until the year 1848.</p>

<p>That the said Rachel about that time came to Georgetown with the permission of said Turner to visit her mother, &amp; while there the Petitioner applied, through the witness, to Mr Turner to permit said Rachel to prolong her <gap extent="one or two words" reason="strikethrough"/> visit, &amp; to hire herself there for the profit of the said Turner, alleging that the climate of Frederick was injurious to her health. that the said Petitioner while

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0296.018.003.jpg"/>

living with her said husband, when speaking of the said Turner recognized him as her Master &amp; about the year 1848 <del>&amp;</del> entered into, or proposed to enter into an agreement with him to purchase her self &amp; her children born after she had left his house &amp; while living with her husband &amp; was about to solicit money to pay for her self &amp; her said children</p>

<p>Whereupon the said <del>Petitioner</del> Deft by his counsel prayed the Court to instruct the Jury that &#8212; (here insert Defts <del>1st prayer</del> 1st 2d &amp; 3d prayer)</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0296.018.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>(2)</p>

<p>Defendants Statement of Ev</p>

<p>Ellen Johnson<lb/>
v<lb/>
Turner</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
