<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.mdcase.0006.043">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Robert Thomas v. Henry Pile. Cornelius Barber's Answers to Interrogatories</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.mdcase.0006.043</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0342</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Cornelius Barber's Answers to Interrogatories</title>
<date when="1794-05-10">May 10, 1794</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Maryland State Archives</repository>
<collection>General Court of Western Shore (Judgments)</collection>
<idno>MSA S498-343</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Interrogatories</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1794-10">October 1794</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term xml:id="per.002025">Barber, Cornelius</term>
<term xml:id="per.002036">Curtis, Mary</term>
<term xml:id="per.002090">Jamison, Thomas</term>
<term xml:id="per.002051">Mingo, Charles</term>
<term xml:id="per.002054">Pile, Elizabeth</term>
<term xml:id="per.002059">Stone, David</term>
<term xml:id="per.002062">Stone, Thomas</term>
<term xml:id="per.002063">Swann, James</term>
<term xml:id="per.002092">Thomas, William, Jr.</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Charles County (Md.)</term>
<term>Saint Mary's County (Md.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.001950">
<persName>Thomas, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.001943">
<persName>Pile, Henry</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>Maryland. General Court of the Western Shore</orgName>
<placeName>Annapolis (Md.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2016-01-19" who="#kln">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.043.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Petition for freedom in the General Court</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Cornelius Barber aged seventy nine years being duly sworn made the several answers <del>to</del> answered to the following interrogatories</p>

<p>1st do you know the petitioner in this suit &amp; how long &amp; did you know his Ancestors &amp; how long &amp; have they &amp; each of them always been held &amp; reputed as slaves.</p>

<p>Answer I know the petitioner in this suit &amp; have known him ever since he was a child. I have also known his Ancesters for a number of years &amp; they &amp; each of them have always been held &amp; reputed as slaves.</p>

<p>2d. Did you known or have you generally understood that Mary Curtis had a Mulatto Bastard &amp; who was the reputed father</p>

<p>Answer. I knew and have generally understood that Mary Curtis had a Mulatto Bastard &amp; that a Negro Man commonly called Charles belonging to a certain Thomas Jameson of Charles County was the reputed father.</p>

<p>3d. Was Charles Mingo the reputed Father of said Bastard a slave to whom &amp; was he the song of a Woman called Betty Mingo, or generally so reputed to be? or was he reputed to be of the same family with the petitioner?</p>

<p>Answer Negro Charles the reputed father of said Bastard was a slave to a certain Thomas Jameson of Charles County. I do not know neither did I ever understand he was the son or reputed to be the son of a Woman called Betty Mingo or that he was of the same family of the petitioner.</p>

<p>4th Was Mary Curtis sold as a Servant &amp; to whom for being the Mother of a Bastard Child. was the said Mary Curtis a Woman of good or bad general character &amp; reputation.</p>

<p>Answer Mary Curtis was sold as a Servant by St Mary's County Court to a certain James Swann of St Mary's County for bringing a Mulatto Bastard Child &amp; her general character &amp; reputation was bad.</p>

<p>5th Was Mary Curtis a Woman of general good or bad Moral Character, conduct in life, veracity &amp; Integrity, or was she a Lewd woman who connected herself with Negroes or Slaves.</p>

<p>Answer Mary Curtis was a Woman of general bad moral conduct in life she was a lewd woman who connected herself with Negros &amp; slaves - turn over</p>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.043.002.jpg"/>

<p>6th Where was Mrs Pile the Mother of the defendant Born. Where did she live at what time did she die &amp; what was her age.</p>

<p>Answer Mrs Pile the Mother of the Defendant was Born in St Mary's County <del>&amp; that</del> she lived there untill she Married Mr Pile &amp; <del>this de</del> died about <del>about</del> twelve or fifteen years ago <del>&amp; that</del> she was <del>aged</del> between sixty &amp; seventy years of age</p>

<p>7th Where did Mary Curtis reside. did she ever reside in Durham Parish in Charles County or was she acquainted with the Stone family of Durham Parish or their neighbours.</p>

<p>Answer Mary Curtis resided with a certain James Swann of St Mary's County when I first knew her I never heard or understood that she lived in Durham Parish or that she was acquainted with the Stone family of that Parish or their Neighbours.</p>

<p>8th Did Mrs Pile ever live in or was she acquainted with the People of Durham Parish in Charles County. did she know David Stone or his father Thomas Stone or their Neighbours.</p>

<p>Answer Mrs Pile did not that I ever knew or heard of live in Durham Parish in Charles County; neither did I ever know or hear that she <del>was</del> was acquainted with David Stone or his father Thomas Stone or their Neighbours.</p>

<p>Cornelius Barber</p>

<p>Saint Mary's County Set.</p>

<p>May 10th 1794</p>

<p>Personally appeared before me the subscriber one of the Justices of the Peace for the County aforesaid Cornelious Barber who upon Oath gave the several answers contained in the within Deposition to the Interrogatories there to annexed</p>

<p>Wm. Thomas Junr.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Cornelious Barber</p>

<p>8 sid</p>

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
Entered a<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Depo.</p>

<p>No. 28.</p>

<p>Cornelius Barber's Deposition</p>

<p>Filed 31 Oct. 1794</p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
