<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0228.007">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Winnie Cryer v. Elizabeth Cocke &amp; Peter Hoffman. Jury Instructions</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="McCormick, Kylie L." xml:id="klm">Kylie L. McCormick</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0228.007</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0233</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Jury Instructions</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note> 
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 728, Folder 162</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Jury Instructions</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1849-03">March 1849</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Alexandria County (Va.)</term>
<term>Alexandria (Va.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Cryer, Turner</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Cryer, Winnie</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Cocke, Elizabeth</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Hoffman, Peter E.</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>    
<change when="2015-01-12" who="#kln">reviewed, edited</change>         
<change when="2014-11" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0228.007.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>If from the whole evidence the Jury shall find that the Petitioner was the slave of the Defendant living in Alexandria (then in the District of Columbia) and <del>was</del> by the permission of the Defendant hired herself out in Alexandria and received her wages, and with the assent of her mistress employed those wages in the support of herself and her children, and afterwards with the consent of the Defendant through her agent P.E. Hoffman, and while Alexandria still formed a part of the said District came to the City of Washington and there hired herself out and received her wages to be applied to the support of herself &amp; children and went at large with the written assent of the said agent, and while so going at large in the said City of Washington by direction of the said agent sent one of her said children to the said agent from the City of Washington to Alexandria in the month of May 1844, and repeatedly visited the said child in Alexandria during the space of three years there next ensuing, and during all that period of time and up to a few days before to the bringing of this Petition, always to the said agent submitted herself as the slave of Defendant and never to him or to his knowledge, or to the said Defendant or to her knowledge set up or pretended that she the said Petitioner was free or had any title or claim to her freedom. it is competent for the Jury to find that the Petitioner never did receive manumission from the Defendant by deed or will.</p>

<p>granted</p>


<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0228.007.002.jpg"/>

<p>But if the Jury find further from the said evidence that the petitioner was the slave of the Defendant residing <del>with the</del> in and being an inhabitant of the town of Alexandria, in the District of Columbia, and was permitted by Defendant to go at large and hire herself and receive her own hire and to apply the same to the support of herself and children as the slaves of Defendant and afterwards by consent of Defendant came to the City of Washington to reside for the purpose of maintaining <del>the said</del> herself and said children <del>for the benefit</del> as the slaves of the Defendant, and for the use of the Defendant, then such removal into the City of Washington does not confer the right to freedom on the Petitioner, and the Defendant is within the provision of the <bibl type="code">9th section of the Act of 1812</bibl>, unless the Jury shall further find that the Defendant prior to the said removal of said Petitioner to said City of Washington, had removed from the said County of Alexandria with intent to reside elsewhere and to relinquish her residence in said County of Alexandria</p>

<p>granted.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>