<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.mdcase.0006.022">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Robert Thomas v. Henry Pile. Leonard Boarman's Answers to Interrogatories</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.mdcase.0006.022</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0342</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Leonard Boarman's Answers to Interrogatories</title>
<date when="1793-03-23">March 23, 1793</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Maryland State Archives</repository>
<collection>General Court of Western Shore (Judgments)</collection>
<idno>MSA S498-343</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Interrogatories</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Petition for Freedom</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1794-10">October 1794</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term xml:id="per.001946">Briscoe, William D.</term>
<term xml:id="per.002077">Boarman, Leonard</term>
<term xml:id="per.002078">Freeman, James</term>
<term xml:id="per.001964">Mingo, Betty</term>
<term xml:id="per.002051">Mingo, Charles</term>
<term xml:id="per.002054">Pile, Elizabeth</term>
<term xml:id="per.001982">Thomas, Elizabeth</term>
<term xml:id="per.001949">Thomas, Judy</term>
<term xml:id="per.002066">Thomas, Sophia</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Charles County (Md.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.001950">
<persName>Thomas, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.001943">
<persName>Pile, Henry</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.001393">
<persName>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.001495">
<persName>Key, Philip Barton, 1757-1815</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>Maryland. General Court of the Western Shore</orgName>
<placeName>Annapolis (Md.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2016-01-04" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>            
<change when="2015-12-10" who="#lkw">added xml:ids</change> 
<change when="2015-06-12" who="#ea">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.022.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Charles County ss:</p>

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Petition for freedom in the General Court</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Interrogatories proposed by the Petitioner to Leonard Boarman.</p>

<p>1st In: Do you know the parties the petitioner &amp; the Defendant in this Cause, and how long have you known them?</p>

<p>Answer. I knew the parties in this Cause and have known the petitioner ever since he was a Child and the Defendant for forty years</p>

<p>2d In: Do you know or have you heard and from whom, that the petitioner is descended from a free person and from what free person? was her name Elizabeth Thomas or what other name had she?</p>

<p>Answer. I have heard that the petitioner is descended from a white woman, and this I heard from Mrs Elizabeth Pile deceased but never heard that her name was Elizabeth Thomas or any other Name.</p>

<p>3d In: Do you know Judy the mother of the Petitioner, and how long have you known her?</p>

<p>Answer I know Judy the Mother of the Petitioner at present in the possession of the Defendant and have known her since she was a child.</p>

<p>4th In: Do you know Sophia the Grandmother of the petitioner at present in the possession of the Defendant Henry Pile and how long have you known <gap extent="one word" reason="strikethrough"/> her?</p>

<p>Answer I know Sophia the Grandmother of the petitioner at present in the possession of the Defendant Henry Pile and have known her for fifty years.</p>

<p>5th In: Did you know Elizabeth the Great Grandmother of the Petitioner, who died in the possession of Mrs. Elizabeth Pile the Defendant's Mother and when did you first know her, was she descended from a free woman that you know or have heard, and from whom did you hear that she was descended from a free woman?</p>

<p>Answer I knew Elizabeth the great Grandmother of the petitioner who died in the possession of Mrs. Elizabeth Pile the defendant's mother    

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.022.002.jpg"/>

Mother and I knew her first about forty years ago. I have heard Mrs. Elizabeth Pile deceased say that Elizabeth the Great Grandmother of the petitioner was descended from a white woman, but that she became a slave by marrying a Negro Slave.</p>

<p>6th In: Did you know Elizabeth Thomas the Mother of the aforesaid Elizabeth was she a free woman and a white woman, with whom did she live at the Time of her Death?</p>

<p>Answer. I did not know Elizabeth Thomas the mother of the aforesaid Elizabeth, neither do I know that she was a free or white woman or with whom she had lived.</p>

<p>Charles County ss: May 22d 1792 I hereby certify that the foregoing Interrogatories and Answers thereto given on Oath has been attentively considered by the Deponant, and he declares the said Answers to be Just and true and these Answers to the Interrogatories to which the severally relate according to the best of his recollection and Belief which he further Confirms by subscribing his name there to<lb/>
Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>Sworn &amp; Subscribed<lb/>
Before Wm D. Briscoe</p>

<p>Leonard Boarman being further asked if he had frequent conversations with Mrs. Pile relative to the Negro Family of Betty Mingos, answers that he had and she told him that they came from a white woman.</p>

<p>being further asked if Mrs Pile informed him how she derived her Information of their descent, and if from the Negroes themselves or their Council, or any person employed for them

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.022.003.jpg"/>

Answers, that he does not recollect that she ever told him from whom or how she obtained that Information. and does not recollect he ever asked her, and he thinks the reason was, that it was generally talked of in the Neighbourhood that they were a Free Family. He never heard any of the <del>Negroes</del> Mulatto's speak of it themselves. Being asked how long he transacted business for the late Mrs. Pile, answers upwards of thirteen years; being asked what was the complexion of the aforesaid Elizabeth, commonly called Betty Mingo the great grandmother of the petitioner, answers she was a middling bright mulatto with long hair, and he knew Charles a brother of the said Betty and he had long hair, but was not so bright a mulatto as his sister; that from the appearance of the aforesaid Betty, he used to think she came of a white woman; being asked if he ever heard that the father of Betty Mingo was a white man, answers he never did, and does not believe he was because he has heard he was not. Being asked if he recollects to have heard from any person besides Mrs. Pile that Betty Mingo was descended from a white woman, answers he does not recollect that he ever did. Being asked if he recollects to have heard Mrs. Piles say, what Negro, or whose negro the said Betty's mother intermarried with, answers, he is pretty sure he has heard her say, but he cannot now recollect whose <gap extent="one word" reason="strikethrough"/> Negro she said he was.</p>

<p>Charles County Set. March 23d 1793 I hereby Certify that the foregoing Interrogatories and answers thereto given on Oath have been attentively considered by Leonard Boarman the deponant and he declares the said answers to be Just and True Sworn before the subscriber one of the Justices of the Peace for County aforesaid</p>

<p>James Freeman</p>

<p>Admitted to be read in evidence<lb/>
G. Duvall for Petr.<lb/>
Philip B Key for deft.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="back">

<p>9&#189;</p>

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Depo.</p>

<p>Entered</p>

<p>Leonard Boarman's Deposition.</p>

<p>No. 14.</p>

<p>Filed 31 Oct. 1794</p>

<p>9&#189;</p>

<p>Leonard Boarman</p>

<p>14.</p>

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
agt<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Depo.<lb/>
L Boarman.</p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
