<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0024.001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Maria White v. Joseph M. White. Circuit Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0024.001</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0091</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Civil and Criminal in the United States Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, from 1801 to 1841</title>
<author n="Cranch, William, 1769-1855">William Cranch</author>
<publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume III</biblScope>
<date when="1852">1852</date>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>December 1829</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people"> 
<term>Cranch, William, 1769-1855</term>
<term>French</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Florida</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>White, Maria</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>White, Joseph M.</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName>Swann</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-06-02" who="ea">updated case number</change>
<change when="2015-04-16" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="report">

<pb xml:id="p663" facs="oscys.report.0024.001.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Negro Maria v. Joseph M. White.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus">

<p>A slave was brought into this county by her master, a delegate from the Territory of Florida, to wait upon his family while attending Congress; and, at the end of the session, not being in a condition to be carried back with safety, was left here until

<pb xml:id="p664" facs="oscys.report.0024.001.002.jpg"/> 

the meeting of the next Congress, with leave to hire herself out, and receive her
wages to her own use, which she did until the return of her master, who was reelected,
and who, at her request, offered to sell her to her husband, a free colored
man, residing in Washington, for $400, if he could raise the money, but he could
not, and never paid it, or any part of it.</p>

<p>The Court (nem. con.) refused to instruct the jury that these facts were not evidence of
an importation, contrary to the <bibl type="code">Maryland Act of 1796, c. 67</bibl>.</p>

<p>They also refused to instruct the jury, that, upon that evidence, they ought to find
their verdict for the defendant; but instructed them that the petitioner is not entitled
to freedom under the first section of the act, unless she was brought into this
county, by the defendant, for sale, or to reside therein; and that the circumstances
stated, although found by the jury, are not conclusive evidence that the petitioner
was brought into this county with such intent, or for sale; and that the residence
contemplated by the first section of the act is a permanent residence, as contradistinguished
from a sojournment.</p>

<p>The Court also refused to instruct the jury, that the defendant's offer and agreement
to sell the petitioner to her husband, under the circumstances stated, was evidence
of an importation, contrary to the <bibl type="code">Act of 1796, c. 67</bibl>, unless the jury should
believe, from the circumstances given in evidence, that the defendant had no intention,
at the time of importation, that she should be sold, or should reside in this
county.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The petitioner, negro Maria, claimed her freedom by reason
of importation, contrary to the <bibl type="code">Act of Maryland, 1796, c. 67</bibl>;
by the first section of which it is enacted, "that it shall not be
lawful to import or bring into this State, by land or water, any
negro, mulatto, or other slave, for sale, or to reside within this
State. And any person brought into this State as a slave, contrary
to this act, if a slave before, shall thereupon cease to be
the property of the person or persons so importing, &amp;c., and shall
be free."</p>

<p>By the fourth section it is provided, "that nothing in this act
contained shall be construed or taken to affect the right of any
person or persons travelling or sojourning with any slave or
slaves within this State, such slave or slaves not being sold, or
otherwise disposed of in this State, but carried out of this State,
or attempted to be carried."</p>

<p>Upon the trial, evidence was given to prove that the petitioner
was the slave cf the defendant, a resident of the Territory of Florida,
and the delegate in Congress from that Territory. That he
brought the slave to Washington to wait upon his family, while
he was attending Congress, in the winter of 1828 - 1829. That
she remained with his family during the session; but, at the
end of the session, on the 4th of March, 1829, was too far
advanced in pregnancy to be removed, with safety, to Florida;
and was, therefore, left by her master in Washington. That, at
her request, after her confinement, she was permitted by her
master, who was reelected, to hire herself out in Washington,
until he should return to Congress, in December, 1829; which
permission was given by a writing inclosed in a letter to Mr.
French, the agent of the defendant. That she accordingly hired</p>

<pb xml:id="p665" facs="oscys.report.0024.001.003.jpg"/>

<p>herself out, and received her wages to her own use. That the
defendant, learning that she had a free husband in Washington,
and that she wished to live with him, agreed that if he could
raise $400 for him he should have her. That the money was
never raised, nor any part of it ever paid to the defendant.</p>

<p>Upon this evidence, Mr. Key, for the petitioner, prayed the
Court to instruct the jury, that if, from the evidence, they found
the facts to be as above stated, then the continuing of the petitioner
in this county, under such circumstances, is evidence of
an importation contrary to the <bibl type="code">law of 1796, c. 67</bibl>.</p>

<p>But the Court (nem. con.) refused to give the instruction.</p>

<p>Whereupon Mr. Swann, for the defendant, prayed the Court
to instruct them, that upon these facts, if believed by them, they
ought to find their verdict for the defendant.</p>

<p>Which instruction the Court refused to give; but instructed
them that the petitioner is not entitled to freedom under the
first section of the <bibl type="code">Act of 1796, c. 67</bibl>, unless she was brought
into this county by the defendant for sale, or to reside therein;
that the circumstances aforesaid, although proved to the satisfaction
of the jury, are not conclusive evidence that the petitioner
was brought into this county with such intent, or for sale; and
that the residence contemplated in the first section of the act is
a permanent residence, as contradistinguished from a sojournment.</p>

<p>Mr. Key then prayed the Court to instruct the jury, that "if
they believed that the defendant contracted with the husband of
the petitioner, (a free man,) for the purchase of the petitioner, at
the price of $400, and that the said husband agreed to pay the
said sum of money, as the price of the petitioner; then such
contract is evidence of an importation contrary to the <bibl type="code">Act of
Assembly of 1796</bibl>. Unless the jury should, from the circumstances
given in evidence, believe that the defendant had no
intention, when he brought in the petitioner, of her being sold, or
residing in this county."</p>

<p>But the Court refused to give the said instruction. And
Cranch, C. J., suggested a doubt, whether a slave gained his
freedom, under the third section of the act, by being sold within
three years after being imported, if he was not originally imported
for sale, or to reside.</p>

<p>The cases cited in argument were, <bibl type="case">Baptiste et al. v. De Volunbrun,
5 Har. &amp; Johns. 86</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Defontaine v. Defontaine, in a note to
the former case, 5 Har. &amp; Johns. 86</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Henry v. Ball, 1 Wheat.
5</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Gardner v. Simpson, in this Court, at April term, 1823, not
reported</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Negro William Jordan v. Sawyer, in this Court, at the
same term, (2 Cranch, C. C. 373)</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Stewart v. Nokes, 5 Har. &amp; Johns. 107</bibl>.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>