<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0010.001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Joe Thompson v. Walter Clarke. Circuit Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0010.001</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0036</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Civil and Criminal in the United States Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, from 1801 to 1841</title>
<author n="Cranch, William, 1769-1855">William Cranch</author>
<publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume II</biblScope>
<date when="1852">1852</date>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1817-12">December 1817</date></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">  
<term xml:id="per.000289">Thompson, John</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">   
<term>Maryland</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="outcome">
<term>Verdict for Plaintiff</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<particDesc>   
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000284">
<persName>Thompson, Joe</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000285">
<persName>Thompson, Nelly</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000286">
<persName>Thompson, Sarah Anne</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.000287"> 
<persName>Clarke, Walter</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000001">
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000460">
<persName>Taney, Augustus</persName> <!-- Too early for it to be August Taney? Cound be Taney, Roger Brooke, 1777-1864, but I think he may have been in Baltimore by December 1817. -->
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000435">
<persName>Jones, Walter, 1776-1861</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-06-25" who="#ea">added case outcome</change>
<change when="2015-06-02" who="#ea">updated case number</change>
<change when="2015-04-13" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>  
   
<div1 type="report">

<pb xml:id="p145" facs="oscys.report.0010.001.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Negro Jo. Thompson v. Walter Clarke.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus">

<p>If a testator by his will manumits his slaves after a certain
term of service, and the widow renounces the provision made for her by the will
and adheres to her rights under the law of Maryland, and there is sufficient
personal estate to satisfy her thirds without resorting to the slaves, they will
be entitled to their freedom, although the executor should have assigned them to the
widow in part satisfaction of her claim.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
 
<p>This was a petition for freedom. John
Thompson by his
will dated December 31st, 1804, devised, that if
his wife should not have a child within nine months after his death, the
petitioner, his slave, should be free after ten years service. The widow
renounced the provision made for her by the will and adhered to her legal
rights; and the executor assigned to her the petitioner in part of her thirds,
there being other personal property enough to satisfy her claim without
resorting specifically to the slaves. Those assigned to her did not exceed her
proportion of the slaves.</p>

<p>By the <bibl type="code">Maryland act of 1798, c. 101, c. 13, § 16</bibl>, if the surplus, after
payment of debts, consists of specific property, and the administrator cannot
distribute it satisfactorily among the parties, the Orphans' Court may
distribute it, or order it to be sold.</p>

<p>By the <bibl type="code">Act of 1729, c. 24, § 2</bibl>, it is enacted that no negro, or other slave
shall be sold by an executor or administrator, or taken in execution for any
debt due from any testator or intestate, so long as there shall be other goods
sufficient, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Mr. Taney and Mr. Key, for the
petitioner, contended that the right of the widow was not absolutely to a third
part of the specific property; but only one third in value of the personal
estate.
 
<pb xml:id="p146" facs="oscys.report.0010.001.002.jpg"/>

That the surplus of the personal estate vests specifically in the executor on
whom the legal title and estate of the personal property devolves by law, and he
is answerable to the respective legatees. That if the slaves had been
specifically bequeathed, and there had been other property enough left to
satisfy the widow's thirds, the rights of the specific legatees would be
protected, and the executor could not assign to the widow any part of the
property thus specifically bequeathed. That the slaves must be considered as
specific legatees, and their rights protected by the same principle. They cited
<bibl type="code">Jacob's Law Dict. tit. Dower</bibl>, to show the distinction between dower and thirds,
and that the widow had no specific title to the property. And <bibl type="code">3 Bac. Ab. tit.
Executors and Administrators, p. 67</bibl>, to show that the assent of the executor was
necessary to complete the title to a legacy; and p. 426, to show that when a
specific legacy is taken in execution the legatee may recover the value.</p>

<p>Mr. Jones, contrà, contended
that the rights of the widow were paramount to the will. The testator, in his
lifetime, might dispose of all his personal estate, but he could not, in his
will deprive her of her thirds. She claims as a distributee. As to her, her
husband died intestate. Distributees have a right to the specific property which
is to be distributed; and it is to be distributed specifically if possible. They
cannot be compelled to take the risk of any loss which may be incurred by a
sale. The legatees have no right to have the effects marshalled to suit their
purposes. A general legatee cannot marshal against a devisee of land, but may
against the heir at law. <bibl type="case">Herne v. Meyrick, 1 P. Wms. 201</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Clifton
v. Burt, Id. 678</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Haslewood v.
Pope, 3 P. Wms. 324</bibl>. So a widow shall have the assets so
marshalled as to save her bona paraphernalia, or to
recompense her, in case they should be taken to pay debts. <bibl type="case">Tipping v. Tipping, 3 P. Wms.
729</bibl>. In that case Lord Chancellor Macclesfield said, "I take it that <term>bona paraphernalia</term> are not devisable by the husband from
the wife, any more than heir-looms from the heir; so that the fight of the wife
to the <term>bona paraphernalia</term> is to be preferred to that of
a legatee. If the husband, by his will, gives a lease, or a horse, or any
specific legacy, and leaves a debt by mortgage or bond in which the heir is
bound, the heir shall not compel the specific legatee to part with his legacy in
ease of the real estate; but though the creditor may subject this specific
legacy to his debt, yet the specific or any other legatee shall, in equity,
stand in the place of the bond creditor or mortgagee, and take as much, out of
the real assets, as such creditor by bond or mortgage shall have taken from his
specific or other legacy. Wherefore, if a legatee shall have this favor in
equity, much more shall the wife be privileged with respect to her

<pb xml:id="p147" facs="oscys.report.0010.001.003.jpg"/>

<term>bona paraphernalia</term> which are preferred to legacies." The
wife's thirds are as much privileged as her paraphernalia. They cannot be
devised away from her. She claims paramount to the will. In the case of <bibl type="case">Corbet v. Delves, 3 Atk. 369</bibl>,
Lord Chancellor Hardwicke said, "At law, where the husband dies indebted, the
widow cannot have her paraphernalia; but this court does not determine so
strictly, for if the personal estate has been exhausted in payment of specialty
creditors, she shall stand in their place, as to so much, upon the real assets
of their heir at law, for she has a prior right, and a superior one to legatees
who take only from the bounty of the testator." <bibl type="case">Graham v. Londonderry, 3 Atk. 395</bibl>; <bibl type="case">Tynt v. Tynt, 2 P. Wms. 544; Toler, 231</bibl>.</p>

<p>The Court (nem. con.) stopped Mr. Key in reply, and refused to instruct the jury that
the petitioner was not entitled to freedom under the will.</p>

<p>Verdict for the petitioner, and judgment. Although the title of several other of
the slaves depended upon the same will, no writ of error was issued. See the
case of <bibl type="case">Fenwick v. Chapman, 9 Pet. 461</bibl> accord.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>