<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.mdcase.0006.039">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Robert Thomas v. Henry Pile. William Swann's Answers to Interrogatories</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.mdcase.0006.039</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0342</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">William Swann's Answers to Interrogatories</title>
<date when="1794-09-30">September 30, 1794</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Maryland State Archives</repository>
<collection>General Court of Western Shore (Judgments)</collection>
<idno>MSA S498-343</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Interrogatories</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1794-10">October 1794</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term xml:id="per.002036">Curtis, Mary</term>
<term xml:id="per.002038">Dyson, Walter</term>
<term xml:id="per.001964">Mingo, Betty</term>
<term xml:id="per.002051">Mingo, Charles</term>
<term xml:id="per.002054">Pile, Elizabeth</term>
<term xml:id="per.002063">Swann, James</term>
<term xml:id="per.002064">Swann, William</term>
<term xml:id="per.001949">Thomas, Judy</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Charles County (Md.)</term>
<term>Saint Mary's County (Md.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.001950">
<persName>Thomas, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.001943">
<persName>Pile, Henry</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.001393">
<persName>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>Maryland. General Court of the Western Shore</orgName>
<placeName>Annapolis (Md.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>  
<change when="2016-01-11" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>       
<change when="2015-12-10" who="#lkw">added xml:ids</change>      
<change when="2015-06-11" who="#ea">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.039.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Petition for freedom in the General Court</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Petitioners Interrogatories to William Swann (on oath) aged sixty years viz., signed G. Duvall for Petitioner</p>
     
<p>1st. Do you know the parties to this Suit and how long have you known them?</p>

<p>Answer, I know Robert one of the parties to this Suit, and have known him for these four or five years past.</p>

<p>2nd Do you know the Mother of the petitioner, and how long have you known her?</p>

<p>Answer, I know the Mother of the petitioner, whose name is Judah and have known her about ten or twelve months.</p>

<p>3rd. Do you know the grand mother of the petitioner, and how long did you know her?</p>

<p>Answer, I have never known her until within these five days past.</p>

<p>4th Did you know Betty Mingoe a mulatto woman, who formerly lived with Mrs Pile mother of the Defendant, if yea, when &amp; how long did you know her; and did you know, or have you known, and from where, that Betty Mingoe was descended from a white woman or a free woman? relate your knowledge fully and truly.</p>

<p>Answer, I never knew Betty Mingoe, last I have hear from Mary Curtis when she lived with my father in the capacity of a white servant, that said Betty Mingoe was the Daughter of a white woman.</p>

<p>W Swann</p>

<p>Charles County Sst: October 15th 1794 personally appeared before me one of the Justices of the Peace for said County William Swann, and on oath gave the several answers annexd to the above Interrogatories</p>

<p>Walter Dyson</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.039.002.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Petition for freedom in the General Court</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>William Swann, aged sixty years, being duly sworn made the several answers annexed to the following Interrogatories</p>

<p>1t. Do you know the petitioner in this suit &amp; how long, and did you know his ancestors and how long &amp; have they &amp; each of them always been held and reputed as slaves?</p>

<p>Answer. I know the petitioner in this suit and have known him about four or five years, I also know his mother and have known her about the same length of time &amp; they &amp; each of them have always been held &amp; reputed as slaves.</p>

<p>2nd Did you know or have you generally understood that Mary Curtis had a Mulatto Bastard, and who was the reputed father?</p>

<p>Ansr. I have generally understood that Mary Curtis had a Mulatto Bastard, and that a certain mulatto man commonly called Charles Mingo was said to be the father of said Bastard.</p>

<p>3rd Was Charles Mingo the reputed father of said Bastard a slave, to whom, and was he the son of a woman called Betty Mingo, or generally so reputed to be? or was he reputed to be of the same family with the petitioner?</p>

<p>Ansr. Charles Mingo the reputed father of said Bastard was held as a slave by a certain Thomas Jameson of Charles County and I have always understood that he was Brother to the woman called Betty Mingo</p>

<p>4th. Was Mary Curtis sold as a Servant, and to whom, for being the Mother of a Bastard Child? was the said Mary Curtis of a good or bad general Character &amp; reputation?</p>

<p>Ansr. Mary Curtis was sold as a servant by St. Mary's County towit to a certain James Swann of St. Mary's County for bringing a Mulatto Bastard child, and that she served him faithfully; but she was reputed to be a lewd loose woman.</p>

<p>5th. Was Mary Curtis a woman of general good or bad moral character, conduct in life, veracity &amp; integrity, or was she a lewd woman who connected herself with negroes and slaves?</p>

<p>Ansr. Mary Curtis was a woman of general bad moral conduct in life &amp; connected herself with negroes and slaves.</p>

<p>Turn over.</p>

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.039.003.jpg"/>

<p>6th. When was Mrs Pile the mother of the defendant born, when did she live at what time did she die &amp; what was her age?</p>

<p>Ansr. Mrs Pile lived and died where the defendant now lives.</p>

<p>7th Where did Mary Curtis reside? did she ever reside in Durham Parish in Charles County; or was she acquainted with the Stone family of Durham Parish as their neighbour?</p>

<p>Ansr. Mary Curtis lived with a certain James Swann of St. Marys County she never lived in Durham Parish in Charles County as I know of or ever heard.</p>

<p>8th. Did Mrs Pile ever live in or was she acquainted with the people of Durham Parish in Charles County? Did she know David Stone or his father Thomas Stone or their Neighbours?</p>

<p>Ansr. Not as I know of</p>

<p>W Swan</p>

<p>Charles County Sst. Septr. 30th 1794.</p>

<p>Personally appeared before me the subscriber a Justice of the peace for said County William Swann and, on oath, gave the several answers to the within Interrogatories thereto annexed.</p>

<p>Walter Dyson</p>

<p>Charles County Sst. Septr. 30th 1794. I do hereby certify that both the petitioner and defendant were present when the within Interrogatories were put and the answers made thereto, and that the same was done between the hours of nine and five oClock agreeably to Mr. Pile's notice to the petitioners. In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand.</p>

<p>Walter Dyson</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.039.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>3</p>

<p>10 sid</p>

<p>William Swann's Interrogatories and Deposition</p>

<p>No 32.</p>

<p>Entered</p>

<p>Filed 31st. October 1794</p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
