<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0258.011">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Walter Thomas &amp; Dennis Thomas v. Alexander Scott. Affidavit of Edward Edmonston</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0258.011</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0260</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Affidavit of Edward Edmonston</title>
<date when="1810-06-26">June 26, 1810</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21, Entry 6</collection>
<idno>Box 20, Folder 217</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Affidavit</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1810-06">June 1810</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Edmonston, Edward</term>
<term>Lindsay, George W.</term>
<term>Rapine, Daniel</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Charles County (Md.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Thomas, Dennis</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Thomas, Walter</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Scott, Alexander</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000045">
<persName>Balch, Lewis P. W.</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>   
<change when="2015-04-27" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>           
<change when="2015-03-19" who="#ea">Encoded and transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0258.011.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>June 26th 1810</p>
     
<p>Some time in the course of January <del>and February</del> last Mr Alexander Scott came to me and informed me that two of his Negro men Walt &amp; Dennis were run away from him and that he was desirous of having them taken and brought home, that said negros had brought suit for their freedom which suits he had got Mr Balch Attorney for said negroes to have it struck off and that he was affraid that said negros would get some other Attorney to renew the suit again before he could get them taken therefore repeatedly pressed upon me to spare no pains to have them taken that he intended to send them to Charles County for he would rather they would bring such there than in the District that some of the same family had sued them before and could not obtain their Freedom</p>

<p>I one day came to Mr Lindsays Tavern and asking a black man if he knew whether Mr Scotts Dennis was about the premises he said that he was and that he was in the stable recovering some fodder into the stable loft, I then went into the stable loft and took the said negro Dennis and took him to the barn of Mr Lindsays Tavern where Mr Lindsay was he asked me what I was going to do with the negro I told him that Mr Scott

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0258.011.002.jpg"/>

had sent me for him he asked me if I had an order for him I told him that Mr Scott had given me an order some time before that and that I had tore it up or left it behind as I had come there before for the Negro and he had got alarmed and ranaway from Mr Lindsays therefore I neglected the order he then said that I should not take the negro away that the time he had hired the negro for had not expiered and that the fellow was as much his as he was Mr Scotts for the term he had hired him for but if I would bring an order from Mr Scott that he would at any time give up the negro</p>

<p>Edwd Edmonston</p>

<p>June 26th. 1810 appeared Edward Edmonston before the subscriber &amp; made oath in due form that the facts stated above are true to best of his knowledge</p>

<p>Danl Rapine</p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>