<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0001.003">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Ben v. Sabret Scott. Circuit Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0001.003</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0001</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Civil and Criminal in the United States Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, from 1801 to 1841</title>
<author n="Cranch, William, 1769-1855">William Cranch</author>
<publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume I</biblScope>
<date when="1852">1852</date>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1807-06">June 1807</date></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">  
<term>Barnes, John</term>
<term xml:id="per.000063">Fitzhugh, Nicholas</term> 
<term>Jameson, Richard</term> <!-- alt spelling: Jamieson -->
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">   
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="outcome">
<term>Verdict for Plaintiff</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<particDesc>   
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000002">
<persName>Ben</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.000005"> 
<persName>Scott, Sabret</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000001">
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000435">
<persName>Jones, Walter, 1776-1861</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000044">
<persName>Morsell, James Sewall</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-05-22" who="#ea">updated case number</change>
<change when="2015-04-07" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>  
   
<div1 type="report">

<pb xml:id="p407" facs="oscys.report.0001.003.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Negro Ben v. Sabrett Scott.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus">

<p>The general issue on a petition for freedom is that which puts in issue the simple question whether free or not.</p>

<p>Under the <bibl type="code">Maryland law of April, 1783, c. 23</bibl>, the slave imported does not gain his freedom by the omission of the master to prove, to the satisfaction of the naval officer or collector of taxes, that the slave had resided in one of the United States three years before importation.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
 
<p>Petition for freedom. The cause being called for trial, and 
no issue made up, Mr. Jones and Mr. Morsell, for the defendant, 
asked for time to put in a plea denying the facts in the petition, 
which were stated as the ground of the right to freedom. The 
petition contained also a general allegation that the defendant unjustly held the petitioner in slavery.</p> 

 <p>The Court said that they would receive the general issue only, 
unless the petitioner should agree to continue the cause.</p> 

 <p>The defendant's counsel contended that a denial of the special 
facts was a general issue.</p> 

<p>But the Court (Fitzhugh, J., absent,) said the general issue was 
that which put in issue the simple question whether free or not.</p> 

<p>Mr. Key, for the petitioner, moved the Court to instruct the 
jury, that they must be satisfied that the defendant made it appear to the satisfaction of the naval officer or collector of taxes, 
that the slave was a resident of one of the United States, agreeably to the <bibl type="code">Maryland Act of April, 1783, c. 23</bibl>, which prohibits the 
importation of slaves generally, but excepts those who should 
have resided three years in some of the United States; and provides that such residence shall be fully proved to the satisfaction 
of the naval officer, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Mr. Jones, for the defendant. It is sufficient if he proves the 
fact now, before the Court. If the defendant had satisfied the 
collector or naval officer, he might have been still called upon to 
prove the fact before this Court. The act is merely directory; it 
is no part of the proviso.</p> 

<p>Mr. Key , in reply. The legislature have expressly declared 
that the proof of the fact shall be made before a certain officer, 
and in a certain manner. They had probably reasons of policy 
which required it should be so done; and the manner of proof is 
equally essential with the substance.</p>

<p>The Court (Fitzhugh, J., absent,) directed the jury as prayed, 
but said it was a question of some doubt, and they would hear the 
point reargued on a motion for a new trial, if the verdict should 
be against the defendant.</p> 

<p>Mr. Jones, for the defendant, then offered a certificate, dated 
June 16, 1807, (four days ago, this being June 20, 1807,) signed 

<pb xml:id="p408" facs="oscys.report.0001.003.002.jpg"/>

by John Barnes, the United States collector and naval officer at 
the port of Georgetown; that the defendant had on that day 
proved to his satisfaction that the petitioner had been a resident 
three years, &amp;c.</p>

<p>Mr. Key, contended that the importation and oath must be concomitant with the coming in of the master. But if not, yet he 
ought to have done it during the existence of the law (the <bibl type="code">Act of 
1783</bibl>.) It is his own negligence if he did not. He had till 1796 
to do it.</p> 

<p>The Court (Fitzhugh, J., absent,) refused to admit the certificate in evidence.</p>

<p>The defendant then offered a like certificate signed by Richard 
Jamieson, collector of the tax for the county of Washington, 
dated June 12th, 1807, which was also rejected by the Court.</p> 

<p>Verdict for the petitioner.</p> 

<p>(Reversed in the Supreme Court. <bibl type="case">6 Cranch, 3</bibl>.)</p> 
 
</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>