<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0016.003">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Susan Bordley v. Anne Tilley. Affidavit of Richard Ponsonby</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Dick, Michael" xml:id="md">Michael Dick</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0016.003</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0016</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Affidavit of Richard Ponsonby</title>
<date when="1810-06-26">June 26, 1810</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21, Entry 6</collection>
<idno>Box 34, Folder 191</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Affidavit</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Petition for Freedom</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1811-06">June 1811</date></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">  
<term xml:id="per.000138">Bordley, Dinah</term>
<term xml:id="per.000139">Bordley, Fortune</term>
<term xml:id="per.000140">Bordley, Phillis</term>
<term xml:id="per.000141">Bordley, Toney</term>
<term xml:id="per.000142">Fenwick, Thomas</term>
<term xml:id="per.000143">McCubbin, James</term>
<term xml:id="per.000144">Miller, James</term>
<term xml:id="per.000145">Miller, Mrs.</term>
<term xml:id="per.000146">Ponsonby, Richard</term>
<term xml:id="per.000147">Pottinger, Mrs.</term>
<term xml:id="per.000102">Queen, Henry M.</term>
<term xml:id="per.000148">Tilley, Molley</term>
<term xml:id="per.000149">Williams, Thomas Owen</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Queen Anne's County (Md.)</term>
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
<term>Bladensburg (Md.)</term>
<term>Glasgow (Scotland)</term>
<term>Philadelphia (Pa.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<particDesc>   
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000132">
<persName>Bordley, Charlotte</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000133">
<persName>Bordley, James</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000134">
<persName>Bordley, Phillis</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000135">
<persName>Bordley, Rachel</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000136">
<persName>Bordley, Susan</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.000137">
<persName>Tilley, Anne</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000023">
<persName>Law, John</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000001">
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
  
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015-11-19" who="#snc">added idno</change>
<change when="2014-10-03" who="#kln">edited document title in TEI header</change>
<change when="2014-07-24" who="#lkw">added xml:ids; removed Anne Tilley from people terms</change>
<change when="2014-06-16" who="#kln">converted to new TEI</change>
<change when="2014-05-30" who="#wgt">reviewed; corrected transcription</change>
<change when="2013-04-30" who="#kln">added attorneys to header</change>
<change when="2013-04-22" who="#kln">reviewed and edited</change>
<change when="2013-04-19" who="#md">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>
   
<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0016.003.001.jpg"/>

<div1 type="case">

<div2 type="body">

<p>26th June 1810.</p>

<p>I do hereby certify, that I have known Susan the Petitioner
at least 36 years, during the whole of which time she has been in the
Neighbourhood of Bladensburgh, except the last twelve or
fifteen months she has lived in the City of Washington. I
have reason to believe and do firmly believe, that the Petitioner Susan
Boadley, her Parents and sister Dinah were
brought from Pennsylvania to
Maryland near 40 years ago, the property of Mr.
James Miller who bought them (as he informed me) in
Philadelphia. The first of my having any knowledge of
Susan was in the year '72 or '73
when she probably might have been about eight or nine years of age, and she then
waited on her Mistress Mrs. Miller in
Bladensburgh, and I often heard Mrs.
Miller call her, her favourite girl
Susan because (as Mrs. Miller
said) she was so remarkably black and smart. and Susan was
usually sent by her Mistress to tell Mr. Miller and the
young Gentlemen in his store to come to dinner. Shortly after Mrs.
Miller's death which happen'd some time in the year '74
or perhaps early in '75, Susan and the rest of Mr.
Miller's people he had in
Bladensburgh were remov'd to his Plantation about
four miles from Bladensburgh, where
Susan's father named Fortune, her
Mother named Phillis, her sister named
Dinah and her brother named Toney
then were. Susan remain'd at the Plantation some years;
afterwards, perhaps about the year '78 or'79 Mr. Miller
hired her to Miss Molley Tilley near
Bladensburgh where she continued several years. After
Susan left Miss Molley Tilley, she
liv'd near Bladenburgh 'till the last twelve or fifteen
months or thereabout, she has been hired in the City of
Washington.</p>

<p>Rd Ponsonby</p>

<p>Washington County, District of Columbia - to wit - On this
   26th day of June 1810, Came Richard Ponsonby before 
   me the subscriber one of the Justices of the Peace for 'said County, and made Oath on the Holy Evangely 
   of Almighty God, that the above Certificate contains a true and faithful relation and statement 
   of facts relative to his knowledge of Negro Woman Susan who calls herself 
   Susan Boadly and has petitioned the said Washington County 
   Court for her freedom. She is the property of Mrs. Ann Tilley. Sworn before, and 
   Certified by Thos Fenwick</p>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0016.003.002.jpg"/>

<p>Did you know or even hear of Captn James McCubbin. Answer -
Have heard of him but never knew him - nor what occupation he follow'd.</p>

<p>Did you ever hear where the Petitioner Susan, and her father 
&amp; mother were landed <del>here</del> when they arrived here. Answer - I was informed that they were 
landed at Queen-Ann, and then carried to Mrs. Pottinger's, where they remain'd until Mr. Miller married the daughter of Mrs. Pottinger late in the year 1771. And shortly after Mr. Miller's marriage, I was 
credibly inform'd, that they were brough to Mr. Millers farm near 
Bladenburgh, to wit Susan's father named 
Fortune, her mother named Phillis and her sister 
Dinah. Susan was kept in Bladensburgh 
to wait upon her Mistress where she remain'd until the death of Mrs. Miller 
in 1774, or 1775. After her Mistress' death she was remov'd from Bladenburgh 
to her Masters farm.</p>

<p>Had they any foreign dialect in their speech. Answer - Old Fortune and Phillis had a foreign dialect, but the Children had not. I know that Phillis had three children - 
Susan the Petitioner, Dinah who died a slave, 
and Toney <del>who</del> who belongs to Major Thomas Owen Williams, 
and is a slave. Toney, I have reason to believe, was about three or 
four years of age when he was brought here. Is Mr. Miller now living. Answer he is now living at Glasgow in Scotland, 
or was living when heard from lately, and left this Country in the year 1787. since when 
they have been the <del>sla</del> property and in the possession of Mrs. Ann Tilley 
Mr. Miller's daughter.</p>

<p>My knowledge of Susan the 
petitioner happen'd in this way. I was long and intimately acquainted with her Master Mr. Miller 
and frequently at his house when he liv'd in Bladenburgh. There I 
often saw Susan and noticed her Mistress, Mrs. Miller 
to be very fond of her. When Susan was at her Master's Plantation 
I frequently saw her there. and whilst she liv'd with Miss Molley Tilley, 
and since she left Miss Molly Tilley I often saw her and spoke to her. 
In short I have known Susan ever since the year '72 or '73. a period 
of about 37 years, during which time, to my certain knowledge, she has liv'd in this neighbourhood. 
When I first knew Susan, to wit in the year '72 or '73 she appear'd to 
be about 8 or 9 years of age. she now may be about 45 or 46 years old. perhaps something 
older or something younger.</p>

<p>Rd Ponsonby<lb/>
City of Washington, 30th June 1810</p>
   
<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0016.003.003.jpg"/>

<p>Washington County, District of Columbia - to wit - 
on the 30th day of June 1810, came Richard Ponsonby 
before me the subscriber one of the Justices of the Peace in and for said County, and 
made Oath on Holy Evangely of Almighty God, the aforegoing Certificate and answers to Interogy are 
Just and true to the best of his knowledge and belief.</p>
   
<p>Sworn before, &amp; certified by Henry M. Queen</p>

<p>Admitted so far as competent testimony.<lb/>
F S Key for Deft.<lb/>
John Law Atty for Plff</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0016.003.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Certificate and Affidavit of Richard Ponsonby relative to Negro woman Susan belonging to Mrs. Ann Tilley.</p>

<p>26th June 1810.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>