<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0028.003">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sally Henry v. Henry W. Ball. Deposition of Elizabeth K. Rankin</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0028.003</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0028</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Deposition of Elizabeth K. Rankin</title>
<date when="1814-06-06">June 6, 1814</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<idno>Record Group 21.6</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>


<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Deposition</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1814-06">June 1814</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people"> 
<term xml:id="per.000233">Rankin, Elizabeth K.</term>                  
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Fairfax County (Va.)</term>
<term>Northumberland County (Va.)</term>
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000231">
<persName>Henry, Sally</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.000232">
<persName>Ball, Henry W.</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.000001">
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.000023">
<persName>Law, John</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-08-08" who="#lkw">added xml:ids; deleted "Rankin" from people, but left "Elizabeth Rankin"; validated</change>
<change when="2014-06-05" who="#wgt">reviewed; corrected transcription</change>
<change when="2014-06-05" who="#kln">converted to new TEI</change>
<change when="2013-04-30" who="#kln">added attorneys to header</change>
<change when="2013-03-06" who="#kln">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>
           
<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0028.003.001.jpg"/>
                
<div1 type="case">

<div2 type="caption">
                
<p>Washington county district of Columbia set</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
                 
<p>On this 3rd day of June <del>before in</del> the subscriber a justice of the peace for the county &amp; districts aforesaid personally appeared Elizabeth K Rankin &amp; being sworn in due form of law deposed &amp; said</p>
                
<p>That a negro girl named Sally then quite a child was a short time before the month of May 1810 <unclear reason="illegible">sent</unclear> to live as a matter of favour with the deponent <unclear reason="illegible">then</unclear> <del>residing in</del> on a visit to Virginia where the deponent lived on said visit for two years with her mother <del>safe but they</del> by Mr Henry W Ball, who also resided at that time in Fairfax County Virginia when the said negro girl was about 9 miles from Washington. That in consideration of the services of the girl this deponent was to furnish the girl with victuals &amp; cloaths; &amp; that this deponent was to keep the girl for a year, but no particular bargain was made between Mr Ball &amp; the deponent about the girl; That some time in the month of May in the year 1810, this deponent removed to the city of Washington from Virginia &amp; brought the said girl Sally with her; Mr Henry Ball being as this deponent thinks in Northumberland county in Virginia at the time of this deponent's removal to Washington.</p>
                
<p>Quest. Did you ever ask or obtain permission of Mr Ball to remove Sally to Washington? Ans: I cannot recollect, but Mr Ball was frequently in the habit of coming to our house, &amp; probably heard of our intention to remove to Washington. But <del>she</del> I do not know whether he <del>gave</del> was ever asked or gave permission for that removal of Sally. At the time of our removal Mr Ball was to the best of my recollection in Northumberland county Virginia, &amp; had gone there some time before our removal.</p>
                
<p>Quest. Did you not after your removal to Washington frequently pass backwards &amp; forwards to &amp; from Virginia, &amp; generally carry Sally with you. Ans: I did in several instances pass <del>back</del> to &amp; from Virginia to Washington, &amp; generally carried Sally with me. &amp; on these visits to Virginia, sometimes stayed a week or ten days. Sally once ran away from me while <del>there</del> here. &amp; went over to Virginia where the deponent sent after her.</p>
                
<p>Quest. How long did Sally remain with you in Washington, &amp; who took her away. Ans: Sally remained with me until after Mr Ball
                
<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0028.003.002.jpg"/>
                
married which was in October 1810 (having remained with me seven or eight months <del>when</del> short time after his marriage Mr Ball took her away &amp; carried her to Virginia, the Deponent conceiving herself bound to give her up to Mr Ball whenever he called for her.</p>
                
<p>Questions on the part of the Petitioner.</p>
                
<p>1st Did or Did not Mr Henry Ball to the best of your knowledge and belief know of your intention to return to the City of Washington &amp; to bring Sally with you? Answers she cannot say possitively but she rather imagines he did.</p>
                
<p>2. Did or Did not Mr Ball shortly after you had brought Sally to the City see you &amp; her there? And did he make any objection to her having been brought here or remaining here? Answers he did &amp; made no objection.</p>
                
<p>3. How far did Mr Ball live from your mother's in Virginia? Answers a mile or two.</p>
                
<p>4. Did you or did you not know of Mr <del>W</del> H. W. Ball's ever residing in <del>Vir</del> Washington till after his marriage? Answers <del>she</del> He did not reside here till after his marriage — though he was frequently here.</p>
                
<p>5. When <del>did</del> was your Husband during the period of your aforesaid stay in Fairfax?</p>
                
<p>Answer This Deponent's husband was an Officer in the Marine Corps stationed in Washington where he was the greater portion of his time &amp; which he only left on obtaining leaves of absence, keeping no house in Washington but living when in Washington in the marine barracks, nearly all his clothes being in Virginia &amp; he contributing to the expences of the family in Fairfax, &amp; visiting in Fairfax sometimes every week sometimes not so often &amp; sometimes staying 6 or 6 weeks together. <del>Before</del> Until the period of the visit the Deponent &amp; Mr Rankin had lived in Washington.</p>
                
<p>This Deponent always contemplated returning to Washington but did not suppose it would take place till late in the year, but Mr Rankin having obtained an appointment, they were induced to return earlier.</p>
                
<p>This Depn is agreed to be read in Evidence as far as admissible. in the case Sally vs Ball.</p>
                
<p>F S Key for Petnr</p>
                
<p>J Law for deft</p>

</div2>
                
<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0028.003.003.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">
                
<p>Filed 6 June 1814</p>
                
</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>