<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0212.006">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Thomas Butler v. Gabriel Duvall. Replication &amp; Demurrer</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0212.006</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0217</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Replication &amp; Demurrer</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note> 
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 454, Folder 80</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Demurrer</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1831-05">May 1831</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Prince George's County (Md.)</term>
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Airy</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Eliza</persName> 
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Liddy</persName> 
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Matilda</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Reason</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Sally</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Sarah</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Thomas</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName>Beale, Robert</persName>
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>   
<change when="2014-12-02" who="#kln">reviewed, edited</change>             
<change when="2014-11" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0212.006.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Thos. Butler &amp; wife &amp; others<lb/>
vs<lb/>
Gabriel Duvall</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>And the said Petitioners by Robert Beall their attorney say<del>ith</del> that this Circuit Court here of the District of Columbia in Washington County <gap extent="one or two words" reason="torn page"/> from taking cognizance of the <gap extent="one or two words" reason="torn page"/> aforesaid by any thing in the plea of the said <gap extent="one or two words" reason="torn page"/> ought not because (protesting that during all the time &amp; times in the said plea mentioned the said Petitioners did not nor did either of them reside in Prince Georges County in the State of Maryland under the direction of said <del>Gabriel</del> Deft. <del>he</del> then &amp; during all the time &amp; times aforesaid being the master &amp; owner of said Petitioners as set forth in said plea by said Deft.) by way of replication to said plea they say that before and at the times of filing their said petition, the said Petitioners &amp; each &amp; every of them were here present residing within the jurisdiction of this Court in their own proper persons in Washington County aforesaid <hi rend="super">X</hi> <del>and were not residents with the said Defendant in Prince George's County Maryland and this they are ready to verify</del></p>

<p>Wherefore they pray judgt. <del>of the said plea</del> &amp; that the said Deft. may <unclear reason="illegible">answer</unclear> over &amp;ca</p>

<p>Beall &amp; Key for Petrs.</p>

<p><hi rend="super">X</hi> without this that at the time &amp; times aforesaid the said Petitioners or any of them did &amp; do reside in the said County of Prince Georges &amp; state aforesaid under the direction of the said Gabriel then &amp; during the time &amp; times aforesaid being the master and owner of the said petitioners &amp; each &amp; every of them as alleged in said plea. <del>Demr.</del> <del>&amp; this he is ready to testify</del> &amp; of this they <gap extent="about six words" reason="illegible"/></p>

<p>(Enter the Demr. in the usual form)</p>

<p>And for causes of demurrer in this behalf the said</p>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0212.006.002.jpg"/>

<p>said Gabriel Duval, in his proper person, sets down the causes following, towit: </p>

<p>1st. Because the sd Petitioners, in their said replication, have not <del>traversed in</del> in any manner traversed, denoted, or admitted (save &amp; except a denial by way of protestation which is inadmissible) the fact that the petitioners at the time &amp; times of the filing of the said petition, and of the commencement of the same, did reside, and always before &amp; ever since have resided, and yet do reside in the County of Prince Georges aforesaid, under the direction of the said Gabriel Duval as their master &amp; owner, and not in the County of Washington aforesaid, or elsewhere in the District of Columbia aforesaid.</p>

<p>2. Because the said Petitioners, in their said <del>petition</del> replication, have put forward a denial of a material averment in the plea of the said Gabriel Duval (namely the residence of the Petitioners) by way of protestation, and not by any direct denial or traverse, either general or special.</p>

<p>3. Because the only fact pleaded by the Petitioners in their said replication, and therein offered or pretended to be verified &amp; put in issue, is not, ether in terms or by necessary implication, a denial or traverse of the matter above pleased by the said Gabriel Duval; nor any sufficient confession &amp; avoidance of the same.</p>

<p>4. Because the said fact so pleased by the Petitioners in their said replication, if put forth as a traverse or <gap extent="one or two words" reason="illegible"/> of the matter so pleaded by the said Gabriel Duval as aforesaid, is merely an argumentative &amp; not a direct denial or traverse.</p>

<p><del>5. Because, if the said fact so pleaded by the Petitioners he put fort as a traverse or denial either direct or argumentative of the matter so pleaded by the sd Gabriel Duval, and not as new matter pleaded by way of <unclear reason="illegible">avoidance</unclear>, the said replication ought to have <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> to the country &amp; not with a verification.</del></p>

<p>6. Because the said replication of the Petitioners, <unclear reason="illegible">with</unclear> the matter therein pleaded, is altogether insufficient, <gap extent="one word"/> and wants form.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Thos Butler &amp; wife &amp; others<lb/>
vs<lb/>
G. Duvall.</p>

<p>Repn. &amp; demr.</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0212.006.003.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>5. Because the <unclear reason="illegible">issue</unclear> taken by the said replication is immaterial in as much as the substantial objection to the jurisdiction of the Court is not merely that the said Petitioners did <del>not</del> reside in the said County of Prince George's under the direction of the said Gabriel but also that they did not reside in the said County of Washington or elsewhere in the District of Columbia under the direction of the said Gabriel at the time of filing their said petition.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>