<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0147.008">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>James Ash v. William H. Williams. Will of Maria Anne T. Greenfield</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0147.008</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0149</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Will of Maria Anne T. Greenfield</title>
<date when="1824-09-16">September 16, 1824</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 617, Folder 25</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Exhibit</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>March 1840</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Alfred</term>
<term>Bell, Ann</term>
<term>Ben</term>
<term>Betty</term>
<term>Billy</term>
<term>Chew, Philimon</term>
<term>Chrissy</term>
<term>Clarke, Ann</term>
<term>Dorsett, Amelia I.</term>
<term>Dorsett, William</term>
<term>Dyre, Edward</term>
<term>Eliza</term>
<term>Elizabeth</term>
<term>George</term>
<term>Greenfield, Gerard T.</term>
<term>Greenfield, Maria Anne T.</term>
<term>Greenfield, Sabrina T.</term>
<term>Greenfield, Walter</term>
<term>Grimes, John</term>
<term>Henry</term>
<term>Hollyday, Clement</term>
<term>James</term>
<term>Kitty</term>
<term>Lewis</term>
<term>Mansa</term>
<term>Maria</term>
<term>May</term>
<term>Nathaniel</term>
<term>Ned</term>
<term>Rebecca</term>
<term>Sophia</term>
<term>Swaine, Ann</term>
<term>Toney</term>
<term>Tyler, Trueman</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places"> 
<term>Prince George's County (Md.)</term>
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Ash, James</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Williams, William H.</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-01-08" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>            
<change when="2014-10" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0147.008.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>In the name of God Amen I, Maria Anne T. Greenfield of Prince Georges County in the State of Maryland being sick and weak in body but of sound and disposing mind memory and understanding do make and publish this my last will and testament in manner and form following that is to say</p>

<p><unclear reason="illegible">Tesit</unclear> and principally I commit my should into the hands of Almighty God and my body to the earth to be decently buried at the discretion of my executor hereinafter named. And after my debts &amp; funeral charges are paid I give and bequeath as follows.</p>

<p>Item I give and bequeath to my niece Amelia T <unclear reason="illegible">Dorsett</unclear> the sum of seventy dollars to be paid to her by my executor hereafter named.</p>

<p>I give and bequeath to my overseer John Grimes one hundred and forty dollars to be paid to him by my executor hereafter named.</p>

<p>Item I give &amp; bequeath to my nephew Gerrard T Greenfield my negro slave Ned to serve him eight years then to have his freedom during his life.</p>

<p>I give &amp; bequeath to my nephew Gerard T. Greenfield Marias three children namely James, Alfred, and Eliza to serve him until they arrive at the age of thirty eight years old. then to be free from servitude during life.</p>

<p>I give and bequeath to my Nephew Gerard T. Greenfield my negro slave Chrissy to serve him untill she arrives to the age of sixteen years old then to be free from servitude during life.</p>

<p>I also give and bequeath to my nephew Gerard T. Greenfield the whole of my part of my sister Sabrina I Greenfield decd Estate that may belong to me when a decision of the said estate may take place</p>

<p>(a) [I also give and bequeath to my nephew Gerard
 
<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0147.008.002.jpg"/>

I Greenfield all my negro slaves namely Ben, Mansa, James, Henry, George, Lewis, Rebecca, Kitty, Sophia, May, Elizabeth, Nathaniel, and Maria also Toney, Billy Betty, and Anne. Provided he shall not carry them out of the state of Maryland, or sell them to any one in either of which events I will and desire the said negroes to be free for life.]</p>

<p>I give and bequeath to my nephew Gerard T Greenfield the residue of my estate not heretofore bequeathed in this will.</p>

<p>I hereby constitute and appoint my nephew Gerard T. Greenfield sole executor of this my last Will and Testament revoking all other wills by me heretofore made and ratifying and confirming this to be my last will as testament. In Testimony Whereof I have hereunto set my hand &amp; affixed my seal this sixteenth day of September in the year of Our Lord. Eighteen hundred and twenty four</p>

<p>Maria Anna T Greenfield (seal)</p>

<p>Signed sealed published and declared by Maria Anna T Greenfield as and for her last Will and Testament in presence of us who at her request &amp; in her presence &amp; in the presence of each other have subscribed our names as witnesses thereto.</p>

<p>Clement Hollyday. Ann Swaine</p>

<p>Prince Georges County towit October 19 1824</p>

<p>Then came Clement Hollyday one of the subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing will and made oath on the Holy Evangely of Almighty God that he did see Maria Anna T Greenfield the testatrix therein named sign &amp; seal this will and heard her

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0147.008.003.jpg"/>

publish pronounce and declare the same to be her last will and testament. That at the time of her so doing she was to the best of his apprehension of sound and disposing mind memory and understanding and that he together with Ann Swaine the other subscribing witness respectively subscribed their names as witnesses to this will in the presence of the testatrix at her request and in the presence of each other</p>

<p>Sworn before Trueman Tyler Regr Wills for Pr Geo Cty</p>

<p>Maryland Prince Georges County Set</p>

<p>I Philimon Chew Register of Wills do hereby certify that the foregoing is a true copy of the last will and Testament of Maria Anna T Greenfield duly proven filed &amp; recorded in my office.</p>

<p>In Testimony whereof I have hereunto subscribed my name &amp; affixed the seal of the Orphans Court of Prince Georges County this 29th Octo 1838.</p>

<p>Phil Chew Regr Wills PGCty</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0147.008.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Negro Ann<lb/> 
&amp;<lb/>
Doc Greenfield</p>

<p>Cost $1.03/3 paid</p>

<p>Copy of Maria Anne T Greenfields Will</p>

<p>Summon for the Deft<lb/> 
Ann Clarke<lb/>
Edward <unclear reason="illegible">Dyre</unclear> Was Cty</p>

<p>Walter Greenfield<lb/>
John Grimes # PG Cty</p>

<p># John Grimes post office Brandywine or Horsehead</p>

<p># Mr Wm Dorset Post office Uppr. Marlbo.</p>

<p><bibl type="case">3 Vis Jr 323</bibl><lb/>
<bibl type="case">1 John C.R. 220</bibl><lb/>
<bibl type="case">2 <unclear reason="illegible">Carne</unclear> R 345</bibl></p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>