<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0249.001">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Clem Joice v. Robert Alexander. Minute Book Entries</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0249.001</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Minutes of the U.S. Circuit Court for the District of Columbia, 1801-1863</title>
<date when="1808-01-19">January 19, 1808</date>
<!--<date when="1809-01-27">January 27, 1809</date>-->
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21</collection>
<idno>Microfilm 1021, Reel 1</idno>
<msName>Minutes of the U.S. Circuit Court for the District of Columbia, 1801-1863</msName>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Minute Book</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>January 1808</term>
<term>January 1809</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people"> 
<term>Boothe, Jeremiah</term>
<term>Brent, William</term>
<term>Burch, Benjamin</term>
<term>Cassin, Joseph</term>
<term>Coombe, Griffith</term>
<term>Craig, Robert</term>
<term>Darling, Dennison</term>
<term>Dobbyn, John</term>
<term>Dodge, Francis</term>
<term>Duckett, Allen Bowie</term>
<term>Eliason, John</term>
<term>Elliot, Richard</term>
<term>Flaut, Christian</term>
<term>Forrest, Richard</term>
<term>French, Thomas</term>
<term>Harris, Ann</term>
<term>Homer, Mary Ann</term>
<term>Hough, John</term>
<term>Huddlestone, Joseph</term>
<term>Hyde, Thomas</term>
<term>Jameson, Richard</term>
<term>Johns, Richard</term>
<term>Key, Philip Barton, 1757-1815</term>
<term>Lindsay, Adam</term>
<term>Lowe, E. M.</term>
<term>Lowe, Michael</term>
<term>McIntire, Samuel</term>
<term>Moore, George</term>
<term>Mountz, Jacob</term>
<term>Newton, Ignatius</term>
<term>Queen, Henry M.</term>
<term>Queen, Nicholas L.</term>
<term>Rabbit, John</term>
<term>Shorter, Catherine</term>
<term>Shorter, Charles</term>
<term>Shorter, Jane</term>
<term>Shorter, Mary</term>
<term>Smallwood, Samuel N.</term>
<term>Soncherez, Alexander L.</term>
<term>Speake, Sameul</term>
<term>St. Clair, George</term>
<term>Sullivan, Ann</term>
<term>Thompson, John</term>
<term>Veitch, James</term>
<term>Warren, Samuel</term>
<term>Washington, Baily</term>
<term>Wharm, David</term>
<term>Wheeler, Edward</term>
<term>Wood, Hezekiah</term>
<term>Wright, Matthew</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">   
<term>Prince George's County (Md.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="related.case"/> 
</classCode>
</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Joice, Clem</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Alexander, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>             
<change when="2015-01-29" who="kln">reviewed; edited</change>
<change when="2015-01-23" who="ea">Encoded and transcribed.</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p575" facs="oscys.case.0249.001.001.jpg"/>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>United States<lb/>
vs.<lb/>
Robert Alexander<lb/>
Joseph Cassin &amp; <lb/>
Saml. N Smallwood</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
     
<p>Recog. in the sum of $800 conditioned that the said Alexander shall not remove Clem Joice a slave out of this District nor obstruct her in attending this court from time to time in support of her petition for freedom &amp;c</p>     

</div2>

<fw>575</fw>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<pb xml:id="p102" facs="oscys.case.0249.001.002.jpg"/>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Clem Joice<lb/>
against<lb/>
Robert Alexander</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">
     
<p>72 Trials</p>

<p>Jury sworn verdict for Deft.</p>

<p>Jury fee paid</p>

<list rend="simple">
<item>1 Jacob Mountz</item>
<item>2 David <unclear reason="illegible">Wharm</unclear></item>
<item>3 Francis Dodge</item>
<item>4 Alexr. L. Soncherez</item>
<item>5 John Dobbyn</item>
<item>6 Henry M Queen</item>
<item>7 Richard Johns</item>
<item>8 Thomas French</item>
<item>9 Christian Flaut</item>
<item>10 Benjn. Burch</item>
<item>11 Dennison Darling</item>
<item>12 Baily Washington</item>
</list>

<list rend="simple">
<head>Witnesses sworn for petitioner</head>
<item>Thos Hyde</item>
<item>Ann Harris</item>
<item>John Rabbitt</item>
<item>Ann Sullivan</item>
<item>Jane Shorter</item>
<item>Rid. Forrest</item>
<item>N L Queen</item>
<item>Chs. Shorter</item>
<item><del>Charles</del> Mary Ann Homer</item>
<item>Cath Shorter</item>
<item>Mary Shorter</item>
</list>

<list rend="simple">
<head>Witnesses sworn for Deft</head>
<item>Philip B Key</item>
<item>Wm Brent</item>
<item>Richd Jameson</item>
<item>Baily Washington</item>
<item>Michael Lowe</item>
<item>E. M. Lowe</item>
<item>Saml. Warren</item>
</list>
    
<p><del>And the Jurrors</del> Let a Jury appear &amp;c</p>

<p><del>And</del> Thereupon the Honorable Allen B. Duckett Esquire one of the assistant Judges of this court, withdraws from the Bench having been formerly council for the former owners of the Petitioner in this cause (in the Court of Prince Georges County Maryland) and the Jurors of the Jury whereof mention is above made being called come that is to say, Jacob Mountz, John Hough, George Moore, David Wharm, Jeremiah Boothe, Samuel McIntire, Francis Dodge, Nichs. L Queen, Alexr. L Soncherez, Edward Wheeler, Samuel Speake, and James Veitch. Whereupon certain of them, towit Jacob Mountz, David Wharm, Francis Dodge, &amp; Alexr. L. Soncherez <del>and John Dobbyn</del> are sworn upon that Jury, and because the rest of the said Jurors so appearing being according to the act of assembly in such cases provided, challenged by the parties, that is to say, John Hough, Nicholas L. Queen, Edward Wheeler &amp; Samuel Speake, on the

<fw>102</fw> 

<pb xml:id="p103" facs="oscys.case.0249.001.003.jpg"/>
    
part of the Petitioner, and the said George Moore, Jeremiah Boothe, Samuel McIntire and James Veitch on the part of the Defendant, others from being called <del>called</del>, come that is to say John Thompson, Matthew Wright, Thomas Hyde, Ignatius Newton, John Eliason, Samuel Queen, Joseph Huddlestone, and George St. Clair. Whereupon none of them were sworn upon the Jury, <del>but are</del> being challenged <del>pe</del> by the parties according to the act of assembly aforesaid that is to say, the said John Thompson, Thomas Hyde, Ignatius Newton Samuel Queen and George St. Clair on the part of the petitioner and the said John Eliason and Joseph Huddleston on the part of the Defendant and it being objected on the part of the Defendant to the said Mathew Wright being sworn on the Jury alledging that he does not stand indifferent between the parties to this issue. Whereupon the said Jacob Mountz and David Wharm the two first of the Jurors herein before impannelled are sworn to try whether the said Matthew Wright stands indifferent between the parties to this issue who having retired from the bar of the Court here afterwards return and on their oath do say that the said Matthew Wright does not stand indifferent between the parties to this issue, thereupon the Court here elect that another Juror be called in his stead. other jurors being called, come that is to say Griffith Coombe, Hezekiah Wood, Robert Craig, John Dobbyn and Adam Lindsay whereupon the said John Dobbyn is sworn upon the jury and because the said Jurors so appearing being in like manner challenged by the parties that is to say, the said Hezekiah Wood and Robert Craig on the part of the Petitioner and the said Griffith Coombe and Adam Lindsay on the part of the Defendant and because a sufficient number of Jurors not being present to complete the said Pannel therefore others of the by-standers by the Marshal of the District of Columbia are summoned who called certain of them come; that is to say Henry M. Queen, Hugh Drummond, Christian Flaut, Richard Johns, Thomas French, <del>Christian Flaut</del> Benjamin Burch and John T Frost Whereupon certain of them, that is to say, the said Henry M Queen, Christian Flaut, Richard Johns Thomas French and Benjamin Burch are sworn upon the Jury and because the rest of the said Jurors so appearing being according to the act of assembly aforesaid <del>being</del> challenged by the parties that is to say, the said Hugh Drummond on the part of the Petitioner and the said John T Frost on the part of the Defendant other Jurors of the By-standers so summoned by the said Marshal being called come, that is to say, Dennison Darling, &amp; Richard Elliot <del>and Baily Washington</del>, whereupon <del>certain</del> one of them that is to say Dennison Darling <del>and Baily Washington</del> is sworn upon the Jury and because the said Richard Elliott is by
    
<fw>103</fw>
    
<pb xml:id="p104" facs="oscys.case.0249.001.004.jpg"/>
    
the Defendant challenged according to the act of assembly aforesaid, another of the By-standers so summoned as aforesaid by the said Marshal, being called, comes that is to say, Baily Washington Whereupon the said Baily Washington is sworn upon that Jury which said Henry M Queen, Richard Johns, Thomas French Christian Flaunt, Benjamin Burch, Dennison Darling and Baily Washington so summoned by the marshall aforseaid from among the by standers elected at the request of the parties and by command of the Court here are added to the pannel whose names to the pannel aforesaid are annexed according to the form of the statute in such case made &amp; provided and the Jurors so added together with the other Jurors aforesaid being impanneled being elected tried and sworn to say the truth in the premises above contained do on their oath say. &amp;c</p>
    
<p>The Court adjourned till tomorrow Morning 10 OClock.</p>

</div2>

<gap reason="sampling"/>

<fw>104</fw>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>

