<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0016.001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Fanny Tarlton v. Cartwright Tippett. Circuit Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0016.001</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0059</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Civil and Criminal in the United States Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, from 1801 to 1841</title>
<author n="Cranch, William, 1769-1855">William Cranch</author>
<publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume II</biblScope>
<date when="1852">1852</date>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>April 1824</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">  
<term>Morsell, James Sewall</term>
<term>Scott, Alexander</term>
<term>Thruston, Buckner, 1763-1845</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
<term>Caracas (Venezuela)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Tarlton, Fanny</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Tippett, Cartwright</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName>Turner, Thomas</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName>Jones, Walter</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-06-02" who="#ea">updated case number</change>
<change when="2015-04-15" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>  

<div1 type="report">

<pb xml:id="p463" facs="oscys.report.0016.001.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Negro Fanny Tarlton v. Cartwright Tippett.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus">

<p>If the owner of a slave in the county of Washington carries her to a foreign country with intent there to reside permanently, and does there reside with her for more than twelve months and is then compelled to quit that country, and returns to the county of Washington, bringing the slave with him there to reside, the slave, by such importation, becomes entitled to her freedom. But if the owner be sent to such foreign country as a special agent of the government of the United States, at a stated salary, with an uncertainty, depending upon contingencies, whether he should remain there or return after accomplishing the purpose of his mission, and is compelled to leave the country before he had actually settled himself as a permanent resident there, then the taking the slave with him and bringing her back, is not an importation against the <bibl type="code">Maryland Act of 1796, c. 67</bibl>.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Petition for freedom. Mr. Alexander Scott had been
appointed by the President of the United States, an agent to Caraccas in South
America. He went with an intention to remain permanently, if certain events
should happen. He took the petitioner with him, and she remained there with him
more than a year. The event not having occurred upon which his decision to
reside there permanently was to be founded, he returned to reside here, and
brought her with him.</p>

<p>Mr. Turner, for the petitioner, moved the Court to
instruct the jury, that "if they should believe from the evidence that Mr.
Scott, at the time of his leaving the District of Columbia, for Caraccas, meant
permanently to reside there, with his family, and did so reside for upwards of
twelve months, carrying with him and there retaining the petitioner; and that
his leaving there was owing to compulsion and not to his will, then the
petitioner is entitled to a verdict in her favor."</p>

<p>The Court (Morsell, J., contrà,) gave the instruction, whereupon Mr. Jones, for the defendant, prayed the Court to
instruct the jury, "that if they find from the evidence that the said Scott
proceeded to Caraccas in a public character on a secret mission for the
government, and on a stated salary; that he also had some ulterior and
contingent views of remaining longer at Caraccas than was necessary for the
purposes of his mission, and of

<pb xml:id="p464" facs="oscys.report.0016.001.002.jpg"/>

engaging there in business; but that when he departed from the district for Caraccas,
the duration of his abode there and the business he should engage in, were
undetermined and uncertain, and dependent upon circumstances; and that, at the time
of his being compelled to leave Caraccas, he had not actually settled himself as a
permanent resident there, but still remained there undecided as to the duration of
his residence, or the footing on which he should establish himself, then the bringing
the petitioner back from Caraccas to Maryland and from Maryland to this district, was
not an importation against the Act of Assembly." Which instruction the Court gave, as
prayed; (Thruston, J., dissenting.)</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>