<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.caseid.0251">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John Davis, Teresa Davis, &amp; Mary Ann Davis v. Hezekiah Wood</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.caseid.0251</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>original</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="related.case">oscys.caseid.0008</ref>
<ref type="related.case">oscys.caseid.0017</ref>
<ref type="related.case">oscys.caseid.0018</ref>
<ref type="related.case">oscys.caseid.0019</ref>
<ref type="related.case">oscys.caseid.0249</ref>
</classCode>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="case">

<div2 type="narrative">
<head>Case Narrative</head>

<p>John Davis, Teresa Davis, and Mary Ann Davis filed a <ref target="oscys.case.0250.006">petition for freedom</ref> against Hezekiah Wood, and the slaveholder retained Francis Scott Key. The Davises claimed that they were entitled to their freedom because they were <ref type="sitelink" target="family/davis">the children of Susan Davis</ref>. Wood had sold Susan Davis to Caleb Swann, and she subsequently filed a petition for freedom arguing that her <!--great grandmother--> ancestor, Mary Davis, was a free white woman from England. The jury <ref target="oscys.mb.0013.002">decided in her favor</ref> at a trial held on January 18, 1809. Her children, however, were still enslaved by Wood. They too won their jury trial in the D.C. Court a year later in December 1809, in part because the verdict in their mother's case was introduced as evidence. The judges instructed the jury that the verdict, having been <ref target="oscys.case.0250.005">admitted as evidence</ref>, was "conclusive evidence for the petitioners in this cause." Key eventually filed a <ref target="oscys.case.0250.007">writ of error</ref> appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court, arguing that the judges had erred in their instructions to the jury. The U.S. Supreme Court <ref target="oscys.report.0006.001">overturned the verdict</ref> in February 1812, holding that the verdict in one case could not serve as conclusive evidence in another unless the parties were the same. The Davises filed another case, and it too went to trial. This time the court disallowed hearsay testimony following the ruling in <bibl type="case">Mima Queen v. Hepburn</bibl>. The jury found for the defendant slaveholder, and the petitioners filed a writ of error before the U.S. Supreme Court. On March 12, 1816, the U.S. Supreme Court reaffirmed the <hi rend="italic">Mima Queen v. Hepburn</hi> ruling on hearsay and <ref target="oscys.report.0006.002">upheld the lower court's ruling</ref> denying the Davises their petition for freedom. (See also <ref target="oscys.caseid.0011"><hi rend="italic">Mima Queen v. John Hepburn</hi></ref>.)</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="commentary">
<head>Commentary</head>

<div3>
<head>Parties</head>
<p>Key argued that Hezekiah Wood was not a "party" to Susan Davis' earlier suit against Swann, nor was there any legal relation tying him to Swann&#8212;for example, by kinship, lease, or contract. Therefore, the resolution of that case could not be used to conclusively render a judgment in Wood's case. Second, and possibly more devastating, Key argued that the verdict in Susan Davis' case was only proof that she was "free at the time of the judgment not that she was born free." Key suggested that she might have been manumitted after the birth of her children who were now petitioning for their freedom, and in that case their status would be unaffected by her manumission. Key pointed out that in Maryland, the only issue in a petition for freedom was "whether the petitioner be free at the time" the case was joined, "not whether she were born free." And in rather circuitous logic, Key suggested that in Maryland the practice was that the form of a petition stated that the petitioners were entitled to their freedom and held as slaves, but the Maryland Act of 1796 charged the jury with determining "those allegations which may be controverted." Key concluded that because the Davises had not stated any other allegations on their petition, "the only allegation controverted is that the petitioner is free." By Key's logic the only claim under this particular petition that could be assessed was whether Susan Davis was free at the time of her petition, not whether she was born free.</p>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="outcome">
<ab type="decision">
<term/>
<bibl/>
</ab>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>