<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0296.002">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Ellen Johnson v. Morris Taylor. Petitioner's Statement of Facts &amp; Defendant's 1st Bill of Exceptions</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
 <name n="Camerone, Stephanie N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0296.002</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0298</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Petitioner's Statement of Facts &amp; Defendant's 1st Bill of Exceptions</title>
<date when="1849-12">December 1849</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 772, Folder 48</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Statement of Facts</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1853-10">October 1853</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Hudson</term>
<term>Johnson, John</term>
<term>Turner Jr., Thomas</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">  
<term>Georgetown (Washington, D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Johnson, Ellen</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Johnson, John Thomas</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Johnson, Louisa</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Johnson, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Adler, Morris</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-07-06" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>            
<change when="2015-03-19" who="#snc">transcribed, encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0296.002.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">
    
<p>The Petitioners Ellen, John Thomas, Robert, and Louisa to maintain the issues on their part respectively joined gave evidence to shew that the Petitioner Ellen was the property of Thomas Turner of Georgetown, and while in his service had one child, and in the <del>spring of</del> month of April in the year 1831 gave birth to twins while at said Turners house &amp; while still in his service. That she was then the wife of John Johnson a free colored man, <del>and</del> that Mr Turner refused to pay more than half, and did pay but half the expense, attending the birth of said twins, and John their father paid the other half, that shortly after the birth of said twins said Ellen with the knowledge of said Turner left his residence &amp; went to live with her said husband <del>take</del> near to the residence of said Turner in a house rented by said Johnson &amp; took with her the three children above mentioned, and

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0296.002.002.jpg"/>

<del>publicly</del> openly &amp; publicly &amp; without any concealment <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> out and stated to the witness Mrs. Hudson that her master had set her free together with the said twins and had let her have the older child to assist in nursing them, &amp; she was to support the said child for her service &amp; that Mr Turner had given her notice, and she gave notice to a white person she was then about to <unclear reason="illegible">employ</unclear> to <unclear reason="illegible">sew</unclear> for herself and her children <del>and to whom she made the foregoing statement</del> that Mr Turner was not thereafter to be liable for any expenses of her maintenance or the maintenance of her said children except the oldest one; that she did then make a contract with and <unclear reason="illegible">employ</unclear> a white woman to work for her, and paid her for said work; that thereafter <del>to the time of bringing of th</del> she gave birth to the other petitioners, and she and her said husband paid the expenses of their birth, nurture, and maintenance: that from &amp; after the spring of 1821 to the bringing of this suit the said Ellen continued to reside in said Georgetown living, dealing, acting, and passing as free, &#38; making contracts and dealing as a free person hiring out her children and receiving their wages and that she <del>never</del> nor the other petitioners, never was 

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0296.002.003.jpg"/>

nor was any one of them ever in the possession or reduced to the control or custody of said Turner or his representatives: that said Turner had <del>other</del> slaves in said Georgetown who were hired out, and when he left the said town of George Town about eight or nine years ago, he either left the said slaves in charge of &amp; under the care and custody of agents, or looked after their wages himself, but said agents if there were such never took charge of or in any manner interfered with said Petitioners or any of them</p>

<p>and upon the cross examination of the witness Mrs. Hudson by the defendants counsel, the said witness stated, that the said declarations of Ellen so made to her, were not repeated by said witness to any other person. To which declarations of the said Ellen so made as aforesaid the Defendant objected as inadmissable evidence to go the jury. but the Court permitted the same to be given &amp; thereupon the Defendant excepted &amp; prayed the Court to sign &amp; seal this his first bill of Exceptions, which is done accordingly this &#160; &#160; day of December in the year 1849</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0296.002.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Petitioners Statement of Evidence &amp; Defts 1st Bill of Exceptions</p>

<p>relating to Ellens declarations to Mrs Hudson</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
