<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0006.002">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>John Davis v. Hezekiah Wood. Supreme Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0006.002</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0006</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Argued and Adjudged in the Supreme Court of the United States, February Term 1816</title>
<author n="Wheaton, Henry, 1785-1848">Henry Wheaton</author>
<publisher>The Banks Law Publishing Co.</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume I. Fourth Edition</biblScope>
<date when="1883">1883</date>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>February 1816</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">  
<term>Davis, Airy</term>
<term>Davis, Mary</term>
<term>Davis, Susan</term>
<term>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</term>
<term>Marshall, John, 1755-1835</term>
<term>Swann, Caleb</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places"> 
<term>Virginia</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>

<particDesc>   
<listPerson>
<person role="plaintiff">
<persName>Davis, John</persName>
<persName>Davis, Mary Ann</persName>
<persName>Davis, Teresa</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant"> 
<persName>Wood, Hezekiah</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName>Law, John</persName>
<persName>Lee, Charles, 1758-1815</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName>Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Supreme Court</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-06-02" who="ea">updated case number</change>
<change when="2015-04-13" who="#kln">transcribed; encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>  
   
<div1 type="report">

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.report.0006.002.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Negro John Davis et al. v. Wood.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus">

<p>Evidence.—Hearsay.—Verdict.</p>

<p>Evidence by hearsay and general reputation is admissible only as to pedigree, but not to establish the freedom of the petitioner's ancestor, and thence to deduce his or her own.</p>

<p>Verdicts are evidence between parties and privies only: and a record proving the ancestor's freedom to have been established in a suit against another party, by whom the petitioner was sold to the present defendant, is inadmissible evidence to prove the petitioner's freedom.</p>

<p><bibl type="case">Mima Queen v. Hepburn, 7 Cr. 290</bibl>, re-affirmed.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>This case was similar to the preceding, in which the petitioners excepted to the opinion of the court below: 1st. That they had offered to prove, by competent witnesses, that they (the witnesses) had heard old persons, now dead, declare, that a certain Mary Davis, now dead, was a white woman, born in England, and such was the general report in the neighborhood where she lived; and also offered the same kind of testimony, to prove that Susan Davis, mother of the petitioners, was lineally descended, in the female line, from the said Mary; and it was admitted, that said Susan was, at the time of petitioning, free, and acting, in all respects, as a free woman; which evidence, by hearsay and general reputation, the court refused to admit, except so far as it was applicable to the fact of the petitioners' pedigree. 2d. That they having proved, that the petitioners are 

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.report.0006.002.002.jpg"/>

the children of Susan Davis, and that she is the same person named in a certain record, in a cause wherein Susan Davis, and her daughter Ary, were petitioners, against Caleb Swann, and recovered their freedom, the plaintiffs offered to read said record in evidence to the jury, as <term>primâ facie</term> testimony that they are descendants in the female line from a free woman, who was born free, and are of free condition, connected with the fact, that the defendant in this cause sold said Susan to Swan, the defendant in said record, which the court refused to suffer the petitioners to read to the jury as evidence in this cause.</p>

<p>Lee, for the plaintiffs in error and petitioners, referred to the opinion of the court (Duvall, J., dissenting) in the case of <bibl type="case">Mima Queen and child v. Hepburn, February term 1813 (7 Cr. 290)</bibl>, as to the admissibility of hearsay evidence, in a similar case, remarking that, unless the court was disposed to review its decision, it must be taken for law, and he could not deny its authority.</p>

<p>Duvall, J. — The petitioners in that case were descended from a yellow woman, a native of South America. In this case, they are descended from a white woman.</p>

<p>Lee cited the opinion of the Virginia court of appeals in the case of <bibl type="case">Pegram v. Isabel, 2 Hen. &amp; Munf. 1913</bibl>, as to the admissibility of the record in which a record was admitted.</p>

<p>Key, contrà, contended, that both grounds were irrevocably closed against the other party. The first, certainly; and the second, equally so; as the evidence could not be admissible as <term>primâ facie</term> testimony merely, but if admitted, must be conclusive. The decisions in the state courts of Virginia are against the evidence of the parent's or other ancestor's freedom being conclusive in favor of a child. The case of <bibl type="case">Pegram v. Isabel</bibl> is no authority here, for it was formerly considered and repudiated by this court in the decision alluded to.</p>

<p>Lee and Law replied, and cited <bibl type="case">2 Wash. 64</bibl>, and <bibl type="code">Swift's Law of Evidence 13</bibl>.</p>

<p>March 12th, 1816. Marshall, Ch. J., delivered the opinion of the court, and stated, that, as to the first exception, the court had revised its opinion in the case of <bibl type="case">Mima Queen and child v. Hepburn</bibl>, and confirmed it. As to the second exception, the record was not between the same parties. The rule is, that verdicts are evidence between parties and privies. The court does not feel inclined to enlarge the exceptions to this general rule, and therefore, the judgment of the court below is affirmed.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>