<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0268.003">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Rachel Johnson v. Morris Adler. Copy of Acts of Assembly of 1833 &amp; 1839</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Camerone, Stephanie N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0268.003</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0288</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Copy of Acts of Assembly of 1833 &amp; 1839</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 763, Folder 75</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Notes</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1852-10">October 1852</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Johnson, Rachel</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Adler, Morris</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>      
<change when="2015-06-23" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>  
<change when="2015-06-18" who="#ea">changed xml id, added case id</change>      
<change when="2015-03-10" who="#snc">Encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0268.003.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p><bibl type="code">1833 Ch. 87</bibl></p>

<p>That is shall be lawful any citizen of this state who has acquired, or may hereafter acquire by marriage or bequest or in course of distribution in another state district or Territory any slave for life or any person who resides or may have resided out of the state, &amp; who may remove or have removed into the same, to become a citizen to introduce into this state any slave owned or so required by them</p>

<p>1 Provided the person so removing shall within 30 days after the removal of such slave make affidavit before some Justice of the peace of this county into which he may remove &amp; have the same filed in the office of the clerk of the county court of said county of his intention to become a citizen of the state</p>

<p>2 Provided that the person so removing or acquiring shall within the time aforesaid file with this sd clerk a list of the slaves removed stating their ages, with our affidavit thereto attached that the same is a true &amp; faithful list of the slaves removed, &amp; that he has not removed the same into the state for the purpose of sale &amp; that they are slaves for life</p>

<p><bibl type="code">1839. Ch</bibl></p> 

<p>That it shall be lawful for any citizen of this state or for any person who <del>may</del> resides or may have resided out of this state &amp; may remove into the same with the intention of becoming a citizen thereof to introduce into this state any negro slave for life from any state District or territory of the U. S.</p>

<p>1 Provided the person so removing shall within thirty days after the removal of such slave into the state make affidavit before some Justice of the peace of the county into which he may remove &amp; <del>file the same</del> have the same filed <del>with</del> in the office of the clerk of this county court of said county of his or her intention to become a citizen of the state</p>

<p>2 Provided &amp; that this person so introducing such slave shall within the time aforesaid file with the said clerk a list of the slaves so removed stating their ages with an affidavit thereunto attached that the same is a true <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> faithful list of His slaves so removed</p>    

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0268.003.002.jpg"/>

<p>1833</p>

<p>3 Provided that the sum of $15 for each slave between the age of 12 &amp; 45, and $5 for each slave above the age of 45 &amp; under 12 so brought into the state shall be paid to the clerk of the county at the time of giving such list to be <gap extent="one word" reason="illegiable"/> over by him to the treasurer of this western shore for the <gap extent="one word" reason="illegiable"/> of the Col. Secy. of this state</p>

<p>4 repealing Clause<lb/>
That any thing in any previous act in any wise contrary to or inconsistent with the provisions of this act be &amp; the same is here by repealed</p>

<p>1839</p>

<p>&amp; that he hath not removed the same into this state for the purpose of sale &amp; that they are slaves for life</p>

<p>3 proviso the same as the <bibl type="code">Act of 1833</bibl></p>

<p>repealing Clause<lb/>
same</p>


<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0268.003.003.jpg"/>

<p><bibl type="code">Act of 1833</bibl></p>

<p>Within 30 days of his removal shall make affidavit before a Justice of the peace of this county</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="back">

<p>Copy of the <bibl type="code">Act of Assembly of 1832 &amp; 1839</bibl> relating to Negroes</p> 

<p>Certificate of Mr. Turners Compliance with the <bibl type="code">Act of 1839</bibl></p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
