<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0212.016">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Thomas Butler v. Gabriel Duvall. Defendant's Objection</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0212.016</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0217</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Defendant's Objection</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note> 
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21, Entry 6</collection>
<idno>Box 454, Folder 80</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Objection</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1831-05">May 1831</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Prince George's County (Md.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Airy</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Eliza</persName> 
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Liddy</persName> 
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Matilda</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Reason</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Sally</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Sarah</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Butler, Thomas</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2014-12-02" who="#kln">reviewed, edited</change>             
<change when="2014-11" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0212.016.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p><del>Tom Butler &amp;c. vs G Duval.</del></p>

<p><del>The petitioners having now amended a third time, 1st for [Copying 1st withdraws a dem to deft's plea after the plea had been ruled good by the court</del></p>

<p>Tom Butler &amp;c vs G. Duval.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The petitioners having already been indulged with pleading three several ways in reply to Deft's plea, and with two amendments, producing great &amp; injurious delay, under the particular circumstances of this case, the Deft objects to any further amendment &amp; prays to judgment of the court on the spl. deme. to the replication as it now stands amended; that amendment not making it necessary for the Deft, as he conceives, to make any change of his deme. to the repln as originally filed. Further amendmt. is objected to on two grounds which he thinks ought to be conclusive to the discretion of the court, which alone is to be enerted on a question of amendt.</p>

<p>1. The plea <del>entered</del> tendered a fair issue which ought to be &amp; can be met in no other way than by a direct &amp; simple denial of the petitioners residence under the control of the master in Prince Georges &amp; a corresponding <unclear reason="illegible">amount</unclear> of residence under the like control &amp; direction here. This was first <del>and</del> replied to by a averment that they were here present &amp;c. arguendo, not present in Prince Georges; ergo not residing under the control of the master 

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0212.016.002.jpg"/>

in P. Georges. The amended repln. is now both affirmative &amp; negative: it affirms a fact, supposed to be inconsistent with the averment of the plea, but not under the control, or in other words, by the will of the master: still non <unclear reason="illegible">constat</unclear> but they were here as removing slaves from another state, attempting by this means to withdraw their case from its proper jurisdiction: the fact denied is that they were not residents with the deft. in P. Georges; the <del>sufficient</del> insufficiency of this averment is obvious, but not necessary to be particularly insisted on, as an affirmative averment of residence here under control &amp; by the will &amp; direction of the master is held to be essential.</p>

<p>After so plain an issue has been three times avoided, firstly demr. &amp; then by two in suppt replns. there shd be some extraordinary merits to justify an application for another amendt.</p>

<p>Whether there be such merits is a question for the direction of the court, and that must <unclear reason="illegible">look</unclear> to the consequences of refusing the amendt. to the parties. <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> to the petrs. it <unclear reason="illegible">simply</unclear> remits them to the proper tribunal, in which it is not pretended but they will receive every justice that the merits of their case can claim here. We will agree to <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> on notice without <unclear reason="illegible">commisn.</unclear> any thing to expedite a decisn. on the merits. To the deft. an allowance now of even a genl. traverse, produces injurious delay (no one can say how long) with all the peculiar <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> of a case for freedom in a foreign jurisdiction.</p>

<p>Any further amendt. is therefore objected to; but if admitted, it is hoped none ether will be received, but a direct &amp; general traverse taking issue on the plea.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>