<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0227.010">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>William Thornton v. George M. Graham. Special Verdict</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0227.010</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0232</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Special Verdict</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note> 
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21, Entry 6</collection>
<idno>Box 454, Folder 82</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Verdict</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1831-05">May 1831</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term xml:id="per.001804">Graham</term><!-- mother -->
<term xml:id="per.001786">Stith, John</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Kentucky</term>
<term>Virginia</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.001782">
<persName>Thornton, William</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.001783">
<persName>Graham, George, 1770-1830</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>         
<change when="2015-11-09" who="#lkw">added xml:ids</change>     
<change when="2015-01-12" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change> 
<change when="2014-11" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0227.010.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>We of the Jury find that negro Will Thornton the Petitioner for freedom, was a Virginia born slave. And was held by Mrs. Graham the mother of the late George Graham for her life and after her death he was the property of the said George Graham. That the mother of the said George Graham resided in Virga. and the said negroe William resided <del>with</del> there also <del>here</del>, until her death which happened in the year 1819. That at the time of the death of Mrs. Graham, negro William was hired out to Mr. Jno. Stith of Virginia, and the said George Graham <del>sent for</del> then a resident of the City of Washington sent for the said slave (with intent to carry him from Washington with his other slaves to the State of Kentucky). That the petitioner did not come so as to go with the other slaves, and the said George Graham left Washington with his other slaves without taking with him the said negro William. That after the said Geo. Grahams departure as aforesaid for Kentucky, and during his absence from Washington, the said negroe William came to Washington that is to say on or about the <del>year</del> last of April 1819 <del>1820</del> and has remained here ever since. That the said George Graham returned from Kentucky in the <del>year</del> month of August (1830) 1819 and took possession of the said negroe William and held him in Washington until the period of his death, which took place in 1830. That the said

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0227.010.002.jpg"/>

George Graham was appointed <del>to a position</del> to an office under the government of the United States in the year 1814 and upon his appointment came reside in Washington and from thence continued to reside in Washington until the period of his death. (That he came to Washington with no intent to make it his permanent residence but to continue only so long as he should remain in office.) That he continued an office under the general government until the year 1817 and in 18     was appointed President of the Branch Bank of the United States in Washington. That he continued to act as President of the said Bank until the year     when he was appointed commissioner of the General Land Office and remained in that office until the period of his death. That the said George Graham uniformly declared that it never was his intention to become a permanent resident of Washington and never <unclear>received</unclear> the right of a Citizen in that place and that his residence in Washington was a sojournment in the said place so long as he should continue in office under the general government. 

</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>