<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.caseid.0217">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Thomas Butler, Sarah Butler, Matilda Butler, Airy Butler, Reason Butler, Sally Butler, Liddy Butler, &amp; Eliza Butler v. Gabriel Duvall</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.caseid.0217</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>original</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>



</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="case">

<div2 type="narrative">
<head>Case Narrative</head>
<p>Thomas Butler filed a petition for freedom against U.S. Supreme Court justice Gabriel Duvall on June 2, 1828 on behalf of himself and his wife, four children, and two grandchildren.  The petitioners argued that they were "persons of colour who are entitled to their freedom." Members of the Butler family had won several cases in Maryland in the 1790s, although it is unclear if the plaintiffs in 1828 were related. Gabriel Duvall maintained that he was officially a resident of Prince George's County, Maryland, and therefore the plaintiffs sued in the wrong jurisdiction and the case in the D.C. court should be dismissed. Duvall's attempt to change the venue indicates that he probably expected a more favorable hearing in his home county. At trial the case turned on the complication of jurisdiction and the respective Maryland and Virginia acts regarding the sale and importation of slaves. The jury found for the petitioners in May 1831, and a motion for a new trail was overruled. Thomas and Sarah Butler, their four children, and two grandchildren, were free.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="commentary">
<head>Commentary</head>

<div3>
<head>Jury Instructions</head>
<p>The central claim of the Butlers centered on their residence three decades earlier when they were sold to Gabriel Duvall in May 1805. Jurisdictional boundaries and the acts on the sale and importation of slaves in D.C. were complex. Gabriel Duvall purchased the Butlers from a barkeeper in Georgetown named John Dales, who moved around Virginia and Maryland trying various pursuits. Dales hired out the Butlers to work in Maryland, Virginia, and D.C., and the Butlers gained independence and a degree of freedom even as their status remained unchanged. Because Dales may have sold the Butlers to Duvall in violation of the <bibl type="code">1796 Maryland Act</bibl>, an act that was in force in D.C., the jury had to determine when and under what circumstances the Butlers were sold to Duvall. As a result <bibl type="case">Butler, et al. v. Duvall</bibl> featured a series of conditional decisions for the jury. If the jury found that Dales moved from Virginia to Washington, D.C. with the Butlers held as slaves and then proceeded to sell them in D.C. within three years of their arrival, then they were imported for the purpose of selling them, a violation of the Maryland Act, and the Butlers were entitled to their freedom. If they were sold to Duvall while he was a resident of D.C. and while Dales lived as a resident in Virginia, they were imported illegally and entitled to their freedom.</p>
</div3>
</div2>

<div2 type="outcome">
<ab type="decision">
<term/>
<bibl/>
</ab>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>