<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.caseid.0001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Ben v. Sabret Scott</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.caseid.0001</idno>
<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>original</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="related.case"/>
</classCode>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="case">

<div2 type="narrative">
<head>Case Narrative</head>

<p>Ben was a "mariner" held in slavery by Sabret Scott, a ship owner and merchant trader based in Washington, D.C., with extensive ties to the West Indies. Francis Scott Key represented Ben in his petition for freedom against Sabret Scott. Key filed the <ref target="oscys.case.0001.025">petition</ref> in September 1806 and argued that Ben "a man of colour" was sold and brought into Maryland in violation of the <bibl type="code">1796 Maryland Act</bibl> banning the importation of slaves into the state. Ben <ref target="oscys.mb.0001.002">won his case</ref> at trial on June 19, 1807, and he was declared free. The defendant filed a <ref target="oscys.case.0001.019">writ of error</ref> and <term>supersedeas</term> to delay the judgment. But apparently the writ of error was <ref target="oscys.case.0001.002">never sent</ref> to the plaintiff. Taking his freedom, Ben left Sabret Scott. Then, sometime in early 1808, Scott claimed Ben was a runaway slave and had Ben arrested and held in the D.C. jail. Francis Scott Key filed a <ref target="oscys.case.0001.003">writ of habeas corpus</ref> in June 1809 and argued that because the defendants had not provided a copy of the writ of error Ben was free and could not be held. In December 1808, the D.C. Circuit Court could not reach a decision on the matter and kept Ben imprisoned. Finally, in the June 1809 term, the Court <ref target="oscys.mb.0001.005">discharged Ben</ref>, finding that the defendant did not file a proper writ of error and provide a copy for the adverse party. The defendant's writ of error <ref target="oscys.report.0001.005">went to the Supreme Court</ref> of the United States in <!--April-->February 1810, and the Supreme Court overturned the D.C. Circuit Court and <ref target="oscys.case.0001.006">ordered a new trial</ref>. The case came <ref target="oscys.mb.0001.007">back to trial</ref> in the D.C. Circuit Court in <!--June-->January 1811, nearly five years after Ben filed his petition for freedom.</p>
</div2>

<div2 type="commentary">
<head>Commentary</head>
    
    <div3>
<head>Bonds</head>
<p>A <term>supersedeas</term> is a defendant's appeal bond that a court requires from an appellant who wants to delay the payment of a judgment until the appeal is complete. William Blackstone, in <bibl type="treatise">Commentaries Vol. 3</bibl>, notes that "before granting any appeal, writ of error, or <term>supersedeas</term>, the appellant must enter into bond with security to pay the amount of the debt, and all costs and damages . . . in case the judgment be affirmed." (409) In this case, Sabret Scott and George W. Riggs put up the <ref target="oscys.case.0001.015">surety bond</ref> of $1,000 paid to Ben. Sabret Scott signed the bond with an "x" indicating that despite his business ties and slaveholding he was illiterate.</p>
    </div3>
    
</div2>

<div2 type="outcome">
<ab type="decision">
<term/>
<bibl/>
</ab>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>