<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.report.0020.001">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Richard v. Abraham VanMeter. Circuit Court Report</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.report.0020.001</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0079</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Reports of Cases Civil and Criminal in the United States Circuit Court of the District of Columbia, from 1801 to 1841</title>
<author n="Cranch, William, 1769-1855">William Cranch</author>
<publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
<biblScope>Volume III</biblScope>
<date when="1852">1852</date>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Court Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1827-12">December 1827</date></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people"> 
<term>Bussard, Daniel</term>
<term>Claggett, Walter</term>
<term>Claggett, William W.</term>
<term>Cranch, William, 1769-1855</term>
<term>Gray, John B.</term>
<term>Miller</term>
<term>Thruston, Buckner, 1763-1845</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="outcome">
<term>Verdict for Defendant</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Hall, Richard</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>VanMeter, Abraham</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc> 
<change when="2015-06-25" who="#ea">added case outcome</change>
<change when="2015-06-02" who="#ea">updated case number</change>
<change when="2015-04-16" who="#kln">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<div1 type="report">

<pb xml:id="p214" facs="oscys.report.0020.001.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="caption">

<p>Negro Richard v. Abraham Van Meter.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="syllabus">

<p>An attachment of contempt will lie against a master who attempts to remove his
slave out of the jurisdiction of the Court after he has notice or knowledge of the
slave's petition for freedom; and the Court will also order the slave to be brought
into court by the marshal, that he may be protected.</p>

<p>A contract between a master and his slave cannot be enforced either at law or in
equity.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<p>This was a petition for freedom, stating in general terms, that
the petitioner is entitled to his freedom, but is held in slavery by
the defendant. It was filed on the 3d of April, 1826.</p>

<p>On the 31st of May, 1827, the petitioner filed an additional
petition stating that he had filed his petition for freedom, which
was still pending, of which the defendant's agent, (Miller) has
been duly notified, as well as the defendant, Van Meter, himself,
who has seized upon the petitioner, and threatens to remove him
from the jurisdiction of this Court, before his suit can be tried,
and praying the protection of the Court, and for general relief.
This was sworn to, by John B. Gray, a white man. Where-

<pb xml:id="p215" facs="oscys.report.0020.001.002.jpg"/>

upon, the following order was made by the Court, (Cranch, C.J., doubting.)</p>

<p>"Ordered, that an attachment issue against the said <persName>Van Meter</persName>,
for a contempt of this Court, in forcibly seizing, and attempting
to carry the petitioner out of the jurisdiction of this Court, after
due notice of the pendency of the said petition; and that the
petitioner be brought before this Court, in order that proper
measures may be taken to protect him from further violence, and
unlawful hindrance in the prosecution of his suit for freedom."</p>

<p>Being brought into court, Mr. Van Meter, upon interrogatories,
purged himself of the contempt; and filed an answer to the petition.
The cause was tried by the Court, neither party having
required a trial by jury, as provided for in the <bibl type="code">twenty-second
section of the Maryland Act of 1796, ch. 67</bibl>.</p>

<p>Cranch, C. J., delivered the judgment of the Court, as follows, (Thruston, J., dissenting.)</p>

 <p>This cause has been tried before the Court, by consent, without
a jury. The facts appear to be, that the plaintiff was the
slave of William W. Claggett, who, on the 25th of June, 1822,
gave him the following written certificate:</p>

<p>"This is to certify that Richard, my negro, wishes to purchase
himself, and it is my wish that he should do so; therefore, he is
at liberty to work for himself, so as he may be able to accomplish
his object. Upon his finally paying one hundred dollars
he then is to be free. Given under my hand this 25th of June,
1822.       William W. Claggett.</p>

<p>On the 6th of December, 1822, Mr. Claggett sold him to
Daniel Bussard, by bill of sale of that date, "as a slave for life."</p>

<p>There is no evidence that Mr. Bussard ever saw Mr. Claggett's
certificate until after he bought him, although there is some reason
to believe, that he knew, that the negro had received some
such promise.</p>

<p>It is probable that some part of the 100 dollars was paid by
Richard to Mr. Claggett; but how much, is uncertain. Mr.
Walter Claggett has testified, that he heard his brother, William
W. Claggett, say, that about thirty-five dollars were due, and
that when that sum was paid, Richard was to be free. There is
no evidence that Mr. Van Meter had any knowledge, at the time
of his purchase of the negro, that he had any promise of freedom.</p>

<p>These appear to be all the material facts of the case. The
claim rests upon a conditional promise made by the master to
his slave. In the case of <bibl type="case">Negro Joseph Brown v. Wingard,
this Court in April, 1822, (2 Cranch, C. C. 300,)</bibl> decided that a
contract between a master and his slave, could not be enforced
at law or in equity. That decision has been adhered to ever

<pb xml:id="p216" facs="oscys.report.0020.001.003.jpg"/>

since, and seems to be decisive of the present case, even if the
whole purchase-money had been paid.</p>

<p>We think the judgment must be against the petitioner.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>