<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0036.011">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Joe Thompson v. Walter Clarke. Memorandum</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Stephanie N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>

<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0036.011</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0036</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Memorandum</title>
<date when="1805-01-25">January 25, 1805</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21, Entry 6</collection>
<idno>Box 123, Folder 446</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Memorandum</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1817-12">December 1817</date></term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">  
<term xml:id="per.000428">Mason, John T.</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>


</textClass>

<particDesc>   
<listPerson>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000284">
<persName>Thompson, Joe</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000285">
<persName>Thompson, Nelly</persName>
</person>
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.000286">
<persName>Thompson, Sarah Anne</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.000287">
<persName>Clarke, Walter</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>

<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc> 
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015-11-09" who="#snc">added idno</change>
<change when="2014-10-01" who="#lkw">added xml:ids</change>
<change when="2014-09-04" who="#kln">converted to new TEI</change>
<change when="2014-01" who="#kln">corrected encoding</change>
<change when="2013-08-13" who="#kln">added Jones forename</change>
<change when="2013-04-26" who="#kln">added attorneys to header</change>
<change when="2013-01-24" who="#kln">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>
   
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0036.011.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>I have read and considered the Will of John Thompson</p>

<p>From my knowledge of the man I assume it is a fact he owed nothing or what is
next to nothing when he died.</p>

<p>If his wife is governed by her own interest she will renounce the will and take
the provision made for her by the law. This will be beneficial to her and in no
respect injurious to any of the representatives of her husband. If she stands to
the will she must take her third of the slaves entitled to their freedom as
limitted by the will of her husband and <unclear reason="illegible">controlled</unclear>
by the operation of the law. If
she renounced the will she will take one third part of the slaves not subject to
the provisions of the will at all but slaves to her absolutely. As to the other
parts of the testators estate real and personal the provisions of the will and
those of the law are precisely the same. If she renounces the will such
renunciation must be made within ninety days after the probate of the will and
it must be made in writing in a certain form which the register of the wills I
am sure will furnish her. The estate being clear of debt and she renouncing the
provision made for her, it seems to be clearly her interest also to renounce the
exertorship. My advice to her is to renounce both.</p>

<p>As to the slaves all those who will be forty five years old at the time or times
limitted by the will for them to be free must remain slaves during life, for by
the law a man cannot emancipate a slave forty five years old without giving
security to keep him off the county which the testator in this case has not
done. All the children born of these during the period of their slavery and
before the time limitted by the will for them to be free will be born slaves and
must remain so.</p>

<p>One of the legatees having died in the life time of the testator that legacy is
lapsed and goes to the residuary Legatee James Thompson
&amp; his family.</p>

<p>In appraising the slaves, as the testator was not in debt, and the whole, after
paying certain monied legacies, is to be divided between James
Thompson and the widow, it seems very unimportant how they are
valued; whether as slaves for life, or according to the time each has to serve
   
<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0036.011.002.jpg"/>  

serve respectively. Some uniform rule should be adopted by which all the slaves
should be valued, either all should be valued as slaves absolutely or all should
be valued according to the time they have by the will and the operation of law
to serve. Otherwise injustice will be done the widow. If she renounces the will
she is entitlled to one third in value of all the negroes considering them all
as slaves. But if those which she has, and valued as slaves, and the rest only
according to the time they have to serve, this will lessen the quantity of
negroes she will get. That will not be right or according to law. If they are
all valued according to the time they have to serve by the will, and by the
operation of law, and then one third assigned to her by that evaluation, she
will only get one third of the whole, and tho her share, being slaves
absolutely, will stand valued very low, yet that does no injustice to any
person; not to creditors because there are more to be effected by a <unclear reason="illegible">contribution</unclear> in whatever way
made; not to James Thompson or his family because tho' the
testator had no power to <unclear reason="illegible">trust</unclear> the wifes interest
in his slaves, he had power over
those which James Thompson must take under his will. So if
they are all valued as slaves absolutely no injury can occur to James
Thompson or any other person, for as the testator owed no debts,
and his monied legacies bear a very small proportion to his estate valued and
appraised in any way, they must be paid, and if the slaves alloted to
James Thompson are appraised to more than they are worth,
seeing they are valued as slaves absolutely when they have only a certain number
of years to serve, yet it is of no consequence to him as to the price, he takes them as a
gift, and has nothing to pay for them to any person. So that in truth view the
subject in any way it is important how the slaves are appraised so that they are
all appraised in the same way and by the same rule.</p>

<p>John T. Mason<lb/>
25th Jany 1805.</p>

</div2>

</div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>