<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0223.010">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>William Kennedy v. Clarissa Purnell. Jury Instructions</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0223.010</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Jury Instructions</title>
<date/>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note> 
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 606, Folder 390</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Instructions</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>March 1839</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Pendleton, Isaac Purnell</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Maryland</term>
<term>Virginia</term>
</keywords>

<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="related.case">oscys.case.0224</ref>
</classCode>
</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Kennedy, William</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Purnell, Clarissa</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>             
<change when="2015-01-12" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>  
<change when="2014-11" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>If the jury believe from the evidence aforesaid that the acts of the petitioner in <del>fleeing</del> going from Myd to Va as aforesaid remaining in the latter state, or in coming thence to this City &#38; remaining here were without the consent of defendant, <del>that</del> then it was not necessary for the deft within any limited period to use coercive measures for the recovery of the petitioner, &#38; that the omissions of such coercive measures does not give the <del>negro</del> petitioner any title to his freedom</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.002.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>(A.)</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="body">

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.003.jpg"/>

<p>If the jury believe from the evidence aforesaid that the petr being the slave of the deft and residing with her in Maryland and by her consent employed by the sd. Pendleton as his servant was in the year 1834 carried by the sd I. P. Pendleton from said sate to the state of Va without the consent of authority either <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> or subsequent of the <unclear reason="illegible">deft</unclear>. Then it is lawful for the deft to <gap extent="two words" reason="illegible"/> petitioner &#38; carry him back to Maryland at any time and the deft does not lose her title to the petitioner by any delay in exercising that right.</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.004.jpg"/>

<div2 type="back">

<p>(B)</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p005" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.005.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>If the jury believe from the evidence that the petitioner having become involved in a breach of the peace in the State of Maryland in company with I. Purnell Pendleton a citizen of said state, and to avoid her consequences thereof the said Pendleton fled to Va. carrying the petitioner with him, &#38; there remained with Petitioner and employing him as his servant during <unclear reason="illegible">two</unclear> years and upwards but never abandoned his residence in Myd and always entertained the purpose of returning to Maryland when he could <del>not</del> do so with safety and did not return the petitioner to Myd, only because he was afraid of the consequences thereof to the petitioner unless accompanied by said Pendleton &#38; said Pendleton at the end of said time <del>returned to</del> sent the petitioner to the City of Washington &#38; afterwards returned himself to Myd. 

<pb xml:id="p006" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.006.jpg"/>

That such acts of the said Pendleton, altho the jury should believe they were with the consent of the deft, <del>the petitioner is not entitled</del> do not entitle the Petr to his freedom.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="back">

<p>(C.)</p>

</div2>

<pb xml:id="p007" facs="oscys.case.0223.010.007.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>There was not <gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/> presented to the Court and they did not give or refuse it.</p>

<p><gap extent="one word" reason="illegible"/></p>

<p>If the jury believe from the evidence that <del>sa</del> I. P. Pendleton during his continuance in Virginia as aforesaid, only remained there as a sojourner and not with the view of making it his domicil that then he did not thereby acquire a residence in Va. or lose his previous residence in Maryland. </p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
