<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.mdcase.0006.024">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Robert Thomas v. Henry Pile. Deposition of William Swann</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Mu&#241;oz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Mu&#241;oz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Askren, Elizabeth" xml:id="ea">Elizabeth Askren</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
<name n="Weakly, Laura K." xml:id="lkw">Laura K. Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.mdcase.0006.024</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0342</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Deposition of William Swann</title>
<date when="1792-10-24">October 24, 1792</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Maryland State Archives</repository>
<collection>General Court of Western Shore (Judgments)</collection>
<idno>MSA S498-343</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Supplementary Documents</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Deposition</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term><date when="1794-10">October 1794</date></term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term xml:id="per.002083">Brice, John</term>
<term xml:id="per.002033">Contee, Benjamin</term>
<term xml:id="per.002036">Curtis, Mary</term>
<term xml:id="per.001964">Mingo, Betty</term>
<term xml:id="per.002051">Mingo, Charles</term>
<term xml:id="per.002064">Swann, William</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Charles County (Md.)</term>
</keywords>

</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner" xml:id="per.001950">
<persName>Thomas, Robert</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant" xml:id="per.001943">
<persName>Pile, Henry</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner" xml:id="per.001393">
<persName>Duvall, Gabriel, 1752-1844</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant" xml:id="per.001495">
<persName>Key, Philip Barton, 1757-1815</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>Maryland. General Court of the Western Shore</orgName>
<placeName>Annapolis (Md.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>            
<change when="2016-01-05" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change> 
<change when="2015-12-10" who="#lkw">added xml:ids</change> 
<change when="2015-06-12" who="#ea">encoded and transcribed</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.024.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>Charles County Set.</p>
     
<p>William Swann, of Allen's fresh, aged about fifty four or fifty five years <del>Th</del> having being sworn on the holy Evangels of Almighty God deposed. That as near as he can recollect about forty four or forty five years ago, a certain Mary Curtis, whom he supposed to be then near fifty years of age, told him, this deponent "that Charles Mingo and Betty Mingo had as much right to their freedom as she (the said Mary, meaning) had herself; for their mother was as white a woman "as she was" meaning, as this deponent supposes, herself. And this deponent adds that she said Mary Curtis was a very fair woman and had a remarkable good <unclear reason="illegible">skin</unclear>. That the said Mary Curtis died about twenty years ago. That she has Known Robert Thomas, the petitioner in the general Court, against Henry Pile, for about five or six years, and that he has also Known Henry Pile for <del>the</del> about same span of time. That the said Robert was reputed to be the slave of the said Henry, and was by him the said Henry held in slavery ever since he has known them the said Henry and the said Robert.</p>

<p>The said William Swann being severally interrogated on the various questions numbered from 1 a 9 both inclusive and contained in a certain paper intitled "The Petitioner's Interrogatories, signed, G Duvall for Petr. and being also examined on each and every of the interrogatories contained in a paper, numbered 1 a 23, inclusive, and signed Philip B. Key for defdts. answered that he knew nothing relative to or concerning the contents of said papers respectively, nor of Robert Thomas or this case, more than is expressed in the above deposition. in confirmation of all which he hath hereunto subscribed his name<lb/>
W Swan</p>

<p>I do certify that the above deposition was sworn to before me, and that the William Swann the deponent therein named attentively <unclear reason="illegible">perused</unclear> it before he subscribed his name and made oath therto. given under my hand at Allen's fresh this twenty first Day of May seventeen hundred and ninety two.</p>

<p>Ben: Contee</p>
     
<p>And the said William Swann being further sworn on the holy evangily of Almighty God on the twenty fourth day of October seventeen hundred and ninety two, and being asked if he knew Charles and Betty Mingo above mentioned

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.mdcase.0006.024.002.jpg"/>

answers he knew Charles very well, but did not know Betty that he recollects and he saith that the said Mary Curtis knew them very well and he has often heard her talk of them; and he further saith that Charles was a mulatto with long black hair, and he has heard it often said in the neighbourhood that the father of Charles was a Mingo Indian. And he further saith that the said Mary Curtis lived at the house of the deponent's father about fourteen years and was nurse to the deponent. Being asked what was the general Character of Mary Curtis for veracity, answers, he never heard anything against her.</p>

<p>Sworn to before me this 24h Octr. 1792<lb/>
Jno. Brice</p>

<p>Admitted to be read in evidence.<lb/>
G. Duvall for petr.<lb/>
Philip B Key for defdt.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="back">

<p>5&#189;</p>

<p>Robert Thomas<lb/>
a<lb/>
Henry Pile</p>

<p>Depo.<lb/>
W. Swann.</p>

<p>filed 31. Octo 1794</p>

<p>5&#189;</p>

<p>Wm Swann</p>

<p>16.</p>

<p>Entered</p>

</div2>

</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
