<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="oscys.case.0202.004">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sam and Ned v. Lewis Childs, Gabriel Childs, &amp; Hiram Emerson. Depositions of Jane St. Clair, Emily Ager, &amp; Ann Ager</title>
<principal n="Guiliano, Jennifer" xml:id="jeg">Jennifer Guiliano</principal>
<principal n="Muñoz, Trevor" xml:id="tm">Trevor Muñoz</principal>
<principal n="Thomas, William G., 1964-" xml:id="wgt">William G. Thomas III</principal> 
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Camerone, Steph N." xml:id="snc">Steph N. Camerone</name>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Maryland</sponsor>
<sponsor>National Endowment for the Humanities</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
    
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
            
<publicationStmt>
<authority>O Say Can You See</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">oscys.case.0202.004</idno>
<idno type="case">oscys.caseid.0207</idno>

<availability>
<licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</licence>
<p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. Derivatives must be credited to O Say Can You See, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<title level="m" type="main">Deposition of Jane St. Clair</title>
<date when="1832-01-04">January 4, 1832</date>
<note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of the original.</note> 
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>National Archives and Records Administration</repository>
<collection>Record Group 21.6</collection>
<idno>Box 465, Folder 392</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Case Papers</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Deposition</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Civil</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="term">
<term>December 1831</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Ager, Ann</term>
<term>Ager, Emily</term>
<term>Alfred</term>
<term>Alley</term>
<term>Caroline</term>
<term>Charlott</term>
<term>Glover, William</term>
<term>James</term> <!-- aka Jim -->
<term>John</term>
<term>Kit</term>
<term>Lucy</term>
<term>Rosett</term>
<term>St. Clair, Jane</term>
<term>Thorton</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Fairfax County (Va.)</term>
<term>Washington County (D.C.)</term>
<term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
</keywords>


</textClass>
            
<particDesc>   
<listPerson>            
<person role="petitioner">
<persName>Ned</persName>
<persName>Sam</persName>
</person>
<person role="defendant">
<persName>Childs, Gabriel</persName>
<persName>Childs, Lewis</persName>
<persName>Emerson, Hiram</persName>
</person>
<person role="attorney_petitioner">
<persName/>
</person>
<person role="attorney_defendant">
<persName/>
</person>
</listPerson>
            
<listOrg>
<org>
<orgName>United States. Circuit Court (District of Columbia)</orgName>
<placeName>Washington (D.C.)</placeName>
</org>
</listOrg>   
</particDesc> 
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>           
<change when="2015-02-18" who="#kln">reviewed; edited</change>   
<change when="2014-11" who="#snc">encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
<text>

<body>  
               
<div1 type="case">

<pb xml:id="p001" facs="oscys.case.0202.004.001.jpg"/>

<div2 type="body">

<p>The Deposition of Jane St Clair taken at her own house in Fairfax County State of Virginia. pursuant to agreement between the parties (herewith returned) to be read as evidence in a case now depending in the Circuit Court for the District of Columbia for Washington County wherein Sam and Edmund are petitioners for their freedom and Lewis &amp; Gabriel Childs &amp; Hiram <unclear reason="illegible">I</unclear> Emerson are Defendants on this 4th day of January 1832.</p>

<p>The Deponant being of lawful age and first duly sworn deposeth and saith.</p>

<p>Question by Defendants<lb/>
Were you or not acquainted with Gabriel L Childs late of Fairfax County Virginia</p>

<p>Answer I was</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Did you or not know the negroes he then had in possession</p>

<p>Answer I know that he was in possession of several negroes</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
What were their names &amp; ages as well as you can recollect</p>

<p>James Rosett Alley &amp; John</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Do you or not know the children of Rosett  &amp; Alley and their ages</p>

<p>Answer I know they had two children Sam and Edmund but do not know their ages. Edmund was the son of Alley and Sam I believe was the son of Rosett</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were they or not born since the death of Gabriel D Childs while their mothers were in the possession of sd Childs widow as slaves in the County of Fairfax Virginia</p>

<p>Answer they were</p>

<pb xml:id="p002" facs="oscys.case.0202.004.002.jpg"/>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
How long since you first became acquainted with sd Childs</p>

<p>Answer Twenty five years or more I cannot exactly recollect</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Have you or not ever since lived a near neighbour and was well acquainted with the two girls Rosett &amp; Alley</p>

<p>Answer Not since I left the neighborhood where they resided in possessions of Mr Childs</p>

<p>Question by Petitioners<lb/>
How do you know the names of said slaves and their ages</p>

<p>Answer From having generally heard them so called in the family as to ages I do not Know</p>

<p>Question by Same are you acquainted with the ages of Rosett &amp; Alley from your own knowledge how do you know them</p>

<p>Answer As to their ages I am not certain but know him from having frequently seen them</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
How many children had Rosett &amp; Alley each what were their names &amp; ages</p>

<p>Answer of their ages I am not certain nor how many they had</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were not Rosett &amp; Alley manumitted and at what time</p>

<p>Answer they were manumitted but when I do not know</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were not Sam and Edmund born before or after their mothers were set free</p>

<p>Answer they were born before their moths were set free but how long I know not</p>

<pb xml:id="p003" facs="oscys.case.0202.003.003.jpg"/>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Did not Gabriel D Childs die leaving a widow who afterwards intermarried with William Glover and when was she so married</p>

<p>Answer I do not recollect the year</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Was Rosett and Alley or either of them set free before the marriage of the said widow Childs</p>

<p>Answer I do not know</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were Sam &amp; Edmund or either of them born before the said marriage</p>

<p>Answer before the marriage how long I do not know</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
What is the differance between the ages of Sam &amp; Edmund</p>

<p>Answer I do not know</p>

<p>And further this deponent saith not</p>

<p>Also the Deposition of Emily Ager taken at the same time and place to be read as evidence in the same suit</p>

<p>The Deponant being of lawful age and first duly sworn deposeth and saith</p>

<p>Question by Defendants<lb/>
Were you not acquainted with Gabriel D Childs late of Fairfax County Virginia</p>

<p>Answer I was</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Did you not know the negroes he had in possession at and before his death if so what was their names and ages</p>

<p>Answer<lb/> 
Jim Alley Rosett and John as to 

<pb xml:id="p004" facs="oscys.case.0202.004.004.jpg"/>

their ages I do not know</p>

<p>Question by Same
Do you not know the children of Rosett and Alley and their ages particularly Sam and Edmund</p>

<p>Answer I know Rosetts children was Lucy Alfred Sam and Thornton I believe Sam to be about twenty one years of age. Alley's children was Kit Charlott Edmund and Caroline. Edmund I think is about twenty years of age.</p>

<p>Question by Same
Were they or not born while their mothers were in the possession of Gabriel D Childs widow as slaves a short time after the death of said Childs</p>

<p>Answer Yes they were</p>

<p>Question by Petitioners
How do you know the names of said negroes</p>

<p>Answer because I was well acquainted with them and always heard them so called</p>

<p>Question by Same
How do you know the ages of Sam and Edmund</p>

<p>Answer From my recollection of the time Edmund was born and knowing Sam was a year the oldest</p>

<p>Question by Same
How many children had Rosett and Alley each and what are their names &amp; ages As to that I have answered and given their names</p>

<pb xml:id="p005" facs="oscys.case.0202.004.005.jpg"/>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were not Rosett and Alley manumitted and at what time</p>

<p>Answer I think it has been about 18 or 19 years since Rosett was manumitted and about 15 years since Alley was </p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were Sam and Edmund born before or after their mothers were set free if before how long</p>

<p>Answer I do not recollect how long but it was some considerable length of time before their mothers were free</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Did not Gabriel D Childs die leaving a widow who intermarried with William Glover and when did she marry</p>

<p>Answer she did and I think she married in 1816</p>

<p>Question by Same Was Rosett and Alley or either of them set free before the marriage of the widow</p>

<p>Answer Roset was but Alley was no I think until two or three weeks after the marriage</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were Sam and Edmund born befor or after the marriage</p>

<p>Answer before four &amp; five years as well as Jean recollect</p>

<p>And further this Deponant saith not</p>

<pb xml:id="p006" facs="oscys.case.0202.004.006.jpg"/>

<p>Also the Deposition of Ann Ager taken at the same time and place to be read as evidence in the same case</p>

<p>The Deponant being of lawful age and first duly sworn deposeth and saith</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Did you not know Gabriel D Childs late of Fairfax County Virginia and the negroes she had at and some time before his death what was their names</p>

<p>Answer Jim Roset Alley and John</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Did you not know the children of Rosett and Alley <del>chur</del> names &amp; ages</p>

<p>Answer Yes</p>

<p>Question by Same What is the ages of Sam and Edmund</p>

<p>Answer Sam is about 21 years old and Edmund about 20</p>

<p>Question by Same<lb/>
Were they not born since the death of Gabriel D Childs while their mothers were in the possession of his widow in Fairfax County Va</p>

<p>Answer Yes<lb/>
Question by Same Have you or not been present all the time Emily Ager was engaged in giving in her deposition and did you or not hear the different questions propounded to her and would or not your answers to the rest of the interrogatories put by both parties be substantially the same as hers</p>

<p>Answer Yes exactly And further she saith not</p>

</div2>
</div1>
    
</body>
</text>
</TEI>