<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="nei.news.00099">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Wholesome Suspicion</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Gossin, Pamela</principal>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2013</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>The Papers of John G. Neihardt</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>nei.news.00099</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">Wholesome Suspicion</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">book review, <hi rend="italic">The History of Psychology</hi>. By W.H. Pillsbury, Ph.D. (W.W. Norton &amp; Co., inc New York.)</title>
<title level="j">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>
<note type="day">Friday</note>
<date when="1929-07-03">July 3, 1929</date>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
<extent> pages</extent>

</bibl>


</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Essays and Reviews</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Review</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Emergent Social Sciences</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subtopic">
<term>Psychology</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>the history of psychology</term>
<term>psychology</term>
<term>history</term>
<term>freudianism</term>
<term>zeitgeist</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Pillsbury, W. B. (Walter Bowers), 1872-1960</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>The History of Psychology</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-09-22"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Corrections; added topics; added The History of Psychology and fixed Pillsbury's name</change>
<change when="2012"><name xml:id="hv">Vahle, Hannah</name> Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2013"><name xml:id="jag">Gavran, Julie A.</name> <name xml:id="mhs">Stephens, Melissa H.</name> <name xml:id="wjs">Szendrey, William J.</name> Transcription</change>
    <change when="2014"><name xml:id="ag">Grosserode, Alex</name>revisions</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<pb />

<head>Wholeseome Suspicion</head>
<head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">THE HISTORY OF PSYCHOLOGY.</hi> By W. H. Pillsbury, Ph.D. (W. W. Norton &amp; Co., inc (New York).</head>
<p>THANKS to the popularization of Freudianism and the growing demand for eight-cylinder <unclear/>anship,  it is quite a la mode to indulge in psychologizing these days.  Nearly everybody seems to be doing it more or less.  To the <unclear>generality</unclear>, psychology often seems to signify the process of discovering highly reprehensible “com-<unclear/> in the other fellow and ex-<unclear/> the apparent best of him <unclear/> terms of mean motives.  To the <unclear/> it seems to signify a bag<unclear/> smooth tricks whereby a pro-<unclear/> victim may be induced <unclear/> buy something he really doesn’t want and can’t afford.  (One of <unclear/> most amusing indoor sports is<unclear/> of being streanuously <unclear>pscyhologized</unclear> by a tyro with something to <unclear>sell</unclear> whose own mental processes <unclear>are as</unclear> transparent as a pane of <unclear>glass</unclear>.</p>

<p>But it is not only we of the general public who seem to be <unclear>confused</unclear> as to this matter of psychology.  Even those who cheerily confess that they are experts<unclear/> so greatly in alleged fundamentals as to make a layman wonder what the deuce they know about the knower, anyhow.  But <unclear>now a</unclear> new theory is propounded <unclear>with</unclear> such an air of triumphant <unclear/>, and such a blare of pub-<unclear/> trumpets that considerable <unclear/> of the reading public are <unclear/> to accept the latest as the <unclear/>.</p>

<p>Under the circumstances, it might be well for the generality of <unclear/> spend some time in reviewing <unclear/> history of men’s guesses on the <unclear>subject</unclear> by way of arriving at a welcome suspicion.  Dr. Pillsbury’s work here noted offers any <unclear/> of average understanding <unclear/> valuable opportunity.  For <unclear/> years Dr. Pillsbury was professor of philosophy and director of the psychological laboratory at Cornell University.  In 1910 he <unclear/> elected president of the American Psychological Association.  He lectured in psychology at Columbia and in 1923 he was exchange professor at the Sorbonne, Paris. <unclear>He</unclear> is now in charge of the department of psychology at the University of Michigan.</p>

<p>Beginning with pre Socratic <unclear>thinkers</unclear> Dr. Pillsbury sets forth <unclear>in</unclear> a direct and easily readable manner “the story of the development of the interpretation man has put upon his acts and his thinking” through the ages.  He ends with Watson in America and Kuhler in Europe.  It is a long way, as we view time from the Atomists to the Behaviorists, from Demokritos to Watson: but if these may be regarded as representative of the beginning and the end of thinking about the human mind, many a reader is likely to wonder if any real progress has been made.  Happily, as Dr. Pillsbury’s story shows, these are not the beginning and the end.  Fashions come and go in theorizing as in everything else, and the time-mood determines the prevailing direction of search.  It is not improbable that along the way somewhere some thinker, now neglected, may have come much nearer to the truth we seek than either the ancient or the modern mechanist.  For a wild guess, Fechner might be named in this connection.  And there was one F. W. H. Myers who, naturally enough considering the highly “practical” persuasion of our day, is not mentioned at all by Dr. Pillsbury. 
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>