<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="nei.news.00082">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">[?f?]</title>
                <author></author>
                <principal>Gossin, Pamela</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Papers of John G. Neihardt</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
                </distributor>
                <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
                <address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
                <idno>nei.news.00082</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author></author>
                    <title level="a" type="main">[?f?]</title>
                    <title level="a" type="sub"></title>
                    <title level="j">St. Louis Post-Dispatch</title>
                    <note type="day">Wednesday</note>
                    <date when="1928-12-26">December 26, 1928</date>
                    <biblScope type="pp">17</biblScope>
                    <extent>1 page</extent>
                    
                </bibl>
                
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p></p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p></p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Essays and Reviews</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Review</term>
</keywords>                
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012"><name xml:id="hv">Vahle, Hannah</name> Initial Encoding</change>
            <change when="2013"><name xml:id="jag">Gavran, Julie A.</name> <name xml:id="mhs">Stephens, Melissa H.</name> <name xml:id="wjs">Szendrey, William J.</name> Transcription</change>
            
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div1 type="article">
                
                <pb />

<p>[ ? f? ]
 <unclear/> [ ? ion crude- <unclear/> [ ? e ] world is <unclear/><unclear/> to a Chris-<unclear/> be not in<unclear/> the con-<unclear/> of being.” <unclear/> [ ? dy ], as fol-<unclear/> truth, in-<unclear/> in matter.<unclear/> its infinite<unclear/></p>
    
<p><unclear/> to a philo-<unclear/> may call<unclear/> [ ? us ] philoso-<unclear/> [ ? nt ] and Oc-<unclear/> [ ? ing ] out that<unclear/> at all new.<unclear/> whom the <unclear/> neither a  <unclear/> adherent <unclear/> sophy.  He  <unclear/> [ ? olled]” scien-<unclear/> of the term. <unclear/> [ ? or ] of astron-<unclear/> of Cam-<unclear/> [ ? btful ] if any <unclear/> higher place <unclear/> elite of the <unclear/></p>
    
<p><unclear/> [ ? et] begin his <unclear/> of the Phys-<unclear/> such appar-<unclear/> [ ? ment ], and it<unclear/> [ ? tures ] to make<unclear/> required to <unclear/> and in those <unclear/> [ ? ange ] of mod-<unclear/> is carefully <unclear/> [ ? ical ] phys-<unclear/> relativity, the <unclear/> [ ? ation ], the <unclear/> It is in the <unclear/> the reader, <unclear/> the further <unclear/> [ ? rn ] scientific <unclear/> suspect where <unclear/> must lead.  That <unclear/> “World Build- <unclear/> [ ? erned ] with the <unclear/> [ ? ed ] process by <unclear/> accept as an <unclear/> reality, a rep-<unclear/> [ ? rid ] that, in Ed-<unclear/> be no more <unclear/> construction <unclear/> remain whole-<unclear/></p>
                
<p><unclear/> entitled “Pointer <unclear/> develops the <unclear/> preceding chapter. <unclear/> a discussion of <unclear/> of which the <unclear/> is made </p>
    
<p><unclear/> appears a <unclear/> set to be “re-<unclear/> that noth-<unclear/> repetition of the <unclear/> will suffice to <unclear/> Eddington’s is <unclear/> A few quo <unclear/> interest in a <unclear/> there, inducing <unclear/> of the book for <unclear/> should be worth [  ? ] <unclear/></p>
   
<p><unclear/> physics is a world contemplated from within, surveyed by appliances which are part of it and subject to its laws.  What the world might be like if probed in some manner by appliances not furnished by itself we do not profess to know.”</p>
                       
<p>“We (scientists) are no longer tempted to take up the attitude that everything which lacks concreteness is thereby self-condemned.”</p>
                       
<p>“ The cleavage between the scientific and nonscientific domain of experience is, I believe, not a cleavage between the concrete and transcendental, but between the metrical and nonmetrical.”</p>
                        
<p>“To put the conclusion crudely &#8212; the stuff of the world is mind stuff.</p> 
    
<p>The mind—stuff of the world is, of course, something more general than our individual conscious minds: but we may think of its nature as not altogether foreign to the feelings in our consciousness.</p>
    
<p>The mind-stuff is not spread in space and time; these are part of the cyclic scheme ultimately derived out of it.  But we must presume that in some other way or aspect it can be differentiated into parts.  Only here and there does it rise to the level of consciousness, but from such islands proceeds all knowledge.”</p>
    
<p>“We are acquainted with an external world because its fibers run into our consciousness: it is only our own ends of the fibers that we actually know; from these ends we more or less successfully reconstruct the rest, as a paleontologist reconstructs an extinct monster from its footprints.”</p>
    
<p>“Nowadays whenever enthusiasts meet together to discuss theoretical physics, the talk sooner or later turns in a certain direction.  You leave them conversing on their special problems or the latest discoveries: but return after an hour and it is any odds that they will have reached an all-engrossing topic &#8212; the desperate state of their ignorance.  This is not a <unclear/> It is not even scientific modesty, because the attitude is often one of naïve surprise that nature should have hidden her fundamental secret successfully from such powerful intellects as ours.  It is simply that we have turned a corner in the path of progress and our ignorance stands revealed before us appalling and <unclear/>. There is something radically wrong with the present fundamental concepttions of physics and we do not see how to set it right.”
</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
