<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="nei.j4c.1.2-4">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from John G. Neihardt to Robert H. Davis, November 14, 1905</title>
<author>Neihardt, John Gneisenau, 1881-1973</author>
<principal>Gossin, Pamela</principal>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2012</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>The Papers of John G. Neihardt</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>nei.j4c.1.2-4</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Neihardt, John Gneisenau, 1881-1973</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from John G. Neihardt to Robert H. Davis</title>
<date when="1905-11-14">November 14, 1905</date>
<extent>3 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 type-written page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>3 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="2">
<handNote xml:id="type"><p>Media: type</p></handNote>
<handNote xml:id="jgn1" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Business</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
<term>honesty</term>
<term>flattery</term>
<term>asafetida</term>
<term>Native Americans</term>
<term>Omahas</term>
<term>medicine</term>
<term>physician</term>
<term>reservations</term>
<term>travel</term>
<term>lodges</term> 
<term>tepees</term>
<term>smoking</term>
<term>horseback riding</term>
<term>humanitarian</term>
<term>music</term>
<term>violins</term>
<term>desert</term>
<term>sadness</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="people">
<term>Davis, Robert H. (Robert Hobart), 1869-1942</term>
<term>Picotte, Susan LaFlesche, 1865-1915</term>
<term>Inshta Theamba, 1854-1903</term>
<term>Tibbles, Thomas Henry, 1840-1928</term>
<term>Fletcher, Alice C. (Alice Cunningham), 1838-1923</term>
<term>Castaigne</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="places">
<term>The Agency</term>
<term>The Louvre</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="works">
<term>Lonesome Trail</term>
<term>Overland Monthly</term>
<term>The War of the Rain Walker</term>
<term>A Bundle of Myrrh</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<person role="recipient"><persName>Davis, Robert H. (Robert Hobart), 1869-1942</persName></person>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>


<revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-08"><name xml:id="jg">Gavran, Julie</name> <name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Keywords</change>
<change when="2012-02-29"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2011-11-28"><name xml:id="ep">Pedigo, Erin</name> Proofreading</change>
<change when="2011"><name xml:id="az">Zeljkovic, Arman</name> Transcription</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="nei.j4c.1.2-4_001" />

<fw>2</fw>


<opener>
<dateline><date>Nov. 14, '05</date></dateline>

<salute>Dear Mr. Davis:&#8212;</salute>
</opener>

<p>I have your letter of the 8th inst, and am pleased to note that you
liked the "Lonesome Trail". I am perfectly willing that you should put the
blue brand on the shoulders of the critter.</p>

<p>I think I was more delighted with the "Second Edition" of your letter
than with the rest. I am glad to have you back me up, for then I feel certain
that you are honest with me. Nothing kills me off quicker than idle
flattery. I want to win fair &#8212; <del quantity="3" unit="chars" /> I'm smart enough for that; yet I do
want to win &#8212; and I'm sport enough for that too. I have ordered a car load
of asafetida, and shall endeavour to kill the scourge. We shall have a more
sanitary arrangement hereafter!</p>

<p>I think you will have some fairly good Indian tales within the near
future. As to the letter from the respectable Indian, I feel quite certain that
Dr. Susan La Flesche Picotte, sister of the late Inshta Theamba, Mrs. T. H. Tibbles,
and daughter of the last chief of the Omahas, will be glad to write you the sort of
letter that you desire. <choice><sic>Sje</sic><corr>She</corr></choice> is an unusually intellectual woman and a 
practicing physician here. I will see her in the near future and have her write you direct.
No doubt you have heard of Alice C. Fletcher, the ethnologist. Mrs. Picotte has done much toward her success in Indian research, and is, wherever known, recognized as an authority upon the affairs of her tribe.</p>

<p>It is generally conceded <del quantity="6" unit="chars" /><add>about</add> here that I have struck upon the real nature of the Omaha. I have had the best opportunities for getting at the thing. I stand in well with their whole reservation crowd, and never lack a place to stay when at the Agency. I am favored with the friendship of about all the Omahas; they take my hand and call me by name whenever me meet. I have sat

<pb facs="nei.j4c.1.2-4_002" />

<fw type="authorial">-2-</fw>
<fw type="curatorial">3</fw>

in their lodges and tepees, eaten their meat, drunk their soup, smoked their pipes and coddled their babies. O, I go after it just like a politician looking for votes. Lately I spent over a week on a pinto trotting about among the brown hills and extending the glad hand to my brown brothers. I love the poor devils. Commercially, I found them dismal failures; but seen with the eye of an humanitarian they are eminently worth while. I can not  bring myself to see fun in them. They have their rude jokes, it is true; but to me their laughter is ghastly- they are passing away. It is just like a consumptive laughing with the rattle in his throat! This explains the fact that I strike the minor chord so often. I say that if one could "set the Omahas to music" (like the dreamer in Castaigne's novel, who wished to set the Louvre to music) that music would abound in minors. Their very songs are minors. There is a pitiful something about them even when they are for a moment majestic, that goes through me like a mournful strain on the G string of a violin. That's the way I look at it. It may be due to my pessimistic German temperament. But, at any rate, I find beauty always written in minors.</p>

<p>You see, I ran a ten months series in the Overland Monthly several years ago. I feel that they were wasted on the desert air, because many of them were as good if not better than these you have seen. I think, however, that you will have some more worth while soon. I have been in a blue funk for several weeks. I dropped down to the city lately and wore that off, so I think I will begin tomorrow on "The War of the Rain Walker". It has been tumbling about in my head for some time.</p>

<p>Enough about Indians. I am sending "A Bundle of Myrrh". You were very kind to write as you did about it. My idea was to see where I <del quantity="2" unit="chars" /> "was at". The "Bundle" has been written more to please myself than anyone else &#8212; <del quantity="1" unit="chars" /> and I sometimes am a queer one. Still, I think that with the exception of a few pieces &#8212; the more "suggestive" ones &#8212; the thing has a little gold in it.

<pb facs="nei.j4c.1.2-4_003" />

<fw type="authorial">-3-</fw>
<fw type="curatorial">4</fw>

Anyway, it has not been forced; it was lived. (Please forget this; I had no wish to betray myself)</p>

<p>Whatever you may think of my "Bundle" you may feel quite certain that I feel much indebted to you for your kindness in the matter. I hope that I may yet hit my pace. When I <choice><sic>di</sic><corr>do</corr></choice>, I will certainly remember Davis.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
					
<signed>Jno. G. Neihardt<lb/>
"</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
