<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="nei.j4c.6.28-30">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from John G. Neihardt to George Sterling, October 21, 1920</title>
<author>Neihardt, John Gneisenau, 1881-1973</author>
<principal>Gossin, Pamela</principal>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2012</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>The Papers of John G. Neihardt</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>nei.j4c.6.28-30</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Neihardt, John Gneisenau, 1881-1973</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from John G. Neihardt to George Sterling</title>
<date when="1920-10-21">October 21, 1920</date>
<extent>3 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>3 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="jgn1" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Business</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>writing</term>
	<term>reading</term>
	<term>human nature</term>
	<term>Greek philosophy</term>
	<term>drama</term>
	<term>plot discussion</term>
	<term>social values</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Sterling, George, 1869-1926</term>
	<term>Rosamund</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
	<particDesc>
		<person role="recipient"><persName>Sterling, George, 1869-1926</persName></person>
	</particDesc>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-12"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2011"><name xml:id="az">Zeljkovic, Arman</name> Proofreading</change>
<change when="2011"><name xml:id="ep">Pedigo, Erin</name> Transcription</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="nei.j4c.6.28" />
<fw type="curatorial">28</fw>

<opener>
<dateline>Oct. 21, '20</dateline>

<salute>Dear Sterling: &#8212;</salute>
</opener>
	<p>I read "Rosamund" last night and found it full of those Sterlingesque images &amp; phrases that I have long admired. You are second to no man in such things. Also, the story is vividly told, and often the drama is tense. I do not object to the violence. The times were so; and, anyway, that objection is for the Christianized to make. Life is full of violence. I do not object in the least to the lust, for it is universal in nature, and I have known nearly every phase of it myself.</p>
	<p>The objection that I would raise is general. I would say that the drama suffers by reason of the fact that the larger human impulses that have made glorious the story of the race are utterly lacking in your treatment. You forget what the Greeks called the <hi rend="italic">ethos</hi> and emphasize the <hi rend="italic">pathos</hi> of human life, and when that is done, the resulting picture can not be true and can not have universal significance. Once, <del/> toward the end, you seemed about to redeem the whole drama gloriously &#8212; where Rosamund expresses her only reason for living, in a monologue. She will live for her daughter

<pb facs="nei.j4c.6.29" />
<fw type="curatorial">29</fw>
<fw type="authorial">2-</fw>

and, hating all the wolves, she will choose the biggest because the biggest can slay the rest. I could wish that note had been struck earlier in the drama, for there is the real motive power in Rosamund's character. Had this come earlier &amp; been allowed to run as an undertone throughout the drama, the whole thing would have been lifted to sublimity, and you would have had something with which to <hi rend="underline">contrast</hi> mere lechery &amp; blood-letting.</p>
      <p>You will note that these larger human motives, of which Rosamund's belated attitude toward her daughter &amp; her male pursuers is an example, are always social in character; while the attitudes that are dominant in the play as it stands are conspicuously <hi rend="italic">anti-social</hi>. I am in no way thinking of giving a Puritanic twist to the action. Damn Puritans! But human nature <hi rend="italic">is</hi> in the last analysis glorious. Your Rosamund is fundamentally glorious, but not because she had a body that men saw was a "golden lily". Rather, because, by your own belated hint, there was something in her bigger than the love of self. That something, as I see it, should by natural right have been the determining element in the drama, progressively developed.</p>

<pb facs="nei.j4c.6.30_0001a" />
<fw type="curatorial">30</fw>
<fw type="authorial">-3-</fw>

      <p>Of course, our difference of viewpoint arises from a fundamental difference in life philosophy. You are in many ways temperamentally anarchistic, while I am by nature socialistic, believing that the only real values are social values after all and that the individual counts only as he contributes to and furthers social process, or the reverse. You won't take any offense, I know; for surely you are aware that in in many important ways I hold you second to no one now writing poetry.</p> 

<closer>
<salute>Affectionately,</salute>

<signed>Jno.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
