<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00086">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ascent of Mount Popocatapetl</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00086</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Twenty-Nine Newspaper and Magazine Items</title>
                    <idno type="callno">MS 4to 188</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1854-03-23" notAfter="1892-03-26">After March 23, 1854</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Unknown author</author>
                    <title level="a">Ascent of Mount Popocatapetl</title>
                    <title level="j">New York Daily Tribune</title>
                    <date when="1854-03-23">23 March 1854</date>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue">4034</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">5</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-01-22">corrected image name</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2011-10-06">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-07-01">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-10-03">Checked bibliographical information.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-11-01">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00086.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab><handShift new="#h2"/><milestone unit="unknown" rend="horbar-short-center"/></ab>
            <ab rend="centered, italic">ASCENT OF MOUNT POPOCATAPETL.</ab>
            <milestone unit="unknown" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <p>The following is an extract of a letter published in an
            English paper, from the Hon. Gerard Noel, M. P., dated
            Mexico, Jan. 2, 1854, and describing his successful attempt
            to ascend Popocatapetl in the depth of winter:</p>
            <p>"I returned yesterday from an expedition to Popocatapetl,
            the highest mountain in North America—17,000 feet
            above the level of the sea. I believe there is no record
            of an ascent before at this season of the year, although it
            has been frequently done in May and June. The first
            night of our ascent we slept at a hut at the line where
            vegetation ceases and perpetual snow commences, and
            at 5¼ the next morning we started for the summit, one of
            the guides leading. At 8 o'clock I found myself one hundred
            yards ahead of the rest of the party, (consisting of
            four,) at 9 out of sight of the party altogether, and at 11
            o'clock I reached the crater. The crater is a vast basin,
            three miles in circumference and 900 feet deep; in some
            parts perpendicular, in others great masses of projecting
            rock form bold and stupendous outlines, with enormous
            icicles hanging from every point. The volcano itself has
            long since ceased to show any signs of eruption. I began
            to feel very much numbed with the cold, and my eyes
            suffered a good deal from the glare of the snow. I should
            have been very glad of something to eat, having had
            nothing but a cup of coffee and a biscuit before leaving
            the hut; but the guide who carried the breakfast had
            remained (the ruffian!) with the others, who had not
            come up. Having examined the crater for about a quarter
            of an hour, I told the guide who had persevered with
            me to lead the way up to the top. The fellow declared it
            was impossible; but not intending, as you may imagine,
            to give it up (having come so far) without any push, I
            started for the top alone. I was now only able to take three
            steps at a time without stopping, as my legs began to give
            way, and I had oppression of the head and chest. A little
            after 1 P. M. I reached the top, and enjoyed one of the
            finest views conceivable of the great valley of Mexico,
            and looking down on the twin volcano (I forget the Mexican
            name, but in English it means the White Lady, from
            its top resembling a woman lying in full length) seemingly
            miles below me, but actually only about 2,000 feet.
            The cold was too intense for me to remain more than ten
            minutes at the top, and I commmenced the descent to the
            crater. By this time the mountain was enveloped in
            clouds, and I could see nothing distinctly, so I commenced
            a further descent, and in a few moments came in sight of
            the pole of Mr. S—e (one of my <hi rend="italic">compagnons de voyage</hi>,)
            and soon after of himself, lying down, black in the face,
            and wishing to be let alone to die. A little lower down I
            saw Mr. C—d, rolling about like a drunken man, but
            still, with undoubted pluck, struggling toward the summit
            at the rate of about a yard in three minutes. However
            after a little rest and encouragement, they both rallied,
            and I returned with them as far as the crater, but no human
            effort could get them any higher. I attribute my being
            able to reach the top to my wind; I never felt want
            of breath at any time, while the others blew like porpoises.
            In our descent from the crater we encountered the only
            real danger. At first the snow was good walking, but as
            we came lower, where the sun makes a sheet of ice of the
            surface of the snow, it became so slippery that we frequently
            lost our footing, and if, after a slip, you get so
            much impetus that you can't stop yourself, the certainty
            is that you arrive at the bottom in much the same condition
            as the man who jumped off the monument. At one
            time I almost gave myself up. However, no accident did
            happen, though it makes me creep to think of the slide I
            took. At five P. M., with my hands cut to bits, my nails
            worn to the quick with holding on, I reached the hut and
            there got my breakfast, glad to think it was over, as hungry
            as fourteen hours' abstinence and battling with 17,000
            feet of mountain snow and ice could make me. One of
            my eyes is completely 'bunged up,' the other just enables
            me to see to write this. My face is a mass of raw flesh
            and blisters; but I have the satisfaction of having perched
            upon a higher mountain than exists in Europe, and climbed
            2,500 feet nearer to heaven than Albert Smith."</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" rend="vertical">Tribune March 23<choice><orig>d</orig><reg>rd</reg></choice> '54</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>