<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00055">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Lessing's Laocoön</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="JDW">J.D.W.</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Sussman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00055</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Magazine Articles and Clippings</title>
                    <idno type="callno">Frey Bibl. III, p. 71</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1851-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After January 1, 1851</date>                   
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                 <author>J.D.W.</author>
                 <title level="a">Lessing's Laocoön</title>
                 <title level="j">American Whig Review</title>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Wiley and Putnam</publisher>
                 <date>January 1851</date>  
                 <biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                 <biblScope type="pp">21&#8211;26</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="brown-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#jdw" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ss" when="2011-12-09">Transcribed.</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2011-12-10">Encoded.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-09-23">Encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-09-24">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-11-07">Checked and revised bibliographical information.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-01-06">Changed cbs.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-03-10">Checked for footnotes.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-10-26">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00055.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h3"/>1851.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Lessing's Laocoön.</hi></fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">21</fw>
            <cb/>
            <p>excites no desire that it does not satisfy. 
                Strictly artistic groups of statuary should 
                then require no label or explanation to make 
                them agreeable and instructive. A sleeping 
                infant, in marble, requires no text nor comment 
                to enhance its value. A blind beggar 
                led by a child stands for the natural symbol 
                of certain truly divine sentiments—innocence, 
                humility, submission to the will of 
                God, and dutifulness. And surely, if the 
                statuary has <hi rend="italic">expressed</hi> all these in his group, 
                it needs no label nor explanation, no quotation 
                from Marmontel, to enhance its value. 
                If in any particular the ancients have excelled 
                us, it is in this, that their artists represented 
                sublime and constant emotions, such 
                as are in themselves complete. The statue 
                of Niobe weeping over her children represents 
                the instant access of a grief, which at 
                once annihilates and replaces all other emotions, 
                which pervades the whole mind and 
                the whole body, which is actionless through 
                despair, and, therefore, representable in the 
                marble. A grief without remedy, and therefore 
                without irritation ; for it is the incompleteness 
                of sorrow, the tincture of a lingering 
                hope, that inspires it and leads to vehement 
                action.  In general the art of the 
                statuary leads him to prefer a sublime or 
                extremely pathetic subject, and for the very 
                reason assigned : the quiet vision of the 
                enthusiast, whose open eyes behold only 
                spiritual things, and whose body sleeps in 
                apathy while the spirit is exalted, is representable 
                in the marble. The countenance of 
                the sage or grave philosopher is more <choice><sic>beautifuiful</sic><reg>beautiful</reg></choice> 
                in marble than in life, perhaps for 
                the very reason that the spirit of mere wisdom 
                partakes more of acquiescence and submission 
                than of action. The famous statue of 
                the Listening Slave, so called, but by Winkelman 
                otherwise designated, represents another 
                species of rest, that of cunning and 
                expectation. The Dying Gladiator, the Apollo 
                Belvidere, the Hercules in Apotheosis, the 
                Medician Venus, the very Caryatides—statues 
                in the places of pillars—serve to illustrate 
                the art of antiquity, and to show the superiority 
                of judgment of the statuaries of 
                Greece over those of later days. They knew 
                the limits of their art, what it could and 
                what it could not express, and they seldom 
                attempted anything beyond those limits. 
                Their bas-reliefs encroach a little upon the 
                province of painting, but not essentially upon 
                that of poetry. From their eminent successes 
                <cb/>and the universal admiration which attends 
                their works, we are forced to concede 
                them the highest praise of criticism, which 
                is that they knew, <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, how to choose the 
                highest subjects that could be executed in 
                marble; and <hi rend="italic">second</hi>, that they carried their 
                execution to a degree unsurpassed by those 
                who have come after them.</p> 
            <p>In illustrating the difference between the 
                artist and the poet, Lessing gives us a beautiful 
                example in the picture of Pandarus, from 
                the Fourth Book of the Iliad, which picture, 
                he says, is one of the most finished and most 
                illusive in the whole poem:—</p> 
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written">"Each moment is delineated, from the grasping 
                of the bow to the flight of the arrow ; and these 
                moments are all so closely connected, and yet so 
                distinct one from another, were we unacquainted 
                with the use of the bow, we might learn it from 
                this picture alone.  We see Pandarus drawing 
                forth his bow; he fastens it on the string, opens his 
                quiver, and chooses a new and well-feathered 
                arrow. He adjusts the arrow to the string, and 
                draws back the string with the channelled end of 
                the arrow, till they come in contact with his breast, 
                while the iron end of the arrow approaches the bow. 
                The large rounded bow now strikes asunder with 
                a mighty noise, the string vibrates with a ringing 
                sound, off springs the arrow, and flies swiftly to its 
                mark."</q></p>
            <p>This series of actions would require a 
                dozen different statues, set in order, for their 
                representation. Homer paints them in a 
                paragraph. He does not describe the bow, 
                nor the arrow, nor the person of the archer—
                these he leaves to imagination, aided by experience; 
                but he gives us the series of actions 
                performed by these, tending all to the accomplishment 
                of the work which he has in 
                hand—the destruction of Troy, or rather of 
                its hero, Hector; or, if we go still farther, 
                the glory of Greece, in the persons of its 
                kings.</p> 
            <p><q who="Lessing">"The painter can only employ,"</q> says Lessing, 
                <q who="Lessing" type="written">"one single moment of the action, and he must 
                    therefore select as far as possible that which is 
                    at once expressive of the past and pregnant with 
                    the future. In like manner the poet, in his consecutive 
                    imitations, can employ but one single attribute 
                    of bodies, and must, therefore, select that 
                    which awakens the most sensible image of the 
                    body, under that particular aspect which he has 
                    chosen to represent. On this principle is founded 
                    the rule of unity in the pictorial or descriptive 
                    epithets of the poet, and of parsimony in his delineations 
                    of bodily objects."</q></p> 
            <p>We see that the unity of poetry is a unity 
                of progress toward a certain end,—the rise, 
                the culmination, and the catastrophe of a 
                single passion in a single individual, reflected
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00055.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">22</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Lessing's Lacoön.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">Jan.</fw>
                <cb/>
                in the inferior members of the group 
                that move with him. And this rule of unity 
                holds throughout the entire range of poetic 
                art, from the point of the epigram, and the 
                single thought of the sonnet, even to the 
                sublime passion of the ode, and the glory 
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>and the majestic ambition of the epic, in 
                which the entire force of human character, 
                in one or in a few persons, is concentrated 
                for a series of years upon the attainment of a 
                single purpose. But this rule of unity, as it 
                appears in the trunk and larger proportions, 
                so carries itself into the minutest leaves, the 
                very <hi rend="italic">if's</hi> and <hi rend="italic">and's</hi> of a vitally organized 
                poem. Every word should have a vital connection 
                with every other in the entire work, 
                and every word should express, or assist in 
                expressing, an act which is a part of the entire 
                action, the whole, together and apart, 
                having a defined and certain aim; and thus 
                all disputes about the unities are set at 
                naught by the very nature and necessity of 
                art.<anchor xml:id="s2"/></p>
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written">"Such principles as I have expressed,"</q> says 
                Lessing, <q who="Lessing" type="written">"will alone enable us to define and explain 
                    the grandeur of Homer's style, as well as to 
                    estimate as it deserves the opposite practice of so 
                    many modern poets, who vainly seek to compete 
                    with the painter on a point on which they must of 
                    necessity be surpassed by him. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">I find that Homer 
                        paints nothing but <hi rend="italic">progressive actions,</hi> and each 
                        body, each individual thing which he introduces, 
                        he delineates only on account of the part it bears 
                        in these actions,</hi> and even then in general with 
                    but a single trait. Is it then surprising that the 
                    painter can find little or nothing to do where 
                    Homer has employed his powers of delineation, 
                    and that the only field he can find to work on is 
                    where the story brings together a number of beautiful 
                    bodies in fine positions, and within a space 
                    advantageous to art, however slight the poet's delineation 
                    of all these circumstances may be?"</q></p> 
            <p>Lessing proceeds to illustrate this great 
                discovery, which, if a new school of constructive 
                art shall ever arise in this country, must 
                be taken as its corner-stone, and in defiance 
                of that abominable miscellaneousness and 
                confusion of purpose which characterize the 
                modern school, by certain well chosen examples 
                from Homer. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1" xml:id="u1">Thus Homer characterizes 
                    the ship by a single trait—the black 
                    <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1" target="#u1">☞</note>ship, or, the hollow ship; but of the embarkation, 
                    the sailing, and the landing, he 
                    draws a highly finished picture, because they 
                    are <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>, or rather a single action, whose 
                    successions belong to poetry.</hi> If it becomes 
                necessary for Homer to fix our view longer 
                than usual on a single object, even then it 
                will be found that no picture is presented 
                <cb/>
                which the painter could follow with his 
                pencil.</p> 
            <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" from="#s3" to="#s4" xml:id="s3"/><q who="Lessing" type="written"><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">"He contrives, by numberless artifices, to place 
                this single object in a series of successive movements, 
                each of which exhibits it under a different 
                aspect,</hi> and in the <hi rend="italic">last</hi> of which the painter must 
                wait to see it before he can fully exhibit what has 
                been described by the poet. For instance, if Homer 
                wishes to delineate the car of Juno, he makes 
                Hebe put it together, bit by bit, before our eyes; 
                we see the wheels, the axles, the seat of the car, 
                the braces and the reins, not so much in actual 
                combination, as in the progress of combination, under 
                the hands of Hebe: the wheels are the only 
                part on which Homer bestows more than one trait, 
                delineating the eight brazen spokes, the golden 
                circles, the bands of brass, and the silver naves, 
                each separately and particularly. One would 
                almost be inclined to think that the poet had 
                chosen to dwell so much longer on the wheels 
                than the other parts, out of deference to the more 
                important service required from them in reality."</q><anchor xml:id="s4"/></p>
            <q who="Homer" type="written"><lg type="linegroup"><l>"Bright Hebe waits; by Hebe ever young,</l>
                <l>The whirling wheels are to the chariot hung.</l>
                <l>On the bright axle turns the bidden wheel</l> 
                <l>Of sounding brass; the polished axle steel.</l>
                <l>Eight brazen spokes in radiant order flame,</l>
                <l>The circles gold, of uncorrupted frame,</l>
                <l>Such as the heavens produce; and round the gold</l>
                <l>Two brazen rings of work divine were rolled.</l>
                <l>The bossy naves of solid silver shone;</l>
                <l>Braces of gold suspend the moving throne:</l>
                <l>The car, behind, an arching figure bore;</l>
                <l>The bending concave form'd an arch before.</l>
                <l>Silver the beam, th' extended yoke was gold,</l>
                <l>And golden reins th' immortal coursers hold."</l></lg></q>
            <p>Lessing's second illustration is a description 
                from Homer of the king, Agamemnon, 
                putting on his dress. We see him draw on 
                the soft tunic, throw the broad mantle 
                around him, fasten his elegant sandals, gird 
                on his sword, and lastly, seize the regal 
                sceptre. Another poet would have delineated 
                the dress and left us without the action. 
                We should have had a tailor's card of Agamemnon.</p> 
            <q who="Homer" type="written"><lg type="linegroup"><l>"First on his limbs a slender vest he drew,</l> 
                <l>Around him next the royal mantle threw.</l>
                <l>Th' embroidered sandals on his feet were tied;</l>
                <l>The starry falchion glitter'd at his side;</l>
                <l>And last his arm the massy sceptre loads,</l>
                <l>Unstained, immortal, and the gift of gods."</l></lg></q>
            <p>Again, in describing the sceptre of the 
                king he supposes that we have already seen 
                it. Instead of a description he gives us its 
                history. First, it is the work of Vulcan, it 
                glitters in the hands of Jove, it marks the 
                dignity of Mercury, it is the baton of Pelops, 
                the staff of Atreus, and, finally, the ruling 
                sceptre of the king of Argos. This makes the 
                sceptre, if we may so speak, respectable in
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00055.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1851</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Lessing's Lacoön.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">23</fw>
                <cb/>
                our eyes; and by such a description, a stick 
                of wood, stuck full of copper nails, is made 
                the significant usher of a line of heroic images, 
                 representing dignity and authority in 
                every grade.</p> 
             <p>Again, when Achilles swears by his 
                sceptre, the poet traces it from the green
                tree upon its native mountains to the hands 
                of the hero, acquiring attributes of dignity.</p>  
            <p>The delineation of the bow of Pandarus 
                is another wonderful instance of the skill of 
                the poet, who attaches to it a high degree 
                of interest.</p> 
             <p>It has long been a matter of wonder 
                 among critics that Dryden, a poet of inferior 
                skill to Pope in the management of 
                verse, should be generally better esteemed 
                by the ripest judges. We believe that an 
                inquiry into the peculiarities of these writers 
                will establish for the elder of the two a great 
                superiority in epic force, in the qualities of 
                action and vital unity. The imitators of 
                Pope and Dryden, understanding nothing 
                of the true vitality of art, imitated only their 
                versification, their antithetic turn, and their 
                epigrammatic point. That the writers of the 
                seventeenth and eighteenth centuries were ignorant 
                of the true principles of classic art, discovered 
                or revived by Lessing, we have evidence
                enough to fill entire libraries, libraries 
                commenting on, and imitating in a frigid manner, 
                the classic unities. Impressed with the 
                idea that unity was necessary to a work of 
                art, they conceived of it as an artificial band, 
                holding the parts of the work together,<hi rend="underline" hand="#h2"> as 
                the tire of a wheel gives unity, and not as 
                the specific or vital principle of an animal 
                gives unity to it.</hi> In treating of the episode 
                and of episodic description, mechanical critics 
                have regarded them as so many ornamental 
                flourishes nailed or stuck upon the body 
                of the work, and for which any other might 
                have been substituted with equal propriety.</p>
             <p>In the correspondence between Goethe 
                and Schiller, of which there is a translated 
                American edition, we find an apparent and 
                continued effort on the part of those great 
                writers and critics to solve the epic and dramatic 
                problem of unity, independently of 
                Lessing, and almost without reference to 
                him, and with signal ill-success. The criticisms 
                of Goethe and Schiller have no entireness, 
                and show the dimmest appreciation of 
                the root principle of epos and drama—an appreciation 
                so dim, the uninitiated reader will 
                perhaps never discover it at all; and in the 
                <cb/>
                 <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top">☟</note>
                 works of these poetic artists there is acknowledged 
                 by all a want of unity and want of 
                 action, which ranks them far below the models 
                 of antiquity. </p>
            <p><span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#s5" to="#s6" xml:id="s5"/>The purposes of art are simple, and not 
                speculative; its materials derived from nature 
                and tradition, and not from excogitation 
                and analysis; and perhaps <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1" xml:id="u2"> it is impossible 
                for any but a people whose actions are free 
                and unrestrained, who have great and national 
                purposes, simple and heroic views, and <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" target="#u2">☜</note> 
                 an experience of life, varied upon sea and 
                land, in peace and war, and through the vicissitudes 
                of calamity and brilliant fortune,<anchor xml:id="s6"/>
                <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#s7" to="#s8" xml:id="s7"/>to produce an original and classic school of 
                poetry,—a people who believe, or incline to 
                believe, that what they think and can do is 
                the best,</hi> saving what their fathers thought 
                and did before them, and who scorn and 
                detest the barbarism and corruption of neighboring 
                monarchies. Had Greece been <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">☜</note> 
                flooded with an Asiatic literature, generated 
                from the vice and luxury of courts, would 
                she ever have produced a Homer or an Aristotle? 
                And will America ever produce 
                great writers and artists who will transmit 
                our glory to future generations, while she is 
                cloyed and debilitated with the sweet and 
                sickly literature of French libertinism and<anchor xml:id="s8"/>
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#s9" to="#s10" xml:id="s9"/> English servilism? Great geniuses may be,<note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">☜</note> 
                indeed, in a measure, self-developed, but the 
                imitative instinct puts them in strong and 
                intimate sympathy with the age, the men, 
                and the books with whom they converse. 
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Let the young poet, and whoever wishes to 
                excel as a writer and a speaker, beware of 
                his company.</hi> If he associates with triflers, 
                neglecting the harsh and disciplinary contacts 
                of duty and business, and if, instead of serious 
                poems and histories, he steeps his intellect in 
                the muddy floods of sentimental fiction, the 
                trifling and sensual, his moral power must 
                decline, the pride and freedom of his soul 
                be impaired, his hours of thought expended 
                in useless reverie or idle criticism; despondency 
                and low despair will take the place of 
                manly ambition. To the inexperienced it is 
                perhaps necessary to add this caution—not 
                to mistake verbal and rhetorical criticism, 
                and classical nibbling, for a study of great 
                models. Sublime and beautiful works should 
                be read as one views a majestic landscape, 
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" from="#s11" to="#s10" xml:id="s11"/> by a rapid and comprehensive glance. 
                Magnitude is said to be an element of the 
                sublime. To appreciate the sublimity of 
                Milton or Homer, one must take in all at <anchor xml:id="s10"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00055.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">24</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Lessing's Lacoön.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">Jan.</fw>
                <cb/>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" from="#s41" to="#s42" xml:id="s41"/>once an entire member of their work,—a 
                secret of criticism which, unhappily, few of 
                our classical scholars possess; for these gentlemen 
                judge a man's scholarship by the 
                neatness and prosody of his quotations from 
                Horace, and their knowledge of the great 
                writers of their own and other tongues is 
                ofttimes more correct than organic; but the 
                poet and the writer who works from a central, 
                living principle, must work from a consciousness 
                very different from that of the 
                analyst, or dissector. English treatises of 
                <anchor xml:id="s42"/>criticism too often resemble a hand-book 
                called the Dublin Dissector, which the student 
                holds in his left hand open, while, with 
                the scalpel in his right, he separates the integument 
                from the muscle. The treatise of 
                Lessing, on the contrary, desorves to be 
                called an organic treatise, because it shows 
                us the vital principle in the living work.</p>
            <p>In the seventeenth section our author 
                dwells at length upon the impropriety of 
                detailed delineations of bodily objects in poetry. 
                The signs of speech are arbitrary. 
                When a word is uttered, or written, it signifies
                nothing to the hearer or reader except 
                by reference to his own experience. The 
                poet cannot describe a thing which no one 
                has ever seen, so that the imagination shall 
                receive it. He can describe only the changes, 
                combinations, and actions of things that 
                have been seen and are already known, or 
               <span rend="singleLine-Left" from="#s13" to="#s15" hand="#h1" xml:id="s13"/><span rend="singleLine-Left" hand="#h1" from="#s13" to="#s14"/>which the imagination shapes from experience, 
                or from pictorial representations. Milton's 
                angels have a human form, speak the 
                English language, and their music was the 
                music known to Milton; their armor is that 
                of English knights, their artillery the modern 
                cannon. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1" xml:id="u3">Thus, in the detail of his work, 
                the greatest of all inventors invented nothing.</hi>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left" target="#u3">No, <lb/>no <hi rend="underline"><choice><orig>in-<lb/>
                ventor</orig><reg>inventor</reg></choice></hi><lb/>
                    was<lb/>
                    Milton</note> He could change, he could magnify; 
                he could darken and illuminate, combine <anchor xml:id="s14"/>
                and put in action; he could inspire his angels 
                with the great passion familiar to his 
                own spirit; he could give them the theology
                and the skepticism which agitated his 
                own intellect, and there invention ceased. <anchor xml:id="s15"/>
                His learning fills out the work coldly and 
                heavily, the pedant and poet contending for 
                mastery; his detailed descriptions of things 
                without action, leave the imagination dull 
                and stagnant; but when he puts in motion 
                the angelic hosts, we hear the clash of armor, 
                the sound of chariot-wheels, and the 
                thunder of artillery—your bosoms burn with 
                the ardor of the fight—and then the poet 
                <cb/>
                seems to be a creator, or inventor, in the 
                right sense.</p>
              <p>America has produced many authors who 
                have excelled in the description of natural 
                scenery. Every one is familiar with the 
                exquisite delineations of Bryant and Longfellow, 
                in those beautiful and pathetic little 
                poems, "The Water-fowl," and the "Loss 
                of the Hesperus." There are touches in 
                these of natural description unsurpassed in 
                their kind. Many of equal or superior 
                beauty are quoted by the readers of Tennyson; 
                but these excellent poets do not describe 
                for the sake of describing; they do 
                not encroach upon the province of the landscape 
                painter; they speak only of what we 
                have seen and are familiar with, and then 
                give us the changes, dramatic motives and 
                pathetic incidents, which the phenomena of 
                nature occasion, attend, or suggest. They 
                combine in their poems the two-fold genius 
                of ode and elegy; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the elegy describing 
                and lamenting past scenes, the ode, interior 
                passions of an instant.</hi> In all that they 
                write there is motion and life, and therefore, 
                we dare say, they are popular and admired.</p>
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written">"I do not deny,"</q> says Lessing, <q who="Lessing" type="written">"to speech in 
            general, the power of delineating a bodily whole, 
            by means of its separate parts; this it possesses,
            because its signs, although consecutive, are yet arbitrary. 
            But I deny that this power is possessed 
            by speech, considered as the mechanical means of 
            poetry, because such verbal delineations of bodies 
            would be deficient in that illusion on which poetry 
            mainly rests; and for this plain reason, that 
            the entireness of the body being destroyed by the 
            consecutive nature of the discourse, and an analysis 
            of the whole into its parts being thus effected, 
            the ultimate reunion of those parts, in the imagination, 
            must always be a work of very great difficulty, 
            and in many cases would even be impossible. 
            Where, therefore, no illusive effect is required, 
            where the understanding of the reader alone is addressed, 
            and where the only aim of the author is 
            to convey distinct, and, as far as possible, complete 
            ideas, those delineations of bodies which are excluded
            from poetry, properly so called, may with 
            perfect propriety be introduced, and may be employed 
            with much advantage not only by the 
            prose writer, but by the didactic poet, who is, in 
            fact, no poet at all"</q></p>
            <p>Lessing quotes instances from Virgil of 
                purely didactic and descriptive poetry, which 
                are only a more agreeable paraphrase of 
                prose, and exhibit skill in language, and a 
                knowledge of husbandry, and nothing more.</p>  
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written">"Except in such cases as these, the detailed delineation
                of bodily objects—without the Homeric 
                artifice of rendering co-existent parts actually consecutive,
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="duk.00055.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1851</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Lessing's Lacoön.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">25</fw>
                <cb/>
                to which I have already alluded—has 
                always been regarded by the best critics as an 
                uninteresting and trifling performance, for which 
                little or no genius is required. When the poetaster 
                feels himself at a loss, he sets to work, as Horace 
                tells us, to delineate a grove, an altar, a rivulet 
                meandering through pleasant meadows, a rapid 
                stream, or perhaps a rainbow."</q></p>  
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written">"When the judgment of Pope had become matured
                by years and experience, he looked back, 
                we are told, with great contempt on the pictorial 
                essays of his youthful muse. He insisted that it 
                was indispensable for any one who desired to render 
                himself really worthy of the name of a poet, 
                to renounce as early as possible the taste for dry 
                delineation; and compared a merely descriptive 
                poem to a feast composed of nothing but sauces."</q></p> 
            <p>Lessing recommends that the poet who 
                has conceived a work in which a series of 
                images are brought forward, with sentiments  
                sparingly interwoven, should change his plan,  
                and make his poem a series of sentiments  
                with but a slight admixture of images. But, 
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">after all, the most perfect descriptive poem  
                must consist of an indistinguishable mixture,  
                a perfect blending of imagery and sentiment.</hi></p> 
            <p>The eighteenth section of our author's 
                work continues the subject. The practice 
                of certain painters who have represented in 
                one picture an entire story—as when Titian 
                gives in one piece the entire story of the 
                Prodigal Son; or as if Cole's four pictures 
                of the Course of Life had been blended into 
                one piece—is condemned as an encroachment 
                of the painter upon the territory of the 
                poet, and serves to show that successions, not 
                in time, but in space, are the proper sphere 
                of the painter. Lessing argues an equal 
                absurdity in those poetical descriptions which 
                give scenes without motion from object to 
                object.</p> 
            <p>And yet there is a certain liberty allowed, 
                both to the painter and the poet. The 
                painter may unite two distinct moments in 
                the posture of a figure. The artist may have 
                the sense and the courage to force a rule of 
                art, in order to attain a greater perfection of 
                expression. The poet may dwell momentarily 
                upon an object, suspending, for a certain 
                time, the entire movement of his piece. The 
                painter may sometimes represent a falling 
                body with effect, as has been done by Hogarth;
                but these are accidental to the main 
                design, and rather heighten than impair the 
                harmony of the whole. Thus, the figures 
                on the right and left of a picture, may seem 
                to be in rapid action, while the more important 
                <cb/>
                figures are at rest. A forest scene 
                may indicate the movement of a tempest so 
                as to produce a perfect illusion, without violating 
                the unity and <hi rend="italic">fixed</hi> lights and shadows 
                of the whole. There is a broad margin allowed
                in all arts for an apparent departure 
                from their peculiar principles.</p>
            <p>One of the most brilliant chapters in this 
                work is the critique on the two descriptions 
                of a shield—the shield of Achilles, by Homer,
                and the shield of Æneas, by Virgil.</p>
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written">"Homer,"</q> says Lessing, <q who="Lessing" type="written">"has composed upwards 
                of a hundred magnificent verses in describing every 
                circumstance connected with the shield of Achilles 
                —its form, the material of which it was composed, 
                and the figures with which its immense surface was 
                covered, so minutely, and so exactly, that modern 
                sculptors have found no difficulty in executing imitations 
                of it, corresponding in every particular. 
                This wonderful example of poetic painting is 
                executed by Homer without the least departure from 
                the principle adhered to by him throughout his 
                work. The shield is epically described—that is to 
                say, created out of the rude iron and brass, by the 
                hands of the poet. Its figures spring gradually 
                and successively into view; the orb rises from an 
                edge to its full splendor. Homer brings before our 
                eyes not so much the shield itself, however, as the 
                divine artist who is employed in making it. <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" from="#s16" to="#s17" xml:id="s16"/>We 
                cannot forbear noticing, at this opportunity, that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">of 
                all descriptions in the ancient poets, those of 
                mechanical and agricultural labor are the most 
                interesting and exquisitely wrought.</hi> The idea <anchor xml:id="s17"/>
                of indignity or disgrace did not attach itself, in the 
                sublime age of the epos, to mechanical labor. The 
                stigma seems to be <hi rend="italic">feudal</hi>, and is certainly the 
                disgrace of our time. Thank God, we are approaching
                a new age, when labor shall no longer <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" target="#u4">☟</note>
                be a disgrace, but shall be dignified, as in heroic 
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#s18" to="#s19" xml:id="s18"/>ages, by sages and poets, with the highest honors 
                of humanity; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1" xml:id="u4">and in the day when toil is honored 
                    and men are free, when they have ceased to 'love <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2" target="#u4">☜</note>
                a lord,' perhaps we shall have other heroes and 
                poets, it may be, even greater than those of antiquity
                —but not while we are cursed with a servile 
                literature, and a more servile art.</hi></q></p>
            <p><q who="Lessing" type="written"> "We see the divine artist approach the anvil 
                with his hammer and pincers, and when he has <anchor xml:id="s19"/>
                finished forging the plate out of the rough ore, we 
                perceive the figures destined for their embellishment, 
                rising one after another from the surface 
                beneath the judicious strokes of his hammer. We 
                never once lose sight of the workman, until his 
                labor is completed, and then the amazement with 
                which we regard his work is mingled with the 
                confident faith of eye-witnesses to its execution."</q></p>  
             <p>Is not the above the finest piece of criticism
                that ever escaped a modern pen—the 
                richest in suggestion, the most refined and 
                discriminating, and with the greatest possible
                breadth of appreciation? Certainly 
                nothing in Longinus approaches it, in comprehensiveness;
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="duk.00055.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">26</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Lessing's Lacoön.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">Jan.</fw>
                 <cb/>
                 <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" from="#s20" to="#s21" xml:id="s20"/>and to have surpassed Longinus 
                 is to have surpassed all critics, not 
                 even excepting the favorite Goethe, whose 
                 subtleties, entitled criticisms, show, indeed, 
                 wonderful observation, but fall short in comprehensiveness,
                 in the place of which they 
                 have often only mysteriousness. In the 
                 criticism of Lessing, the artist finds laid open 
                 for him, and clearly expressed, the rules by 
                 which he must work, if ever he succeed; 
                 rules derived not from speculation, but from 
                 a truly Baconian analysis (with an aesthetic<anchor xml:id="s21"/>
                 guidance) of the greatest works that have 
                 been produced.</p>
              <p>Virgil's description of the shield of Æneas 
                 is treated by Lessing with great severity, and 
                 apparently with great justice. Moral simplicity 
                 of intention is wanting in the work. 
                 It is made a vehicle of flattery. Virgil introduces 
                 us to a view of the god Vulcan 
                 busied with the Cyclops, and produces a few 
                 celebrated lines. He then leads us off into 
                 a different scene; Venus and Æneas appear 
                 together in conversation; the shield is leaning 
                 against the trunk of an oak—it might 
                 have been any other tree, or a rock. The 
                 hero Æneas has already inspected, and admired,
                 <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" from="#s22" to="#s23"/>and handled the arms in a very common-
                 place manner, which only excites the 
                 restless desire of the reader to get him out 
                 of the way, and handle them for one's self. 
                 And then follows what Lessing pronounces  
                 to be a tame and tedious description, made<anchor xml:id="s23"/> 
                 by the poet, of the figures wrought upon 
                 the shield, while Venus and Æneas stand by, 
                 either whispering in a side scene, or with 
                 signs of great impatience, we may suppose, 
                 for the poet to have done with his tedious 
                 ciceronism and cease from making them 
                 ridiculous. <q who="Lessing" type="written">"Homer,"</q> says Lessing, <q who="Lessing" type="written">"makes 
                 the god elaborate the decorations of the 
                 shield because he, the divine artist, with 
                 that high moral simplicity which characterizes 
                 true art, desires to produce a piece of
                 workmanship worthy of his skill. Virgil, 
                 on the contrary, would lead us to imagine 
                 that the shield was executed for the sake of 
                 the ornaments."</q> A degradation of the armor
                 itself, of the poet, and of the divine artist, 
                 Hephistos.</p>
            <cb/>
            <p><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top">☟</note><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" from="#s24" to="#s25" xml:id="s24"/>The twentieth section of the Laocoön, 
                following out the principle already laid down 
                by our author, prohibits the description of 
                personal beauty by the poet, except in the 
                most general terms. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Homer tells us that 
                Nireus was beautiful—that Achilles was 
                still more so, and that the beauty of Helen 
                was divine. "Nowhere do we find him entering 
                into a circumstantial delineation of 
                these examples of beauty; yet the beauty 
                of Helen was the very pivot on which turns<anchor xml:id="s25"/>
                    the entire fabric of the poem. How luxuriantly 
                would one of our modern poets have 
                dwelt on its details."</hi> These elaborate encroachments
                upon the province of the painter 
                create confusion, and confusion only, in the 
                imagination. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The painter or the statuary 
                can alone give us the picture or the statue
                of a Helen.</hi> After quoting an example 
                from the Italians of this kind of description, 
                Lessing draws a distinction between admiration 
                for an artist and admiration for his 
                work. We may admire the artist for the 
                knowledge he displays, and the beautiful 
                materials he brings together; we may condemn 
                the work from its failure to produce a 
                powerful and simple effect upon the imagination.</p> 
             <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" from="#s26" to="#s27" xml:id="s26"/><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#s26" to="#s27"/>Beauty should be described in poetry by 
                its effects alone, by the grace of its actions, 
                and by the admiration and the ardor which
                it excites.<anchor xml:id="s27"/>
                The only remaining topic of general interest 
                touched upon in the Laocoön, is the 
                use of deformity as a subject in art. It is 
                argued that deformity is not a fit subject for 
                the painter or the statuary, but is very 
                proper for the uses of poetry; to this, however, 
                there must be certain liberties permitted, 
                since deformity may be used to set off 
                beauty, oven in painting; and we know that 
                in the department of humorous painting, 
                deformity is employed with great effect. 
                The examination of this part of the Laocoön
                requires a separate treatment; and 
                with every acknowledgment of his great 
                genius, we here take our leave of the author 
                with a protest and reservation against these 
                conclusions of his twenty-fourth and twenty- 
                fifth chapters.</p>
            <ab>J. D. W.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>