<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00164">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Indians in American Art</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.00164</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>The Trapper's Bride</title>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 39, Folder 7</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1856-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After January 1, 1856</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title level="a">The Indians in American Art</title>
                    <title level="j">The Crayon: A Journal Devoted to the Graphic Arts, and the Literature Related to Them</title>
                    <date>January 1856</date>
                    <biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">27&#8211;28</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="type"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2012-01-24">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2012-05-20">Checked, revised.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.00164.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top"><subst><del rend="overstrike" seq="1">Marriage of the Trapper</del>
                <add rend="unmarked" place="inline" seq="2">The Trapper's Bride</add></subst><lb/>
                by a Baltimore artist</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><handShift new="#h2"/>THE CRAYON.</fw>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <head type="main-authorial">THE INDIANS IN AMERICAN ART.</head>
                <p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">T</hi> seems to us that the Indian has not
                    received justice in American art. The simple
                    dignity of his ordinary carriage does not, perhaps,
                    permit those picturesque accessories which
                    are indulged in by mere picture-makers; but
                    there are sublime passages in his history that
                    deserve illustration at the hands of our historical
                    painters. It should be held in dutiful
                    remembrance that he is fast passing away from
                    the face of the earth. Soon the last red man
                    will have faded for ever from his native land,
                    and those who come after us will trust to our
                    scanty records for their knowledge of his habits
                    and appearance. His mighty wrongs will be
                    charged to our account, and the repulsive
                    savage, elevated to the dignity of a martyr, will
                    flaunt in a thousand graces not his own, while
                    the native grandeur of his simple habits will be
                    lost in a glare of picturesque romanticism.
                    Already, he is oftener seen in our pictures,
                    bedecked with European finery, than in the
                    unadorned simplicity of his primitive condition.
                    It suits better the purpose of our picture-makers
                    to represent him in the more attractive aspect of
                    his demi-civilized degradation than in the wild
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>freedom of aboriginal manhood. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Seen in his
                        primitive garb, the wild, untamed denizen of an
                        unknown country,</hi> he is <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">a sublimely eloquent
                            representative of the hidden recesses, and the
                            mental solitude of the uncivilized wilderness.</hi><anchor xml:id="s2"/>
                    But tainted by the vices of his conquerors,
                    clothed in the disjointed fragments of their
                    <choice><orig>habiliments</orig><reg>habilliments</reg></choice>, he is an object of disgust, too
                    pitiable for comic portraiture, and too debased
                    for serious art.</p>
                <p>We all love to dwell upon the Indian's story.
                    Posterity will regard him with intense interest.
                    They will seek eagerly for every scrap of his
                    tradition, history, and habits. We, who know
                    by observation and are near his times, should
                    endeavor to transmit the truth in regard to
                    him. As it is, what with the romancer and
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/>the so-called historical painter, he stands a
                    chance of figuring on the future canvas as a
                    kind of savage harlequin, lost in a cloud of
                    feathers and brilliant stuffs; or else in the other
                    extreme, hung about with skulls, scalps, and the
                    half-devoured fragments of the white man's
                    carcass. All this is dramatic enough, but it is
                    not the truest color of the historical Indian.<anchor xml:id="s4"/>
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Absorbed in his quiet dignity, brave, honest,
                        eminently truthful, and always thoroughly in
                        earnest, he stands grandly apart from all other
                        known savage life.</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">As such, let him be, for
                            justice sake, sometimes represented.</hi></p>
                <p>We should rejoice to see the Indian figure
                    more upon our canvas, and the costumed
                    European less; for it cannot be hidden that<cb/><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="vertbar-full"/>
                    it is the seductive blandishments of the white
                    man's clothes that allures the artist into the
                    portraiture of his history. We have had some
                    remarkable pictures of the red man already
                    painted, but few of them of sufficient pretension
                    to be considered by posterity as authority.
                    A few years since, Chapman's marriage of
                    Pocahontas, in the Rotunda at Washington,—
                    the most ambitious attempt we now remember.
                    Penn's treaty will of course always be regarded
                    with reverence. West knew the Indians when
                    comparatively untainted by the white man's
                    vices. Some years ago, a young man by the
                    name of Deas, sent to New York some excellent
                    pictures of Western Indian life. They had
                    the stamp of being truthful portraits. He has,
                    in a few instances, engaged the attention of the
                    sculptor, but altogether we think, his claims
                    have been sadly neglected.</p>
                <p>Setting aside all the Indian history of the
                    West, how much there is that is romantic, peculiar,
                    and picturesque in his struggles with
                    civilization in our own section of country. In
                    Captain Church's history of Philip's war, there
                    are innumerable incidents for the painter. Towards
                    the close of the war, when Philip's followers
                    were nearly all slain, and his ruin near,
                    the captain suddenly came upon the solitary
                    warrior, in an open clearing, seated on a stump,
                    his face buried in his hands, brooding over the
                    fallen fortunes of his country. Tho generous
                    old captain, touched by the picture of the chief's
                    distress, allowed him to seize his gun, and
                    plunge, astonished, into the recesses of the
                    forest. Could anything be more beautiful than
                    this incident, justly treated, either by sculpture
                    or painting? A naked man, a stump, a few
                    chips, a gun, would tell the whole history of the
                    war, and a heroic man's great struggles for his
                    nation's liberty.</p>
                <p>In the beginning of that war, the Indians
                    were induced, by fair promises, to assemble
                    peaceably in the log cabin church at Taunton.
                    They were seated on one side of the house, and
                    the English on the other, who, after lecturing
                    them upon the white man's religion, suddenly
                    rose and seized their arms. A brief struggle, a
                    strife, rather of looks than hands, and the incident
                    which settled the fortunes of New England
                    was consummated. Is this not a subject
                    for a great picture!</p>
                <p>Picture the group of Aborigines, who, hiding
                    in the forest, wonderingly watched the landing
                    of the Pilgrims. What attitudes for the sculptor.
                    One of them, perhaps, crawling along on
                    his hands and knees in the snow, holding one
                    hand over his eyes to hide the light, and the
                    other by his side, clutching his bow, peering
                    cautiously through a vista at the approaching
                    strangers. Suppose an Indian hunter in this
                    attitude, crawling along in sight of his prey,
                    beckoning back with his hand behind him, his
                    crouching dog, and holding with the other his
                    gun. Here is an original action, unknown in
                    antique sculpture—picturesque, composing agreeably,
                    wholly American, full of lively incident,
                    and telling its story perfectly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The Indian, reposing at night by his campfire,<cb/>
                    or seen in the energy of his fiercest fight,
                    skulking behind logs and trees, stealthily tracing
                    his enemies' path in the leaves and bushes,
                    grouped in council or roving in solitude</hi>—in all
                    these positions, and in hundreds of others, is
                    eminently picturesque and interesting. As an
                    accessory in landscape, the Indian may be used
                    with great effect. He is at home in every
                    scene of primitive country. Picture them
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">marching in "Indian file," winding silently along
                        through the light and shade of some grand old
                        primitive forest.</hi></p>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">Has any poem yet <hi rend="underline">really</hi> <choice><orig> pourtrayed</orig><reg>portrayed</reg></choice> them?
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/></note>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">Would not the Indian, and the full
                sentiment of their life, looks, fate, simplicity &amp;c
                be a good theme for a full poem?—</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.00164.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>