<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03784">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A Sermon Preached in the Central Reformed Protestant Dutch Church</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="JB">Jacob Brodhead</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lcb">Laura Beerits</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03784</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Brooklyn Churches: Marginalia in Pamphlet</title>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 48, Folder 13</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1851-07-27" notAfter="1892-03-26">After July 27, 1851</date>                   
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Jacob Brodhead</author>
                    <title level="m">A Sermon Preached in the Central Reformed Protestant Dutch Church, Brooklyn, on Sabbath Morning, The 27th Day of July, 1851</title>
                    <publisher>I. Van Anden</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Brooklyn</pubPlace>
                    <date when="1851">1851</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#JB" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lcb" when="2013-06-16">Transcribed.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-09-14">Encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-09-15">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-11-07">Checked and revised bibliographical information.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2014-03-15">Updated footnote encoding.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-11-01">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <front>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03784.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
<titlePage>
    <docTitle><titlePart type="main"><handShift new="#h2"/>A
        SERMON
        PREACHED IN THE 
        Central Reformed Protestant Dutch Church,
        BROOKLYN,
        ON
        SABBATH MORNING, THE 27TH DAY OF JULY, 1851,</titlePart></docTitle>
    <byline>BY
        <docAuthor>JACOB BRODHEAD, D. D.</docAuthor></byline><lb/>
    <docImprint>PUBLISHED BY REQUEST OF THE CONSISTORY.<lb/><lb/>
        <pubPlace>BROOKLYN:</pubPlace>
        PRINTED BY I. VAN ANDEN, 30 FULTON ST.<lb/>
        <docDate when="1851">1851</docDate>.</docImprint>
</titlePage></front><body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03784.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
        
            <fw type="PageNum" place="top">11</fw>
            <p>obliged, when they wished to partake of the sacraments,
            to take the long, and at that time, the difficult 
            Sabbath day's journey, to the Metropolitan
            Church, at New Amsterdam. In the year 1654,
            Dominie Joannes Polhemus came from Brazil, and 
            was installed as minister of the united charge of
            Flatbush, Flatlands, and Breuckelen.  Soon afterwards
            a small cruciform church—the First Dutch
            Church on Long Island—was built by general subscription,
            at Flatbush.  Dominie Polhemus preached
            in this church every Sunday morning, and, in the
            afternoon, at Breuckelen and Flatlands, alternately.
            This continued until 1660, when Dominie Henricus
            Selyns accepted a call from the people of Breuckelen,
            and was installed as their pastor.</p>
            <p>On his arrival at Breuckelen, Dominie Selyns found
            one elder, two deacons, and twenty-four members; 
            and the congregration, having no church, worshipped
            in a barn.</p>
            <p>In the year 1666, two years after the Dutch Province
            of New Netherland became the English
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">1666<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">125</hi><lb/>
                1791</note>
            Province of New York and ten or eleven years
            after the erection of the church at Flatbush, the
            First Reformed Protestant Dutch Church was built
            in Brooklyn, near to its present location. In reference
            to this church, it has been most impressively
            remarked, that, for the space of one hundred and 
            twenty-five years, it stood "solitary and alone," in 
            this town.  Forty-one years previous to the building
            of this church, in the year 1625, the first
            European family settled itself at the Waal-bogt,
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03784.003.jpg" type="verso" n="12"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">12</fw>
            within the present corporate bounds of our city. In
            1660, the population was one hundred and thirty-
            four souls: in 1698 it had increased to five hundred
            and eleven.  During this period, and for a long time
            afterwards, almost all the inhabitants of Brooklyn
            were Dutch, or of Dutch descent. But, there is a
            fact connected with the history of its church, which
            is to me perfectly inexplicable, and which, I must
            add, is not reputable to the christian zeal and enterprise
            of our Dutch ancestors.  It does not appear
            that for the period of more than a century, during
            which they had the almost entire possession and
            control of the town, they made any serious attempt
            to establish another church. And, what is still
            more surprising, is the fact, that from the time of the 
            settlement of the Rev. Selah S. Woodhull as Pastor,
            in 1806, nothing was done to form another church,
            until 1837, when this congregation was organized.
            These are painful remembrances; for they come
            over the mind mingled with feelings of regret that
            so many opportunities and so many means of building
            up the Church of Christ have been neglected.</p>
            <p>The other denominations of Christians,as it regards 
            the establishment of churches, are, with the exception
            of the Episcopalians, of comparatively recent
            origin. Nor did that denomination build a church
            in Brooklyn, until the year 1785; for it is well
            known that during the Revolution, the Episcopalians
            were permitted to worship, and they did worship, in
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>the Dutch Church, when it was not occupied by its
            own congregation. In 1785, a small frame house
            which had been erected on the Episcopal burying</p><anchor xml:id="s2"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03784.004.jpg" type="recto"/>    
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top">Get
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">"History of the Town of
                        Flatbush"</hi>
                    published some 10 or 15 years ago,
                    by Rev. Dr. Strong, of Ref. D. Church there.</note>
            <ab>APPENDIX.</ab> 
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <ab>NOTE A.</ab>  
                <p>The mother church in Brooklyn was composed of members of the Reformed Church of
                the Netherlands. Immediately after the discovery of the North River by Henry Hudson in
                1609, the Dutch tooks steps to occupy the territory which their enterprize had explored.     
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="s4"/> In 1613, there were four houses on the southern point of Manhattan Island, now the Battery
                    of New York.  The next year, a block house, called "Fort Nassau," was built on Castle<note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" target="#s3">☜</note>
                    Island, now forming a part of the city of Albany. In the autumn of 1614, the Government
                    at the Hague named the whole of the territory between Canada and Virginia "New Netherlands";
                    and in 1621 they incorporated the Dutch West India Company, and invested it<anchor xml:id="s4"/>
                    with full powers to govern their American Province.</p>
                    <p>It was not until 1623 that any vigorous attempt at colonization was made. In that year,
                    a number of emigrants, chiefly Walloons, were sent out from Holland to Manhattan, under
                    the command of Cornelius Jacobsen May, whose name yet survives in that of the southern
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">Cape
                        May.—</note>Cape of New Jersey Colonization was now actively prosecuted; and in 1625, there were
                    over two hundred souls in New Netherland. Some of the first Walloon emigrants settled
                    themselves on the Bay just north of Brooklyn, which, from this circumstance, became commonly
                    known as the "Waalbogt," or Walloon's Bay.  At this place, Sarah Rapelje, the 
                    first known offspring of European parentage in this State, was born in June, 1625. In the
                    summer of the next year, Director Peter Minuit purchased from the aborigines, the whole
                    of Manhattan or New York Island, for the West India Company for sixty guilders, or about
                    twenty-four dollars of our present currency. Fort Amsterdam was now commenced on 
                    the south point of the Island; and a horse-mill was built, over which was a spacious loft
                    sufficient to acccomodate a large congregation. In this loft divine service was conducted by
                    two "Krank-bezockers," or Comforters of the Sick, officers recognized in the Church of
                    Holland as assistants to the regularly ordained clergy. The first Comforters of the Sick
                    were Sebastian Jansen Crol and Jan Huyck, and they and their successors continued their
                    ministrations by reading texts of Scripture and the creeds to the people, on Sundays, until
                    the arrival of an ordained minister from Holland.</p>
                    <p>The first clergyman in New Netherland was the Reverend Everardus Bogardus, who 
                    probably came out from Holland with Director Wonter Van Twiller, in 1633. Bogardus
                    immediately took charge of the congregation, which still continued its worship in the barn
                    it had occupied since 1626. This building is said to have been situated near the corner of
                    Broad and Stone streets, in the city of New York. The authentic records of the Church
                    at Manhattan begin in the year 1639. In 1642, under Director Kieft's administration, a 
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>Stone Church was built within the walls of Fort Amsterdam. The same year, another clergyman,  
                    the Rev. Joannes Megapolensis, was commissioned by the Classis of Amsterdam, to
                    preach at Beverwyck, now Albany  Dominie Megapolensis did not confine his labors to
                    the Dutch inhabitants, but began also to preach to the Mohawk Indians; and it is worthy 
                    of remembrance that these missionary labors preceded, by several years, the first attempt
                    of the famous apostle of New England, John Eliot, to teach the gospel to the savages, near
                    Boston.<anchor xml:id="s8"/></p>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03784.005.jpg" type="verso" n="2"/>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">2</fw>
                        <p>In the meantime, the first English Puritan Colonists of Massachusetts had settled
                        themselves at New Plymouth, towards the end of the year 1620.  They came over from
                        Holland, where they had found a cordial welcome and a secure asylum from the persecution
                        of their native land.  The liberal government of the Netherlands allowed them freely to organize
                        a church at Leyden.  A majority of this congregation remained in Holland, under
                        their clergyman, the Reverend John Robinson : another part, (about one hundred in all)
                        came over to Massachusetts, in the Mayflower, under the spiritual guidance of Elder William
                        Brewster, who, for many years afterwards performed most of the duties of an ordained 
                        clergyman.  In 1628 a new settlement was commenced at Salem, under Governor 
                        John Endicott.  The Rev. Samuel Skelton, the Rev. Francis Higginson, and the Rev. 
                        Francis Bright, who came out in 1629, were the first regularly ordained ministers in Massachusetts.</p>
                        <p>Dominie Bogardus continued his ministrations at Manhattan until 1647 when he embarked
                        for Holland, with the late Director Kieft, and was succeeded by Dominie Joannes
                        Backerus, who arrived with Director Stuyvesant. Backerus continued to be the clergyman
                        at Manhattan, or as it now began to be called, New Amsterdam, until the year 1649, when
                        he returned to Holland. At his departure, Dominie Megapolensis accepted a call from the 
                        church at New Amsterdam, and removed there from Beverwyck At the latter place, he
                        was succeeded, in 1650, by Dominie Wilhelmus Grasmeer. In 1652, Dominie Samuel
                        Drisins who had been preaching for sometime in England, was commissioned by the Classis
                        of Amsterdam as a Colleague to Dominie Megapolensis.  The same year Dominie Gideon 
                        Schaats succeeded Dominie Grasmeer, at Beverwyck.</p>
                        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/><p>Up to this time there had been no Dutch clergyman settled on Long Island.  The people
                        of Breuckelen, which was then a hamlet about a mile inland from what was known as the
                        "Ferry," were in the habit of attending divine service in the church, at New Amsterdam.
                        The people of Midwout or Flatbush and Amersfoort or Flatlands, were likewise in the habit 
                        of making the same journey.<anchor xml:id="s10"/></p>
                         <p>In 1654 Dominie Joannes Theodorus Polhemus arrived from Brazil,and accepted a call from
                            the people of Flatbush, where a small church,in the form of a cross,about sixty feet long and
                            28 feet wide,was soon afterwards built by a general subscription of the inhabitants of that and
                            the adjoining Dutch villag s.  Dominie Polhemus preached every Sunday morning in this 
                            church; and in the afternoons, alternately at Brooklyn and Flatlands In this condition,
                            things remained for six years. In 1660, Domine Henricus Selyns, and Dominie Hermanus
                            Blom, arrived from Holland. The latter of these immediately settled himself at Esopus,
                            now Kingston, in Ulster county,from the Dutch colonists, at which place he had accepted
                            a call the autumn before. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Brooklyn, however, had now increased to thirty-one families,
                                and one hundred and thirty-four souls;</hi> and it had one Elder, two Deacons, and twenty-four
                            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">1660</note>members of the united congregation. A call was therefore presented to Dominie Selyns,
                                which he accepted, and, upon his installation, Dominie Polhemus confined his subsequent
                                services, to Flatbush and Flatlands.  At first, the congregation, like that at Manhattan, worshipped
                                in a barn  The attendance was good, and was frequently augmented by persons
                                from Flatbush, Flatlands, and Gravesend, but chiefly from New Amsterdam.</p>
            <p><handShift resp="#h1"/><ref target="#note1" xml:id="ref1">*</ref><handShift resp="#h2"/>In a few years, Brooklyn found itself able to build a church; and in 1666, a building was
                                    erected near the site of the present First Reformed Dutch Church. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">For more than a century, 
                                    this church was the only church in Brooklyn.</hi> By the articles of capitulation under
                                    which New Netherland was surrendered to the English in 1664, the Dutch were to enjoy 
                                    liberty of conscience in Divine worship, and church discipline. The Classis of Amsterdam,
                                    which had been from the first, the ecclesiastical superior of all the Dutch churches in New 
                                    Netherland, continued to be the ecclesiastical superior of all the Dutch churches in New 
                                    York, until 1772, when the American Reformed Dutch Church became independent of,
                                    yet continued in friendly correspondence with, the church of the Fatherland. The first
                                    Episcopalian clergyman in the Province of New York was the Reverend Mr. Vesey. He
                                    was inducted into office as Rector of Trinity Church, in New York, in December, 1697.
                                    The ceremony took place in the Reformed Dutch Church, in Garden street ; on which occasion
                <note xml:id="note1" target="#ref1" type="footnote" place="bottom" anchored="true" resp="#h1">* This church stood in the middle of the road 
                                            in what is now Fulton avenue, near the 
                                            junction of Duffield street.— It had a
                                            conical roof, was a round building, and
                                            the road <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">to the old Ferry</add> went both sides of it.—</note>
                                                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03784.006.jpg" type="recto"/>
                                                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">3</fw>
                                                two Dutch clergymen, (Dominie Selyns, who was then one of the pastors of that
                                                church,and Dominie J.P.Nucella,of Kingston,) assisted in the services. After his induction
                                                Mr. Vesey officiated in the Garden Street Church, alternately with the Dutch clergymen,
                                                until the building of Trinity Church was completed. Governor Burnet afterwards presented
                                                to the Garden Street Church, an Organ, which was destroyed during the Revolutionary
                                                war. In 1779, the New Dutch Church, afterwards known as the "Middle Dutch,"
                                                and now used as the New York City Post Office, was converted into a Hospital for the
                                                British Troops.  The Corporation of Trinity Church, as their records show, "impressed
                                                with a grateful remembrance of the former kindness of the members of that A<hi rend="smallcaps">NCIENT</hi> 
                                                C<hi rend="smallcaps">HURCH</hi>," accordingly offered them the use of Saint George's Church, for celebration 
                                                divine worship. The offer was gratefully accepted.</p>
                                                <ab rend="centered">NOTE B.</ab>
                                                <p>The author avails himself by this note, of the opportunity afforded him to record the
                                                names of two individuals who were associated with him for a season before he relinquished
                                                his charge, viz: the Rev. Mr. Thompson and the Rev. Mr. Talmage.  The latter is laboring 
                                                as a missionary in a foreign field: the former is the accomplished and beloved pastor of a 
                                                new church, which he is now establishing on Staten Island. His communion with these 
                                                brethren was pleasant and profitable, while laboring together; and although now seperated 
                                                from them, his prayer is, that they may both sow abundantly, and reap abundantly in the 
                                                harvest field of the Gospel, for many years.</p>
                                                <ab rend="centered">NOTE C.</ab>
                                                <p>Since the delivery of this discourse the Central Church and lots attached to it have
                                                been sold under foreclosure of the first mortgage; and as the property did not sell for more 
                                                than the amount of the mortgage, the five thousand dollars granted by the Consistory of
                                                the Collegiate Church, in New York, for which a second mortgage is held, cannot be returned.
                                                This is a matter of regret. It was reasonably expected that the property would
                                                sell for more than it did, by a considerable amount. But when it is considered that the 
                                                new church in Pierrepont street, erected by the commendable public spirit and liberality
                                                of a few members of the old church and congregation, will accommodate all the members 
                                                of that congregation who may wish to worship in the new church, the appropriation of the 
                                                Consistory of the Collegiate Church, instead of being lost, will be more productive of beneficial
                                                results than it would have been if the old church had been continued. The new
                                                edifice, when completed, will be one of the most commodious, elegant, and ornate structures
                                                in this or any other city. May the friends of the church who have voluntarily made
                                                themselves responsible for the accomplishment of this enterprise, be richly rewarded, by 
                                                the gratification of seeing it soon one of the most flourishing and numerous churches
                                                in Brooklyn!</p>
                                                <ab rend="centered">NOTE D.</ab>
                                                <p>"U<hi rend="smallcaps">NDER A</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">AME</hi>." The new church has adopted the name of "The Reformed
                                                Protestant Dutch Church, on the Heights." This designation and the location which it
                                                occupies, naturally remind us of some interesting events in the history of this place. The
                                                ground on which the church is erected is part of what formed one of the intrenchments
                                                of our army, stationed on Long Island, during the revolution. These works extended
                                                down to the river, and back, beyond Fort Green, and from the Wallabout to Gowanus. The 
                                                disastrous battle of the Heights of Brooklyn occurred on the 27th of <del hand="#h1" rend="overstrike">July</del>1776, but a few<note resp="#h1" place="right">no—
                                                August</note> days after the Declaration of Independence. All around were then open cultivated fields
                                                with farm houses. Over these fields and dwellings were heard the thunder of cannon,
                                                the rattling of small arms,and the groans of the dying. Hundreds of our little army who were
                                                overwhelmed by the superior numbers of the invading enemy, found death on the battle
                                                field,and poured out their blood for the invaluable blessing which we enjoy in peace. God,
                                                in His infinite mercy, grant that this P<hi rend="smallcaps">EACE</hi> may never again be taken from us by any foreign  
                                                foe; and may the gospel of peace, be proclaimed in the "R<hi rend="smallcaps">EFORMED</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">ROTESTANT</hi> 
                                                D<hi rend="smallcaps">UTCH</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">HURCH, ON THE</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps">EIGHTS</hi>," from generation to generation, until the whole world 
                                                    shall be filled with the knowledge and G<hi rend="smallcaps">LORY</hi> of the L<hi rend="smallcaps">ORD</hi>.</p> 
                               <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03784.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                                                          <ab rend="circled"><handShift resp="#h1"/>Walter Libbey
                                                            Magnolia House
                                                            St. Augustine</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>