<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03456">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The History of Long Island</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="bft">Benjamin F. Thompson</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03456</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>The History of Long Island</title>
                    <idno type="callno">F127.L8 T4 Copy 4 Vol. 1-2</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1843-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After 1842</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Benjamin F. Thompson</author>
                    <title>The History of Long Island, from Its Discovery to the Present Time</title>
                    <date when="1843">1843</date>
                    <publisher>Gould, Banks &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#bft" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2012-02-22">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-09-10">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-11-07">Checked and revised bibliographical information and encoding.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2014-03-15">Revised footnote encoding.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-10-11">Proofed.</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-01-27">corrected image names</change><change who="#nhg" when="2015-02-26">completed date information</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03456.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <head type="main-authorial"><handShift new="#h1"/><hi rend="smallcaps">THE</hi>
            HISTORY
            <hi rend="smallcaps">OF</hi>
            LONG ISLAND.</head> 
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <head type="sub" rend="centered">GENERAL DESCRIPTION.</head>
            <p>L<hi rend="smallcaps">ONG</hi> I<hi rend="smallcaps">SLAND</hi> may be described as the south-easterly portion
                of the state of New-York, and extending from about 40&#730; 34´ to
                41&#730; 10´ North Latitude, and from 2&#730; 58´ to 5&#730; 3´ East Longitude
            from Washington City; being <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">in length, from Fort Hamilton at<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">length
            140
            miles
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            breadth
            from 12
            to 20
            miles
            —(in 90 miles)</note>
            the Narrows to Montauk Point, nearly one hundred and forty
            miles,</hi> with a mean range North 69ª 44´ East. Its <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">breadth</hi> from
            the Narrows, as far east as the Peconic Bay, varies <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">from twelve
            to twenty miles in a distance of ninety,</hi> widening in a space of
            forty miles from Brooklyn, and then gradually lessening in width
            to the head of Peconic Bay. This bay is an irregular sheet of
            water, into which the Peconic River discharges itself, expanding
            in width as it proceeds eastwardly from Suffolk Court House, and
            separating this part of Long Island into two distinct branches,—
            the northerly branch terminating at Oyster Pond Point, and the
            southerly branch at the extremity of Montauk; the latter branch
            being the longest of the two by about twenty miles.</p>
            <p xml:id="p1a" next="#p1b">Long Island is bounded on the West party by the Narrows,
            partly by New-York Bay and the East River, and partly by Long
            Island Sound; on the North by the Sound; on the East by the
            Sound and Gardiner's Bay; and on the South by the Atlantic
            Ocean, including the islands called the North and South Brother,
            and Riker's Island in the East River; Plumb Island, Great and
            Little Gull Island, Fisher's Island, and Gardiner's Island in the
            Sound; and Shelter Island, and Robin's Island in Peconic Bay.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03456.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top">area about 1500 square miles—or 960,000 acres</note>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">24</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">HISTORY OF LONG ISLAND.</fw>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left">a chain of
                Hills
                —a spine</note><p xml:id="p1b" prev="#p1a" next="#p1c">Probable area of the whole, fifteen hundred square miles, or nine
                hundred and sixty thousand acres. A ridge or chain of hills,
                more or less elevated, commences at New Utrecht in King's
                County, and extends, with occasional interruptions and depressions,
                to near Oyster Pond Point in the County of Suffolk. In
                some parts this ridge or spine (as it is sometimes called) is covered
                by forest, and in others entirely naked, having stones, and frequently
                rocks of considerable size, upon their very summits, presenting
                to the geologist and philosopher a curious subject of inquiry
                and speculation. The surface of the island north of the
                ridge is in general rough and broken, excepting some of the necks
                and points that stretch into the Sound, which are, for the most
                part, level; while the surface south of the ridge is almost a perfect
                plain, destitute not only of rocks, but even of stones exceeding
                in weight a few ounces. On both sides of the island are
                numerous <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear"><handShift new="#h2"/>very small</add> <handShift new="#h1"/>streams, discharging their contents into bays and harbors,
                affording convenient sites for various manufacturing establishments;
                while the bays themselves are navigable for vessels of
                considerable size, where they are well protected from storms and
                heavy winds. On the south side of the island is that remarkable
                feature in the geography of the country, the great South Bay, extending
                <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2">Bay
                70 miles</note>from Hempstead in Queen's County, to the eastern boundary
                of Brookhaven—a distance of more than seventy miles of
                uninterrupted inland navigation. It is in width from two to five
                miles, and communicating with the sea by a few openings in the
                beach, the principal of which is opposite the town of Islip, called
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Fire Island</hi> Inlet, and through which most of the vessels enter the
                bay. In this bay are very extensive tracts of salt marsh, and
                islands of meadow, furnishing an immense quantity of grass annually
                to the inhabitants; and its waters are equally prolific of
                almost every variety of shell and scale fish, which can never be
                exhausted. Wild fowl of many kinds, and in countless numbers,
                are found here, affording a pleasant recreation to the sportsman,
                and a source of profitable employment to many hundreds of individuals,
                who pursue it as matter of emolument. Indeed, the
                country generally, as well as the markets of New-York and
                Brooklyn, are mostly supplied by the produce of this bay, and is
                a mine of inexhaustible wealth. The bony fish that abound here</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03456.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">GENERAL DESCRIPTION.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">25</fw>
            <p xml:id="p1c" prev="#p1b">are used extensively for fertilizing the soil, and are unsurpassed
            by any other manure. The beach which separates this bay from
            the ocean is composed entirely of sand, which in many places is<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">Beach</note>
            drifted by the winds into hills of the most fantastic forms, and in
            other parts is low and flat, scarcely rising a few feet above the
            level of the ocean. This beach is in some places nearly half a
            mile in width, and has upon many parts, a considerable growth of
            forest, and some tillable land, although less of the latter than formerly.
            Very great and extraordinary changes are constantly taking
            place on this beach, composed of drift sand and exposed, as it
            is, to the continual action of the winds and the heavy waves of
            the wide and boisterous Atlantic. While in some parts much of
            the beach has been washed away, in others large accretions of alluvial
            matter have been made; and at the same time the sand is
            carried onward, so that the guts or inlets are constantly progressing
            to the westward. In some instances these changes have been so
            rapid, that persons now living can remember when some of these
            inlets were miles farther to the eastward than they now are. Some
            persons have accounted for this progressive alteration from what
            they suppose to be the indirect effects of the Gulf Stream, which,
            moving in immense volume with a velocity of five miles the hour
            without diminution or interruption, in an eastwardly direction,
            sweeping past the American coast from the Gulf of Mexico to
            Newfoundland, causes a current or eddy upon the shore in an opposite
            direction; and its materials being composed of loose sand,
            are carried onward by the force of the current, and deposited in
            places to the westward. The existence of such a current upon
            the southern shore of Long Island is demonstrated by a fact of
            ordinary occurrence, that goods cast into the sea near the coast
            will soon be found floating to the west, without the agency of the
            wind, or other cause than the motion of the water in that direction.<ref target="#note 1">*</ref></p>
            <p xml:id="p2a" next="#p2b">The existence of this current, not being known generally to mariners,</p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <note xml:id="note1" type="footnote" place="bottom" anchored="true">*In the winter of 1814 and 1815, the bodies of those who were drowned by
            the wreck of the British sloop of war Sylph, as well as parts of the vessel
            and cabin furniture, were found, in a surprisingly short period after, along the
            beach to the westward, even as far as Fire Island, more than 50 miles from
            the place where the accident occurred.</note>
            <fw type="vol" place="bottom left">V<hi rend="smallcaps">OL.</hi> I.</fw> 
                <fw type="sig" place="bottom">4</fw>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03456.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">26</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">HISTORY OF LONG ISLAND.</fw>
            <p xml:id="p2b" prev="#p2a">may account for some shipwrecks upon this coast. This may
            be presumed, as some of them would seem to be otherwise unaccountable,
            except from a <choice><orig>wilful</orig><reg>willful</reg></choice> exposure of property and life, by
            intentional casting of vessels upon the coast. The southern shore
            of the island is everywhere inaccessible to vessels of a large class,
            <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2">the
            under‑bars</note>in consequence of the flats and sand bars which stretch parallel
            with, and at a short distance from, the beach. This is usually
            denominated the bar, and in some places there are two, called the
            outer and the inner bar.</p>
            <p xml:id="p3a" next="#p3b">The north, or Sound shore of Long Island is very irregular, being
            influenced in shape and form by the numerous bays and headlands,
            and is fortified against the wasting effects of the waves by
            masses of stones and rocks, projecting in some places beyond the
            edge of the cliffs; and where these are not found, the coast has
            evidently been worn away to a considerable extent by the sea in
            the course of centuries. The ridge or spine of the island has
            some considerably high hills, and are seen at a great distance at
            sea, serving as <choice><orig>land-marks</orig><reg>landmarks</reg></choice> to the sailor nearing the coast. One
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>of these, called Harbor Hill in the town of North Hempstead, has
            <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2" target="#s1">West
            Hills
            339 ft
            high</note> been ascertained to be 319 feet above tide water; and another in
            the West Hills, town of Huntington, is 339 feet above the sea.
            There is, however, reason to believe that both are much higher
            than has heretofore been supposed.<anchor xml:id="s2"/> Long Island Sound, a Mediterranean
            Sea, separating the island from the main land of Connecticut,
            is connected with the ocean at each end of the island,
            and affords a sheltered line of navigation of about 120 miles in extent.
            The <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2"><hi rend="italic">Sound</hi> proper may be said to commence near Throg's
            Point,</hi> where the tides by Sandy Hook and Montauk meet each
            other. The course of the Sound is about N. E. for 18 miles, between
            Stamford and Lloyd's Neck, in which distance, the shores
            are rugged, the channel rocky, and interrupted by small islands
            and projecting points. Beyond Lloyd's neck, the Sound opens
            into a noble elliptical expanse, from 10 to 20 miles wide; presenting
            a fine view of gently rising hills and sloping valleys, forests
            and cultivated fields, beautifully intermixed. The water of the
            Sound is generally of sufficient depth for vessels of the largest
            draught, and is free from obstructions to navigation. Its length is
            about 150 miles, reckoning from Sandy Hook to Montauk; and</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03456.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">GENERAL DESCRIPTION.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">27</fw>
            <p xml:id="p3b" prev="#p3a">its breadth in some places more than 20; average breadth about
            12 miles. The force of the current between Oyster Pond Point
            and Plumb Island is very great, yet it is exceeded by that called
            the <hi rend="italic">Race</hi> in the vicinity of the Gull Islands, which, when increased
            by a N. E. storm, is tremendous.</p>
            <p>The Bay of New-York being about 9 miles in length and 5 in
            breadth, has a communication with the Atlantic through a strait of
            about a mile broad between Long and Staten Islands. This is
            called <hi rend="italic">the Narrows</hi>, and on each side, as well as in the channel, are
            forts for protecting the harbor. This magnificent bay is completely
            sheltered from the stormy Atlantic by Long Island, forming
            a noble basin, and offering a spacious and safe anchorage for
            shipping to almost any extent; while the quays which encompass
            the town, afford facilities for loading and discharging cargoes. The
            shipping in the harbor of New-York, therefore, without the erection
            of breakwaters or covering-piers, is, in all states of the wind,
            protected from the roll of the Atlantic. Without the aid of docks,
            or even dredging, vessels of the largest class lie afloat during low
            water of spring-tides, moored to the quays which bound the seaward
            sides of the city; and, by the erection of wooden jetties,
            the inhabitants are enabled, at a small expenditure, to enlarge the
            accommodations of their port, and adapt it to their increasing
            trade.</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left" target="#u1">5 ft
            rise of
            tide</note><p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u1">The perpendicular rise of tide is only 5 feet.</hi> The tidal wave,
            however, increases in its progress northward along the coast, till
            at length in the Bay of Fundy, it attains the maximum of 90 feet.
            A bar extends from Sandy Hook to the shore of Long Island,
            across the entrance to the harbor, over which is a depth of 21 feet
            at low water, which is sufficient to float the largest class of merchant
            vessels. Proceeding easterly from the city of New-York,
            the river has a tortuous course for a distance of 16 miles. From
            the battery to the mouth of Harlaem River, 8 miles, the course is
            N. N. E., and from thence to Throg's Point, E., nearly 8 more.
            At the bend, situated opposite Harlaem River, is the noted pass
            or strait called Hell Gate, which is crooked; and from the numerous
            rocks, islands, eddies, and currents, is somewhat difficult
            and dangerous, particularly for vessels of large size; and many
            serious accidents have occurred at this place. The danger, how-</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03456.006.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">SOIL AND CLIMATE.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">29</fw>
            <p>the aid of a scanty soil, sufficient fertility to yield a rich pasture
            for thousands of cattle and sheep, for seven months in the year.
            With lime or ashes, it is rendered quite productive. Along the
            north side of this immense heath, in the region of Queen's county
            court house, and the settlement of Westbury, are some of the best
            farms in the county, and if the whole of this open waste was disposed
            of and inclosed in separate fields, the agricultural products
            of this portion of the island would be nearly doubled. A stupid
            policy, consequent upon old prejudices, has hitherto prevented any
            other disposition of it, than as a common pasturage. It is hoped
            the time is not far distant, when this extensive tract shall abound
            in waving fields of grain, yielding not only support, but profit, to
            thousands of hardy and industrious citizens.</p>
            <p>Eastward from this plain and extending to near the head of
            Peconic Bay, is a vast tract of barren land, so entirely composed
            of sand, as to be unsusceptible of profitable cultivation, by any
            process at present known.</p>
            <p>The soil of Kings county is in the aggregate possessed of a
            greater natural fertility than most other parts of Long Island; yet<note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="right">necks</note>
            the lands about Newtown and Flushing, as well as those upon
            Little Neck, Great Neck, Cow Neck, and portions of Oyster Bay,
            are wonderfully prolific.</p>
            <p>The numerous and extensive tracts of salt meadows and marshes,<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">salt
            marshes</note>
            in various places, and upon the south side of the island particularly,
            produce an almost inexhaustible quantity of food for cattle
            and horses, of a nutritious quality.</p>
            <p>The immense shell banks which heretofore existed on the sites
            of ancient Indian villages, have in many instances been removed,
            and their contents applied for fertilizing the soil with eminent advantage.
            Upon the southerly side of the island, as well as in the
            towns of Riverhead and Southold, the bony fish have been principally
            used for manure, and with great success. The profusion of
            this species of fish and the consequent cheapness of the article,
            will probably always insure its use in those parts of the island
            where they abound. It is probable that at least 100,000,000 are
            annually taken for this purpose</p>
            <p>There is reason to believe that the farmers of Long Island furnish
            yearly for market a surplus of beef, pork, hay and grain,</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03456.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">REPRESENTATIVES AND SENATORS.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">247</fw>
            <list>
            <item>1st congress, 1789, William Floyd, Suffolk.</item>
            <item>2d " 1791, Thomas Tredwell, "</item>
            <item>3d " 1793, Same.</item>
            <item>4th " 1795, Jonathan N. Havens, "</item>
            <item>5th " 1797, Same.</item>
            <item>6th " 1899, John Smith, "</item>
            <item>7th " 1801, Same.</item>
            <item>8th " 1803, Samuel Riker, Queens.</item>
            <item>9th " 1805, Eliphalet Wickes, "</item>
            <item>10th " 1807, Samuel Riker, "</item>
            <item>11th " 1809, Ebenezer Sage, Suffolk.</item>
            <item>12th " 1811, Same.</item>
            <item>13th " 1818, Same, and John Lefferts, Kings.</item>
            <item>14th " 1815, Same, and George Townsend, Queens.</item>
            <item>15th " 1817, Tredwell Scudder, Suffolk,
            and George Townsend, "</item>
            <item>16th " 1819, Silas Wood, Suffolk.</item>
            <item>17th " 1821, Same.</item>
            <item>18th " 1823, Same.</item>
            <item>19th " 1825, Same.</item>
            <item>20th " 1827, Same.</item>
            <item>21st " 1829, James Lent, Queens.</item>
            <item>22d " 1831, Same, and John T. Bergen, Kings.</item>
            <item>23d " 1833, Abel Huntington, Suffolk.</item>
            <item>24th " 1835, Same.</item>
            <item>25th " 1837, Thomas B. Jackson, Queens.</item>
            <item>26th " 1839, Same.</item>
            <item>27th " 1841, Charles A. Floyd, Suffolk.</item>
            <item>28th " 1843, Henry C. Murphy, Kings,
            and Selah B. Strong, Suffolk.</item></list>
            <add rend="unmarked" place="inline"><handShift new="#h2"/>45 Henry I Seaman
            47 H. C. Murphy<handShift new="#h1"/></add>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <p>The only persons, native or residents of Long Island, who
            have been elected to the Senate of the United States, were Rufus
            King, John Lawrence, De Witt Clinton, John Smith and Nathan
            Sanford—all of whom are now deceased.</p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <p>The following named individuals, of Long Island, have been
            members of the Senate of the State of New York., since the
            adoption of the Constitution, in 1777.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>