<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03445">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="hdt">Henry David Thoreau</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03445</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Excerpt from Thoreau's Week on the Concord</title>
                    <idno type="callno">F72.C5 T4 Copy 5</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1849-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After 1849</date>                   
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
                    <title level="m">A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers</title>
                    <date>1849</date>
                    <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>James Munroe and Co.</publisher>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="blue-pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#unk" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h4" scribeRef="#hdt" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-05-19">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-10-15">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-11-27">Updated bibliographical information.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-03-09">Added dimensions to pasteons, checked cbs, footnotes.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-10-18">Proofed.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-07-15">Made edits suggested by K. Price and schematron.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text type="marginalia">
    <body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_nhg.00228.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <add rend="pasteon" source="#r1">
            <q who="unknown" type="written">
                <floatingText rend="flippy">
                    <body>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_nhg.00228a.jpg" type="recto" rend="col-12"/>
        <p><handShift new="#h4"/>What a contrast between the stern and desolate poetry
        of Ossian, and that of Chaucer, and even of <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>
        and Milton, much more of Dryden, and Pope, and Gray.
        Our summer of English poetry, like the Greek and Latin
        before it, seems well advanced toward its fall, and laden
        wtih the fruit and foliage of the season, with bright autumnal
        tints, but soon the winter will scatter its myriad
        clustering and shading leaves, and leave only a few desolate
        and fibrous boughs to sustain the snow and rime, and
        creak in the blasts of ages. We cannot escape the impression
        that the Muse has stooped a little in her flight,
        when we come to the literature of civilized eras. Now
        first we hear of various ages and styles of poetry; it is
        pastoral, and lyric, and narrative, and didactic; but <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">the
        poetry of runic monuments is of one style, and for every
        age.</hi> The bard has in a great measure lost the dignity
        and sacredness of his office. Formerly he was called a
        <hi rend="italic">seer</hi>, but now it is thought that one man sees as much as
        another. He has no longer the bardic rage, and only
        conceives the deed, which he formerly stood ready to perform.
        Hosts of warriors earnest for battle could not
        mistake nor dispense with the ancient bard. His lays
        were heard in the pauses of the fight. There was no
        danger of his being overlooked by his contemporaries.
        But now the hero and the bard are of different professions.
        When we come to the pleasant English verse, the storms
        have all cleared away, and it will never thunder and
        lighten more. The poet has come within doors, and ex-</p>
        <note type="authorial" place="bottom" resp="#h2">In <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">the geography of</add> poetry there are only four<lb/>
        or five continents—the rest<del rend="overstrike"><unclear reason="deletion" resp="#lmg" cert="medium">,</unclear></del><lb/>
        range among the plenteous archepelag<lb/>
        gos,—some large islands, and countless<lb/>
        little ones.—</note>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_nhg.00229.jpg" type="verso" rend="col-8"/>
                        <delSpan rend="hashmark" hand="#h2" spanTo="#d01"/><p>the nucleus, and that it was not an iceberg;—the practical
                        British reviewer proceeds thus, sticking to his last,
                        "On the 22d of January, afternoon, the Expedition made
                        the latitude of 74° 20', and by 7h P. M., having ground to</p><anchor xml:id="d01"/>
                        <add rend="pasteon" source="#r1">
                            <q who="unknown" type="written">
                                <floatingText rend="flat">
                                    <body><delSpan rend="hashmark" hand="#h2" spanTo="#d02"/>
                                        <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_nhg.00229a.jpg" type="recto" rend="col-10"/>
                                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">386</fw>
                                    <fw type="header" place="top">A WEEK.</fw>
                                    <p>deserve an extra allowance of grog only.</p>
                                        <p>We endeavored in vain to persuade the wind to blow
                                        through the long corridor of the canal, which is here cut
                                        straight through the woods, and were obliged to resort to
                                        our old expedient of drawing by a cord. When we
                                        reached the Concord, we were forced to row once more in
                                        good earnest, with neither wind nor current in our favor,
                                        but by this time the rawness of the day had disappeared,
                                        and we experienced the warmth of a summer afternoon.
                                        This change in the weather was favorable to our contemplative
                                        mood, and disposed us to dream yet deeper at our
                                        oars, while we floated in imagination further down the
                                        stream of time, as we had floated down the stream of the
                                        Merrimack, to poets of a milder period than had engaged
                                        us in the morning. Chelmsford and Billerica appeared</p>
                                        <fw type="sig" place="bottom">33</fw><anchor xml:id="d02"/>
                                    </body>
                                </floatingText>
                            </q>
                        </add>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
        </add>
        <add rend="pasteon" source="r1">
            <q who="unknown" type="written">
                <floatingText rend="flat">
                    <body>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_nhg.00230.jpg" type="recto" rend="col-10"/>
                          <head type="main-authorial" rend="circled"><handShift new="#h1"/>Thoreau</head>
                        <head type="main-authorial"><handShift new="#h2"/>Chaucer</head>
                        <ab><handShift new="#h3"/>10)</ab>
                        <fw type="header" place="top">FRIDAY.</fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">387</fw>
                      
                        <p>changed the forest and crag for the fireside, the hut of
                        the Gael, and Stonehenge with its circles of stones, for
                        the house of the Englishman. No hero stands at the door
                        prepared to break forth into song or heroic action, but a
                        homely Englishman, who cultivates the art of poetry.
                        We see the comfortable fireside, and hear the crackling
                        fagots in all the verse.</p>
                        <p>Notwithstanding the broad humanity of Chaucer, and
                        the many social and domestic comforts which we meet
                        with in his verse, we have to narrow our vision somewhat
                        to consider him, as if he occupied less space in the landscape,
                        and did not stretch over hill and valley as Ossian
                        does. Yet, seen from the side of posterity, as the father
                        of English poetry, preceded by a long silence or confusion
                        in history, unenlivened by any strain of pure melody, we
                        easily come to reverence him. Passing over the earlier
                        <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">continental poets,</hi> since we are bound <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">to the pleasant
                        archipelago of English poetry,</hi> Chaucer's is the first name
                        after that misty weather in which Ossian lived, which can
                        detain us long. Indeed, though he represents so different
                        a culture and society, he may be regarded as in many respects
                        the Homer of the English poets. Perhaps he is
                        the youthfullest of them all. We return to him as to the
                        purest well, the fountain furthest removed from the highway
                        of desultory life. He is so natural and cheerful,
                        compared with later poets, that we might almost regard
                        him as a personification of spring. To the faithful
                        reader his muse has given an aspect to his times, and
                        when he is fresh from perusing him, they seem related to
                        the golden age. It is still the poetry of youth and life,
                        rather than of thought; and though the moral vein is obvious
                        and constant, it has not yet banished the sun and
                        daylight from his verse. The loftiest strains of the muse</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
        </add>
        <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_nhg.00231.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">394</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top">A WEEK.</fw>
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">A true poem is distinguished not so much by a felicitous
        expression, or any thought it suggests, as by the atmosphere
        which surrounds it.</hi> Most have beauty of outline
        merely, and are striking as the form and bearing of a<anchor xml:id="s2"/>
        stranger, but true verses come toward us indistinctly, as
        the very breath of all friendliness, and envelope us in their
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/>spirit and fragrance. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Much of our poetry has the very
        best manners, but no character.</hi><anchor xml:id="s4"/> It is only an unusual
        precision and elasticity of speech, as if its author had
        taken, not an intoxicating draught, but an electuary. It
        has the distinct outline of sculpture, and chronicles an
        early hour. Under the influence of passion all men speak
        thus distinctly, but wrath is not always divine.</p>
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6"/><p xml:id="p1a" next="#p1b">There are two classes of men called poets. The one
        cultivates life, the other art,—one seeks food for nutriment,
        the other for flavor; one satisfies hunger, the other
        gratifies the palate. There are two kinds of writing, both
        great and rare; one that of genius, or the inspired, the
        other of intellect and taste, in the intervals of inspiration.
        The former is above criticism, always correct, giving the
        law to criticism. It vibrates and pulsates with life forever.
        It is sacred, and to be read with reverence, as the works
        of nature are studied. There are few instances of a sustained
        style of this kind; perhaps every man has spoken
        words, but the speaker is then careless of the record.
        Such a style removes us out of personal relations with its
        author, we do not take his words on our lips, but his sense
        into our hearts. It is the stream of inspiration, which
        bubbles out, now here, now there, now in this man, now
        in that. It matters not through what ice-crystals it is
        seen, now a fountain, now the ocean stream running under
        ground. It is in <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>, Alpheus, in Burns, Arethuse;
        but ever the same.— The other is self-possessed</p><anchor xml:id="s6"/>
        <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_nhg.00232.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top">FRIDAY.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">395</fw>
        <p xml:id="p1b" prev="#p1a"><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>and wise. It is reverent of genius, and greedy of inspiration.
            It is conscious in the highest and the least degree.
            It consists with the most perfect command of the faculties.
            It dwells in a repose as of the desert, and objects are as
            distinct in it as oases or palms in the horizon of sand.
            The train of thought moves with subdued and measured
            step, like a caravan. But the pen is only an instrument
            in its hand, and not instinct with life, like a longer arm.
            It leaves a thin varnish or glaze over all its work. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The
            works of Goethe furnish remarkable instances of the
            latter.</hi><anchor xml:id="s8"/></p>
            <p>There is no just and serene criticism as yet. Nothing
                is considered simply as it lies in the lap of eternal beauty,
                but our thoughts, as well as our bodies, must be dressed
                after the latest fashions. Our taste is too delicate and
                particular. It says nay to the poet's work, but never yea
                to his hope. It invites him to adorn his deformities, and
                not to cast them off by expansion, as the tree its bark.
                We are a people who live in a bright light, in houses of
                pearl and porcelain, and drink only light wines, whose
                teeth are easily set on edge by the least natural sour. If
                we had been consulted, the backbone of the earth would
                have been made, not of granite, but of Bristol spar. A
                modern author would have died in infancy in a ruder age.
                But the poet is something more than a scald, "a smoother
                and polisher of language;" he is a Cincinnatus in literature,
                and occupies no west end of the world. <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>Like the
                sun, he will indifferently select his rhymes, and with a
                liberal taste weave into his verse the planet and the stubble.</p><anchor xml:id="s10"/>
        <p xml:id="p2a" next="#p2b">In these old books the stucco has long since crumbled
            away, and we read what was sculptured in the granite.
            They are rude and massive in their proportions, rather</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_nhg.00233.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">396</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top">A WEEK.</fw>
        <p xml:id="p2b" prev="#p2a">than smooth and delicate in their finish. The workers
            in stone polish only their chimney ornaments, but their
            pyramids are roughly done. <span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/>There is a soberness in a
            rough aspect, as of unhewn granite, which addresses a
            depth in us, but a polished surface hits only the ball of the
            eye. The true finish is the work of time, and the use to
            which a thing is put. The elements are still polishing
            the pyramids.<anchor xml:id="s12"/> Art may varnish and gild, but it can do
            no more. <span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">A work of genius is rough-hewn from the first,
                because it anticipates the lapse of time, and has an
                ingrained polish, which still appears when fragments are</hi><anchor xml:id="s14"/>
            <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">broken off,</hi> an essential quality of its substance. Its beauty
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">is at the same time</hi> its strength, and it breaks with a
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">lustre.</hi></p>
            <p>The great poem must have the stamp of greatness as
                well as its essence. The reader easily goes within the
                shallowest contemporary poetry, and informs it with all
                the life and promise of the day, as the pilgrim goes within
                the temple, and hears the faintest strains of the worshippers;
                but it will have to speak to posterity, traversing
                these deserts, through the ruins of its outmost walls, by
                the grandeur and beauty of its proportions.</p>
        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
            <p>But here on the stream of the Concord, where we<gap reason="cutaway" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                all the while been bodily, Nature, who is superior <gap reason="cutaway" unit="word" quantity="2"/>
                styles and ages, is now, with pensive face, composin<gap reason="cutaway" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                poem Autumn, with which no work of man will bear<gap reason="cutaway" unit="word" quantity="2"/>
                compared.</p>
            <p>In summer we live out of doors, and have only impulses
                and feelings, which are all for action, and must wait commonly
                for the stillness and longer nights of autumn and</p>
        <ab><handShift new="#h2"/>winter before any thought will sub-<lb/>
            side. We are sensible that behind<lb/>
            the rustling leaves, and the stacks of<lb/>
            grain, and the bare clusters of<lb/>
        grape, there is the field of a</ab>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>