<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03782">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Report of the Special Committee</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
        <author xml:id="tpt">Thomas P. Teale</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <persName xml:id="lb">Laura Beerits</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName><persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2014</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>loc.03782</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
          <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Walt Whitman</author>
          <title>Report…on Ferry and Water Rights</title>
          <idno type="callno">Box 48, folder 13</idno>
          <date notBefore="1849-03-26" notAfter="1892-03-26">After March 26, 1849</date>         
          <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
          <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
        </bibl>
        <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
          <author>Thomas P. Teale</author>
          <title level="m">Report of the Special Committee, of the Common Council, of the City of Brooklyn, on Ferry and Water Rights</title>
          <pubPlace>Brooklyn, New York</pubPlace>
          <publisher>E.B. Spooner, Printer to the City Corporation</publisher>
          <date>1849</date> 
          <note type="project"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <handNotes>
        <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#tpt" medium="typescript"/>
        <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
        <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#tpt" medium="black-ink"/>
      </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#lb" when="2014-01-01">Transcribed.</change>
      <change who="#tra" when="2014-03-07">Encoded.</change>
      <change who="#lmg" when="2014-03-15">Checked and added cbs, footnotes, pasteon dimensions when necessary.</change>
      <change who="#mc" when="2015-07-15">Proofed.char</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="marginalia">
    <front>
    <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03782.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
      <titlePage>
        <fw type="header" place="top right"><handShift new="#h1"/>[DOCUMENT 12.]</fw>
      <docTitle><titlePart type="main">
          REPORT
          OF THE 
          SPECIAL COMMITTEE,
          OF THE
          COMMON COUNCIL,
          OF THE CITY OF BROOKLYN, ON
          FERRY AND WATER RIGHTS,
          PREPARED UNDER THE DIRECTION OF THE COMMITTEE BY
          THOMAS P. TEALE,   
        And submitted to the Common Council, March 26, 1849.</titlePart></docTitle>
        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>BROOKLYN:</pubPlace> 
          E. B. SPOONER, PRINTER TO CITY CORPORATION,<lb/>
      No. 57 Fulton Street.<lb/>
      1849. </docImprint>
      <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="vertical" resp="#h3">To W. Whitman Esq
        with the compliments 
        of the writer</note></titlePage></front>     
    <body>
    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03782.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
 
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">12</fw>
        <p>that they had a right to use it solely for their own exclusive benefit
        or to exercise jurisdiction or control over it and make a monopoly 
        of it forever; as well as it being of a public character, it was 
        temporary, and being so they could be divested of it at any time.—
        New York has not now nor ever has had any exclusive or vested
        rights whatever on the Brooklyn shore; it is true she has held possession
        of our shore and our ferries for many years, and by far too
        long, and still continues to hold possession of them, but the certainly 
        is no evidence that she ever had the right or any good reason why 
        she should retain it; and moreover, she cannot produce any real substantial,
        legal or honest evidence or claim to any such right. No 
        man nor body of men moves or acts without a motive, and there
        was a double motive which prompted the granting of this charter to 
          <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/> <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left" target="#s1">☞</note> New York. The first was gain, the love of money; the next is expressed
          in the charter in these words: "to prevent divers persons
          from transporting themselves and goods over the river without coming 
          to the ferry, and for the better improvement and accommodation 
          of said ferry, with full power to establish other ferries."</p><anchor xml:id="s2"/>
          <p>Now what right had a colonial governor or any body else to prevent
          any person from crossing the river, a great public highway, in 
          his own boat, and further compel him to go to a ferry established by 
          the same governor for his own benefit? None whatever. To say 
          the least of it, it was an outrage, and a gross, high-handed exercise
          of undelegated power. The East River is, and always has been a 
          public highway, and it never was in the power of any man or body 
          of men whatever to prohibit the people from using it as a public
          highway, and that too, of persons who lived on the shore and owned
          their own boats; it is unprecedented in the history of the world.
          The only object apparently, in compelling persons to go to the ferry
          was that the revenue of the governor might be increased. Again,
          upon what principle or upon what precedent could this have been 
          founded except to oppress with a heavier hand the people of Brooklyn, 
          and add another injury to the many they were already suffering
          under from this unprincipled governor and his spurious charter. Can
          there be any reason or palliation in taking by fraud possession of <hi rend="smallcaps">FOUR
            MILES</hi> of the shore to protect or establish a ferry or a dozen of them?
          There can be no excuse, no justification for such palpable injustice
          and robbery. If any of our governors, legislatures, or any other
          authority should attempt such a high-handed assumption of power
          and arrogrance at this day, and advance such vague unreasonable and</p> 
    <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03782.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">17</fw>
        <p>note by governor Dongan, was the granting a charter to the city of
        New York, on the <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">22d day of April 1686.</hi> In <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u1">this charter <hi rend="italic">one</hi> ferry <note place="right" anchored="true" target="#u1" resp="#h2">☜</note>  
        is mentioned, wh</hi>ich was from the foot of the Breede Graft, (Broad
        street) in New York, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">to a place about fifteen hundred yards west of 
        its present location on the Broklyn side</hi>. The language of the charter
        in reference to the ferry is as follows: "of one ferry and jurisdiction
        all round Manhattan Island to low water mark." This was the
        first charter granted to New York, and her rights are clearly set forth
        and defined in it in these words: "the lands, hereditaments, liberties,
        privileges, franchises, rights, royalties, free customs, jurisdictions and 
        immunities <hi rend="italic">in the city of</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">UPON</hi> M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTANS</hi> I<hi rend="smallcaps">SLAND</hi>,
        <hi rend="italic">aforesaid</hi>."</p>
        <p>Here then, it will be perceived that this charter expressly declares
        that the rights, jurisdictions, franchises &amp;c. &amp;c. do not extend beyond 
        low water mark, round Manhattan Island. This charter then goes
        on to particularize and specify all the property of the city of New
        York, such as the public buildings and commons on that island only,
        and in no part of it is there a word mentioned concerning Brooklyn or
        the strip of land lying between high and low water mark on our shore.</p>
        <p>This charter of Dongan's to New York, like the succeeding ones
        were petitioned for by the Mayor and Common Council of New York,
        and like them also was obtained from the governor with a bribe of
        money, as the following proceedings will show.</p>
        
        <p>"Citty of New Yorke, Att a Common Councill helt att the Citty 
        Hall, for the sayd citty, on Monday, the 2nd day of February, 1684.
        Present — Mayor, Recorder, N. Bayard, Mr. Jno. Lawrence, Mr.
        Andrew Bowne, and Mr. Cerfleck, Mr. Wm. Merritt, Mr. Abm. Corbett,
        Mr. Debruque, Mr. Saml. Wilson, Mr. Kipp, Common Councill.
        Resolved unanimously, That the Governour be treated with to
        confirme to this citty all the vacant land in and about this citty and
        island, to low water mark. The Ferry, &amp;c."</p>
        
        <p>This petition, it will be noticed, is dated and the proceedings had,
        on the 2d day of February, 1684. Two years and two months elapsed
        before any thing was done in this matter, when the following proceedings
        were had which explains the reason of the long delay of 
        the governor in not granting the prayer of the petitioners.</p>
        
        <p>"Att a Common Council held for the citty of New Yorke, the
        24th day of Aprile, Anno Domini, 1686."</p>
        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">3</fw>
    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03782.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">19</fw>
        <p>rights of the inhabitants of Brookland are clearly and explicitly set
        forth and enlarged with additional guards and protection for the safety
        and perpetuity of the rights and privileges of the people of Brooklyn.
        There is a <hi rend="italic">reddendum</hi> or quit rent added in this instrument, to
        be paid by the town of Brooklyn, which neither of the previous patents
        or grants contained or required. This quit rent was merely 
        nominal, and was regularly and promptly paid from the date of
        the charter, May 13th, 1686, to the 6th day of April, 1775, a
        period of eighty-nine years. Here there was an interregnum of eleven
        years, during which time no quit rent was paid, in consequence
        of the revolutionary war. Shortly after the termination of our struggle
        for liberty, a demand was made on Brooklyn for arrearages of
        quit rent, which had accrued during the eleven years. The whole
        of these arrearages were paid, as the following receipts will prove.</p>
        
          <p>"Received of Charles Debevoice, collector for Brookland, twenty
        bushels of wheat, in full for one years quit rent of the said township,
        due the 25th of March last.</p>
          <l>New York, 6th of April, 1775.</l>
        <ab>JOHN MOORE,
          D'R GEN."</ab>
        
            <l>The last one is as follows:</l>
        <p>"Received, Nov. 9th, 1786, from Messrs. Fernandus Suydam and
        Charles C. Doughty, two of the Trustees of the township of Brookland,
        public securities which with the interest all owed thereon,
        amount to one hundred and five pounds ten shillings in full for the
        arrears of quit rent that would have arisen on the pattent granted to
        the town of Brookland, the 13th day of May, 1686.</p>
                       <ab>GERARD BANCKER, Treasurer"</ab>
        <p>Thus therefore, we have the evidence that the requirements of the 
        charter were complied with on the part of Brooklyn, for a period of
        one hundred years. If Brooklyn was not entitled to the water front, 
        why should she have been required to pay for what she did not own?
        <span hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/>There certainly can be no just or legal reason for withholding from
          her what upon every principle of justice and equity she is entitled to.
            In the year 1670 a purchase was made by the Trustees of Brooklyn
            from the Indians, by permission of governor Lovelace, of some lands
            which were in dispute between the Trustees and the Indians, located 
            about Bedford. This purchase finally and satisfactorily settled all
            differences in the town of Brooklyn in regard to their town, and the<anchor xml:id="s4"/>
            rights and privileges belonging to it were amicably adjusted. This
        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03782.005.jpg" type="verso"/>
          <fw type="pageNum" place="top">20</fw>
          was the last executive act on this subject, and any more would have
          been superfluous and unnecessary. These several patents, grants
          and purchases were however, confirmed by a legislative act on the 
          6th day of May, 1691. By this act all the patents, grants, charters
          and purchases were confirmed, thus giving supreme legislative sanction
          and authority to the acts of the several executives. Taking 
          then, all these proofs into consideration, what stronger or more positive
          and conclusive evidence do we require to recover our ancient 
          rights and privileges? certainly none, they are unanswerable and undeniable.
          Let, then, our claim be prosecuted with vigor and energy,
          and the result will be that Brooklyn will be vested with her ancient
          ownership again. It must be borne in mind that up to this time,
          (1691) Brooklyn had supreme control and full and complete possession
          of the town, and the appurtenances thereunto belonging, for the 
          space of fifty-three years, long enough certainly, to establish permanently 
          and beyond all cavil or dispute, her claim. The people of
          Brooklyn felt themselves secure in their town rights during this long
          period, and until the year 1694, when New York began to look on
          Brooklyn with a jealous and envious eye, eagerly watching and 
          wishing for an opportunity to get a foothold in Brooklyn, and in this 
          year they entered into negotiations with one William Morris, for a 
          small piece of land near the old ferry, (now Fulton Ferry.) The 
          deed of conveyance is dated the 12th day of October, 1694, and is 
          from William Morris to the Corporation of New York.</p>
          <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2">1694
            The ferry
            was in 
            regular
            operation</note>  
          <p>The reason assigned by New York at that time for their anxiety
          to purchase this small plot of land, was t<hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">hat they required a
          place for the safe keeping of cattle which were driven to the ferry,
          and oftentimes compelled to wait a long time for the boat, there being
          then but one boat, and that propelled by men with oars, and were
          frequently a long time in crossing the river</hi>. How, at what time,
          and in what manner Mr. Morris came in possession of this land, does
          not appear, as there is no record of his purchase of it anywhere to 
          be found. The right of Morris to convey this land is doubtful and
          questionable, as it does not appear how he came possessed of it.— 
          There are some suspicious circumstances connected with this affair,
          one of which is, that there is no consideration mentioned in the deed
          to New York, which gives it very much of the complexion of a fraud or
          a conspiracy. The following is a true copy of the deed:</p>
         <p>"This Indenture, made the 12th day of October, in the sixth year</p>
    <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03782.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">22</fw>
        <p>This deed, doubtful as the conveyance is, having no consideration 
        named in it, did not extend to the river, there being another piece of 
        land containing one acre of land lying between that conveyed to the
        corporation of New York by Morris, and the East River. This acre
        of land belonged to Samuel Gerritsen, who sold it to David Aerson,
        on the 15th day of January, 1717. On the next day (16th) David
        Aerson sold this identical acre of land he had purchased but the day
        before, to Gerrit Harsum, of New York, for £108 New York currency. 
        It is somewhat singular that such haste was resorted to in 
        disposing of this property in order to get it in possession of some 
        person in New York.</p>
       <p>From this purchase by the corporation of New York from Morris, 
        and the two subsequent conveyances of the land adjoining, may be
        attributed the first cause which led New York to imagine that they
        had a right to the whole of the water front on the Brooklyn shore,
        which contains by actual measurement, 127 acres. New York saw 
        and felt the great advantages which this little plot of ground afforded
        them on our shore, securing to them a foothold on which they 
        might encroach to any extent with impunity. They therefore were
        resolved and fully determined that as soon as an opportunity offered,
        they would make an effort to get possession of the whole of the water
        front. An opportunity did present itself in the year 1708, and
        they were not slow in embracing and improving it, by the aid and
        co-operation of the governor, as will be seen hereafter. Having 
        briefly reviewed the miscalled charters granted to New York, relating
        to the ferry and water front of Brooklyn, it is now proposed to begin
        with the first settler on Long Island, and with him the first grant of
        land also on Long <choice><orig>Islaud,</orig><reg>Island</reg></choice> and trace up each successive one in their
        regular order, as could be obtained, with several confirmations.
        The first patent of land granted on Long Island, was in the town of
        Breucklen, at the Waale-Boght, a part of which is now occupied by
        the U.S. Naval Hospital, granted by Peter Minuet, first Director
        General and Governor of New Netherlands.</p>
        <p>This patent was to Sarah Rapelje, daughter of George Jansen De
        Rapelje, the first white settler on Long Island. Sarah was born on 
        the 9th day of June, 1625, and as governor Minuet avers, he granted
        to Sarah twenty morgen (forty acres) of land at the Waale-Boght, 
        in consideration of her being the first white child born on Long Island.
        Sarah Rapelje married Hans Hanse Bergen, by whom she had
        six children, soon after the birth of the sixth child, Hans Hanse died.</p>
        <note type="authorial" place="bottom" resp="#h2">—a Dutch "morgen" is 
          <hi rend="underline">two acres</hi></note>
    <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03782.007.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <note place="top" resp="#h2" type="authorial" anchored="true">Nicolls's Charter to Brooklyn
          <del rend="overstrike">Nicholls</del></note>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">24</fw>
        <p>The next evidence in favor of Brooklyn is a charter <handShift new="#h2"/><add rend="insertion" place="interlinear"/><add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">1667</add> <handShift new="#h1"/>to the freeholders
        and inhabitants as patentees, and their associates and successors
        forever, confirmatory of the former grants and patents, reciting them
        more at large, and explaining them more at length and more particularly
        specifying and fixing the boundaries of the town in express and
        plain terms, as follows:</p>
        
        <p>"[L.S.] Richard Nicolls, Esq. Governor General under his Royal
        Highness James, Duke of Yorke and Albany, &amp;., of all his terretorys
        in America. To all whom these presents shall come, Greeting:
        Whereas, there is a certain town within this government, situate, lying
        and being in the West Riding of Yorkshire, upon Long Island,
        commonly called and known by the name of Breuckelen, which said
        town is in the tenure or occupation of several freeholders and inhabitants, 
        who having heretofore been seated there by authority, have been
        at considerable change in manuring and planting a considerable part
        of the lands belonging thereunto, and settled a competent number of 
        families thereupon.</p>
        <p>Now, for a confirmation unto the said freeholders and inhabitants
        in their possession and enjoyment of the premises, Know Ye, That
        by virtue of the commission and authority unto me given, by his Royal
        Highness, I have given, ratified, confirmed and granted, and by 
        these presents do give, ratify, confirm and grant unto Jan Everts, Jan
        Damen, Albert Cornelisen, Paulus Veer Beeck, Michael Enyel, Thomas
        Lamberts, Teunis Guysbert Bogart and Joris Jacobsen, as patentees,
        for and on behalf of themselves and their associates, the freeholders
        and inhabitants of the said town, their heirs successors and assigns,
        all that tract together with the several parcels of land, which 
        already have or hereafter shall be purchased or procured, for and on
        behalf of the said town, wether from the native Indian proprietors
        or others, within the bounds and limits hereafter set forth and exprest,
        viz: that is to say, the town is bounded westward on the farther side
        of the land of Paulus Veer Beeck, from whence stretching southeast
        they go over the hills, and so eastward along the said hills to a southeast
        point, which takes in all the lotts behind the swamp, from which 
        said lotts then run northwest to the river, and extend to the farm on
        the t'other side of the hill heretofore belonging to Hans Hansen, over
        against the Kicke or Lookout, including within the said bounds and
        limits all the plantations lying and being at the Gowanis, Bedford,
        Wallabout and the Ferry. All which said parcels and tracts of land
        and premises within the bounds and limits aforesaid mentioned, described, 
        and all or any plantation or plantations thereupon, from 
        henceforth, are to bee, appertaine, and belong to the said town of
        Breuckelen. Together with all the havens, harbours, creeks, quarreys,
        wood land, meadow ground, reed land or valley of all sorts, 
        pastures, marshes, runs, rivers, lakes, hunting, fishing, hawking, and
        fowling, and all other proffits, commoddities, emoluments, and hereditaments
    <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03782.008.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">25</fw>
          to the said lands and premises, within the bounds and <choice><reg>limits</reg><orig>limitts,</orig></choice>
          all forth belonging or in any wise appurtaining, and withall to
          have freedom of commonage, for range and feed of cattle and horse,
          into the woods, as well without as within these bounds limitts,
          with the rest of their neighbors, as also one third part of a certain
          neck of meadow ground or valley, called Sellers' neck, lying and being 
          within the limits of the town of Jamaica, purchased by the said
          town of Jamaica from the Indians, and sold by them unto the inhabitants 
          of Breuckelen aforesaid, as it has been lately laid out and divided 
          by their mutual consent and my order, whereunto and from 
          which they are likewise to have free egress and regress, as their occasions 
          may require. To have and to hold all and singular the said
          tract and parcell of land, meadow ground or valley, commonage,
          hereditaments and premises, with their and every of their appurtenances,
          and of every part and parcell thereof, to the said patentees
          and their associates, their heirs, successors and assigns, to the proper
          use and behoof of the said patentees, and their associates, their heirs, <span from="#s6" to="#s7" xml:id="s6" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2"/>
            successors and assigns forever. Moreover, I do hereby give, ratify,
            confirm and grant unto the said patentees, and their associates, their
            heirs, successors and assigns, all the rights and privileges belonging
            to a town within this government, and that the place of their present
            habitation shall continue and retain the name of Breuckelen, by which 
            name and stile it shall be distinguished and known in all bargains and
            sales made by them, the said patentees, and their associates, their
            heirs, successors and assigns, rendering and paying such duties and<anchor xml:id="s7"/>
            acknowledgements, as now are or hereafter shall be constituted and 
            established by the laws of this government, under the obedience of
            his Royal Highness, his heirs and successors.</p>
            <p>Given under my hand and seal at Fort James, in New Yorke, on 
            the Island of Manhattat, this 18th day of October, in the nineteenth
            year of the reign of our Sovereign Lord, Charles the Second, by the
            grace of God, of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, Defender
            of the Faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <ab>Annonque Domini, 1667.
            RICHARD NICOLLS.
            Recorded by the order of the Governor, the day and the year above
            written.
            MATTHIAS NICHOLLS, Secretary."</ab>
            
          <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s8" resp="#h2" from="#s8" to="#s9"/><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#s8" to="#s9"/><p>This charter, is in all respects confirmatory of the two grants made
              to Sarah Rapelje in 1625, the one to Abraham Rycken in 1638, and
              the one to Jan Manje in 1642, as also the patent of Governor Stuyvezant
              in 1648, together with the several patents to individuals, and 
              purchases by them from the Indians. That this charter grants to<anchor xml:id="s9"/>
              Brooklyn the whole of the water front, and the land lying between 
              high and low water mark, there can be no doubt. Notwithstanding
              <fw place="bottom" type="catch">4</fw>
    <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03782.009.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">26</fw>
            these full, explicit and plain grants, patents, and this confirmation to
            Brooklyn of all these rights and franchises, there appeared to exist
            some doubts in the minds of some of the freeholders in the town that
            they had not yet fully secured to their own satisfaction, and particularly 
            to the satisfaction of the Indians, full and complete possession 
            of certain lands which the Indians claimed as still their own, having, 
            as they averred, not been purchased from them or included in any 
            of the previous grants, patents, purchases or confirmations.</p>
            <p><span rend="singleLine-left" from="#s10" to="#s11" xml:id="s10" hand="#h2"/>The freeholders and inhabitants of the town, desirous of living at
              peace with their neighbors, the Indians, and quieting and satisfying
              them, they agreed among themselves, if permission could be obtained
              from the Governor, to purchase from them all the lands which they
              claimed within the limits of the town. Accordingly the freeholders 
              and inhabitants of the town held a public meeting, and resolved to
              petition the Governor to grant them permission to purchase such
              land within the town as the Indians claimed. At this time Francis
              Lovelace was the governor of the colony.</p>
              <p>In the month of April, 1670, the freeholders and inhabitants presented
              to the governor a petition in which they assign the following
              as a reason for the purchase:</p><anchor xml:id="s11"/>
         
          <span rend="singleLine-left" from="#s12" to="#s13" xml:id="s12" hand="#h2"/><p>"For their own better and more permanent security, and having 
              been at considerable expense in clearing, fencing, and manuring their
              lands.'"</p>
              
              <p>This reasonable and respectful request was presented to Governor
              Lovelace, which he took into consideration, and on the 1st day of
              May, 1670, the governor, under his own hand and seal granted to the
              applicants permission to purchase from the Indians all the lands and
              appurtenances thereto belonging, and on the 14th day of the same 
              month, (May) and year (1670) a public meeting of the freeholders
              and inhabitants of Brooklyn was held, whereat four persons, freeholders
              of the town, where chosen as commissioners, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u2">to treat with the
                five Indian Chiefs for the lands claimed</hi> by them.</p><anchor xml:id="s13"/> 
        <span rend="bracket-left" xml:id="s89" from="#s89" to="#s90" hand="#h2"/><p>The following is a true copy of the license granted by Governor
                Lovelace, empowering these commissioners to make the purchase for
                and on behalf of the freeholders and the inhabitants of the town of
                Brooklyn:</p>
                
                <p>[L.S.] "Whereas the inhabitants of Breucklyn, in the west Riding
                of Yorkshire, upon Long Island, who were seated there in a town-
                
                <note type="authorial" target="#u2" resp="#h2" place="bottom">? subject for a print? 
                  engraving?</note><anchor xml:id="s90"/>
    <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.03782.010.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">27</fw>
                  <span rend="singleLine-Right" xml:id="s14" from="#s14" to="#s15" hand="#h2"/>ship, by the authority then in being, and having bin at considerable
                  charges in clearing, ffencing and manuring their land, as well as building
                    ffor their conveniency have requested my lycence for their further
                    security to make purchase of the said land of some Indians who lay
                    claim and interest therein: These are to certify, all whom it may concern,
                    that I have and doe hereby give the said inhabitants lycense to 
                    purchase their land according to their request, the said Indians concerned,
                    appearing before me as in the law required, and making their
                    acknowledgements to be fully satisfied, and payed for the same.</p>
                    
                    <p>Given under my hand and seal at ffort James, in New York, the 
                    ffirst day of May. in the 22nd year of his Majesties reign, Annoque
                    Dom. 1670.</p>
                               <l>FRANCIS LOVELACE."</l>
                    
                    <p>This license was placed in the hands of the four town commissioners
                    immediately after their appointment, when they proceeded to the 
                    performance of the duty imposed upon them by the freeholders and 
                    inhabitants of the town, by making an appointment to meet the five
                    Indian Chiefs, in order to consummate the purchase.</p>
                    <p>They accordingly met and agreed upon the terms, and drew up the 
                    following deed, each party signing it respectively.</p>
                    
                    <p>"To all people to whom this present writing shall come: Peter,
                    Elmohar, Job, Marquiquos, and Shamese, late of Staten Island, 
                    send Greeting:</p>
                    
                    <p>Whereas, they, the said Peter, Elmohar, Job, Marquiquos, and Shamese,
                    aforesaid mentioned, doe lay claime to the land now in the tenure
                    and occupation of some of the Inhabitants of Breuckelen, as
                    well as the true Indian owners and proprietors thereof: Know Yee,
                    that for and in consideration of a certain sum of wampum and divers
                    other goods, the which in the schedule annext are exprest unto 
                    the said sachems, in hand payed by <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Monsier Machiell Hainelle, Thomas
                    Lambertse, John Lewis and Peter Darmentier,</hi> on the behalf of
                    themselves, the inhabitants of Breuckelen, the receipt whereof they 
                    doe hereby acknowledge, and themselves to be fully satisfyed and 
                    payed therefor, have given, granted, bargained and sold, and by 
                    these presents doe fully, freely, and absolutely give, grant, bargain
                    and sell unto the said Monsier Machiell Hainelle, Thomas Lambertse, 
                      John Lewis and Peter Darmentier, ffor and on behalf of themselves
                    and the inhabitants aforesaid, their heyrs, and successors, all that
                    parcell of land and tract of land, in and about Bedford, within the
                    jurisdiction of Breuckelen, beginning ffrom Hendrick Van Aarnhem's
                    land, by a swamp of water, and stretching to the hills, then going
                    along the hills to the port or entrance thereof, and so to Rockaway
                    ffoot path, as their purchase is more particularly set fforth: To have<anchor xml:id="s15"/>
                      <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.03782.011.jpg" type="verso"/>
                      <fw type="pageNum" place="top">28</fw>
                      <span from="#s17" to="#s18" xml:id="s17" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>and to hold all the said parcell and tract of land and premises within
                      the limits before described, unto the said Monsier Machiell Hainelle, 
                      Thomas Lambertse, John Lewis and Peter Darmentier, ffor and on 
                      behalf of the inhabitants aforesaid, and their heyres and successors, to
                      the proper use and behooff of the said inhabitants, their heyres and
                      successors forever. In witness whereof, the partyes to these presents
                      have hereunto sett their hands and seals, this 14th day of May, in
                      the 22nd yeare of his majestyes reigne, Annoque Dom. 1670.</p>
                     <p>Sealed and delivered in the presence of Matthias Nicholls, R.
                     Louch, Samuel § his mark Davis, John Garland</p>
                      <l>The mark of § PETER, L.S.
                      The mark of O ELMOHAR, L.S.
                      The mark of X JOB, L.S.
                      The mark of ? MARQUIQUOS, L.S.
                      The mark of 7 SHAMESE, L.S.</l>
                      
                      <p>This deed was acknowledged by the within written Sachems, before
                      the Governor, in the presence of us, the day and year within
                      written.</p><anchor xml:id="s18"/>
                      
                      <l>MATTHIAS NICHOLLS, Secretary.
                        The mark of § SAMUEL DAVIS.</l>
                      <p>Recorded by the Governor,</p>
                      <l>MATTHIAS NICHOLLS, Secretary."</l>
                      
                      <p>The following is the consideration agreed upon by the parties to 
                        this deed, and paid to the five Indian Chiefs by the four commissioners:</p>
                      
                      <p>"The payment agreed upon ffor the purchase of the land in and 
                      about Bedford, within the jurisdiction of Breuckelen, conveyed this
                      day by the Indian Chiefs, proprietors, is, vis:</p>
                      
                      <p>100 Guilders Seawant.
                      Half a tun of Strong Beer.
                      2 half tuns of Good Beer.
                      3 Guns, long barrels, with each a pound of powder and lead, proportionable,
                      2 bars to a gun, 4 match coats."</p>
                      
                      <p>In the foregoing deed, it will be observed that the utmost friendship
                      and amity existed between the inhabitants of this town and the
                      Indians, and from this time the wild shriek of the war whoop and 
                      the clanking of the tomahawk of the red man was heard no more in 
                      this town. The calumet of peace was smoked, and all bitterness and
                      hostility was buried with the tomahawk, never to be exhumed.</p>
                      <p>This purchase entirely, completely and satisfactorily settled and
                      quieted all disputes and disaffections which had but slightly existed 
                      in this town, between the inhabitants and aborigines, a short time
    <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc.03782.012.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">29</fw>
          prior to this purchase. The freeholders and inhabitants of the town
          of Brooklyn up to the time of the consummation of this purchase,
          were positive that the former purchases, patents, grants and charters
          were full, complete and comprehensive, to all intents and purposes,
          for their town, and embraced and comprehended all the lands, runs, 
          rivers, creeks and water front, franchises, ferries, rights and privileges 
          within the limits of the town. Of this fact there can be no doubt, 
          and the strongest evidence in favor of this opinion is, that it was the
          last purchase made by the inhabitants, and that no future claim was
          ever set up by any person or persons, to any of the lands or rights
          within the town.</p>
          <p>Certain as were the inhabitants of this of their right to the
          whole of the lands which comprised this town, they desired not only
          ownership but quiet and peaceable possession of it, and to live with
          their red brethren in the utmost harmony and friendship.</p>
         <p>Peace, as well as possession was a great object with the inhabitants,
          and they were willing to accede to any reasonable terms or demands,
          and to make some sacrifice to accomplish this desideratum.
          This last act accomplished a final settlement; and extinguished every
          claim which the Indians had ever had in any part of the town of Brooklyn,
          and all and every franchise they had ever possessed, and established
          harmony throughout the town, among all parties.</p>
        <p>The consummation of this purchase had the desired effect, as it 
          allayed all acrimonious feeling, satisfied all parties, and also produced
          among the Indians cheerful and willing obedience, and a ready co-operating
          acquiescence in the town government, acknowledging its authority, 
          obeying its laws, and in adhering firmly and contentedly to
          the pledges made, and writings executed between them and the freeholders
          and inhabitants of this town.</p>
        <p>Nothing worthy of note occurred in the colony of New York from
          the abdication of Governor Lovelace until the arrival of Col. Thomas
          <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="s19" from="#s19" to="#s20" hand="#h2"/>Dongan, in 1683. The first public act of any importance by governor
          Dongan was, the granting of the charter to New York, on the 22nd 
          day of April, 1686.</p><anchor xml:id="s20"/>
          <p>This was the first charter in reality, which had been granted to
          them, whatever others they may have had were of a very limited
          character, and contained only the plan of the government of that
          city, and instructions how it should be administered, and who were
          qualified and who not.</p>
    <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc.03782.013.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top" anchored="true">&#8212;is this the first
          of the ferry?</note>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">30</fw>
        <span from="#s21" to="#s22" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s21"/><p>This charter of Dongan's <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear"><handShift new="#h2"/>1686</add> <handShift new="#h1"/>" establishes one ferry to Long Island,
        which is the only matter in it which interests Brooklyn, and is in these
        words: "and have established and settled one ferry from the said
        city of New York to Long Island, for the accommodation and conveniency
        of passengers, the said citizens and travellers."</p>
        <p>The travellers here referred to, doubtless were intended to apply
        and did so apply to the people of Brooklyn, and from the tenor 
        and language used in the charter, it is conclusive that the granting
        of this ferry to New York, was not to that city exclusively, or permanently,
        neither was it a franchise to them solely, but for the benefit 
        of all persons who had occasion to use the ferry.</p>
        <p>This charter also contains a proviso which is of some importance 
        to Brooklyn, being a saving clause of the rights, privileges, franchises
        and immunities conferred on the free holders and inhabitants of
        Brooklyn in the several purchases, grants, patents, and charters previously 
        made and confirmed to them; this proviso is as follows:</p>
        
        <p>"Provided always that the said privileges, franchises and powers
        be no inconsistent with or repugnant to the laws of his Majesty's
        Kingdom, of England, or other laws of the general Assembly of
        this Province as aforesaid."</p>
        
        <p>These two extracts contain all which in any way concerns Brooklyn.
        It will be observed that this instrument grants to New York 
        but one ferry, (and that for public purposes,) but is entirely silent in
        regard to the land lying between high and low water mark on the
        Brooklyn shore. We must therefore take it for proof positive, in the
        absence of any proof to the contrary, that New York had no rights
        whatever, either express or implied, to establish or take the control of<anchor xml:id="s22"/>
        more than this one ferry; and certain it is also, that they had not the 
        slightest shadow of a shade to the strip of land lying between high
        and low water mark on the Brooklyn shore; but the contrary appears
        as regards this right, wherein it is clearly set forth and established
        beyond all doubt in the various documents relating thereto, executed
        to Brooklyn. It will be recollected that this charter was granted to
          <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24" hand="#h2"/>New York on the 22nd day of April, 1686, and at the request of the<span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s24" hand="#h2"/>
        Common Council, who petitioned the governor for it, and gave him 
        £200 for it. On the 13th day of May, 1686, twenty-one days after
          <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left" anchored="true">☞</note> the date of the charter to New York, governor Dongan granted a charter
        and confirmation to Brooklyn, of all the former ones, enlarging<anchor xml:id="s24"/>
    <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="loc.03782.014.jpg" type="recto"/>
       <fw type="pageNum" place="top">31</fw>
          if possible, and more firmly and fully guaranteeing to the town
          of Brooklyn all the rights, privileges, franchises, and other things,
          which they had enjoyed peaceably and uninterruptedly for a period 
          of forty-four years: all former patents and charters having stood
          firm and unaltered up to this time, and the people contented and happy,
          and in quiet and undoubted possession of their town. <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="s27" from="#s27" to="#s28" resp="#h2"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">It was the
          <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s26" from="#s26" to="#s28" hand="#h2"/>prevailing custom in those times with each successive governor to
          issue his proclamation as soon after his induction in the gubernatorial
          chair as convenient to himself, to the people, or the Common Council,
          as the case might be, throughout the Province, and require of them
          to present to him their former and present patents or charters, for his 
          examination;</hi> if they were found to be satisfactory to him, and not
          prejudicial to or inconsistent with his Majesty's prerogatives, or contrary
          to the common law of England, which was the same in this
          Province, he usually confirmed all the former ones, and sometimes extended<anchor xml:id="s28"/>
          and enlarged them, and where he could levy a fee upon the
          grantees he invariably done it and pocketed it, which he considered his
          perquisite. In the instance of New York, however, with governor
          Dongan, this custom (as it was only a custom, there being no law, 
          authority, or right for it, other than the tyrranny and avarice of the
          governor,) was not adhered to for the reason that the Common Council 
          <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s91" from="#s91" to="#s92"/>of New York did not give the governor time to issue his proclamation
          to them. The Common Council of New York anticipated the
          governor by passing a resolution, and appointing a committee with 
          power to offer the governor £200 for a charter. The committee presented
          to his excellency a copy of the resolution, and he told the
          committee that he would take time to consider it.</p>       
              <p>This proposition was agreed to, and in a few days the committee
                again waited upon the governor and presented to him the £200 when<anchor xml:id="s92"/>
              the governor handed over the charter to the committee. The reason 
              may easily be conceived why the Common Council of New York 
              were in such haste for a charter, and why they were so willing to give
              the price required for it. It is obvious, also, as the subsequent acts
              of this same Common Council upon the subject of charters, uncontradictorily 
              and plainly prove that they were fearful they would not
              be able to obtain a charter which would suit them, if they did not
              hold out some tangible inducement in the form of money. Such 
              transactions can be considered in no other light than as bribes. Not
              so, however, with Brooklyn; they were contented and satisfied with
              the various patents, purchases, and charters which they had of their
    <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="loc.03782.015.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">32</fw>
                town, and had no desire to enlarge their dominions, except by an
                honest, open, straightforward course, rendering a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>
                for all the newly acquired territory or privileges which might be desired
                by them, or conferred upon them. Their principle and their
                maxim was, L<hi rend="smallcaps">ET US ALONE</hi>. The freeholders and inhabitants of
                Brooklyn waited patiently and unconcernedly until the governor required 
                of them the surrender of their old charters, and gave them a 
                new one, confirming all the previous ones. Neither did they offer or 
                give to the governor anything whatever for their charter, nor did the
                governor demand anything. The just and equitable conclusion is 
                therefore, that the governor granted nothing to Brooklyn but what
                clearly and indisputably belonged to them, and which could not except
                by fraud, deception, or chicane be taken away from them.</p>
                <p>The charter and confirmation granted by governor Dongan to 
                Brooklyn, is of a very important character, inasmuch as it is a full,
                explicit and ample grant, embracing the whole town of Brooklyn,
                and all the privileges, franchises, rivers, ferries, and all other things
                appertaining to the town, and confirming and ratifying all previous 
                ones. This charter to Brooklyn is of such vital and great importance
                to us that it is deemed advisable to copy it at full length, as upon it
                hangs and depends our rights, and with it they can be obtained. It 
                deserves a careful and attentive perusal, as much of interest and value
                to Brooklyn will be found in it.</p>
          <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="interlinear">1686</note>
                <p>[L.S.] "Thomas Dongan, Lieutenant Governor and Vice Admiral
                  of New York and its dependencies, under his Majesty, James the
                  Second, by the grace of God, of England, Scotland, France, Ireland,
                  King, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c., supreme lord and proprietor of the
                  colony and province of New York and its dependencies in America,
                  &amp;c. To all to whom this shall come, sendeth greeting: Whereas the 
                  Honorable Richard Nicolls, Esq., formerly governor of this province,
                  did, by his certain writing or patent, under his hand and seall bearing
                  date the eighteenth day of October, Annoque Domini one thousand
                  six hundred and sixty-seven, ratifie, confirm and grant unto Jan
                  Everts, Jan Damen, Albert Cornelisson, Paulus Veer Beeck, Michael
                  Eneyl, Thomas Lamberts, Tunis Guisbert Bogart, and Joris Jacobson,
                  as patentees for and on behalf of themselves and their associates, the
                  free holders and inhabitants of the town of Breukelen, their heirs,
                  successors and assigns forever, a certain tract of land together with 
                  the several parcels of land which then were or thereafter should be
                  purchased or procured for and on behalf of the said town, whether 
                  from the native Indian proprietors, or others within the bounds and
                  limits therein set forth and expressed. That is to say: the said town</p>
          <pb xml:id="leaf011v" facs="loc.03782.016.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">34</fw>
                  <p>pertaining to any of the afore-recited tract or parcels of land, and
                  divisions, allottments, settlements made and appropriated before the
                  day and date hereof. To have and to hold all and singular, the said
                  tract or parcells of land and premises, with their appurtenances, unto
                  the said Teunis Gysberts, Thomas Lamberts, Peter Jansen, Jacobus
                  Vander Water, Joris Jacobs, Jeronimus Rappellee, Daniel Rappellee,
                  Jan Jansen, Adrian Bennet, and Michael Hanse, for and on behalf of
                  themselves and the present freeholders and inhabitants of the town
                  of Breuckelen, their and every of their heirs and assigns forever, as
                  tenants in common, without let or hindrance, molestation, right of
                  survivorship or otherwise, to be holden in free and common socage,
                  according to the tenure of East Greenwich, in the county of Kent,
                  in his Majesty's Kingdom of England. Yielding, rendering and,
                  paying therefor yearly, and every year, on the five and twentieth day
                  of March, forever, in lieu of all services and demands whatsoever, 
                  as a quit rent to his most sacred Majesty aforesaid, his heirs and successors
                  at the city of New York, twenty bushels of good merchantable
                  wheat. In testimony whereof I have caused these presents to 
                  be entered and recorded in the Secretary's office. and the seal of the 
                  Province to be hereunto affixed, this thirteenth day of May, Anno
                  Domini, one thousand six hundred and eighty-six, in the second year 
                  of his Majesty's reign."</p>
                  <l>"THOMAS DONGAN."</l>

                  <p><span from="#s29" to="#s30" hand="#h2" xml:id="s29" rend="singleLine-left"/>This was the last patent, grant or charter made or given to Brooklyn,
                    and this together with all the former ones, was subsequently
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">confirmed by the general Assembly of the Province, on the 6th day
                      of May, 1692,</hi> having stood firm, unaltered and undisputed five years, 
                    certainly long enough to have discovered if anything wrong or prejudicial
                    was contained in the charter. But not a word was said or 
                    a whisper heard, from any source in regard to it; contrarywise, all<anchor xml:id="s30"/>
                    parties coincided with it, and no one doubted its validity, force and 
                    authority.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">This was the fourth charter and confirmation made to Brooklyn, by</hi>
                    the highest authority known in the Province, and in addition to several
                    purchases from the aborigines, and lastly and finally, by a solemn 
                    legislative act, in general council, assembled in accordance with the
                    known law of this Province, the established custom, usage, and common 
                    law of England, giving if possible, more force, legality and authority 
                    to this act, and all others of a like character and nature. A 
                    more ample, full and explicit grant or charter than this one given by
                    governor Dongan, could not be desired or needed, as it recites in express
                    and plain language, not to be mistaken or misunderstood, all
                    and every right, franchise, and privileges in the town, and to and in                   
    <pb xml:id="leaf012r" facs="loc.03782.017.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">35</fw>
                  the river to low water mark, and the ferries, with all the profits and
                  revenues arising therefrom forever. With this charter alone, had we
                  no other evidence, we could, by taking the proper course, obtain possession
                  of our water front and ferries for a more conclusive or stronger 
                  proof of our ownership and title cannot be produced, and to sustain
                  this, if need be, we have several other equally strong testimonials
                  which go to strengthen and confirm our right.</p> 
                  <p>In these ancient documents are shown beyond a peradventure, that 
                  all the right, title, ownership and possessions which the native Indians
                  had (and no person will doubt their right) in the town of Brooklyn,
                  were obtained from them by purchases, by and with their consent
                  and a consideration, and a full and satisfactory equivalent given therefor.</p>
                  <p>It is a matter of history as well as of fact, and it is to the honor
                  and everlasting fame of the Long Islanders, that not the slightest evidence
                  could ever be adduced, wherein force, illegal or dishonorable
                  means were ever employed by them, to obtain the land with its rights,
                  and secure the various claims of the Indians in this town. But on
                  the contrary, a volume of facts are here produced and substantiated,
                  all of which are corroborative of each other, and cannot be gainsayed,
                  that these purchases were made in good faith by the freeholders
                  and inhabitants of the town of Brooklyn, from the Indians; and that
                  the subsequent confirmations of these purchases were strictly honest
                  and legal. It is a natural and self-evidence fact, that the Indians owned 
                  the land to low water mark all round Long Island, and no person
                  or persons, government or law could deny or invalidate their right,
                  disenherit or dispossess them legally and honestly of it. To deny 
                  this principle, would be to deny the established and immutable principle 
                  of original ownership by the aborigines, beyond which we cannot
                  go. The Indians, then owning the land to low water mark, and 
                  that land with all the privileges, rights, franchises and immunities
                  connected therewith, and having been purchased from them, by and
                  for the inhabitants at large of the town of Brooklyn, and their successors
                  forever, we, therefore, the successors of the then inhabitants
                  <span from="#s31" to="#s32" hand="#h2" xml:id="s31" rend="singleLine-left"/>are the natural, legal and inherent owners of all the above mentioned 
                  and described lands and rights.</p>
                   <p>Governor Dongan arrived in the Province on the 27th day of August, 
                    1683, and immediately after convened the council of the Province,
                    who held a secret session, during which they passed the following
                    order:</p><anchor xml:id="s32"/>
    <pb xml:id="leaf012v" facs="loc.03782.018.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">36</fw>
      <p><span from="#s311" to="#s312" hand="#h2" xml:id="s311" rend="singleLine-left"/>"At a council, held at Fort James, March 31st, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u3">1684,</hi><note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top" target="#u3"><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">?</hi></note> ordered that
            the inhabitants of Brookland and Bedford, bring their Patents and
            Indian deeds on this day seven night."<anchor xml:id="s312"/></p>
            <p>This order was passed in council and promulgated by governor 
            Dongan. Similar orders were issued and sent to the town officers of
            Harlaem, Borswyck, Flatlands, New Lotts, New Utrecht, Bushwick,
            Gravesend, Newtown, Messpoth, Hemsted, Jamaica, Flushing, and
            all the other Dutch towns in the Province, each having a day set when 
            they were required to deliver up to the governor and council all evidence
            of ownership to their lands.</p>
            <p>On the days set apart by the governor and council, for this wanton
            and high-handed outrage upon the rights and property of the people,
            each person or town holding a patent, charter or deed, of the kind
            named in this special edict, took them on the day ordered, to Fort 
            James, in New York, where the council were in session, and handed 
            them over. This part of the ceremony having been gone through
            with, the patentees and others were briefly told that they could go,
            and when they were wanted again they would be sent for. It so happened
            however, unfortunately for the patentees, that they were never 
            wanted after that time, and consequently were never sent for, as the
            governor and council had accomplished by duplicity, deceit and fraud
            all they wished, by cajoling and purloining from these unsuspecting 
            and innocent men, the titles by which they held their property, and
            robbing them of all evidence of ownership. This shameful and dishonest
            transaction has no parallel from the first settlement in the Province
            to the present day.</p>           
            <p>The demanding and retaining these patents and deeds, were in direct 
            contradiction and a gross violation of a section contained in the 
            charter granted by this same Dongan to New York, on the 22nd day 
            of April, 1686, which is in these words:</p>
        
            <p>"Provided always, that this said license, so as above granted, be
            not extended, or be construed to extend to the taking away of any person
            or persons' right or property, without his or her consent, or by
            some known law of the said Province." </p>
        
        <p>This act, therefore, of the governor and council, in dispossessing
            the patentees of their title deeds, without some consideration, shows
            and proves the utter recklessness and disregard of all law, custom, 
            honor or honesty, and a faithlessness and hollow-heartedness, unpar-</p>
    <pb xml:id="leaf013v" facs="loc.03782.019.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">38</fw>
        <p>Money was the god of their idolatry, and their chief study was,
        which would be the easiest, most expeditious and effectual mode of
        obtaining it. These cormorant governors came here poor, having by
        extravagant and riotous living at home become bankrupt and insolvent;
        they were sent here to repair their shattered fortunes by robbing 
        <span from="#s33" to="#s34" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s33"/>the people of their property, and most thoroughly did they accomplish
        their designs. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Each successive governor, with but one or two 
        exceptions, from Nicolls in 1664, down to Montgomerie in 1731, accumulated
        large fortunes by defrauding the people of their property</hi>.
        The last act of this Dongan, as a sort of cap climax to all his other
        acts of oppression and wrong, occurred upon his receiving notice
        from the King that his successor had been appointed, and directing
        Dongan to vacate the office he had so unworthily held. It was this:</p>
              <p>On the 28th day of July, 1688, Dongan set himself industriously 
                at work and collected together all the public papers <choice><orig>ond</orig><reg>and</reg></choice> records he
              could lay his hands upon relating to and connected with Long Island,
              and particularly to Brooklyn, as those places were the most convenient 
              to him, and suddenly and secretly retired to a farm in a sequestered 
              part of New Jersey, where he remained secreted until a favorable
              opportunity offered, when he sneaked out of the country carrying
              the stolen records with him to England, where they now are. The
              legislative act previously referred to confirming, among others, the
              several patents, grants and charters in this Province, was passed the
              7th day of May, 1691. This was during the administration of Henry 
              Slaughter, who held the office of governor here a few months.<anchor xml:id="s34"/>
              The act speaks for itself, and is invaluable for its full and perfect
              confirmation by the General Assembly of the rights, privileges and 
              franchises of this town, and will be of essential service in establishing
              our claim and recovering our rights. The following is the act:</p>
        <l>"May 7th, 1691."</l>
              <p>"An Act for settling, quieting and confirming unto the cities, towns,
              manors and freeholders within this Province, their several grants patents
              and rights, respectively:</p>
              <p>General Assembly of the Province of New York.—Forasmuch as
              the many changes, alterations, and disturbances that have been lately
              given unto their Majesties subjects inhabiting within this, their Province,
              hath and doth very much discourage the settling, improving, 
              and the growth and strength thereof: and that the rights and privileges
              held by and granted to the respective cities, towns, manors and
              freeholders within this Province, &amp;c., should be now ratified and confirmed.</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf014r" facs="loc.03782.020.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top" anchored="true">1708—Under Cornbury's Charter, then, 
          New York claims the control over the 
          rivers, ferries, &amp;c., and the ownership of
          the Brooklyn shore lands</note>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">41</fw>
        <p>tyranny and oppression. A faint estimate may be formed of his
        character from the fact that he was a deserter from the army of 
        James the 2nd, and as a reward for his disloyalty and treachery to
        him, King William, (the successor of James 2d,) upon his accession
        to the throne, appointed Cornbury governor of the colony of New
        York.</p>        
        <p><span from="#s35" to="#s36" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s35"/>After committing many outrages upon the people of Brooklyn and 
          Long Island, he, a few months before his recall, granted a charter to <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">☜</note>
          the corporation of New York, on the 19th day of April, 1708. This
          charter is of an extremely important and serious character to Brooklyn,
          as it is in this instrument the ferries and all the land lying between 
          high and low water mark on the Brooklyn shore, from the easterly 
          side of the Wallabout to the westerly side of Gowanus bay, were
          granted tot New York. It is upon this charter that New York claims
          ownership and jurisdiction on the Brooklyn shore, and the right to
          control all the ferries from our city. This charter begins with a base
          and unmitigated falsehood, and is throughout a tissue of untruths.
          He first grants to them the ferry, with its profits, benefits, and advantages,
          and then proceeds as follows;</p>
          
          <p>"And also all of that vacant and unappropriated land from high
          water mark to low water mark on the said Nassau Island, (alias Long
          Island,) lying contiguous and fronting the said city of New York,
          from a certain place call the Wall-About unto the Red Hook, over
          <note place="left" anchored="true" type="authorial" resp="#h2">Governor's
            Island</note>against <hi rend="underline" hand="#ww">Nuttens Island,</hi> for the better improvement and accommodation
          of the said ferry."</p>
              
          <p>What right had Cornbury or any one else to grant lands in Brooklyn
            to New York, which had been purchased, patented, and granted<anchor xml:id="s36"/>
            to Brooklyn sixty years before by his superiors and predecessors, and
            confirmed from time to time by four preceeding governors, and sanctioned
            by a special act of the highest legislative authority known in 
            the colony, which was the General Assembly? Certainly, none 
            whatever. It was, to say the least of it, an unwarrantable assumption
            of undelegated power, which he nor any other governor had no
            <span from="#s38" to="#s39" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="s38"/>right to exercise. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">It was a right reserved by the common law of
              <note place="left" type="authorial" resp="#h2" anchored="true">☞</note> England to the King, </hi>but was never exercised by him in these colonies.
            <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Cornbury denominates this strip of land vacant and unappropriated
            land. Such however was not the fact, for this strip of</hi> land
            <anchor xml:id="s39"/>was held, owned, and constantly used by the grantees, inhabitants
            and freeholders of Brooklyn at the time this fraudulent charter was
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">6</fw>
    <pb xml:id="leaf014v" facs="loc.03782.021.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">42</fw>
            given to New York, and had been so held, used and owned by them 
            for more than half a century before, quietly and peaceably, and entirely 
            free from any interference from any source whatever. This 
            infamous charter contains another clause, which adds fuel to the flame,
            and insult to injury, and oppression to fraud. It is as follows;</p>
              <span from="#s40" to="#s41" xml:id="s40" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left"/><p>"So always as the said person or persons do only transport themselves
              only and their own goods in their own boats only, and not any
              stranger of their goods, horses or cattle, or in any other boat."</p>
              <p>By this clause it will be observed that all those who unfortunately
              had no boats of their own, were compelled, when they had occasion
              to cross the river, to pay whatever tribute the avarice of the governor 
              might demand, or the caprice of the ferryman would exact, which in
              the most favorable times were exorbitant, burthensome and procrastinating.</p>
              <p>Those also who owned their boats, did not escape the jaundiced 
              and jealous eye or the grasping desires of the governor, for
              they also were compelled to pay extravagant wharfage and ferriage
              for the privilege of crossing the river in their own boats. They were
              prohibited from taking in a friend in their boat and carrying him 
              across the river, or any article or thing under a heavy penalty by fine
              or imprisonment. The people of Brooklyn chafed and groaned under
              these burthens and wrongs for a long time, and repeatedly, in a 
              respectful and loyal manner, asked and petitioned for relief, but a 
              deaf ear was turned to their applications. They, therefore, finding
              that redress for the manifold wrongs which had been inflicted, and
              relief from the burthens which had been imposed upon them was
              denied them, they continued peaceably but reluctantly to bear these
              burthens and unjust exactions and frauds for thirty-seven years.</p>
              <p>Having shown in the foregoing remarks, substantiated by extracts
              <anchor xml:id="s41"/>from the records, who was the first perpetrator and in what manner
              the first inroad and great palpable wrong was done to Brooklyn, it is 
              necessary to follow through the whole of this transaction, and give
              the closing acts and manoeuvers, which were by John Montgomerie
              and the Common Council of New York. This man commenced his 
              administration of governor of the colonies on the 14th day of April,
              1728. He was a Scotchman by birth, and had entered the British 
              army at an early age and was bred a soldier, but had never attained
              to any eminence or office in the army. He remained in comparative 
              obscurity until the accession of George the 2nd to the throne, when
    <pb xml:id="leaf015r" facs="loc.03782.022.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">43</fw>
        he was favored by that sovereign with the appointment of groom of
        the royal bedchamber, in which capacity he served a few years, and
        in 1728 was appointed by the King, governor general and commander-
        in-chief of these colonies.</p>
        <span from="#s42" to="#s43" xml:id="s42" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-right"/><p>His talents were rather below mediocrity than otherwise, his habits
        indolent, and his address repulsive and disagreeable. He was moreover
        weak-minded and flexible, and was easily made the pliant tool of
        the Common Council of New York, giving and granting extravagantly
        to them, any property and privileges they would ask for, provided
        they would pay him sufficient money to allay his thirst for gold. His
        maxim was, "Money answereth all things," and most thoroughly<anchor xml:id="s43"/>
        did he illustrate it during his short sojourn in these colonies, which 
        lasted <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">three year</hi>s, and was characterized by an act of the same nature
        in reference to Brooklyn, as the one of his prototype Cornbury.
        The first grand move under Montgomerie's administration was made
        by the Common Council of New York, be petitioning the governor
        for a confirmation of the infamous and illegal charter granted to them
        by Cornbury. This petition is quite a voluminous one containing 
        many sections.</p>
        <p>The following one will show that the Common Council did not feel
        themselves secure in the Cornbury charter, and doubted its legality.
        Here it is;</p>
        
        <p><span from="#s44" to="#s45" xml:id="s44" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/><span from="#s44" to="#s45" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2"/>"And whereas divers questions, doubts, opinions, ambiguities,
          controversies and debates have arisen, and been made as well upon
          and concerning the validity and force of the said writing, &amp;c."</p>
              
          <p>Here is a public and open acknowledgement by the Common Council,<anchor xml:id="s45"/>
          that they did not deem the charter of Cornbury legal or valid, or 
          of any force, and that they considered it absolutely and indispensably
          necessary to obtain another charter at any cost, let the consequence
          be what it might, to legalize and make valid, if possible, their
          then charter.</p>
          <p>This, however, could not be done, as governor Cornbury in the first
          place, had no right, power or authority, either express or implied, to
          grant any such rights, privileges and franchises to New York, for the
          very good reason that he had no control or jurisdiction over the ferry, 
          or the land lying between high and low water mark, on the Brooklyn 
          shore, and had no interest therein, and consequently could not
          legally grant it away, or confer it upon any person or corporation without
          the consent of the individual owners of the town of Brooklyn.
     <pb xml:id="leaf015v" facs="loc.03782.023.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top" anchored="true"> 1729 — under Montgomerie</note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">44</fw>
                  The wants of the Common Council were very numerous as expressed
                  in this petition, but they most desired to be made secure in the possession 
                  of our ferry, and the whole of the water front.</p>
                  <p>Annexed to this petition was the following resolution: </p>
                  
                  <p>"Att a common council, held att the City Hall, the 23rd day of
                    March, 1729.</p>
                  <p>Resolved, <hi rend="italic">Nemine Contradicente</hi>, that this corporation do make application
                  to his excellency the Governor, for his Majesties' grant of
                  confirmation of the charter of this corporation, in royal stile, and
                  of all the ancient rights or privileges, as can be obtained for the 
                  advantage, good rule and government of the inhabitants of this city;
                  and ordered that Mr. Mayor, (Robert Lurting) Mr. Recorder, (Francis
                  Harrison) Alderman Cruger, Alderman Cortlandt, Alderman 
                  Philipse, Mr. Roosevelt and Mr. Chambers, or any five of them,
                  whereof the Mayor or Recorder to be one, be a committee to consider
                  of what things will be needful to be petitioned for by this corporation;
                  that they draw up the laws, and make their report with all expedition."</p>
                  
                  <p>This committee proceeded forthwith to draft a petition, agreeable 
                  to the instructions contained in this resolution, and on the 28th day 
                  of March, five days only, after the passage of the above resolution,
                  and their appointment, the committee presented their report in full,
                  classifying and enumerating every specific thing they coveted, comprising
                  23 articles. The 15th reads <choice><orig>os</orig><reg>as</reg></choice> follows:</p>
                  
                  <p><span from="#s46" to="#s47" xml:id="s46" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>"That they have a confirmation of the patent of the ferry and
                    grounds on Nassau Island."</p><anchor xml:id="s47"/>
                  
                  <p>This report, as a matter of course, was unanimously adopted and
                  the committee was ordered to present the petition to the governor,
                  and ask his acquiescence to its demands. Considerable delay was 
                  experienced in obtaining the governor's consent to grant them a new
                  charter, or a confirmation of the old one, as upon this their first application
                  to him, he would not give them a decisive answer, or hold
                  out to them any encouragement. The reason of the governor treating
                  the committee thus cavalierly is obvious.</p>
                  <p>The committee has not made any overtures, or pecuniary offers to
                  the governor, not having been empowered so to do by the Common
                  Council. They understood, however, from the manner and character
                  of the governor what he wanted, and the committee, as the subsequent 
                  proceedings fo the Common Council prove, made known their
    <pb xml:id="leaf016r" facs="loc.03782.024.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">45</fw>
                    opinions to that body, which proved to be correct, and the recommendations
                    made by them carried out. The committee having been rather
                    cavalierly and coolly treated on their first interview with the governor,
                    were not to be thwarted or disheartened into an abandonment of
                    their design, or give up all hope of ultimately being successful in accomplishing
                    so desirable and important an object, by the unsatisfactory 
                    and repulsive manner in which the governor met and received
                    them at this time.</p>
                    <p>The committee continued to apply to his excellency from time to
                    time, to grant them this darling object of their wishes. The governor
                    considering himself unnecessarily annoyed by the committee, secretly
                    resolved to take a short sojourn in New Jersey, during which interregnum
                    the committee and the Common Council would have time 
                    and opportunity to interchange opinions with each other, and bring
                    their minds and consciences to comply with any unreasonable demand
                    which the governor might make upon them.</p>
                    
         <span from="#s48" to="#s49" xml:id="s48" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left"/><p>The price demanded by Montgomerie for a new charter and a confirmation
                        <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" target="#u4" place="left">☞</note>o<hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u4">f the old one was £1000.</hi> This, the committee deemed a
                        most outrageous and extravagant price, but upon frequent consultations
                        among themselves and other members of the council, they finally
                        <anchor xml:id="s49"/>agreed to give the governor his price, as they had no faith in 
                        the validity of the charter which they had obtained from Cornbury.
                        It was therefore, absolutely necessary in their opinion, that this one
                        should be obtained, which would legalize and make valid the one they
                        then had. In due time the governor returned to the fort in New
                        York, and soon after his arrival the committee again waited upon him 
                        and informed him that the Common Council would give him any sum
                        which he required, and that they would take the necessary measures
                        to consummate the bargain. The committee thereupon convened the
                        Common Council forthwith, when they communicated to them the
                        substance and result of the numerous interviews which they had with
                        the governor, whereupon the following order was passed;</p>
                        
                        <p>"At a common council held at the City Hall, the 6th day of April, 
                          1730.</p>
                        
                        <p>Ordered Mr. Recorder (Francis Harrison,) do prepare the draft of
                        a new charter, with a confirmation of the present charter, and all of
                        the ancient rights and privileges of this corporation, &amp;c., for the perusal 
                        of this court."</p> 
                        
    <pb xml:id="leaf016v" facs="loc.03782.025.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">46</fw>
        <p>The committee had a long, tedious and laborious task in securing
        the consent of the governor, having been occupied thirteen months in
        prosecuting their application, and obtaining the governor's consent.
        The Recorder, Mr. Harrison, applied himself with renewed energy
        and vigor to the task assigned him, of preparing the new charter, as
        no time was to be lost, and in the short space of fourteen days, the 
        Recorder completed the draft, when another meeting of the Common
        Council was immediately held, the new charter presented and approved,
        and the following order passed:</p>
        
          <span from="#s50" to="#s51" xml:id="s50" hand="#h2" rend="singleLine-left"/><p>"At a common council held at the City Hall, on the 20th day of 
          April, 1730—and it being the unanimous opinion of this court that
          the sum of fourteen hundred pounds will be needful to be provided
          by this corporation, for obtaining the said charter, it is hereby ordered,
          that the said committee do continue their application for obtaining
          the said charter."</p><anchor xml:id="s51"/>
          
          <p>When this order was passed there was no money in the treasury
          of the city of New York, and the Common Council were compelled 
          to resort to the borrowing system, in order to procure the required 
          amount to consummate this nefarious scheme. It gave the Common
          Council considerable uneasiness and trouble to procure this large sum
          of money, as at this early day there were very few persons in the
          colony who could command so large an amount of money. The 
          amount required for the charter alone, or in other words, for the simple
          sign manual of the governor was £1000, but £400 more was
          necessary to pay the expense of surveying this "unpatented, vacant,
          and unappropriated land," on the Brooklyn shore, for drafting the
          charter, and also for drafting, executing, and recording a mortgage
          to secure the payment of the whole amount, £1400.</p>
          <p>Some difficulty was experienced and delay occasioned in procuring
          the money, it being nearly $7000. The committee cast about a long
          time, nearly nine months, before they found a person who was willing
          to hazard so enormous a sum as this was deemed to be at that 
          time, and considering the security offered by the Common Council, it 
          being unproductive, and some of it looked upon as worthless. They
          however, at length succeeded, and were fortunate enough to obtain
          the £1400 from one James De Lancy, who advanced the funds.—
          This gentleman had previously held several very lucrative sinecures
          in the colony, and was accredited the wealthiest man in the colony,
          and became Lieutenant Governor of the colony a few years after.</p>
    <pb xml:id="leaf017r" facs="loc.03782.026.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">47</fw>
        <p>All thing being now completed, and all the necessary preliminaries
        arranged for the grand <hi rend="italic">finale</hi> of this fraudulent transaction, another
          meeting of the common council was held on the 3rd day of
          August, when the following was passed:</p>
          
        <p>"Resolved—<hi rend="italic">Nemine Contradicente</hi>—that one thousand pounds current
            money of this colony, be borrowed by this corporation, on interest
            for one year, towards defraying the expence of procuring a new
            charter and confirmation to this corporation, &amp;c, and that Mr. Mayor,
            (Robert Lurting) Alderman Philipse, and Mr. Chambers, be a committee
            to procure the same, and they have power to mortgage any of
            the lands belonging to this corporation on this Island, Manhattans,
            for the do payment thereof, and this corporation will authorize Mr.
            Mayor (Robert Lurting) to execute such mortgage accordingly, under
            the publick seal of this corporation."</p>
            
        <p>The Recorder, Francis Harrison, having been previously empowered
            to draft this mortgage, he immediately after the passage of the 
            foregoing resolution, set about preparing the mortgage in due form,
            which was finished in a few days, and on the 14th of January ensuing,
            he presented it complete to the Common Council, when the following
            order was passed, to wit:</p>
            
        <p>"At a common council held at the City Hall, on the 14th of January,
          Anno Dom. 1730—A draft of a mortgage from this corporation<span from="#s52" to="#s53" xml:id="s52" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2"/>
            to James De Lancy, Esqr., for a thousand pounds with interest, read 
            and approved, and ordered 'it be engrossed and that the Mayor execute 
            the same under the seal of this corporation."</p>
              
        <p>This was the last act by the Common Council of New York in relation 
              to this matter, and this done it was only necessary to secure 
              the signature of Montgomerie to the charter, and the whole of this
              illegal and fraudulent affair was complete. The committee lost no 
              time in fulfilling and accomplishing this their last duty, and proceeded
              forthwith to the governor, with the spurious charter in one hand,
              and the thousand pounds in the other. The governor received the 
              committee very cordially, and received also the newly fledged charter
              and the bribe of one thousand pounds.</p>
        <p>The governor, however, very unexpectedly, and much to the disappointment 
              and dismay of the committee, told them that he was not 
              prepared to sign it at so short notice, and bade the committee call<anchor xml:id="s53"/>
              again, fixing a time, and telling them that he desired to peruse the
              charter, in order to ascertain whether it contained any thing prejudicial
    <pb xml:id="leaf017v" facs="loc.03782.027.jpg" type="verso"/>  
         <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top" anchored="true"> Montgomerie charter finally signed
           11th Feb. 1730 — by the Gov. M.</note>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">48</fw>
          to his interest. Accordingly, the committee left the governor
          and went their way.</p>
          <p>A month rolled round and nothing was heard from his excellency 
          about the charter, which alarmed the Mayor and his associates of the 
          committee, when they resolved among themselves to depute the 
          Mayor, Robert Lurting, to wait upon the governor and obtain the
          charter. The Mayor accordingly made it his special business to see
          the governor, and on the 11th day of February, 1730, the governor
          <span from="#s54" to="#s55" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s54"/>delivered the charter, signed by himself only, to the Mayor, for which
          the Mayor thanked his excellency for his great goodness, wishing 
          him health, long life and prosperity, in the name of the Common
          Council. The Common Council were holding a session at this time,
          awaiting the return of the Mayor. When he returned to the city
          hall and presented the long wished-for charter, the Common Council 
          directed Recorder Harrison to prepare an address to his excellency
          for his condescension and great goodness for granting them this 
          charter; and a more cringing, flattering, sycophantic and fulsome address
          cannot be found in the archives of this country, from its discovery
          to the present day. This was the finishing stroke for Brooklyn.
          The fiat had gone forth, and Brooklyn, her rights, her privileges
          <anchor xml:id="s55"/>and her land were wrested from her, and sacrificed by unprincipled
          knaves and fortune haunting marauders. These were schemes of the
          blackest dye, conceived in iniquity, brought forth in fraud, nurtured
          by stratagem and chicane, and consummated by the most villainous
          system of bribery, corruption and deceit that the page of history in 
          any country records.</p>
          <p>In the foregoing narrative has been shown, as taken from the public 
          records, this shameful and disgraceful affair. These are facts,
          stubborn, undeniable, and incontrovertible facts, which stand out in
          bold relief, though the ravages of time are making sad havoc with 
          these relics of the olden time, and transcribed here that all trace of 
          them might not be lost forever to the people of Brooklyn, who are
          deeply interested in them.</p>
        <p>Matters remained in <hi rend="italic">statu quo,</hi> from this time until the year 1745,
          when the spirit of resistance to oppression (which is obedience to
          God,) began to infuse itself among the Brooklyn people, and the
          Long Islanders having submitted to the oppressive yoke thirty-seven 
          years. At this time the corporation of New York, not satisfied with 
          <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">the revenue which they were receiving from the ferry and other
          sources in Brooklyn,</hi> connected with the water front, attempted to
    <pb xml:id="leaf018r" facs="loc.03782.028.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">49</fw>
          <span from="#s56" to="#s57" xml:id="s56" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">prevent the people of Brooklyn who owned their own boats from
            crossing the river in them without paying ferriage.</hi> In order to test 
              the right of New York to impose such an outrageous law and prohibition 
              upon the people of Brooklyn, one Hendrick Remsen established 
              a ferry from Brooklyn to New York, and transported persons and
              goods over the river, and received ferriage from his passengers. Remsen
              kept a correct account of all ferriage money he received, so that 
              in the event of a suit being commenced against him or <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>, and
              he should be mulcted in any damages, he would be enabled to know 
              the exact amount he had received. The Common Council of New 
              York, however, did not deem it prudent to commence an action, doubtless
              well satisfied that their claim and rights on the Brooklyn shore
              was invalid and illegal.</p>
              <p>In the month of July, 1745, Remsen entered suit against the corporation 
              of New York. The following is the title of the suit:</p><anchor xml:id="s57"/>
                  
              <span from="#s58" to="#s59" xml:id="s58" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>
              <ab xml:id="ab1">Hendrick Remsen,
              <hi rend="italic">vs.</hi>
              The Mayor, Aldermen, and
              Commonalty of the City of
              New York.</ab>
              <note type="main-authorial" target="#ab1">Supreme Court, July Term, 1745.</note>
              <note place="left" type="authorial" resp="#h2" anchored="true">☞</note><p>This action was commenced by Hendrick Remsen, of the town of
              Brooklyn, against the Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the City
              of New York, for the sum of five shillings, unlawfully demanded and
              received from him as ferriage for the goods and persons of his neighbors
              of the town of Brooklyn, who did not live on their own land at
              the water side, the goods were laden on board a market boat in the 
              public slip, on the highway at Brooklyn Ferry, and the persons taken
              on board at the same place and landed at the market in the city of 
              New York. The prosecution of this suit was made common cause
              by the town of Brooklyn, and after a lapse of 27 years, the following 
              judgment was obtained, viz:</p>
                      
              <p>"October Term, in the year of our Lord 1773.—At which day
              came here the parties aforesaid, by their attornies, upon which all
              and singular the premises being seen and by the justices here fully
              understood, and mature deliberation being thereupon had for as it 
              seems to the Justices here upon the whole matter aforesaid, that the 
              aforesaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the city of New <anchor xml:id="s59"/>
              York did assume upon themselves in manner, and form as aforesaid,
              Henrick Remsen doth complain. Therefore it is considered that the
              said Hendrick Remsen recover against the aforesaid Mayor, Aldermen
              <fw type="catch">7</fw>
    <pb xml:id="leaf018v" facs="loc.03782.029.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">50</fw>
                and Commonalty of the city of New York, his damages aforesaid,
                by the jurors aforesaid, in form aforesaid assessed, and one
                hundred and eighteen pounds fourteen shillings and ten pence halfpenny
                for costs, and charges to the said Hendrick by the same
                Justices, now here of his assent, and increase adjudged, which damges
                in the whole do amount to one hundred and nineteen pounds and
                fourteen pence half-penny, and the aforesaid Mayor, Alderman and 
                Commonalty of the city of New York, in money, &amp;c.</p>
                
                <p>The decision of this suit put a temporary stop to these unjust expectations.
                Albeit: the delay of justice in this case amounted almost to
                a denial of justice.</p>
                <p>It requires but the same indomitable and persevering spirit at this
                time to overthrow the flimsy and iniquitous charter by which New 
                York holds possession of our ferries and water front. During the 
                pendency of this suit, the trustees of the town of Brooklyn, on behalf
                of themselves, the freeholders and inhabitants of the town held
                a meeting in the winter of 1745, and resolved to lay a petition before 
                the General Assembly, stating their grievances and asking for redress
                and relief. Accordingly, at the next meeting of the General Assembly,
                in January, 1746, they presented their petition, in which they 
                plainly and explicitly set forth the manifold grievances under which
                they had for a long time suffered, and were then suffering, and complained
                very truly and justly about the great wrongs which had been
                done them by Cornbury and Montgomerie, in depriving them of their
                property and their rights in the two charters granted by them to
                New York. On the presentation of this petition, the following proceedings
                were had;</p>
                
                <span from="#s62" to="#s63" type="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s62"/><p>"January 30th, 1745-6. In General Assembly a petition of the 
                  trustees of the town of Broockland, in Kings County, in behalf of
                  themselves, and the freeholders and inhabitants of the said township,
                  <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2" anchored="true">Ferry
                    1745</note>
                    was presented to the House and read, setting forth that a great number 
                    of the inhabitants of the said township living near the ferry from
                    Nassau Island to New York, and having their chief dependence 
                    of supporting their families by trading to the New York markets, are
                    by one act of the General Assembly, entitled to an act to regulate the
                    ferry between the city of New York and Island of Nassau, and
                    to establish the ferriage thereof, passed in the sixth of his Majesty's
                    reign, debarred from transporting their goods in their own vessels to
                    the said markets, which exposes them to very great hardships, difficulties
                    and expenses, and therefore humbly praying that they may 
                    have leave to bring in a bill to relieve them from the aforesaid hardships.
                    Upon motion of Major Van Horn, (of New York,) ordered<anchor xml:id="s63"/>         
    <!--<pb xml:id="leaf019r" facs="loc.03782.030.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">51</fw>
                  that the clerk of this House serve the corporation of the city of 
                  New York with a copy of the said petition forthwith."</p>
                  
                  <p>Three months elapsed, and nothing more was done. On the 12th 
                  day of April, a bill was reported to the House as follows:</p>
                  
                 <p>"In General Assembly, April 12th, 1746, Mr. Abraham Lott, according 
                  to leave, presented to the House a bill entitled an act to repeal 
                  an act therein mentioned, so far as it relates to the freeholders
                  and inhabitants of the township of Brooklyn, in Kings county, within 
                  this colony, which was read the first time and ordered a second reading.
                  Ordered that the corporation of the city of New York be
                  served with a copy of the said bill."</p>
                  
                  <p>Up to this time, not a word was heard from the corporation of 
                  New York, and it appeared the Assembly were rather fearful or taking
                  any definite action on this matter until they did hear from them,
                  as at the close of every proceeding relating to this matter, they ordered
                  a copy of what they had done to be served upon them. On the 
                  18th of April, the subject came up again, when the following progress
                  was made.</p>
                  
                   <p>"April 18, 1746, in General Assembly, the bill entitled an act to
                  repeal an act therein mentioned so far as it relates to the freeholders
                  and inhabitants of the township of Brooklyn in Kings county, within
                  this colony, being offered to be read a second time, Captain Richards
                  (of New York) moved that the second reading of the said bill might
                  be deferred until the next meeting of the House, after the first day
                  of June next, which was agreed to by the House, and ordered accordingly."</p>
                  
                  <p>The General Assembly met again on the 20th of June, agreeable
                  to adjournment, when the corporation of New York sent in a petition 
                  asking to be heard at the bar of the House, through counsel
                  against the bill; and upon the receipt of this petition, the following 
                  order was made and proceedings had:</p>
                  
                  <p>"June 20th, 1746, in general Assembly, a petition of the Mayor,
                  Alderman and Commonality of the city of New York, was presented
                  to the House, and read, setting forth that the corporation having 
                  been served with a copy of a bill now before this House, entitled an 
                  act to repeal an act, therein mentioned, so far as it relates to the freeholders
                  and inhabitants of the town of Brooklyn, in Kings County,
                  within this colony, do conceive that the passing the said bill into a -->
    <pb xml:id="leaf019v" facs="loc.03782.031.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">52</fw>
                    law, may affect their ancient rights and freehold, and therefore humbly
                    praying that they may be heard by their counsel, against the
                    said bill at the bar of this House, on Friday next. Ordered, that
                    the trustees of the township of Brooklyn be heard by their counsel,
                    in support of the said bill, at the bar of this house, on Friday next,
                    and that Mr. William Smith appear for them.</p>
                    <p>Ordered that the clerk of this House serve the parties with a copy 
                    of these orders forthwith."</p>
        
                    <span from="#s64" to="#s65" xml:id="s64" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/><p>Accordingly on the 27th of June, the trustees of Brooklyn were in 
                      attendance with their counsel, as also the corporation of New York
                      with their counsel, which information being conveyed to the Speaker,
                      the House organized, and the subject brought forward, and proceeded
                      with it as follows:</p>
                      
                      <p>"June 27, 1746, in general Assembly, the House being informed
                      that the corporation of the city of New York were attending with
                      their counsel, to be heard against the bill, and that the trustees of the
                      township of Brooklyn were also attending with their counsel, to be 
                      heard in support of said bill, both parties were called in, and the
                      counsel on both sides having been fully heard, for and against the
                      said bill, they were directed to withdraw, and the bill being read the
                      second time, the question was put, whether the said bill should be
                      committed and carried in the affirmative, in the manner following:</p>
                      <p>Affirmative, Messrs. Johannis Lott, Chambers, Stilwell, Livingston,
                      Harring, Cornell, Abraham Lott, Lecount, Bradt, Nicoll, Hardenburgh,
                      and Gale, 12.</p>
                      <p>Negative, Messrs. Richards, Cruger, Clarkson, Van Horne, Philipse,
                      Morris, Verplank, and Thomas, 8."</p>
                      
                      <p>The next thing necessary to be done, was to engross the bill, and
                      send it to the council for concurrence, and the 4th day of July was 
                      fixed for this branch of the colonial legislature, to act finally upon
                      this bill now that it was gone through with, but not without the most
                      violent and strenuous opposition from one of the New York members,
                      Colonel Morris.</p>
                      <p>The final passage of the bill was follows:</p>
                      
                      <p>"July 4, 1746, in general Assembly, the engrossed bill entitled an
                      act to repeal an act therein mentioned so far as it relates to the freeholders
                      and inhabitants of the township of Brooklyn, in Kings County, 
                      within this colony, was read a third time, and upon the Speaker's 
                      putting the questions whether the bill should pass, A motion was made
                      by Colonel Morris, in the words following, viz:</p>
                      <p>As this bill has been already ordered to be engrossed by a majority 
                      of this House, and the question that is now put is, whether this<anchor xml:id="s65"/>
    <pb xml:id="leaf020r" facs="loc.03782.032.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">53</fw>
                        bill should pass, I must beg leave to give my reasons for opposing 
                        its passage. The first is, it is alleged by this bill that the people of
                        Brooklyn had a right prior to the act passed in the year 1732, which
                        was not proved or attempted, upon the hearing before this House,
                        but if we pass this bill we allow that right to be proved, and then it
                        becomes our allegation, which I conceive inconsistent with the honor
                        and justice of this House, to alledge any thing in such a case, but
                        what has been proved. The second is, it implies that the act in 1732
                        took away unjustly, a right from the people of Brooklyn, that they 
                        were entitled to. Thirdly, it implies that the House have fixed the
                        two points before mentioned, and then it will necessarily follow, that
                        we have considered the rights of the corporation as well as those of
                        the people of Brooklyn; that we have not, I appeal to the House, 
                        who must allow that no such right ever appeared to us, at least as a 
                        House, and for us to declare certain facts by a bill which has never
                        been proved, will be doing what I conceive we ought not to do, if 
                        we make justice and equity the rule of our conduct. For these reasons,
                        I move that the bill may be rejected. The question being put
                        thereon, it was carried in the negative, in the manner following, viz:</p>
                        <p>For the negative, Messrs. Abraham Lott, Chambers, Hardenburgh,
                        Lecount, Cornell, Johannis Lott, Bradt, Gale and Harring. 9.</p>
                        <p>Affirmative, Messrs. Van Horne, Morris, Cruger, Philipse, Richards,
                        Verplank, Clarkson and Thomas, 8.</p>
                        <p>Resolved—That the bill do pass. Ordered that Colonel Harring
                        and Hardenburgh do carry the bill to the Council, and desire their
                        concurrence."</p>
                        
                        <p>This committee of two, were directed by the Speaker to inform
                        the Council that the bill had passed the House and the Supreme 
                        Court and that the rights and claims of the people of Brooklyn had
                        been clearly and satisfactorily proven.</p>
                        <p>The bill was smothered in the Council, and it is not known what
                        ever became of it, consequently it never was matured into a law,
                        though it did not alter the principle, or effect the right of Brooklyn.
                        That, as has been shown heretofore, was clearly settled, and this last
                        act of the general Assembly added yet another proof. The Council 
                        of the colony usually held their sessions with closed doors, and was
                        emphatically a S<hi rend="smallcaps">TAR</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">HAMBER</hi>. </p>
                        <p>Comment upon such conduct by a set of unprincipled and treacherous 
                          myrmidoms is unn<choice><orig>ce</orig><reg>ec</reg></choice>ssary, it carries with it its own condemnation.</p>
                        <p>The duty of these men and their sense of justice and honor (if they 
                        had any) should have prompted them to send the bill back to the
                        House where it originated, stating if nothing more, their refusal to</p>
    <pb xml:id="leaf021r" facs="loc.03782.033.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">55</fw>
        <p>freeholders and inhabitants of the township of Brookland, by these
        presents do fully impower and authorize the aforesaid trustees, Jacobus
        Lefferts, Peter Vandervoort, Jacob Remsen, Rem Remsen and
        Nicholas Vetche, elected and chosen by the freeholders and inhabitants
        of the township of Brookland aforesaid, to defend our patent
        wherein any manner our liberties, privileges and rights in our patent
        specified is encroached, lessened or taken away by the commonalty
        of the city of New-York: And that we hereunder subscribers of the 
        township of Brookland oblige ourselves, our heirs, executors and administrators, 
        to pay to the aforesaid trustees all cost that they are at 
        in protecting of the profits of our patent, and that money shall be collected 
        in by the constable of our town, And that the abovesaid trustees
        do oblige themselves to render upon oath a true account of all
        such moneys they have expended in protecting or defending our patent, 
        to <choice><reg>any</reg><orig>anv</orig></choice> person or persons as the hereunder subscribers shall appoint
        for that purpose, And in defending our patent so that verdict
        shall come in our favor where income of money or other profits should
        arise concerning the premises; all such profits or income should be
        kept towards defraying all the necessary cost and charges of our
        township of Brookland, till such time as it is altered by the majority,
        And that the trustees should have three shillings per day for their
        service and no more."</p>
          
            <span from="#s66" to="#s67" xml:id="s66" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/><p>Thus it will be perceived that New York did not hold or retain uninterrupted,
            quiet and unmolested possession of the ill-gotten property 
            on our shore, as efforts were continually being made by the people
            and trustees of Brooklyn to test the right, and try the validity of the
            false and fraudulent miscalled charters by which their rights and property 
            had been taken away from them. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">New York has ever been extremely
            fearful that some energetic, determined and successful effort
            would be made on the part of Brooklyn to obtain possession of the
            ferries and water front, which they well knew they unjustly and illegally
            held, having no color of right to them, and whenever a movement
            has been made by Brooklyn in the premises, the Common Council
            of New York have invariably resorted to every species of stratagem,
            low device, bribery and deception, with the powerful aid of
            money, to retain and bolster up these</hi> "doubtful, suspicious and ambiguous"
            <anchor xml:id="s67"/>charters. By the above proceedings in relation to defending
            the patents and charters of Brooklyn, it is very evident that the 
            matter was prosecuted by those persons who were chosen for that
            purpose; but unfortunately for Brooklyn, the result of the prosecution
            cannot be found among our records, but that the matter was
            prosecuted there can be no doubt, and that the evidence of the fact,
            with a record of the proceedings are still in existence, is equally reasonable
    <pb xml:id="leaf021v" facs="loc.03782.034.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">56</fw>
              <span from="#s68" to="#s69" xml:id="s68" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>and probable. This is demonstrable from the following facts:
              <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left" anchored="true">☞</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The records of the town of Breukelen and Kings County were regularly 
              and accurately kept by each successive town and county clerk, 
              from the first settlement in 1625,</hi> up to 1777.</p><anchor xml:id="s69"/>
              <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">In 1688</hi> Governor Dongan was superceded in the gubernatorial 
              office, much to his surprise and contrary to his wish, and coming so 
              unexpectedly upon him, as the first intimation he had of his removal 
              was from his successor, who informed him of the fact in person.— 
              <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">This so enraged Dongan that he sought revenge by stealing all the
              public documents and records he could lay his hands upon, among
              which were very many belonging to Brookl</hi>yn and Kings County.— 
              As soon as he had availed himself of these papers he decamped to
              England with the plunder.</p>
        <span from="#s70" to="#s71" xml:id="s70" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/><p>Many of those taken by Dongan have since been recovered by
              the State of New York, through an agent who was appointed for 
              that purpose, but those recovered principally relate to the cities of 
              New York and Albany. The greatest outrage of this character however, 
              remains to be recorded.</p><anchor xml:id="s71"/>
              <p>It is this. At the breaking out of the revolutionary war in 1775,
              a man named John Rapelye, was the clerk of Kings county, and also
              a member of the General Assembly of the Colony from this county.
              He continued to hold these offices as long as prudence dictated, and 
              his own personal safety warranted, which was until the month of
              September, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">1777.</hi> He was a hot-headed tory, and uncompromisingly
              hostile to the American cause, and rendered himself peculiarly obnoxious
              to his neighbors in and about Brooklyn. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">He resided near
              where the Fulton ferry now is, and was consequently within the 
              American lines.</hi> It soon became known throughout Kings county,
              that Rapelye was inimical to the revolutionary movement, and was
              aiding the British in every possible manner. This news was not long
              in reaching the American Legislative Assembly who were then in 
              <span from="#s72" to="#s73" xml:id="s72" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>session in Westchester. The Assembly soon after receiving this information
              well authenticated, concerning Rapelye, passed an act of 
              attainder in October, 1777, by which a very large estate in Brooklyn
              owned by Rapelye, was confiscated to the State of New-York, <add rend="unmarked" resp="#h2" place="inline">(</add>and
              afterwards sold to Comfort and Joshua Sands, for £12,430.<add rend="unmarked" resp="#h2" place="inline">)</add> By this
              act, Rapelye was also compelled to leave this country forthwith,
              which he soon did, and went with spirits more congenial with his own.
              <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Before his departure, however, he stealthily collected together all
              the records and public documents of Kings county and Brooklyn</hi>;
    <pb xml:id="leaf022r" facs="loc.03782.035.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note place="right" resp="#h2" anchored="true">☟</note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">57</fw>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s93" from="#s93" to="#s94"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">the records of the county being in his own possession, and the town
                  <span from="#s76" to="#s73" xml:id="s76" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2"/>records in possession of Leffert Lefferts, who was at that time the
                    town clerk of Brooklyn</hi>. The manner and mode by which Rapelye
                      obtained the town records, was by going to the house of Leffert Lefferts, 
                      where the records were kept, at a time when Lefferts was absent
                      from home, and obtaining permission from Lefferts' wife, by
                      false representations, he selected such papers from among the mass,
                      as answered his purpose, and with them and the county records, he
                      decamped in disguise with them, secreting himself, and as soon as a
                      favorable opportunity offered, left the country with the stolen records,
                      leaving his wife and children in Brooklyn, to follow him as best they 
                      could. These records are still in existence and come-at-able, if the 
                      proper steps be taken to recover them. They are in possession of a 
                      relative by marriage of Rapelye, a grand son-in-law, who resides in
                      England, and who brought them to this country in the year 1810, 
                      for the purpose of recovering the confiscated property of Rapelye.
                      Upon arriving here, he employed Aaron Burr and David B. Ogden,
                      Esqs. of New York, as his counsel, for this object. These two lawyers
                      investigated the matter thoroughly, and after having finished their examinations,
                      they informed the gentleman that they could not recover 
                      any of the property thus confiscated, as the act of attainder was strictly
                      legal and constitutional, and could not be repealed, annulled or effected
                      in any way. Upon receiving this information, this man packed up all
                      the papers which he brought with him, consisting of the deeds for 
                      the Rapelye estate, and the public documents, and records of the 
                      town of Brooklyn and Kings county. These papers were so numerous, 
                      that they filled three ordinary sized travelling trunks. This man
                      took passage immediately for England, with the trunks and their
                      contents, he still retaining them in his possession.</p><anchor xml:id="s73"/><anchor xml:id="s94"/>
                      <span from="#s77" to="#s78" xml:id="s77" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2"/><p>The following certificate is corroborative of the statement above,
                      in relation to the stolen records of this town. It is a true copy from
                      the original, which is in the hand writing of Mr. Leffert Lefferts, who
                      was the town clerk of Brooklyn, from 1761, to the commencement
                      of the revolution, in 1776, a period of fifteen years:</p><anchor xml:id="s78"/>
             
                     <p>"This is to certify, that I, the subscriber, was clerk to the town of
                      Brooklyn, In the Year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred and
                      seventy-six, at the commencement of the Revolutionary War with 
                      Great Britain, And being Obliged to Leave my House and Property
                        <fw type="catch">8</fw>
    <pb xml:id="leaf022v" facs="loc.03782.036.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">58</fw>
                       for Some time, When I returned my Books and the Records for said
                       town were taken away.
                       Witness My Hand,
                       LEFFERT LEFFERTS."</p>
                       
        <p><span from="#s79" to="#s80" xml:id="s79" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>The following also appears on the records relative to the same
          matter:</p>
                         
        <p>"In consequence of the total Loss of the town of Brooklyn Records,
          in the late Revolutionary War with Great Britain,
          We, the
          Subscribers were Nominated By the Commissioners and Trustees for
          Town of Brooklyn, to make Search among the records for the County 
          of Kings, for such Papers, Documents and records as have Relation 
          to the said Town.
          We have therefore
          carefully Examined, Selected and entered the Same in a book Provided
          for that Purpose, and authenticated with the Clerk of the 
          County's Certificate annexed.
          Brooklyn, the 19th December, 1797.
          Certified.
          J. N. FISHER,
          JOHN DOUGHTY, T. C'k.'<anchor xml:id="s80"/></p>
                         
          <p>The records and documents mentioned in the last section of the 
            above certificate, as having been entered in a book provided for that
            purpose, were very few in number, compared to what there were belonging
            to the town of Brooklyn and county of Kings: and those 
            found, were completely chiefly of wills of deceased person, inventories
            of household furniture and agricultural implements, and a few deeds
            of conveyance of small plots of land—the most important, valuable
            and useful, having been stolen by John Rapelye, and up to this time,
            have not been recovered. These two certificates furnish undoubted 
            evidence that the principal records were stolen, as a diligent and most
            thorough search was made for them, which proved to be unsuccessful.</p> 
            <p>Thus, two wicked and unprincipled officials have by stealth, deprived
            Brooklyn of some of the principal means of establishing her 
            rights, and recovering a valuable property, dishonestly obtained and 
            illegally and unrighteously held and retained by the corporation of
            New-York. Enough, however, has been fortunately discovered, to 
            ultimately secure our long lost rights, if the Common Council of our 
            city will but take the matter in hand, and prosecute it with a determined
            energy to accomplish it; of which, there can be no doubt that</p>           
    <pb xml:id="leaf023v" facs="loc.03782.037.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">60</fw>
        <p><span from="#s81" to="#s82" xml:id="s81" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>The advantages which must necessarily flow to Brooklyn
        from the wharves, piers and ferries, would be immense. The revenue
        would also be considerable, while the many other advantages will very
        far exceed that of any other in the city. The sources from which
        this revenue will be derived, and the advantages which must accrue
        to Brooklyn, will be from the ferries and the erection of wharves,
        piers and bulkheads, at the termination of each street at the river.</p>
        <p>These piers may be built to the distance of three or four hundred
        feet in length into the river, and two hundred feet in width, without 
        the least obstruction to the navigation of the river. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The East River,
        at the foot of Fulton street, is 2193 feet wide, being nearly half a 
        mile. At the foot of Main street, 2205 feet wide, and at the foot of</hi>
        Atlantic street, 3198 feet wide, affording ample space at or between 
        any of these points, for piers of the above mentioned length and 
        width. There are 21 streets between Hudson avenue on the east,
        and the intersection of Hamilton avenue, at the commencement of the
        Atlantic Dock, on the south; the terminus of each of which street
        is at the river where a pier may be erected by the Common Council 
        of Brooklyn, which is, and would be no more or less than the continuation 
        of the street so terminating, being a public highway.</p>
        <p>That the Common Council would have, (and I contend they now
        have) the right to erect such piers, wharves, or bulkheads, in the<anchor xml:id="s82"/>
        event of graining possession of the water front and ferries, there can 
        be no doubt, as these erections would be, in fact and in reality, the
        same as the streets of our city, being a continuation of the streets— 
        P<hi rend="smallcaps">UBLIC</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps">IGHWAYS</hi>.</p>
        <p>By these improvements, the commerce of our city will be greatly 
        increased. The Mechanic, the Merchant, the Artizan, and the laboring
        man, and every grade and character of business will be unmeasureably 
        augmented, the population and trade of our city enhanced,
        and the people's treasury will materially feel the good effects which 
        must inevitably result from regaining possession of our ferries and
        water rights. Instead of Merchants, Mechanics, Traders and citizens
        going to New York in order to supply themselves with many
        articles of merchandise, domestic and foreign, which cannot now be
        obtained here, there will be vessels of every grade and dimensions
        from abroad, unlading their rich and varied treasures on our docks,
        and on our shores, and receiving in return the manufactures and inventions
        of our people, and the rich products of our fertile and prolific 
        Island, making the city of Brooklyn what it should be, and what 
    <pb xml:id="leaf024v" facs="loc.03782.038.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">61</fw>
    it was designed it should be, a great commercial mart, and thereby
    effecting advantageously and profitably every branch of business,
    and verifying the proverb that "commerce moves all."</p>
    <p>Another great object and advantage to be attained by the consummation 
    of this object is, that the city of Brooklyn must inevitably become 
    a P<hi rend="smallcaps">ORT</hi> of entry, also from this cause, giving employment in various
    ways to thousands, and multiplying the resources of the city to
    an incalculable extent. </p>
    <p>These are a few of the many great and desirable advantages, which 
    beyond a peradventure, or the possibility of a doubt, must naturally 
    and unequivocally result to Brooklyn, in the final accomplishment of
    this great desideratum. All classes of this community will be benefitted,
    as the increase of every occupation and employment, will receive
    and feel its proportionate influence and benefit.</p>
    <span from="#s83" to="#s84" xml:id="s83" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/><p>A part of the property which New York claims ownership to, is the
    wharves and buildings now occupied by the Fulton Ferry Company,
    at the foot of Fulton street, and is assessed by the assessors of the 
    2nd Ward at $55,000, against the Ferry Company, the taxes on this 
    property as collected for the year 1848, was $510,51, and paid by
    the corporation of the city of New York.</p><anchor xml:id="s84"/>
    <p>This valuable property, of right belongs to the city of Brooklyn.
    From the manner in which it is entered on the assessor's and collector's 
    books, we are led to believe that the property belongs to citizens
    of Brooklyn, being assessed to the Ferry Company, as each one of 
    the gentleman composing this Company, are citizens of Brooklyn.— 
    <span from="#s85" to="#s86" xml:id="s85" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>Such however, is not the case, as the taxes upon this property is paid
    by the corporation of New York, who claim it as their own. The
    only object in thus misrepresenting this matter, can be no other than
    that the corporation of New York would have the city of Brooklyn
    believe that this property is owned by citizens of Brooklyn, and to
    keep us entirely in the dark as to the true state of the affair. The<anchor xml:id="s86"/>
    buildings, bridges, wharves, and all the appurtenances belonging to
      <span from="#s87" to="#s88" xml:id="s87" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2"/>and connected with this Ferry, have been erected by the Ferry Company,
    at the expense of said Company. They however, have only
    the use of them during the term of their lease, as there is a provision 
    in the lease that at the expiration of the said lease, should the 
    present Company elect not to renew the lease, that then and in that 
    case all the improvements of whatever nature or kind soever made
    by the said Ferry Company, shall revert to the corporation of the city
    of New York, and become the property of the said corporation.—</p><anchor xml:id="s88"/>
        <note place="bottom" type="authorial" anchored="true" resp="#h2">—Ah, this then is the reason
            we have such shabby Ferry Buildings</note>
      </body>    
  </text>
</TEI>