<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03453">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A Defence of the Christian Doctrines of the Society of Friends</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03453</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Vindication of the Quakers, &#38;c.</title>
                    <date notBefore="1838-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After 1838</date>
                    <idno type="callno">BX7731.V5 1820</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman,
                        1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title>A Defence of the Christian Doctrines of the Society of Friends</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1825">1825</date>
                    <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-03-26">changed document name</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-01-22">corrected image name</change>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-11-20">transcribed and encoded</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-05-22">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <div2>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_nhg.00328.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">PREFACE.</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">ix</fw>
                    <p>approaching the communion of modern unbelievers, but by the most unfair
                        means, are endeavouring to press into their company, many honourable
                        christian Quakers, who have long since fallen asleep in Jesus; and who in
                        life, and in death, declared that they had no fellowship with such
                        unfruitful works of darkness.</p>
                    <p> It is not, however, surprising that those who have thus swerved from the
                        ancient faith of the gospel, as held forth by this society, are anxious to
                        gloss over their pernicious principles, and to plume themselves with the
                        credit of antiquity and the authority of " primitive friends." There is
                        something so forbidding–so unpromising, so utterly comfortless and
                        unamiable, in the principles and character of an unbeliever, that few have
                        been found, who were bold enough to throw off the % mask, and voluntarily to
                        embrace it. They have generally sought to soften down the term, and to give
                        their doctrines a more inviting aspect, by pretending that they differed not
                        in essentials from sound christians; that they only stripped Christianity of
                        human trappings, and taught it "in its native excellence and purity," and
                        that many pious men were of their way of thinking. But the veil is too thin
                        to conceal the deformity which lies beneath. Infidelity, in its most
                        specious forms, has been too often detected, and too fully exposed, to give
                        them any hope of success, and the time is at hand, when they will be made
                        fully manifest.</p>
                    <p>The society of Friends, holds the same relation to other christian
                        professors, that ever it did. William Penn, in his "Testimony to the truth
                        as held by the people called Quakers,"written in 1698, says, " Because we
                        are separated from the publick communion and worship, it is too generally
                        concluded, that we deny the doctrines received by the church, and
                        consequently introduce a new religion; whereas we differ least; where we are
                        thought to differ most. For, setting aside some school terms, <hi rend="italic">we hold the substance of those doctrines, believed by the
                            Church of England, as to God, Christ, Spirit, Scripture, repentance,
                            sanctification, remission of sin, holy living and the resurrection of
                            the just and unjust to eternal rewards and punishments.</hi>
                        <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right"><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jyc">353</unclear></note> <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b001" from="#b001" to="#b002"/>But                        that wherein we differ most, is about worship, and conversation, and the <hi rend="italic">inward qualification</hi> of the soul, by the work of                         God's Spirit thereon, in pursuance of <hi rend="italic">these good and generally received doctrines</hi>." 2d vol. fol.
                        p. 881.<anchor xml:id="b002"/></p>
                    <p>It is the certain effect of a faithful submission to the leadings of the Holy
                        Spirit of Christ, to bring its followers into an humble and sincere belief
                        in the sublime doctrines of the christian religion; and as occasion
                        requires, to qualify them earnestly to contend for that precious faith once
                        delivered to the saints, against those who are labouring to destroy it.
                        Hence, it is not surprising,</p>
                    <fw type="footer" place="bottom">B</fw>
                </div2>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_nhg.00329.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <div2> 
                    <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                        REMARKS.</hi></head>
                    <p>It is no new thing for the writings of the early Quakers to be mutilated and
                        perverted, in order to prove their denial of the doctrines of our Lord Jesus
                        Christ and his apostles. Among the many accusations and calumnies which were
                        heaped upon this despised people, there was none more frequently reiterated,
                        nor more fully refuted and denied, than this, which the compilers of the
                        pamphlet are now endeavouring to support; and it is a fart, that,in order to
                        sustain it, the enemies of the society have <hi rend="italic">always</hi>
                        been compelled to resort to garbling or misrepresentation of their
                        language.</p>
                    <p>It is well known that the fundamental principle of the Society, is a belief
                        in, and an obedience to, the sensible influences of the holy spirit of 
                        Christ, in the soul. At the time of its first rise, this important doctrine
                        was too little known or believed in, while great dependence was placed upon
                        the observation of mere outward rites, and a bare historical belief in the
                        life, suffering, and death of Christ; the scriptures being considered as the
                        word of God, and the alone treasury of that knowledge which gives life
                        eternal. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note>Hence it
                        was, that the Society of Friends, strenuously enforced the <hi rend="italic">necessity</hi> of coming to the real experience of the work of
                        regeneration in the heart; to feel Christ ruling there by his spirit; that
                        so the blessed and most comfortable truths of Holy Scripture might be sealed
                        in, their experience, be the revelation of that power which gave the
                        scriptures forth. Now, because Friends preached the necessity of coming to
                        know <hi rend="italic">Christ within</hi>, they were charged with denying 
                            <hi rend="italic">Christ without</hi>, and with believing in Christ no
                        otherwise than as the <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">—</note>spirit in man. And because they taught the necessity of
                        the new birth in the soul, and a real change of heart, whereby all things
                        came to be of God, they were accused of slighting, or wholly denying, the
                        virtue of all that the Son of God had done for them, <hi rend="italic">without them</hi>.</p>
                    <p>These several accusations they again and again refuted; declaring that while
                        they enforced the necessity of the inward work, they were so far from <hi rend="italic">denying the outward</hi>, that they were taught by the
                        Holy Spirit, <hi rend="italic">most reverently and gratefully to believe,
                            and acknowledge all that was done by Jesus Christ without them</hi> ;
                        and that although, with the apostle, they believed the spirit of Christ was
                        in all men, who were not reprobates, yet, so far from doubting, they were
                        taught by this very spirit, unfeignedly to believe and own, both the Godhead
                        and manhood of Jesus Christ, "his miraculous conception, holy life,
                        miracles, propitiatory sacrifice, death, resurrection, ascension, mediation
                        and intercession; and openly to avow their full faith in all that was
                        contained in the Holy Scriptures of truth.</p>
                    <p>So repeatedly has the Society declared its belief, in all these doctrines of
                        the Christian religion, that the generality of liberal minded men have been
                        convinced of the soundness of its faith, and of its</p>
                    <fw type="footer" place="bottom">E</fw>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_nhg.00330.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                        REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">xix</fw>

                    <p>following pages, and to give a clear view of the great discrepancy and
                        contradiction between them; we subjoin the following extracts from his
                        letters, sermons, &amp;c. viz: <q><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SENTIMENTS OF
                                    ELIAS HICKS.</hi></p>
                            <p>"I dont admire at the difficulties thou hast had to encounter, in
                                regard to the <hi rend="italic">mode of redemption, generally held
                                    by professing</hi> christians, as being effected by the <hi rend="italic">death</hi> or <hi rend="italic">outward dying of
                                    Jesus Christ</hi> upon the outward wooden cross. <hi rend="italic">This</hi>, as it regards the redemption of the
                                immortal soul from the bondage of sin, <hi rend="italic">I consider
                                        <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">—</note>a vulgar error</hi>, that came in with the
                                apostacy from primitive christianity. The redemption effected by <hi rend="italic">this outward offering</hi>, would <hi rend="smallcaps">ONLY</hi>, according to the true analogy of
                                things, be a <hi rend="italic">redemption</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">outward bodies</hi>; for, as under the legal
                                dispensation, there were many legal institutes, that were binding
                                upon the people of Israel, and on no other people, and a breach of
                                these, produced <hi rend="italic">legal crimes</hi> to which
                                penalties were attached, and these inflicted on the <hi rend="italic">bodies of the Israelites</hi>; now I consider that
                                the offering of the body of Jesus Christ on the outward cross
                                applied only as <hi rend="italic">a matter of redemption to the
                                    Israelites</hi>; redeeming them from the curse of that covenant
                                and the penalties attendant on every breach thereof, and this
                                outward redemption was the top stone of that figurative
                                dispensation, as by it that dispensation with all its legal rites
                                and ceremonies was abolished and done away."—<hi rend="italic">Elias Hicks' letter to William B. Irish</hi>.</p>
                            <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b003" from="#b003" to="#b004"/>Why shouldst thou think it cruel or painful, that
                                God sent his Son into the world, and when in the world, permitted
                                him to suffer death by the hands of wicked men, when history informs
                                us that many thousands of righteous men and women have, by the
                                permission of the Almighty, been persecuted to death by wicked men;
                                yet, nevertheless, we do not believe that God sent any of these into
                                the world purposely to suffer death, in the cruel way they did, by
                                the cruel power of the wicked; <hi rend="italic">neither do I
                                    believe</hi> that <hi rend="italic">God sent Jesus Christ</hi>
                                into the world <hi rend="italic">purposely to suffer death</hi> in
                                the way he did, <hi rend="italic">any more than all them</hi>; for
                                    <hi rend="italic">I do not believe that God created</hi> any
                                rational being and <hi rend="italic">sent him into the world, to
                                    suffer death for other men</hi>; because they were wicked and he
                                was righteous; but that it was the righteousness of all these that
                                aggravated the wicked, and was the procuring cause of their hatred
                                and vengeance toward them when they cruelly persecuted them to
                                death. <anchor xml:id="b004"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note><span xml:id="s023" from="#s023" to="#s024" hand="#h1"/>But their sufferings was entirely
                                opposite to, and inconsistent with, the purpose and will of God, for
                                if it was not, the perpetrators of these dreadful crimes, and most
                                atrocious deeds, would all stand justified in his sight."<anchor xml:id="s024"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">]</note>—<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</p>
                            <p>"Hence we conclude, that <hi rend="italic">God never sent his Son,
                                    Jesus Christ</hi>, nor any of his rational creation, <hi rend="italic">purposely into the world to suffer death</hi>, by
                                cruel men, but only in his free and voluntary choice to attend to
                                and do his holy will in all things, and thereby glorify and enjoy
                                him, which all agree to be the chief <hi rend="italic">end and
                                    design of man's creation</hi>."—<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</p>
                            <p>"But as divine wisdom foresaw that his people Israel, would revolt
                                from his commandments, and rebel against his law, and become cruel
                                and hard hearted, so likewise he foresaw that the wicked
                            among</p></q>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_nhg.00331.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">xxi</fw> even our bodily lives, to
                        surrender for the gospel sake, and the testimony of a good
                            conscience."—<hi rend="italic">Wisdom Justified</hi>.</p>
                    <p>"First, By what means did Jesus suffer? The answer is plain,by the hands of
                        wicked men, and because his works were righteous, and theirs were wicked.
                        Query. Did God send him into the world, purposely to suffer death by the
                        hands of wicked men? By no means, <hi rend="italic">but to live <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">—</note>a righteous
                            and godly life</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">which was the design and end of
                            God's creating man in the beginning</hi>,) and thereby be a perfect
                        example to such of mankind as should come to the knowledge of him and of his
                        perfect life. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">(</note><span hand="#h1" xml:id="s081" from="#s081" to="#s082"></span>For
                        if it was the purpose and will of God, that he <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">should</hi> die by the hands of wicked men, then the Jews, by
                        crucifying him, would have done God's will, and of course would all have
                        stood justified in his sight, which could not be.<anchor xml:id="s082"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">)</note> But it was permitted so to be, as <hi rend="italic">it had been</hi> with many of <hi rend="italic">the
                            prophets</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">wise and good men</hi> that were
                        before <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, who suffered death by the hands of wicked
                        men for righteousness sake, <hi rend="italic">as ensamples</hi> to those
                        that came after, that they should account nothing too dear to give up for
                        the truth's sake, not even their own lives."—<hi rend="italic">Letter
                            to Dr. JV. Shoemaker</hi>.</p>
                    <p>"But I <hi rend="smallcaps">DO NOT CONSIDER THAT THE CRUCIFIXION OF THE
                            OUTWARD BODY OF FLESH AND BLOOD OF JESUS ON THE CROSS, WAS AN ATONEMENT
                            FOR ANY SINS BUT THE LEGAL SINS OF THE JEWS</hi>; for as their law was
                        outward, so their legal sins and their penalties were outward, and these
                        could be atoned for by an outward sacrifice; and this last outward sacrifice
                        was a full <hi rend="smallcaps">type</hi> of the inward sacrifice that every
                        sinner must make, in giving up that sinful life of his own will, in and by
                        which he hath from time to time crucified the innocent life of God in his
                        own soul, and which Paul calls, the old man with his deeds, or the man of
                        sin and son of perdition, who hath taken God's seat in the heart, and there
                        exalteth itself above all that is called God or is worshipped, sitting as
                        judge and supreme. Now all this life, power,and will of man, must be slain
                        and die on the cross spiritually, as Jesus died on the cross outwardly, and
                        this <hi rend="italic">is the true atonement</hi>, which that outward
                        atonement was a clear and full <hi rend="italic">type of</hi>. This the
                        apostle Paul sets forth in a plain manner. Romans, vi. 3,4. Know ye not that
                        so many of us as were baptised into Jesus Christ, were baptised into his
                        death ? Therefore, we are buried with him by baptism into death, that like
                        as Christ was raised up from the dead, (outwardly,) by the glory of the
                        Father, even so we, having by the spiritual baptism witnessed a death to sin
                        shall know a being raised up spiritually and walk in newness of
                            life."—<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b005" from="#b005" to="#b006"/>And inasmuch as those idle promulgators of original sin, believe they are
                        made sinners, without their consent or knowledge, which, according to the
                        nature and reason of things, every rational mind must see is impossible; so
                        likewise, they are <hi rend="italic">idle</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ignorant</hi> enough to believe they are made righteous without their
                        consent or knowledge, <hi rend="italic">by the righteousness of one</hi> who
                        lived on the earth near two thousand years before they had an existence; and
                        this by the cruel hands of wicked men, slaying an innocent and righteous
                        one; and these are bold and daring enough, to lay this cruel and unholy act
                        in the charge of divine justice as having purposely ordained it to be so:
                        but what an outrage it is against every righteous law of God<anchor xml:id="b006"/>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_nhg.00332.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">xxii</fw>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw> 
                         and man, as the scriptures
                        abundantly testify. See Exod. ch. 23, v. 7. " Keep thee far from a false
                        matter, and the innocent and righteously thou not, for I will not justify
                        the wicked." Deut. 27 ch. 25 v. "Cursed be he that taketh reward, to slay an
                        innocent person ;" and much more might be produced to show the <hi rend="italic">wickedness and absurdity of the doctrine</hi>, that would
                        accuse the perfectly just all-wise and merciful Jehovah of so barbarous and
                        cruel an act as that of slaying his innocent and righteous son, to atone for
                        the sins and iniquities of the ungodly.</p>
                    <p>"Surely <hi rend="italic">is it possible</hi> that any <hi rend="italic">rational being</hi>, that has any right sense of justice or mercy, that
                            <hi rend="italic">would be willing to accept forgiveness of his sins, on
                            such terms</hi>! Would he not <hi rend="italic">rather</hi> go forward
                        and offer himself wholly up, to suffer <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the <hi rend="italic">penalties due</hi> to his crimes, rather than the innocent
                        should suffer? Nay, was he so hardy, as to acknowledge a willingness <hi rend="italic">to be saved through such a medium</hi>, would it not
                        prove, that he stood in <hi rend="italic">direct opposition</hi>, to <hi rend="italic">every principle of justice and honesty</hi>, <hi rend="italic">of mercy and love</hi>, and show himself to be a poor,
                        selfish creature, and unworthy of notice!" Ibid.</p>
                    <p>Elias Hicks, in his letter to Thomas Willis, on the miraculous conception of
                        the Lord Jesus Christ, says :</p>  
                    <p>"Finding this to be the case, <hi rend="italic">I examined the accounts given
                            on this subject, by the four Evangelists, and according to my best
                            judgment on the occasion, 1 was led to think there was considerable more
                            scripture evidence for his being the son of Joseph than otherwise</hi>;
                        although it has not yet changed my belief, are the consequences which follow
                        much more favourable; for as the Israelitish covenant rested very much upon
                        external evidence by way of outward miracle, <hi rend="italic">so I conceive
                            this miraculous birth was intended principally to induce the Israelites
                            to believe he was their promised Messiah, or the great prophet, Moses
                            had long before prophesied of, that should come, like unto
                        himself.</hi></p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b007" from="#b007" to="#b008"/>But, when we consider that he was born of a woman that was joined in
                        lawful wedlock with a man of Israel, it would seem that it must shut the way
                        to the enforcing any such belief, as all their neighbours would naturally be
                        led to consider him the son of Joseph, and this it appears very clear they
                        did, by the scripture testimony: and although it has not, as above
                        observed, given cause as yet, to alter my views on the subject, as tradition
                        is a mighty bulwark, not easily removed, yet it has had this salutary
                        effect, to deliver me from judging my brethren and fellow creatures who are
                        in that belief, <hi rend="italic">and can feel the same flow of love and
                            unity with them, as though they were in the same belief with myself;
                            neither would I dare to say, positively, that it would be my mind, they
                            should change their belief, unless 1 could give them much greater
                            evidence than 1 am at present possessed of, as 1 consider in regard to
                            our salvation, they are both non-essentials; and I may further say,
                            that I believe it would be much greater sin in me, to smoke tobacco that
                            was the produce of the labour of slaves, than it would be to believe
                            either of these positions;</hi>"—See <hi rend="italic">Letter to
                            T. Willis</hi>.<anchor xml:id="b008"/></p>
                    <p><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="j005" from="#j005" to="#j006"/>I admit that I did
                        assert, and have long done it, that we cannot <anchor xml:id="j006"/><pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_nhg.00333.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">xxiii</fw>
                        <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b009" from="#b009" to="#b010"/>believe what we do not understand; this the scripture affirms; Deut.
                        xxix. 29.' The secret things belong unto the Lord our God, but the things
                        that are revealed belong unto us, and our children forever, that we may do
                        all the words of this law;' and all that is not revealed is to us the same
                        as a nonentity, and will forever remain so, until it is revealed; and that
                        which is revealed enables us, agreeably to the apostle's exhortation, to
                        give a reason of the hope that is in us, to honest inquirers."—<hi rend="italic">E. Hicks' Letter to Dr. E. A. Atlee.</hi><anchor xml:id="b010"/></p>
                    <p>"As to what she [Anna Braithwaite,] relates as it regards the manner of our
                        coming into the world in our infant state, it is my belief that we come into
                        the world in the same state of innocence, and endowed with the same
                        propensities and desires, that our first parents were, in their primeval
                        state; and this Jesus Christ has established, and must be conclusive in the
                        minds of all true believers, when he took a little child in his arms, and
                        blessed him, and said to them around him, that except they were converted,
                        and became as that little child, they should in no case enter into the
                        kingdom of heaven. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b011" from="#b011" to="#b012"/>Of course, <hi rend="italic">all the
                            desires</hi> and <hi rend="italic">propensities</hi> of that little
                        child, and of our first parents, in their primeval state, must have been
                        good, as they were all the endowments of their Creator, and given to them
                        for a special and useful purpose. But it is the improper and unlawful
                        indulgence of them that is evil."<anchor xml:id="b012"/></p>
                    <p>"I readily acknowledge I have not been able to see or understand how the
                        cruel persecution and crucifixion of Jesus Christ, by the wicked and hard
                        hearted Jews, should expiate my sins; and <hi rend="italic">I never have
                            known any thing to effect that for me</hi>, but the grace of God, that
                        taught me, agreeably to the apostle's doctrine, to deny all ungodliness and
                        the world's lusts, and to live soberly, righteously and godly, in this
                        present world; and as I have faithfully abode under its teachings, in full
                        obedience thereto, I have been brought to believe that my sins were
                        forgiven, and I permitted to sit under the Lord's teaching, as saith the
                        prophet, that the children of the Lord are all taught of the Lord, and in
                        righteousness they are established, and great is the peace of his children.
                        And so long as I feel this peace, there is nothing in this world that makes
                        me afraid, as it respects my eternal condition. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b013" from="#b013" to="#b014"/>But if any of my
                        friends have received <hi rend="italic">any known benefit</hi> from <hi rend="italic">any outward</hi> sacrifice, I do not envy them their
                        privileges. But surely they would not be willing that I should acknowledge,
                            <hi rend="italic">as a truth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">that which I have
                                no kind of knowledge of</hi>." &#8211;Ibid.</p>
                    <anchor xml:id="b014"/>
                    <p>We shall now quote some extracts from Elias Hicks' sermons, recently
                        delivered in the city of Philadelphia, and the neighbouring counties, which
                        will be found to correspond with the sentiments expressed in his
                        letters.</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b015" from="#b015" to="#b016"/>Sermon I. at Arch street, pages 10, 11. Speaking of Christ, he said, "Who
                        was his father? He was begotten of God. <hi rend="italic">We cannot suppose
                            that it was the outward body of flesh and blood that was begotten of
                            God</hi>, but a birth of the spiritual life in the soul. We must apply
                        it <hi rend="italic">internally and spiritually</hi>. For <hi rend="italic">nothing can be a son of God, but that which is spirit</hi>; and nothing
                        but the soul of man is a recipient for the light and spirit of God.
                        Therefore, <hi rend="italic">nothing can be</hi><anchor xml:id="b016"/></p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_nhg.00334.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                        REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">xxv</fw>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">gether, and make a being, nor make a son of God</hi>.  
                        Nothing but the rational souls of men and women can come to know a birth of
                        God: and the rational soul never was created by flesh, or through flesh.
                        The animal part is taken, and created flesh, by the power of God."</p>
                    <p>In the same sermon, speaking of " the life which was the light of men," he
                        says, "Here now are we all to have a portion of the same light, for the
                        life was the light of men, and it remains eternally so. It all comes from
                        God, and is dispensed to the children of men, and <hi rend="italic">it was
                            to Jesus Christ likewise, as man</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic">same
                            proportion</hi> as to inscrutable wisdom seemed necessary and
                        consistent, to effect the great design in the creation and redemption of the
                        children of men."</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b017" from="#b017" to="#b018"/>So here we see Jesus made lower than the angels, on account of his
                        suffering death. He was tempted in all points, as we are. Now, how could he
                        be tempted, <hi rend="italic">if he</hi> had been fixed <hi rend="italic">in
                            a state of perfection in which he could not turn aside</hi>? <anchor xml:id="b018"/>Can you suppose, as rational beings, that such a being
                        could be tempted? No, not any more than God Almighty could be tempted. <hi rend="italic">Perfection is perfection,<note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">—</note> and cannot be tempted</hi>. It is
                        impossible: and here it is proved to a demonstration, that <hi rend="italic">he came to be an example</hi> to the children of men; a great high
                        priest and teacher in those things which concern the salvation of the
                        children of men. And here he did his office, as a great high priest of <hi rend="italic">the Jewish covenant, in that outward</hi> dispensation, in
                        which he was limited to the Jewish people as a child of Abraham; to sum up
                        all the righteousness of the law; by faithfulness to it: and when he had
                        effected that part, <hi rend="italic">by the grace of God</hi> that was upon
                        him, for we read that he grew in stature and in favour with God and man ;
                        and the grace of God was upon him.' Then <hi rend="italic">it was not</hi>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">HIS</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">grace</hi>, but the grace of God, <hi rend="italic">communicated to him, as it was communicated to the rest of Abraham's
                            children</hi>; to every one in a sufficient<note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">—</note> degree to enable them to come up
                        to the law and commandments given them. It will not do for us to suppose,
                        for a moment, that the Almighty, when he gave this law, did not at the same
                        time give them power to fulfil it in all its parts. For if he did not, they
                        could not be accountable for a neglect. But we see that he did this, for
                        here was a child of Abraham, <hi rend="italic">endued with his spirit, which
                            he has given <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">—</note>to every rational creature</hi> to profit with. He
                        lived up to the law and covenant given by the Father, and in this he
                        justified his heavenly Father in giving this law and covenant, and thereby
                        condemned the Israelites for not fulfilling it. Well, when he had done this,
                        for we hear of <hi rend="italic">no miracles till after all this was
                            done</hi>, none at all; nor any thing of <hi rend="italic">his
                            righteousness or acts</hi>; but now, when he went into the last
                        institute of the legal dispensation, which was called watery baptism, and
                        the ministry of John, his forerunner, was nearly at an end, divine wisdom
                        thought fit to reveal to John, by what medium he should know who it was that
                        was to baptize with the Holy Ghost. It was him on whom the spirit should be
                        seen descending and resting upon him.</p>
                    <p>"Now, we find, that when he came up out of the water, John having baptized
                        him, the Holy Ghost descended in bodily shape like a dove, and rested upon
                        him. Now, whether this was open to John's <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_nhg.00335.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">xxvi</fw>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                         external eye, or whether it
                        might not rather be an expression of John's, that as the dove is the most
                        innocent creature of the feathered race, he made use of it, to express what
                        he beheld in him, and in this power that descended upon him. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note><span xml:id="s021" from="s021" to="s022" hand="#h1"/>This was a
                        power from heaven—an <hi rend="italic">additional</hi> power and gift
                        from heaven; as by his righteousness in fulfilling the law, he was prepared
                        to enter into a <hi rend="italic">higher</hi> dispensation.<anchor xml:id="s022"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">]</note></p>
                    <p>"I consider, according to the tenor of the law, that the whole design was to
                        lead up some of the Israelites into this state of perfection, and fulfilment
                        of the law; and then that it should be abolished. Hence, the fulfilment of
                        the law was the abolishment of the law. He abolished it by nailing it to his
                        cross. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note>Oh! had the
                        professors of Christianity left it there, and been willing to go forward,
                        under the illumination of the Holy Ghost, which alone could qualify Jesus to
                        be a gospel minister; so likewise, according to his own testimony, nothing
                        ever did or can qualify for the ministry, but the descending of the Holy
                        Ghost from heaven, upon rational creatures. And, therefore, in the same
                        proportion <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">as we have</hi> the descending of
                        the holy spirit upon us, in the same proportion, till we gain a conquest
                        over <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">——</note>our
                        passions and propensities, we shall be <hi rend="italic">more tempted and
                            tried</hi>. So it was with Jesus, when this holy spirit descended upon
                        him, the spirit drove him into the wilderness to be tempted of Satan.,</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b019" from="#b019" to="#b020"/>
                        "Now, let us pause a little, and consider what is here meant. Can it be
                        supposed that he was driven into an <hi rend="italic">outward</hi>
                        wilderness? Or shall we not suppose, that he was brought, by the power of
                        divine light, <hi rend="italic">to see the wilderness state in his own
                            mind</hi>? Because, in the outward wilderness a man loses his way, and
                        meets with many trials; and so there is a spiritual wilderness, where man is
                        tempted and tried. Here the natural propensities which are fixed in man, no
                        doubt for an excellent purpose, rise up and attempt to gain an ascendency
                        over us. Here we find it in all things in us. The propensity to
                        thirst&#8211;what does it do? It is a gift of God to the children of men. It
                        leads them to do that which might sustain their natural life. But if not
                        regulated and kept under subjection by the immortal soul, which is placed in
                        us to regulate these animal desires and propensities, it will become
                        injurious to us, by being indulged to excess. For you know we have many
                        propensities; many that are necessary to us: for we could not eat or drink,
                        or have a desire to do if, if we had not a propensity to it. We could not
                        fulfil the command, to increase and multiply, and replenish the earth, had
                        we not a desire which led to it. These propensities are all good in their
                        place; and we could not answer the end of our creation without them. As it
                        is not in bones to think, or flesh to reason, so there is no bounds to our
                        natural desires: but the soul must wait for counsel from on high, and direct
                        the body, and by faithfulness to it, regulate all these desires, and keep
                        them within the bounds of reason and truth. This was the case with the
                        blessed Jesus, so that he never offended in any one point; but learnt
                        obedience by the things he suffered. <hi rend="italic">He had all these
                            desires. The desire after knowledge, and the things of the world,
                            presented itself to his animal part</hi>; and thus it is said to have
                        driven him into the wilderness: that is, he felt <hi rend="italic">that
                            wilderness</hi><anchor xml:id="b020"/>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc_nhg.00336.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">xxvii</fw> which man feels, while in a
                        state of probation. It is the way in which divine wisdom speaks of the
                        church.' I will allure her, and draw her into the wilderness, and speak
                        comfortably unto her.' I will allure her&#8211;see, I will draw her. Now
                        what wilderness was this? It was not an outward wilderness; but the same
                        which Jesus was led up into: and here it was that he was tried. Here the
                        tempter <hi rend="italic">led him up to aspire after the glory of the
                            world</hi>. He told him if he would fall down and worship him, that he
                        could arrive at it—if he would only submit to this desire, and fall
                        down and worship it, all should be his: but you see how ready he was to
                        reply to this temptation. The divine law always gives us an answer, and if
                        <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">—</note>we are faithful, <hi rend="italic">we shall be like Jesus</hi>; when we are
                        tempted to aspire after the glories of the world. We shall be always able to
                        give a righteous answer, if we are faithful to the truth in our own minds,
                            <hi rend="italic">as fully as he was</hi>, no doubt; because he is our
                        example, and we are to follow his steps. Jesus said, ' Get thee behind me,
                        satan.' Oh! how often has my poor soul been brought to this point, when
                        temptations have arisen, 'Get thee behind me, satan.' Oh! I have seen that
                        it was mine enemy; the light of truth has revealed it to me; and I have felt
                        sometimes, in a degree, like the blessed Jesus. I have seen that mine enemy
                        hath wanted to exalt me: but I could ask no honour or power, for I knew that
                        he had none to give, nor any power to preserve me one moment.</p>
                    <p>"'Get thee behind me, satan: for it is written, thou shalt worship the Lord
                        thy God, and him only shalt thou serve.' Is not this the case with all of
                        us? Have we not this language in our souls; that sometimes tells us it is
                        not right to serve any thing else in this world. Here, if we are faithful to
                        the divine light, we shall in proportion be able to withstand every
                        temptation that may assail us in our state of wilderness, travel, and
                        probation.</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b021" from="#b021" to="#b022"/>"We read that he was taken up and set upon a pinnacle of the temple. And do
                        you suppose there was some power which actually took him up, and set him
                        upon a pinnacle? No, I hope there are none so ignorant as to suppose so. It
                        was <hi rend="italic">a temptation to exalt himself, for his
                            righteousness</hi>—<hi rend="italic">his goodness</hi>. And have
                        you not, many of you, been set upon this pinnacle of high honour?<anchor xml:id="b022"/> Have <hi rend="italic">you not a little religious
                            pride</hi>? What was that saying then to the tempter? He was placed in
                        a dangerous situation; but not more so than the soul is when tempted to
                        aspire in consequence of its righteousness. The tempter 'saith unto him, if
                        thou be the son of God, cast thyself down: for it is written,he shall give
                        his angels charge concerning thee; and in their hands shall they bear thee
                        up, lest at anytime thou dash thy foot against a stone.'" Pages 252 to
                        259.</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b023" from="#b023" to="#b024"/>Sermon XI. Trenton. Page 292. "If we believe that God is equal and
                        righteous in all his ways; that he has made of one blood all the families
                        that dwell upon the earth, it is impossible that he should be partial; and
                        therefore, he has been as willing to reveal his will to every creature, as
                        he was to our first parents, to Moses and the prophets, to <hi rend="smallcaps">JESUS CHRIST</hi>, and his apostles. He never can <hi rend="italic">set</hi>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ANY</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">of these above us</hi>, because, if he did, he would be
                        partial. His love is the same for all, and as no man can save his brother,
                        or give<anchor xml:id="b024"/>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc_nhg.00337.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">xxviii</fw>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                         a ransom for his soul,
                        therefore (he Almighty must be the only deliverer of his people."</p>
                    <p>Sermon V. Germantown. "All must go away. We must <hi rend="italic">no longer
                            look to the letter, let it come from what source it may, it is no
                            difference</hi>. He directed them to wait for the spirit. 'I will pray
                        the Father,and he will send you another comforter;' another than the letter,
                        and different from any that you ever heard verbally <hi rend="italic">from
                            me</hi>, or from men; for it is <hi rend="italic">all but letter</hi>;
                        all that can come to you through your external senses. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="j001" from="#j001" to="#j002"/>But the will of God
                        manifested within us never can come through the external senses, it must
                        come through the spiritual senses: and then it will quicken the soul, open
                        the blind eye and deaf ear of the soul, so that it can see and hear the
                        things of God clearly.<anchor xml:id="j002"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">]</note> The time has come, I believe, when it is necessary to give up
                        all our old foundations, and suffer them, my friends, to pass under
                        judgment, that judgment may pass upon all, and that this truth may be
                        revealed. It is expedient that I go away: for if I go not away the Comforter
                        will not come, but if I go away I will pray the Father, and he will send you
                        another Comforter? Another, in what respect? A spiritual one disencumbered
                        with any thing corporal; <hi rend="italic">entirely spiritual and nothing
                            else</hi>. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b025" from="#b025" to="#b026"/> Why?&#8211;Because the soul of man is purely
                        spiritual, and nothing can have communion with the Father but that which is
                        spiritual, an immortal soul. <hi rend="italic">Every thing then derived from
                            the letter</hi>, must come through the external senses<anchor xml:id="b026"/>, <hi rend="italic">and can only answer for the outward
                            creature</hi>: but when the spiritual senses are quickened by the coming
                        in of the spirit of God, and the shining of his light upon the soul, it
                        opens a renewed intercourse with his creature man, as he did with our first
                        parents in the beginning in Eden's garden." Pages 112,113.</p>
                    <p>Same sermon, page 119. "We have a gracious God to do with, who is able to
                        give all that is necessary. If the Scriptures were absolutely necessary, he
                        had power to communicate them to all the nations of the earth. For he has
                        his way as a path in the clouds; he knows how to deal out to all his
                        rational children. But they were not necessary, and perhaps <hi rend="italic">not suited to any other people than</hi> they to whom they
                        were written. Is it to be supposed that he has neglected any nation? Can we
                        suppose that he has forgotten the rest of the nations of the earth ? No, he
                        has dispensed a suitable law, to answer every purpose, as completely as the
                        law to the Israelites answered for them; for otherwise he is a partial
                        God.</p>
                    <p>Sermon VI. Abington. "The New Testament so called, which is usually bound up
                        in the book called the Bible, <hi rend="italic">comprehends no covenant;
                            there is nothing</hi> in it that appertains to a covenant. It consists
                        chiefly and principally in a biographical account of the birth, the
                        miracles, and the excellent life of Jesus Christ, the son of Mary, and of
                        the epistles and writings of his apostles. But the covenant made with
                        Israel, as comprehended in what is called the Old Testament, was a real
                        covenant, and was bound in a very solemn manner, and had its witnesses."
                        Page 124.</p>
                    <p>Sermon VII. page 163. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">[</note><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="j003" from="#j003" to="#j004"/>Nothing can write God's law upon our hearts but the finger of
                        God. There it it is, then, that we must gather, as the only place of safety;
                        there the work is to be<anchor xml:id="j004"/> <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc_nhg.00338.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">INTRODUCTORY
                                REMARKS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">xxix</fw> <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="j020" from="#j020" to="#j021"/>done. It is there, we find
                        our enemy, if we have any, and there we must find our friend. But people are
                        too generally looking outward to find God; and in this outward looking,
                        they are told about a devil; some monstrous creature, some self-existing
                        creature, that is terrible in power. Now all this seeking to know God, and
                        this devil or the serpent without, is the work of darkness, superstition,
                        and tradition. It hath no foundation; it is all breath and wind, without the
                        power. We need not look without for enemies or friends, for we shall not
                        find them without. Our enemies are those of our own household, our own
                        propensities and unruly desires, are our greatest, and I may almost say, our
                        alone enemies."<anchor xml:id="j021"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">]</note></p>
                    <p>Sermon XI. Trenton, 293. "There is nothing can give us faith but God. Faith
                        is the gift of God. But this faith in creeds and the traditions of our
                        fathers, what is it? It is worse than nothing. We had better have no faith
                        at all. It is no better than the faith of devils. Thou believest that there
                        is one God; thou dost well: the devils also, believe and tremble." Who are
                        the devils?&#8211;Apostate men and women, who go contrary to God. They are
                        all devils. Every thing that is in opposition to the will of God is a devil.
                        In short, <hi rend="italic">they are nothing</hi> but what opposes the law
                        of light and the spirit of truth in the heart; <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> but what is in opposition to the law of God; and that
                        devil is in us all; <hi rend="italic">as sure as the kingdom of God is in
                            us</hi>, so sure the devil is in us. Were you ever tempted by any devil
                        but one in your own souls? No: you never were.&#8211;There it is that we
                        come to know God, and no where else. It is the only place where he is
                        manifested."</p>
                    <p>Such are the absurd, inconsistent, and antichristian sentiments of Elias
                        Hicks; and <hi rend="italic">to support these</hi>, the compilers of the
                        pamphlet have adduced their quotations from the writings of primitive
                        Friends. It being fully proved, and well known, that not only Elias Hicks,
                        but many of his adherents, do openly and <choice>
                            <orig>publickly</orig>
                            <reg>publicly</reg>
                        </choice> deny the miraculous conception, divinity, and atonement of Christ,
                        and the authenticity, and divine authority of Holy Scripture; and the
                        compilers having made their extracts purposely to prove that our early
                        Friends were coincident in their faith; we consider, that the publication of
                        the pamphlet, is, undeniably, a renewal of the often refuted charge against
                        the Society, of denying the doctrines of the christian religion.</p>

                    <p><hi rend="italic">Note</hi>.&#8211;The limits of this work will not admit of
                        extending our quotations from the Sermons to great length. We can embrace
                            <hi rend="italic">but few</hi> of the objectionable sentiments with
                        which the <hi rend="italic">whole volume</hi> is replete. Those we have
                        quoted, are amply sufficient to show the <hi rend="italic">striking
                            contrast</hi> between the christian doctrines of the Quakers, and the
                        notions of Elias Hicks. The books from which we have made our extracts are
                        easily accessible to all, and we respectfully recommend those persons who
                        read them, to compare the sentiments they contain, with those asserted by
                        "primitive Friends," in the extracts given in the following pages. </p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc_nhg.00339.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">89</fw>
                    <p>The Light of Christ was as all-sufficient for salvation in the days of
                        Cornelius as it is now; It could as easily have unfolded to him, the counsel
                        of God, as to bid him send for Peter to tell him what he ought to do. But
                        because the Lord ordained the use of instrumental means, was it any reason,
                        why Cornelius should reject the teaching of Peter, as being subordinate to
                        the Spirit? If when Peter came, Cornelius had said to him, I have the Light
                        in myself&#8211;this is all-sufficient for my direction and government; I
                        "have no need to go to books or men;" thou may go thy way, I have no need of
                        any human teaching; would this have been honouring and reverencing the
                        Light, or is it probable that Cornelius would have been favoured with its
                        further illuminations ? Certainly not&#8211;it would have been <hi rend="italic">pretending</hi> honour to the Spirit, while at the same
                        time, he was despising those very means which the Spirit of Christ had
                        sanctified for his use.</p>
                    <p>Let those in the present day, who are making use of this specious but
                        dangerous and delusive reasoning, against the use of the Sacred Volume,
                        remember, that in all ages and dispensations of the world, it has pleased
                        Almighty God to teach his people not only immediately but
                        instrumentally&#8211;immediately by his grace and good spirit, and
                        instrumentally by the Holy Scriptures and his faithful servants. Both of
                        these are blessings, sanctified and given for our use; and although the
                        revelations of the Holy Spirit are above all other teachings, yet they are
                        not at our command; and if we slight and reject the secondary means, which
                        are given forth by the same Spirit for our instruction in righteousness, we
                        do as certainly rebel against, and deny the Holy Spirit, and whatever
                        pretences we may make to the contrary, set up in its stead, our own
                        self-confident spirit as judge in the case.</p>
                    <p>The next quotation, on page 72 of the pamphlet, is taken from William Penn's
                        "Guide Mistaken, and Temporizing Rebuked, or a brief reply to Jonathan
                        Clapham's book, entitled, A Guide to the True Religion." It is contained in
                        his 12th section or paragraph, in which he discusses the Guide's first
                        article of true religion; viz. that there is one God, of an infinite,
                        perfect, and spiritual nature, subsisting in <hi rend="italic">three
                            glorious persons</hi>. To which distinction of <hi rend="italic">persons</hi> William Penn replies&#8211;</p>
                    <p>"As for his strange distinction of the Deity, which he enforces on the faith
                        of all that value their eternal welfare, I cannot find one Scripture that
                        will bear him out; and if they had been of so much credit with this Guide,
                        as to have been by them led into their undeniable form of sound words, he
                        would not have intruded tradition for Scripture, to the creed of any, but
                        rather have inserted the text or phrase itself, whose authority might have
                        commanded an assent: and it had become him to give the world a reason for
                        his requiring a submission to, and credence of his doctrine, rather than
                        barely to draw up so many articles, and thus imperiously to call on all for
                        a subscription, as they would be saved; especially since he cannot but know
                        how strongly these very points have been debated in ancient councils, and
                        not less controverted by modern persons of reputation and learning." [Here
                        William Penn introduces</p>
                    <fw type="footer" place="bottom">M</fw>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc_nhg.00340.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">298</hi></fw>
                    <p>inference, I say, is as irrational, as it would be for any to conclude, that
                        because we say of the shining and appearance of the Sun, there is the Sun;
                        or the Sun there appears; therefore we exclude the Being of the Sun
                        elsewhere. For its virtue is communicated to our natural bodies, every one
                        having in measure, some enjoyment of the virtue or light of the natural Sun,
                        which is light to the eye, even as the outward eye is light to, or of the
                        natural body; and whosoever they are, whose invisible senses are quickened
                        by the influencing virtue which proceeds from the eternal Sun of
                        righteousness, do thereby see and discern, that these things are according
                        to the clear manifestation of Truth in their inward parts; and from a true
                        sense thereof, can of a truth give this certain testimony, that Christ, the
                        Lord, by his holy, quickening spirit, hath appeared in them, to the
                        quickening of their immortal souls; and that through believing in the
                        light, and obedience to his appearance, being come out of that state which
                        is reprobated by the Lord, can of certain experimental knowledge say, Christ
                        is in us the hope of glory. And so when we direct people to this Word,
                        Light, Law, Grace and Spirit, we do not thereby intend, that Christ Jesus,
                        the Light of the World, and Gift of God, is not the true Saviour, Redeemer,
                        and Reconciler of mankind unto God." &#8211;Works, page 71 to 77. 1673.</p>
                    <p>In a piece entitled "A Warning unto the Rulers and People of England,
                        &amp;c." C. Marshall speaks thus&#8211;</p>
                    <p>"In the tender love of God, unto whose ears the misrepresentations,
                        vilifications or aspersions underwritten, have or may come&#8211; Give ear, and
                        hear, all you rulers and inhabitants of these northern islands: God
                        Almighty, even the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, in this later age of the
                        world is risen and arising, and causing his ancient horn of salvation to be
                        revealed: of whom all the holy men, prophets and servants of God gave
                        testimony, through, ages and generations, to be that Holy One, on whom he
                        hath laid help, who is mighty to save, Christ Jesus the Lord; of whose
                        spiritual appearance and coming we are witnesses this day; and by the arm of
                        his eternal power are raised up, to declare him unto these Northern Islands
                        of the Gentiles, as their Light to lighten them, according to the prophet's
                        testimony, of John, old Simeon, Christ Jesus, the Apostles and messengers of
                        God Almighty, through many ages and generations, of which many demonstrative
                        testimonies, in the evidence and demonstration of the spirit and power of
                        Christ Jesus, have been, and are daily borne both by word and writing;
                        against which holy, certain testimonies, men of the spirit of Jannes and
                        Jambres, men of corrupt minds have risen up to withstand, and by lies,
                        slanders, misrepresentings, &amp;c. have endeavoured their utmost to veil
                        and cloud this testimony; which work and way of theirs God hath beheld, and
                        hath determined to blast, because in their right hand hath been found a lie,
                        and the poison of asps is under their tongues, to reproach, vilify, and
                        misrepresent the servants and people of God, under hideous and odious
                        disguises, that they might thereby (as much as in them lies) effect such a
                        work, as the old heathens did on the Christians; namely, by putting lions'
                        skins and bearskins on them, that thereby they might cause the dogs to take
                        hold on them: so hath there been an</p>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">Probably torn by a child&#8211;</note>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>