<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03801">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Poet Laureate as Philosopher and Peer</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="hss">Henry Stevens Salt</author>
                <author xml:id="er">Ernest Radford</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lcb">Laura Beerits</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03801</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>The Poet Laureate as Philosopher and Peer: marginalia</title>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 49, Folder 3</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1884-02-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After February 1, 1884</date>                   
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Henry Stevens Salt</author>
                    <title level="a">The Poet Laureate as Philosopher and Peer</title>
                    <title level="j">To-Day: The Monthly Magazine of Scientific Socialism</title>
                    <date when="1884">1884</date>
                    <biblScope type="pp">135&#8211;147</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                    <publisher>The Modern Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base2" xml:id="r2">
                    <author>Ernest Radford</author>
                    <title level="a">"The Sun-Maiden"</title>
                    <title level="j">To-Day: The Monthly Magazine of Scientific Socialism</title>
                    <date when="1884">1884</date>
                    <biblScope type="pp">148</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                    <publisher>The Modern Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#hss" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#er" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lcb" when="2013-06-16">Transcribed.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-09-12">Encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-09-13">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-11-12">Revised bibliographical information and encoding.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-11-24">Checked revisions.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-03-10">Checked footnotes.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-11-02">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03801.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right"><handShift new="#h2"/>135</fw>
            <head type="main-authorial">The Poet Laureate as Philosopher and 
                Peer.</head>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <p>IN one of Victor Hugo's most remarkable novels, "L'Homme 
            qui Rit," we have a strange account of the discovery of an 
            unknown Baron, and his sudden and startling appearance in 
            the House of Lords. Gwynplaine, "the man who laughs," 
            the hero of this fantastic story, was the heir to an English 
            peerage, who, by a Court plot, had been stolen in his infancy,
            mutilated, and exposed to die on the shore of Dorsetshire.
            By a refinement of cruelty, the muscles of his face had been 
            so cut as to cause him to wear a perpetual and ghastly grin,
            which had the effect of producing the contagion of irrepressible 
            laughter in those who beheld him. Rescued from death,
            and brought up as a strolling stage-player, under the title of 
            "L'Homme qui Rit," he was at last discovered to be a peer 
            of the realm, and took that place in the august assembly to 
            which his rank entitled him. A memorable scene then 
            ensued. Rising to speak on the motion then before the 
            House, which was the question of a grant of money to a 
            member of the royal family, he succeeded in restraining, by 
            a desperate effort, the laugh which was usually on his face, 
            and delivered to the astonished peers a powerful democratic 
            and revolutionary harangue. His audience sat in amazed 
            silence; but, unfortunately, in the middle of his speech, he 
            was so carried away by emotion that he relaxed the constraint 
            which he had put upon his features, and broke forth 
            into the fatal laugh. The effect was instantaneous. A vast
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03801.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">136</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            
            and uncontrollable fit of laughter seized upon the whole 
            assembly; dukes and lords clapped their hands and vied in 
            their derisive shouts; bishops held their sides; the Lord 
            Chancellor covered his face; and the House adjourned in 
            the wildest excitement and confusion.</p> 
            <p>But what has this to do with Lord Tennyson? The 
            gravity of his features, and his well-known aversion to any 
            display of revolutionary sentiment, seem to preclude any 
            possibility of a comparison of his appearance in the House 
            of Lords with the scene I have just described. He is not a 
            man who laughs, and he is not likely to say anything which 
            would appear ridiculous to his fellow peers. And yet, rightly 
            regarded, his advent to the House of Lords is perhaps a 
            more laughable event than any which fiction has imagined.
            That a man who bore the name of Alfred Tennyson, a name 
            which will always be remembered and revered wherever the 
            English language is spoken, should be willing to enter an 
            assembly which is in direct and glaring opposition to all the 
            noblest instincts of the English people, this in itself is 
            enough, one would imagine, to elicit laughter, loud and irrepressible,
            from the gravest of poets and the demurest of 
            senates. And if it excites no such audible display of feeling 
            among the parties most closely concerned, it is nevertheless 
            a fact that it has caused much amazement and ridicule in the 
            nation at large. The civilized world has laughed at this 
            ludicrous spectacle—a man of genius, a man of the people,
            joining the ranks of the most bigoted and selfish of aristocratic 
            assemblies.</p> 
            <p>Yet it should be remembered that this last act, which has 
            excited such widespread surprise and disapprobation among 
            almost all classes of Englishmen, is nothing more than the 
            culminating point of a process which has long been going on.
            It cannot be denied that during the last ten years the whole 
            weight of the Poet Laureate's influence has been thrown 
            more and more in favour of the Conservative and reactionary 
            party; while professing to stand aloof from the troubled
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03801.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE POET LAUREATE.</hi></fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">137</fw>
            element of politics, he has, for all practical purposes, done 
                all that he could to arrest the march of free thought, and to 
                hinder the awakening of the people. The bigoted and intolerant 
                tone of many of his late poems has caused sorrow 
                and disappointment to all true-hearted Reformers, and is the 
                more deplorable and inconsistent since it comes from one 
                who hitherto posed as himself a champion of independent 
                thought and a lover of liberty. But, after all, it is perhaps 
                better that we should now have in Lord Tennyson a professed 
                opponent rather than a lukewarm friend; and, in spite 
                of his great and deserved reputation as a poet, his loss to the 
                cause of liberty will be found to be less serious than might 
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" from="#s1" to="#s3"/>at first sight be imagined. For, while we fully admit the 
                greatness of his purely poetical powers, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">we have no hesitation 
                in asserting that the <hi rend="italic">thought</hi> which runs through his writings 
                is as feeble as the <hi rend="italic">expression</hi> is beautiful.</hi> His philosophy, if 
                such it can be called, was false and hollow from the beginning, 
                and has become more and more unscientific with increasing age 
                and intolerance. <anchor xml:id="s3"/></p>
                <p>Here it may be objected that we are raising unnecessary 
                difficulties in discussing the philosophy of a poet. "It is the 
                duty of a poet," say some, "to sing, and not to teach." This 
                may or may not be true as regards the duty of poets in 
                general, but it certainly is not the course that has been followed 
                by Lord Tennyson; it is not the view that he himself 
                has taken of his own duties and capabilities. Would to 
                heaven that it were so! It would have been better for him 
                and for all of us if he had thought it well to follow the wise 
                example of Gray, and Collins, and Keats, and restrain himself 
                to that art of poetry in which he has so few rivals. For 
                if ever a poet has come near to perfection in his work, Lord 
                Tennyson has done so in those poems where a great but 
                simple thought had to be expressed, and where there was no 
                room for the introduction of any controversial matter. For 
                example, in "Ulysses" we have a splendid representation of
                the indomitable energy of the will; in the "Lotos Eaters,"<anchor xml:id="s2"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03801.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">138</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            of rest; in "St. Agnes' Eve," of purity and resignation; in
            "Rizpah," of horror, and pity, and love. But, unfortunately, 
            the Poet Laureate was not content with this simplicity of
            subject; he has deliberately descended into the arena of
            strife, and must be judged accordingly. Indeed, it is so 
            obviously useless to attempt to exonerate him from this
            criticism that many of his admirers boldly take the bull by
            the horns and claim for him the position of a great teacher 
            and thinker. It will be found, I fear, that his thoughts when
            sifted are light as chaff, and that his philosophical system is
            a mixture of opportunism and shallow optimist theories. In
            his delightful poem of "Will Waterproof's Lyrical Monologue," 
            he has described the process of his own poetic inspiration,
            and the influence of his Muse:</p>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"Until the charm have power to make</l> 
                <l>New life-blood warm the bosom,</l>
                <l>And barren common-places break </l>
                <l>In full and kindly blossom."</l></lg>
            <p>One could hardly desire a more correct description of Lord
            Tennyson's practical philosophy. It is expressed in language
            of the fullest and kindliest blossom; but the common-places 
            of his thought will be found on investigation to be very
            barren indeed.</p>
            <p>Let us now proceed to consider the tendency of the Poet
            Laureate's teaching on questions of religion, morality, and
            politics. Lord Tennyson is often claimed as an ally by the
            orthodox church party; but it may be doubted whether he is
            at heart a very 'sound' champion of the faith, at any rate on
            the question of the truth of Christian dogma. It should be
            noticed that on this subject the assistance he has given to
            orthodox belief has been less by any outspoken avowal than
            by hints and suggestions, which imply a sympathetic feeling,
            but are no guarantee of personal adherence. He gives the
            Christian the advantage, so to speak, of the best position in
            his poems; he loves to throw a favourable light on the
            orthodox portions of the picture and an unfavourable light on 
            the reverse; and thus in an indirect way he has undoubtedly
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03801.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE POET LAUREATE.</hi></fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">139</fw>
            done service to the Church. But his attitude is always such 
            as to suggest the idea that he believes Christian doctrine 
            must be upheld less for its own inherent truth, than because 
            it is bound up with some external advantage to mankind. 
            As an instance of this indirect approval, we may refer to the 
            passage in "The Two Voices," where the speaker, after 
            long hesitation between the advantages of death or life, is 
            cheered by the sweet and balmy airs of a lovely morning. It 
            is of course a Sabbath morning.</p>
        <lg type="stanza"><l>"Like softened winds that blowing steal,</l>
                <l>When meres begin to uncongeal,</l>
                <l>The sweet church bells began to peal.</l></lg> 
                <lg type="stanza"><l>"On to God's house the people prest:</l>
                <l>Passing the place where each must rest,</l>
                <l>Each entered like a welcome guest."</l></lg> 
            <p>The sight of this solemn scene rescues the would-be suicide 
            from the gloomy depths of his despair. It is a slight touch,
            but it is characteristic of Lord Tennyson's narrow and partial 
            delineations of human nature.</p> 
            <p>Other examples will readily occur to the mind; perhaps 
            the most striking is to be found in one of his later poems, "In 
            the Children's Hospital." There, among other characters, we 
            have a description of a terrible doctor, with red hair, big 
            voice, big merciless hands, fresh from the surgery-schools of
            France, and addicted to the worst practices of vivisection, 
            who roughly informs the hospital nurse that one of the 
            children under her charge is dying and will not need more of
            her care. When she timidly suggests that there is the more 
            need "to seek the Lord Jesus in prayer," he treats her with 
            brutal scorn.</p> 
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"Then he mutter'd half to himself, but I know that I heard him say,</l>
                <l>'All very well—but the good Lord Jesus has had his day.'"</l></lg>
            <p>In this passage Lord Tennyson has deliberately gone out 
            of his way to couple disbelief with roughness and brutality,
            and I cannot imagine anything more disingenuous than to 
            draw a picture which may conceivably be true in itself, but 
            is calculated to suggest an absolutely erroneous inference to 
            the mind. There may be doctors like the one described,
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03801.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">140</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            devoid of all gentleness and humanity; but, as Lord Tennyson 
            knows very well, it is not their belief or disbelief that has 
            made them so. Gentleness is not an invariable concomitant 
            of Christianity any more than of scepticism.</p>
            <p>We shall come to still worse instances by-and-by on other 
            questions, but this is no unfair example of the illogical and 
            indirect aid which the Poet Laureate renders now and again 
            to the church party on the subject of Christianity. He never 
            meets the unbeliever face to face as an avowed opponent, but 
            he sneaks behind him and trips him up unawares, or gives 
            him a foul blow "below the belt," while posing all the time 
            as the impartial and philosophical by-stander who wrote those 
            famous lines (but that was many a year ago.)</p>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"There lives more faith in honest doubt,</l> 
                <l>Believe me, than in half the creeds."</l></lg> 
          <p>Such is Lord Tennyson's attitude with regard to Christianity. 
            But there is another question in which he has taken 
            a far more pronounced part, and has shown himself more and 
            more intolerant and dogmatic in his advancing age; though, 
            unfortunately, here also he has adopted that circuitous and 
            illogical method which I have just noticed. The immortality 
            of the soul is not merely the cardinal belief of the Poet 
            Laureate's philosophy—in that he would be at one with many 
            of the best and noblest teachers of mankind; but it is the 
            <hi rend="italic">sine quâ non</hi> of his morality, the condition without which life is 
            worthless, the criterion by which he passes immutable judgment 
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s4" from="#s4" to="#s5"/>on the characters of his fellow-men. To illustrate this it will 
            be necessary to touch briefly on three or four of his poems,
            and first <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">on "In Memoriam," the tenderest and noblest of all 
            his works.</hi> It is worthy of remark that in this poem, where 
            he has himself felt most deeply, he is least intolerant of the 
            opinion of others. As he himself says:—<anchor xml:id="s5"/></p>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"If these brief lays, of sorrow born,</l>
                <l>Were taken to be such as closed</l>
                <l>Grave doubts and answers here proposed,</l>
                <l>Then these were such as men might scorn."</l></lg> 
                <p>This is a true and sensible estimate of the philosophical 
              value not only of "In Memoriam," but of all Lord Tennyson's
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03801.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE POET LAUREATE.</hi></fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">141</fw>
            poetry; and had this wise thought been kept in remembrance 
            such a poem as "Despair" would never have been written, 
            and that ill-starred drama, "The Promise of May," would 
            never have made its brief appearance on the stage. But 
            even in "In Memoriam," tender and beautiful as the poem is,
            we may discover the germs of that fatal fallacy, lately developed 
            to the full in the Poet Laureate's philosophy, that 
            happiness and morality in this present life are dependent on 
            a belief in a future existence.</p>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"Not only cunning casts in clay:</l> 
                   <l>Let Science prove we are, and then </l>
                   <l>What matters Science unto men—</l>
                <l>At least, to me? <hi rend="italic">I would not stay.</hi></l></lg>
                <lg type="stanza"><l>Let him, the wiser man, who springs </l>
                   <l>Hereafter, up from childhood shape </l>
                   <l>His action like the greater ape,</l>
                <l>But I was born to other things."</l></lg>
            <p>Passing over this astounding misrepresentation of the 
            theory of evolution let the reader note well the extraordinary 
            idea of "<hi rend="italic">not staying</hi>;" for therein is struck the key-note of 
            much of the Tennysonian philosophy. It is indeed sad that 
            a great writer should lend his sanction to the foolish clamour,
            so often raised by those who cling desperately to some particular 
            form of belief, that unless their special doctrine be 
            true, life would no longer be worth living, and the call of 
            duty would no longer fall with authority on our ears. How 
            different from this cuckoo-cry are the noble words of Frederick 
            Robertson, himself a far firmer believerthan Lord Tennyson:—</p> 
            <p><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s6" from="#s6" to="#s7"/>If there be no God and no future state, yet, even then, it 
            is better to be generous than selfish, better to be true than 
            false, better to be brave than to be a coward. Blessed beyond 
            all earthly blessedness is the man who, in the tempestuous 
            darkness of the soul, has dared to hold fast to these venerable 
            landmarks."<ref target="#note1">*</ref></p> 
            <p xml:id="p1a" next="#p1b">This, however, is not the opinion of the Poet Laureate.<anchor xml:id="s7"/>
             With him there must be a sure belief in futurity, or there can 
             be no action in the present. Virtue is not her own reward,</p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <note xml:id="note1" type="footnote" place="bottom" anchored="true">*Address to Brighton working men.</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03801.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">142</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            
            <p xml:id="p1b" prev="#p1a">as we have lately been taught by some mistaken moralists,
                but, as we learn from the poem entitled, "Wages," needs</p> 
            <l>"The glory of going on, and still to be."</l>
            <p>But let me quote Lord Tennyson's own words:—</p> 
            <lg type="stanza"><l>The wages of sin is death: if the wages of virtue be dust,</l> 
                <l>Would she have heart to endure for the life of the worm or the fly?"</l></lg>
            <p>One would have thought that even under these depressing 
            circumstances a really religious and virtuous man would find 
            much work to do in the world, and many a duty to perform;
            but virtue, in the gospel according to Lord Tennyson, thinks 
            otherwise. Take away the eternity on which she has set her 
            heart, and—"She will not stay."</p>
            <p>But if there is some faulty teaching in "Wages" and "In 
            Memoriam," what shall we say when we come to "Despair" 
            and "The Promise of May"? In the former of these we 
            have a terrible picture of a hopeless life and attempted 
            suicide; in the latter of a life spent in deliberate vice and 
            heartless libertinism; in both we are given to understand 
            that the evil is the direct consequence of scepticism and unbelief.
            Can anything be more grossly unfair and misleading 
            than this? No doubt cases may occur where, in a peculiar 
            class of character, loss of belief leads to unhappiness and 
            even ruin; but that can hardly be held to justify a poet or 
            dramatist in taking such individual cases and representing 
            them as a general law. It would be at least equally easy to 
            produce instances where exactly the contrary has occurred,
            where disbelief in the supernatural has led to a surer 
            morality, a sounder judgment, and an altogether happier 
            estimate of life. But, we, know, any stick is good enough 
            to beat a dog with; and, in his crusade against dogs of unbelievers,
            Lord Tennyson has no scruples as regards his 
            choice of weapons.</p>  
            <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s8" from="#s8" to="#s9"/>Since <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">morality, according to the Poet Laureate's teaching, 
                    is thus dependent on the holding of certain religious beliefs,</hi>
                we shall not be surprised if we find it taking strange forms in 
                some of the characters which he has delineated in his poems. 
                His treatment of the chief characters in the "Idylls of the<anchor xml:id="s9"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03801.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s22" from="#s22" to="#s23"/><fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE POET LAUREATE.</hi></fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">143</fw>
                King," especially at the close of the story, will furnish a 
                   remarkable instance of his <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi>. Anyone who has
                   read Sir Thomas Malory's "History of King Arthur" compiled 
                   about the year 1470 from still earlier romances, must 
                   have noticed how greatly Lord Tennyson is throughout 
                   indebted to the old historian for the subject-matter and even 
                   the words of his Epic. But there is one important difference 
                   in his version of the Arthurian legend, and that too in the 
                   most vital and interesting part—the love of Lancelot and 
                   Guinevere. In the old story, though the fatal results of this 
                   <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s10" from="#s10" to="#s11"/>guilty love are narrated sternly and unsparingly, the fact is 
                   never lost sight of that the lovers are true to each other to 
                   the bitter end; it is Lancelot and not the King who visits 
                   Guinevere in the sanctuary; it is Lancelot who, after the 
                   Queen's death, bears her body from Almesbury to its resting-place 
                   at Glastonbury; it is Lancelot who lingers and agonizes<anchor xml:id="s11"/> 
                   over her tomb, until death relieves him from his sorrow, and 
                   "the angels heave up Sir Lancelot towards heaven, and the 
                   gates of heaven open against him." Nothing can exceed the 
                   simple pathos and dignity of the story as thus told by the 
                   ancient historian, and those who know and love it cannot 
                   readily forgive Lord Tennyson for the alterations he has 
                   thought fit to introduce, however beautiful the language, in 
                   his Idyll "Guinevere." The sudden repentance of the Queen; 
                   the discovery that Arthur, not Lancelot, is her own true lord; 
                   the one hope to be the mate of Arthur "hereafter in the 
                   heavens"—all this is very gratifying to the cheap <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi> 
                   morality of the nineteenth century, but it is very untrue 
                   to nature, and very unlike the work of a great teacher. It is 
                   worthy of Dr. Watts, of Martin Tupper, or of Canon Farrar
                   —that complacent trinity of well-meaning moral mediocrities 
                   —but it is not worthy of Alfred Tennyson.</p> <anchor xml:id="s23"/>
                <p>The defects of the teaching in "Maud" are as glaring as 
                      the poetry is beautiful; but they have been so often exposed 
                      before now, that there is no need to dwell upon them here. It 
                      may be said, of course, that the Crimean war was a national</p>  
                      <fw type="sig" place="bottom">Vol. I.—No. 2. New Series. K.</fw>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03801.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">144</fw><fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            
            <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s12" from="#s12" to="#s13"/>and not an individual error; yet <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">it is sad to think that the
                most furious denunciation of peace and the most foolish 
                beatification of war are to be found in the works of the leading 
                English poet of that generation.</hi> Lord Beaconsfield is 
                <anchor xml:id="s13"/>popularly regarded as the chief author and exponent of the 
                doctrine of Jingoism, but even that cynical statesman never 
                advocated a spirited policy with such deliberate persistence as 
                was done in the pages of "Maud" by that great moral teacher,
                Lord Tennyson, author of the famous lines—</p>
                <lg type="stanza"><l>"Ring out the thousand wars of old,</l>
                    <l>Ring in the thousand years of peace."</l></lg> 
                <p>I have no space here to consider the questions treated of 
                in the "Princess" and "Enoch Arden." The more one studies 
                the former, the more one is convinced that it was rightly 
                styled by its author "A Medley"; and those who analyse the 
                story of Enoch Arden may well feel a grave doubt whether it 
                has been handled with the delicacy which is supposed to be 
                one of the Poet Laureate's special characteristics.  But,
                letting that pass, I should like to remark, before leaving this 
                part of our subject, that the characters drawn by Lord Tennyson 
                are, with few exceptions, conspicuous for some grave 
                defect, some moral flaw, which is the more fatal because it is 
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s14" from="#s14" to="#s15"/>unintentional on the part of the author. For <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">of all faults 
                to which a teacher of morality is liable, the worst is obviously 
                that of not knowing whether he is describing what is moral 
                or the contrary.</hi> If we study the Tennysonian characters,
                <anchor xml:id="s15"/>whether it be the hero of "Maud," rushing off to the wars to 
                kill other people because he has been unfortunate in his 
                domestic career; or the hero of "Locksley Hall" departing 
                "seaward," and invoking a thunderbolt on his Amy's 
                residence; or Leoline, in "Aylmer's Field," committing 
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s16" from="#s16" to="#s17"/> suicide on the news of Edith's death; or <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the nurse in "The 
                    Children's Hospital" passionately asserting that she could
                        not serve in the wards unless Christianity were true; we sha<gap atLeast="2" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/></hi> 
                    recognise in all of them the same moral defect, the same lac<gap atLeast="3" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/> 
                    of any solid faith and well-founded enthusiasm, such as alon<gap atLeast="3" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/><anchor xml:id="s17"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03801.011.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE POET LAUREATE.</hi></fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">145</fw>
            can enable a man to fight the battle of life for the sake of 
            virtue itself and without reference to any selfish ulterior consideration.
            They all mean well; but they are all subject to 
            the same unfortunate weakness before alluded to, that, under 
            the stress of trial or disappointment, they "<hi rend="italic">cannot stay</hi>." Two 
            noble exceptions readily occur to the mind, the character of 
            Enoch Arden, which is all of the Poet Laureate's own creation,
            and that of Arthur in the "Idylls of the King," which, 
            in its best points, is drawn from the old prose History.</p>
            <p>Lastly, let us briefly consider the drift of Lord Tennyson's 
            political tendencies. We shall find some fine sentiments <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s18" from="#s18" to="#s19"/>
            concerning freedom and a limited monarchy scattered here 
            and there among his earlier poems, but <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">his system is at heart 
            nothing more than pure opportunism coloured by a mild 
            optimism.</hi> His opportunism appears most distinctly in the 
            nameless poem beginning "Love thou thy land," which by a 
            significant juxtaposition is placed in some editions next to<anchor xml:id="s19"/>
            "The Goose." Among other wise saws we are there taught 
            to "pamper not a hasty time," to "watch what main-currents 
            draw the years," "nor wed raw Haste half-sister to delay," 
            while in the same poem it is admitted that</p> 
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"Meet is it changes should control</l> 
                <l>Our being, lest we rust in ease."</l></lg>
            <p>It would be amusing to hear Lord Tennyson urging this 
            last sentiment on his fellow peers in the House of Lords, and 
            at the same time warning that sedatest of assemblies against
            the danger of wedding raw Haste!</p> 
            <p>In "Will Waterproof" we find an exposition of some of 
            <gap atLeast="1" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>he Poet Laureate's pet optimistic doctrines. He will not 
            <gap atLeast="1" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>cramp his heart," or "take half views of men and things," 
            <gap atLeast="2" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>r the outcome of the party warfare of Whig and Tory is "a 
            <gap atLeast="2" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>e result of good." Being assured of this satisfactory event, 
            <gap atLeast="3" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/> Poet Laureate has naturally a lofty contempt for all 
            <gap atLeast="3" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>reme politicians, and considers those the truest statesmen 
            <gap atLeast="3" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>make it their aim to strike a balance between contending 
            <gap atLeast="3" unit="chars" reason="cut away"/>ies, and are never guilty of any indiscreet enthusiasm in 
            <fw type="sig" place="bottom">K2</fw>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03801.012.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">146</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            a great cause, which, in Tennysonian phraseology, would be 
                termed "the falsehood of extremes."</p> 
            <p>If you ask the Poet Laureate why, though ill at ease, he 
            continues to "subsist" in England, the answer is that it is 
            the land of freedom; and so great is his love for that deity 
            that if the time should ever come when individual freedom 
            should be mute, we have (once again) his own word for it 
            that "he will not stay." The thought never suggests itself 
            to Lord Tennyson that Whig and Tory may, after all, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> 
            be working together for a true result of good; that our 
            English freedom may, after all, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be of the most satisfactory 
            kind; and that, if "banded unions persecute," it would be 
            nobler to stay at home and fight them than to hurry off to
            the "palms and temples of the South."</p>
            <p>After what we have seen of the Poet Laureate's opinions,
            religious, social, and political, I do not think we can justly be 
            surprised at his having become a member of the House of 
            Lords. He was always a half-hearted "Liberal" in his 
            youth; and in his old age he has become more and more 
            illiberal and dogmatic. He cannot correctly be called a 
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s20" from="#s20" to="#s21"/>Lost Leader for <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">he never was a leader of thought, certainly 
            not of advanced thought; yet, in one sense, he has 
            done battle for the party of progress, for all true poets, apart 
            from their teaching, must in some degree aid the great cause.</hi>
            And whatever we may think of Lord Tennyson's philosophical 
            teaching, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">we must all alike admire and revere his grand 
            poetical gifts;</hi> indeed it is just because we do so revere them,
            <anchor xml:id="s21"/>because we have known his poems from childhood, and have 
            conned them over and over till they have become almost a 
            part of our being, it is precisely for this reason that we deplore
            the intolerant tone of his later writings and the final hallucination 
            which has made him deem it expedient to <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">prefix [to]
            the name of Alfred Tennyson a foolish and inglorious tit[le.]</hi>. 
            How can I conclude better than with Mr Browning's famo[us]
            words, which are certainly not less applicable to the pres[ent]</p>    
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03801.013.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE POET LAUREATE.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">147</fw>
                <p>Poet Laureate than to the predecessor to whom they are 
                    supposed to refer?</p>
               <lg type="stanza"><l>We shall march prospering,—not thro' his presence;</l> 
                    <l>Songs may inspirit us,—not from his lyre;</l> 
                    <l>Deeds will be done,—while he boasts his quiescence,</l> 
                    <l>Still bidding crouch whom the rest bade aspire.</l></lg>
            <ab>******</ab> 
            <lg type="stanza"><l>Shakespeare was of us, Milton was for us,</l> 
                <l>Burns, Shelley, were with us,—they watch from their graves!</l> 
                <l>He alone breaks from the van and the freemen,</l>
                <l>He alone sinks to the rear and the slaves!"</l></lg>
                                                              <ab>H.S.S.</ab> 
              <p><handShift new="#h1"/>One of the considerations of our
              age, literature, society, standards, &amp;c,
              is, <del rend="overstrike">that</del> they are <hi rend="underline">in transition,</hi>— &amp;
              <del rend="overstrike">that</del> therefore T. fairly voices
              that immense part of all
              that is torn between the pulls
              of the past &amp; the to-come—
              that lets "I dare not wait
              upon I would"—</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03801.014.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">48</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic"><handShift new="#h3"/>TO-DAY.</hi></fw>
            
            <ab><handShift new="#h3"/>The Sun-Maiden.</ab>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>I looked out over the ocean,</l> 
                <l>And saw a maiden stand,</l>
            <l>Where billow and cloud commingled </l>
                <l>In a vanishing golden land.</l></lg>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>I passed out over the ocean,</l>
                <l>And held the Sun-Maiden's hand,</l> 
            <l>And lost for ever a treasure </l>
                <l>That was mine in the Fatherland.</l></lg>
            <ab>ERNEST RADFORD.</ab> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>