<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03428">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Mrs. Siddons as Lady Macbeth</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="gjb">George Joseph Bell</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt><resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName><persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName><persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName><persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName><persName xml:id="bb">Brett Barney</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03428</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Reading &amp; Elocution</title>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 41, Folder 62</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1878-02-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">After February 1, 1878</date>                   
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>George Joseph Bell</author>
                    <title level="a">Mrs. Siddons as Lady Macbeth: From Contemporary Notes by George Joseph Bell</title>
                    <title level="j">The Nineteenth Century: A Monthly Review</title><!--Edited by James Knowles.-->
                    <biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <date when="1878-02">February 1878</date>
                    <biblScope type="pp">296&#8211;313</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="blue-pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h4" scribeRef="#gjb" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2011-11-29">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-07-05">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#tra" when="2013-10-17">Checked and revised bibliographical information and encoding.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-03-09">Added dimensions to pasteons, checked cbs, footnotes.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-11-02">Proofed.</change>
            <change who="#bb" when="2015-11-04">tweaked encoding of footnotes</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03428.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">February 1878</note>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">296</fw>
                   <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic"><handShift new="#h4"/>THE NINETEENTH CENTURY.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">February</fw>
                <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">MRS. SIDDONS AS LADY MACBETH.</hi></head>
                <head type="sub">F<hi rend="smallcaps">ROM</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ONTEMPORARY</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">OTES </hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">BY</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">EORGE</hi> J<hi rend="smallcaps">OSEPH</hi> B<hi rend="smallcaps">ELL</hi>.</head>
                <p>W<hi rend="smallcaps">HEN</hi> any great work of art perishes from among us, we not only 
                grieve, but we rebel against the decree of fate. The wars, the traffic,
                the mechanical arts of old, nay even the men and women, wither 
                into an oblivion which is not painful but kindly. We sigh and smile 
                and acquiesce—better so, for here was nothing fitted to endure for 
                ever. They had their time, as we have ours, and who would wish 
                that the strife, the bustle, the men of to-day should last for ever? 
                But the destruction of any beautiful thing, whether it be the work of 
                art or nature, fills us, on the contrary, with sickening regret. The 
                temple, statue, picture gone imply a loss of joy to uncounted gene 
                rations. We suffer real pain when we think of lost tragedies by 
                Sophocles, and our whole classical system of education is a protest 
                that though kingdoms, peoples, tongues may die, their works of 
                beauty shall endure.</p>
                <p>If this be our feeling as to the more durable works of art, what 
                    shall we say of those triumphs which by their very nature last no 
                    longer than the action which creates them—the triumphs of the 
                    orator, the singer, or the actor? There is an anodyne in the 
                    words 'must be so,' 'inevitable,' and there is even some absurdity in 
                    longing for the impossible. This anodyne and our sense of humour 
                    temper the unhappiness we feel when, after hearing some great performance, 
                    we leave the theatre and think, 'Well, this great thing has been, 
                    and all that is now left of it is the feeble print upon my brain, the 
                    <supplied reason="cut away" source="#r1">little th</supplied>rill which memory will send along my nerves, mine and my 
                    neighbours'; as we live longer the print and thrill must grow feebler, 
                    and when we pass away the impress of the great artist will vanish 
                    from the world.' The regret that a great art should in its nature be 
                    transitory explains the lively interest which many feel in reading 
                    anecdotes or descriptions of a great actor, and it is this feeling which 
                    prompts the publication of the following notes on Mrs. Siddons' 
                    acting made by an eye-witness of ability and true artistic feeling.</p>
                <p xml:id="p1a" next="p1b">The public of to-day are perhaps hardly aware of the height <supplied reason="cut away" source="#r1">to</supplied> 
                    which the art of acting may rise. Yet those who have been <supplied reason="cut away" source="#r1">familiar</supplied>
                    with the creations of Rachel and Salvini will not only <supplied reason="cut away" source="#r1">credit the</supplied> 
                    assertion that the genius of Mrs. Siddons in representing the <supplied reason="cut away" source="#r1">characters</supplied></p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03428.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <delSpan rend="hashmark" hand="#h3" spanTo="#d01"/><fw type="date" place="top left">1878.</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE 'INFLEXIBLE.'</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">295</fw>
                    <ab>reading them, can be attached to their opinion at page 8 of the report</ab>
                    <gap reason="covered" unit="lines" quantity="44" corresp="#pasteon1"/>
                    <ab>R<hi rend="smallcaps">OBERT</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">PENCER</hi> R<hi rend="smallcaps">OBINSON</hi>.</ab><anchor xml:id="d01"/>
                    <add rend="pasteon" source="#r1" xml:id="pasteon1">
                        <q who="#ww" type="written">
                            <floatingText rend="flat">
                                <body>
                                    <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03428.002.jpg" type="recto" rend="col-10"/>
                                    <p><handShift new="#h2"/>In my reading, elocution, 
                                    I must constantly <subst><del rend="overstrike" seq="1">refer</del><add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear" seq="2">measure</add></subst> every 
                                    gesture, tone, conception, shade, 
                                    burst, <add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear">or</add> radiation, &amp;c. as to its 
                                    fitness, appropriateness, advantage 
                                    (or disadvantage) with reference <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">to 
                                    me</hi>, to <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">my personnel</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">style</hi>, 
                                    &amp; <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">physical &amp; emotional</add> individuality—not <del rend="overstrike">be thinking</del> 
                                        <del rend="overstrike">merely</del> of its abstract <subst><del rend="overstrike" seq="1">propriety</del><add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear" seq="2">authority</add></subst>
                                    <subst><del rend="overstrike" seq="1">in the</del><add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear" seq="2">as a</add></subst> rule, or in art, merely.</p>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </q>
                    </add>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03428.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h2">a really good reader is like <gap reason="cut away" quantity="1" unit="word"/>
                    painter—the latter can take any thing, a<gap reason="cut away"/> 
                        subject, &amp; so paint it, that it is fine, effective</note>
                    <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h4"/>1878.</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MRS. SIDDONS AS LADY MACBETH.</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">297</fw>
                    <p xml:id="p1b" prev="p1a"><handShift new="#h4"/>of Murphy, Lillo, Southerne, and Otway, was greatly superior to 
                        that of the writers, but that, even when representing Shakespeare, 
                        she supplied much which enriched the conceptions of the poet. 
                        To-day we often speak of an actor as the mere interpreter of Shakespeare. 
                        We are apt to imagine that there is some one Hamlet 
                        or Lady Macbeth, a creature of Shakespeare's brain, an <hi rend="italic">eidolon</hi> which 
                        the actor must of necessity endeavour to represent, his success being 
                        measured by the approach which he makes to this unattainable ideal. 
                        Those, however, who have seen the acting of the last thirty years in 
                        Paris will know that this view of the actor's province is far from true 
                        when he interprets even the best modern authors. They know that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">an 
                        actor, when he receives the manuscript, has to create his part</hi> in the 
                        sense of conceiving a complete human being who, under the given 
                        circumstances, employs the words which the author has supplied. 
                        They know that no critic could, by reading a play, evolve a portrait 
                        of the man whom an original actor will represent as the embodiment 
                        of some new part. They know that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">each new actor of real merit recreates 
                            the persons of the older drama, sending traditions to the 
                            winds and producing a new person on the stage</hi> using the old words, 
                        but with marvellous differences of manner, voice, gesture and intention. 
                        They know that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">there is not merely one good way of representing 
                        a great part, but as many ways as there are great actors.</hi> 
                        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s2"/><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s4" from="#s4" to="#s2"/>Each actor is bound so to fashion his conception that his own physical 
                        attributes and mental powers will lend themselves to its execution, 
                        and thus the great parts on the French stage have bound up with 
                        them a long series of portraits each representing the creation of a 
                        separate actor—all the creations good and to be judged of on their 
                        own merits, not by reference simply to the mind of the author.<anchor xml:id="s2"/></p>
                    <p xml:id="p2a" next="p2b"><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6"/>In small parts, and in the lower walks of the art, the English 
                        public will admit this truth readily. No one can suppose that the 
                        writer of <hi rend="italic">Rip van Winkle</hi> conceived his man with the tones and 
                        gestures which we find so admirable in Mr. Jefferson;<anchor xml:id="s6"/> <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>but the majesty 
                        of Shakespeare's name overawes us when we hear that a <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Mrs.<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">☜</note> 
                        Siddons created a part which Shakespeare wrote</hi>—when we are told that 
                        an actor's first business is not to think how Shakespeare conceived his 
                        character as standing or looking, but how he, the actor, can make a 
                        real human being stand and look while speaking Shakespeare's words. 
                        Yet the words of the part do not by themselves supply the actor with 
                        one-hundredth part of the actions he has to perform. Every single <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">☜</note>
                        word has to be spoken with just intonation and emphasis, while not 
                        a single intonation or emphasis is indicated by the printed copy. 
                        The actor must find the expression of face, the attitude of body, the 
                        action of the limbs, the pauses, the hurries—the life, in fact. There 
                        is no logical process by which all these things can be evolved out of 
                        the mere words of a part. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The actor must go direct to nature and <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">☜</note>
                        his own heart</hi> for the tones and action by which he is to move his<anchor xml:id="s8"/></p> 
                    <note type="authorial" place="bottom left" resp="#h2">☝</note>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03428.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">298</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE NINETEENTH CENTURY.</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">February</fw>
                        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" from="#p2b" to="#s12"/><p xml:id="p2b" prev="p2a">audience; these his author cannot give him, and in creating these, if 
                            <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">☞</note>he be a great actor, his art may be supremely great.</p>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h3" from="#p3"/><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h3" from="#p3"/><p xml:id="p3">The distinction between the mechanical arts and what are commonly 
                    called the fine arts lies in the creation or invention required 
                    by the artist as compared with the skill or dexterity which are alone 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>required by the craftsman. The one copies or executes; the other 
                    creates, invents, or <hi rend="italic">finds</hi> the treasure which he gives to the world. 
                    <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h3">☞</note>Arts are great or small as the thing created is noble or petty; the 
                    artist is true or false as he possesses more or less of this creative<anchor xml:id="s10"/> 
                    power, for the exercise of which he in all cases requires skill more or 
                    less mechanical, which technical skill is often called 'art' as if there 
                    were no other. This technical skill can be taught and must be learned 
                    by every artist. The poetic creative power can never be taught, 
                    though in a sense it is learned from every sight, sound, and feeling; 
                    but this greater art is learned unconsciously, and few have the power 
                    to learn the lesson.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/><p>Judged by this canon, the art of the actor may claim high rank 
                    whenever its scope is the presentment of the highest human types. 
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">To truly great actors, the words they have to speak are but opportunities 
                    of creating these types</hi>—opportunities in the sense that a 
                    beautiful model, a fine landscape, are opportunities to the painter. 
                    In these he finds his picture, in those the actor finds his person; 
                    but the dramatist does less for the actor than nature for the painter. 
                    It is the involuntary unconscious perception of this truth which<anchor xml:id="s12"/>
                    makes men accord a generous recognition to artists such as Mrs. 
                    Siddons while treating, not without justice, the rank and file of the 
                    profession as mere skilled workmen.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" from="#p4" to="#p5a"/><p xml:id="p4">It is probable, nay certain, that in writing the words to be uttered 
                    by each character, a great author has vividly present to his mind an 
                    ideal man or woman speaking these with natural and effective tones 
                    and gestures—perhaps in Shakespeare's case, though not in others, 
                    the best tones and gestures possible; perhaps, however, with tones 
                    and gestures so old-fashioned that they would not move us now; what 
                    is certain is that we have no means of discovering these; indeed, he 
                    could not himself have imparted them to a fellow-actor. Moreover, 
                    when writing the words of Macbeth, he cannot have had present to 
                    his mind all the gestures and expressions of Lady Macbeth as she 
                    listened. Yet this by-play of the great actress was such that the 
                    <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2">☞</note>audience, looking at her, forgot to listen to Macbeth. Corneille never 
                    thought of how Camille would listen to the account of the death of 
                    her lover in <hi rend="italic">Les Horaces</hi>, or, if he thought of it, his conception must 
                    have been a mere sketch as compared with the long and marvellous 
                    scene which Rachel, playing the part, showed to the astonished 
                    audience.</p>
                <p xml:id="p5a" next="p5b">In truth, the spectators do not know the marvellous study which 
                    a great actor applies to every word of a speech. Some think that</p> 
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03428.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h2">Perhaps the time will come when it 
                will not be so much <choice><orig>Shakspere</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> and the <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">great</add> poets <add rend="lasso" place="supralinear">artists</add>
                as the reader-artists and the great actors and actresses</note>    
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1878.</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MRS. SIDDONS AS LADY MACBETH.</hi></fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">299</fw>
                    <p xml:id="p5b" prev="p5a"><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/>the study consists in finding out what the author meant the hero to 
                        say or express by given words. Sometimes this demands study; more 
                        often with great writers it is as plain as can be, requiring no study. 
                        When the meaning is understood, next comes the consideration of 
                        the feeling which the speech implies or requires in the speaker. The <anchor xml:id="s14"/>
                        conception of this is far more difficult than the simple interpretation 
                        of the words, and <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">will alter with each new actor;</hi> not differing <hi rend="italic">toto 
                            c&#230;lo</hi>, but differing in shade, colour, and intensity. Any one of us 
                        can understand the reasoning in 'To be or not to be.' Very few of 
                        us can form any vivid conception of the state of Hamlet's mind, 
                        sentence by sentence, word by word, as he utters them. Of the few 
                        who can form any conception beyond a mere colourless, shadeless, 
                        pointless impression of gloom or bitterness, each one must of necessity 
                        form a distinct and new conception. In order that such a 
                        speech may sway a house, it must represent a series of emotions, each 
                        intense, natural, and noble—each succeeding the other in a natural 
                        <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16"/>sequence. <add rend="unmarked" place="inline"><handShift new="#h2"/>(</add><handShift new="#h4"/>After the speech has been understood and the feelings to 
                        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s16"/>which it corresponds conceived, comes a task of ineffable difficulty
                        —that of finding tones, look, and action, which shall represent those <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">☜</note>
                        feelings. The author gives an outline, which the actor must fill up 
                        with colour, light, and shade, so as to <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">show a concrete fact</hi>; and no 
                        two actors can or ought to do this in one and the same way.<anchor xml:id="s16"/> Let 
                        any reader who doubts this—who thinks, for instance, that there is 
                        some one Hamlet, Shakespeare's Hamlet, who could only speak the 
                        speech in one attitude, with one set of tones—open the book, and in 
                        the solitude of his chamber try first to find out the emotions which 
                        Shakespeare meant his Hamlet to feel, and then try to express those 
                        emotions in tones which would indicate them to others. If honest 
                        and clever, he will find out after half an hour's study how little the 
                        author has done for the actor, how much the actor is called upon to 
                        do for the author.</p>
                <p>These views will find their illustration in the remarkable notes by 
                    Professor G. J. Bell on Mrs. Siddons' acting, which are now published 
                    for the first time, having been kindly placed at the disposal of 
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s18" from="#s18" to="#s19"/>the writer by his surviving son, Mr. John Bell, of the Calcutta bar. 
                    Written apparently on the spot, and during the red-hot glow of appreciation, 
                    they bring the great actress before us in a way which no 
                    laboured criticism or description could do. They show how noble an 
                    art she practised, and might almost inspire some young and generous<anchor xml:id="s19"/>
                    mind with the power once more to create heroic men and women on 
                    the stage.</p>
                <p xml:id="p6a" next="p6b">Professor G. J. Bell, brother of the great surgeon Sir Charles 
                    Bell, was Professor of Scottish Law in the University of Edinburgh, 
                    and author of <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Law of Scotland</hi>, a standard 
                    work still in high repute. He was well known by his friends to be a 
                    man of fine taste and keen sensibility, as is indeed proved by these</p> 
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03428.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">300</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">THE NINETEENTH CENTURY.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">February</fw>
                <p xml:id="p6b" prev="p6a" next="p6b">notes. They were made in 1809, or about that time, and are contained 
                    in three volumes, lettered 'Siddons,' which of themselves 
                    prove the great interest taken in Mrs. Siddons' acting. They contain 
                    acting editions of the plays in which she appeared, edited by Mrs. 
                    Inchbald. Professor Bell was himself in the habit of reading aloud, 
                    and, besides critical remarks, he has noted in many places the rise or 
                    fall of Mrs. Siddons' voice, putting a mark / for a rise, and \ for a 
                    fall. The words on which the emphasis fell are underlined. The 
                    following is an introductory note on <hi rend="italic">Macbeth:</hi>—
                
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" from="#q1" to="#ggg"/><q xml:id="q1" who="G. J. Bell" type="written">Of Lady Macbeth there is not a great deal in this play, but the wonderful 
                    genius of Mrs. Siddons makes it the whole. She makes it tell the whole story of 
                    the ambitious project, the disappointment, the remorse, the sickness and despair of 
                    guilty ambition, the attainment of whose object is no cure for the wounds of the 
                    spirit. Macbeth in Kemble's hand is only a cooperating part. I can conceive 
                    Garrick to have sunk Lady Macbeth as much as Mrs. Siddons does Macbeth, yet 
                    when you see Mrs. Siddons play this part you scarcely can believe that any acting 
                    could make her part subordinate. Her turbulent and inhuman strength of spirit 
                    does all. She turns Macbeth to her purpose, makes him her mere instrument, 
                    guides, directs, and inspires the whole plot. Like Macbeth's evil genius she hurries 
                    him on in the mad career of ambition and cruelty from which his nature would 
                    have shrunk. The flagging of her spirit, the melancholy and dismal blank beginning 
                    to steal upon her, is one of the finest lessons of the drama. The moral is 
                    complete in the despair of Macbeth, the fond regret of both for that state of innocence 
                    from which their wild ambition has hurried them to their undoing.<anchor xml:id="ggg"/></q>
                    
                    The writer of this note obviously, like Milton, considered a tragedy 
                    the moralest of poems, as indeed it is; but special attention may be 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s20" from="#s20" to="#s23"/>paid to two points. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">First, Mrs. Siddons did not herself conceive 
                    Shakespeare's Lady Macbeth as turbulent and with inhuman strength; 
                    she represented her as a woman of this type because this conception 
                    <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2">☞</note>suited her physical powers and appearance.</hi> But in her own memoranda, 
                    published in her life by Campbell, she speaks thus of Lady 
                    Macbeth's beauty:—<anchor xml:id="s21"/>
                    
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" from="#q2"/><q xml:id="q2" who="Mrs. Siddons" type="written">According to my notion it is of that character which I believe is generally 
                        allowed to be most captivating to the other sex—fair, feminine, nay perhaps even 
                        fragile—
                        
                        <q who="unknown" type="written"><l>Fair as the forms that, wove in fancy's loom,</l>
                            <l>Float in light visions round the poet's head.</l></q>
                        
                        Such a combination only, respectable in energy and strength of mind, and captivating 
                        in feminine loveliness, could have composed a charm of such potency as to 
                        fascinate the mind of a hero so dauntless, a character so amiable, so honourable as 
                        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s22" from="#s22" to="#s23"/>Macbeth.</q>
                    
                    There is something to be said for Mrs. Siddons' argument that an 
                    overbearing woman could never have guided Macbeth; but this point 
                    is for the moment of secondary interest, compared with the light 
                    which her remark throws on the statement made above, that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">there is 
                    not one conception which alone the actor must form of a given part. 
                    Here we have a great actress forming two distinct conceptions: for</hi><anchor xml:id="s23"/></p> 
                    <note type="authorial" place="bottom left" resp="#h3">☝</note>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03428.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1878.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">MRS. SIDDONS AS LADY MACBETH.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">301</fw>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" resp="#h2" from="#p6c" to="#fff"/><p xml:id="p6c" prev="p6b"><hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">no one can believe that if Mrs. Siddons had been able to appear the 
                        fair and fragile beauty she conceived, she would have used a single 
                        gesture or one inflection similar to those employed when she was 
                        representing turbulent inhuman strength.</hi></p>
                <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" from="#p7"/><p xml:id="p7">The second point of interest in Professor Bell's note is, that the 
                    melancholy and dismal blank beginning to steal on Lady Macbeth is 
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">more the creation of Siddons than of Shakespeare</hi>. There is nothing 
                    in the text to contradict it, but little to indicate it. This will become 
                    more apparent when we reach the detailed notes.<anchor xml:id="fff"/></p>
                <p>A second notice in another copy of <hi rend="italic">Macbeth</hi> appears as follows:—
                    
                    <q who="unknown" type="written">Mrs. Siddons is not before an audience. Her mind wrought up in high conception 
                        of her part, her eye never wandering, never for a moment idle, passion and 
                        sentiment continually betraying themselves. Her words are the accompaniments 
                        of her thoughts, scarcely necessary, you would imagine, to the expression, but highly 
                        raising it, and giving the full force of poetical effect.</q>
                    
                    What a tribute! Shakespeare's words hardly necessary! And this 
                    was written by a man who idolised Shakespeare.</p>
                    <p>Professor Bell elsewhere remarks:—
                        
                        <q who="G. J. Bell" type="written">A just observation that it is unhappy when the part of Lady Macbeth is in the 
                            hands of a Siddons, and Macbeth (with?) an inferior actor. She then becomes not 
                            the affectionate aider of her husband's ambition, but the fell monster who tempts 
                            him to transgress, making him the mere instrument of her wild and uncontrollable 
                            ambition.</q></p>
                        
                        <p>The notes on this play will now be given, only so much of each 
                            scene being quoted as is necessary to render the note intelligible. 
                            The text of Shakespeare is given as found in the edition annotated 
                            by Professor Bell.</p>
                
<p>                ACT I.
                    
                    SCENE 5. <hi rend="italic">Macbeth's castle at Inverness</hi>.
                    
                    <hi rend="italic">Enter</hi> LADY MACBETH,<ref target="#fn1" rend="supralinear">0</ref> <hi rend="italic">reading a letter</hi>.</p>
                    
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Lady</hi>. 'They met me in the day of success: and I have learned by the <hi rend="italic">perfectest</hi> 
                        report, they have <hi rend="italic">more</hi> in them than mortal knowledge. When I burned 
                        in desire to question them further, they made themselves air, into which they 
                        vanished. Whiles I stood rapt in the <hi rend="italic">wonder of</hi> it, came missives from the 
                        king, who all-hailed me "Thane of Cawdor "; by which title, before, these weird 
                        sisters saluted me, and referred me to the coming on of time,' with "Hail, king 
                        that shalt be!" This have I thought good to deliver thee, my dearest partner of 
                        greatness, that thou mightest not lose the dues of rejoicing, by being ignorant of 
                        what greatness is promised thee. Lay it to thy heart, and farewell.'</p>
                        
            <p>Glamis thou art, and Cawdor, <hi rend="italic">and shalt be</hi><ref target="#fn2" rend="supralinear">1</ref></p>
            <p>What thou art promised:<ref target="#fn3" rend="supralinear">2</ref> yet do I fear thy nature;</p>
                            
            <note xml:id="fn1" n="0" type="footnote" place="bottom" anchored="true">Mrs. Siddons.</note>
            <note xml:id="fn2" n="1" type="footnote" place="bottom" anchored="true">Exalted prophetic tone, as if the whole future were present to her soul.</note>
            <note xml:id="fn3" n="2" type="footnote" place="bottom" anchored="true">A slight tincture of contempt throughout.</note>            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03428.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <div1 type="section"><delSpan rend="hashmark" hand="#h3" spanTo="#d1"/><fw type="pageNum" place="top left" rend="overstrike">314</fw>
                        <fw type="header" place="top" rend="overstrike"><hi rend="italic">THE NINETEENTH CENTURY</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="date" place="top right" rend="overstrike">February</fw>
                        <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">HOW THE TURKS RULE ARMENIA.</hi></head>
                            <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">UPPOSE</hi> an English Prime Minister were to persuade himself and a 
                                large section of the public that the security of our dominion in India 
                                required the sacrifice, once a year, of twenty innocent natives of both 
                                sexes, with every circumstance of cruelty and indignity which could 
                                add bitterness to death; and suppose a bill were introduced into 
                                Parliament for the purpose of giving practical effect to such conclusion. 
                                How many members of Parliament would be found to vote for 
                                it? Not one, I believe. The most loyal and submissive of the 
                                Minister's followers would recoil from participation in the guilt of so 
                                great a crime, even though the alternative should be the probable loss 
                                of our Indian empire. He would say to himself that the alternative 
                                supposed, though possible or even probable, was by no means certain; 
                                that the danger was perhaps, after all, not so great as had been supposed, 
                                and might perchance be altogether averted by the operation 
                                of events as yet unforeseen; but that, in any case, he must decline to 
                                have a hand in the commission of a great crime, be the political gain 
                                accruing therefrom ever so important.</p>
                            <p>Now what is the difference, in point of morality, between the 
                                policy which I have supposed and that which has found so many 
                                advocates in England during the last eighteen months? We have 
                                been told on high authority—and the doctrine has been energetically 
                                defended in high quarters—that we are bound for the sake of 'our own 
                                interests' to 'uphold' a political system of which we know that one 
                                of the inevitable fruits is the periodical torture and slaughter of 
                                '10,000 or 20,000' innocent human beings, to say nothing of other 
                                evils which are not periodical, but chronic. We are not simply to 
                                stand aloof and let matters take their course; we are to 'uphold' this 
                                periodical sacrifice to the Moloch of 'British interests,' and must 
                                accordingly interfere actively 'to prevent changes from occurring' in 
                                Turkey which would put an end to the sacrifice, if we think that such 
                                changes would be 'detrimental to ourselves.'<ref target="#fn4">1</ref> In point of morality 
                                there really is no difference at all between upholding a system which 
                                now and then massacres 20,000 persons, and committing the massacre 
                                ourselves. Yet so inconsistent is human nature that those who do 
                                not scruple to defend the one would shrink in horror from the other</p>
                            <note xml:id="fn4" type="footnote" n="1" place="bottom" anchored="true" rend="overstrike">See Sir Henry Elliot's famous despatch, Blue Book No. 1, for 1877, p. 197.</note>
                        <anchor xml:id="d1"/>
                        </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>