<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00007">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Robert Southey</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00007</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman's Manuscript Notes on Southey, Browning and Others</title>
                    <idno type="callno"/>
                    <date notBefore="1847-09-25" notAfter="1892-05-26">After 1847</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="mid">Middlebury College Library, Special Collections</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Clipping on final page appeared in <hi rend="italic">Scientific American</hi>, 25 September 1847; here it is pasted on a February 1851 essay on Robert Southey from the <hi rend="italic">American Whig Review</hi>. Transcribed from our digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title level="a">Robert Southey</title>
                    <title level="j">American Whig Review</title>
                    <date>February 1851</date>
                    <pubPlace/>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="pasteon" xml:id="r2">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title>"Robert Burns"</title>
                    <date when="1847-09-25">September 25, 1847</date>
                    <publisher>Scientific American</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black-ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-05-14">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-02-07">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-05-22">Proofed.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-07-20">Edits per K. Price.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="mid.00007.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h1"/>1851.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">157</fw>
            <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h2">(☟<hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">This is a very finely done criticism.</hi>)</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2" rend="centered">Southey born 1774</note>
            <head type="main-authorial" rend="centered"><handShift new="#h1"/>ROBERT SOUTHEY.<ref target="#note1">*</ref></head>
            <cb/><p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">T<hi rend="smallcaps">HERE</hi> is a species of even-handed justice
                attending literary men, which generally
                makes all straight in the end;</hi> the old
                axiom of "Extremes meet" seems to govern
                this rule, and <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">in proportion as an author is
                    abased by some, he is lauded by others,
                    not only personally but poetically.</hi> There are,
                of course, the usual exceptions,&#8212;some one
                way, as Walter Scott,&#8212;some the other, as in
                the case of Southey; but action and reaction
                is a principle of nature.</p>
            <p>We doubt if there ever were a writer so
                fiercely vilified as the author of "Wat
                Tyler," who had so little of the pleasanter
                side of praise administered to him in his
                lifetime, notwithstanding his influence and
                position. There has not even been the
                usual re-action when the grave has consecrated
                his virtues, and obliterated his failings;
                indeed, so far as we may be allowed
                to judge from present appearances, he seems
                already shrinking into the very narrow compass
                of his "Life of Nelson," and the poem
                he repudiated, "Wat Tyler!" That posterity
                may reverse this decision is possible, although,
                taking the past as a guide, not probable.
                The two causes which deprived him
                of enthusiastic eulogizers during his life, will
                operate, we think, even more conclusively as
                the circle expands, and deposit him on the
                bleak shore of respectability, leaving him
                farther removed from human sympathy as
                the tide of time recedes.</p>
            <p>The causes we allude to are, his want of
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">high or distinctive genius, and moral geniality.
                    In the greatest imaginations these are
                    generally found together, as in Homer, Ariosto,
                    <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>, and Cervantes.</hi> Some cases,
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>however, exist in which they are separated,
                as in Dante and Milton; but possibly in
                both these latter instances political and domestic
                sorrows, as well as the severe temper
                of the times, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u1">may have had a modifying, if
                    not an altogether deviating influence upon
                    them, which if not exercised would have left
                    them as jovial fellows as Anacreon himself.</hi></p><anchor xml:id="s2"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="bottom" target="#u1">☝</note>
            <cb/>
            <p>That Southey was altogether deficient in
                that logical and creative phrenzy (if we may
                like Willis or Emerson coin on our own account)
                which <hi rend="italic">our</hi> great Anglo-Saxon poet
                calls "a fine phrenzy"&#8212;(we advisedly say <hi rend="italic">our</hi>,
                for <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> as much belongs to the American
                people as he does to the English, seeing
                that <hi rend="italic">our</hi> ancestors claimed him as a fellow-citizen)
                &#8212;that Southey was deficient in this
                godlike faculty is evident to any who has
                read all or even any of his voluminous
                poems; that he was destitute of <hi rend="italic">bonhomie</hi>
                was as equally apparent to a casual acquaintance,
                or an old friend.</p>
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/><p>He had no impulse. In a word, we may
                define him as the Genius of Routine; that
                was the only <hi rend="italic">genius</hi> he possessed. In saying
                this let our readers clearly understand
                that we neither undervalue nor disparage
                Southey, or the regularity of which he was
                so striking an example; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">we merely define
                    what he <hi rend="italic">really was</hi>, just as a mathematician
                    means no insult to a triangle when he says
                    it is not a circle.</hi> Indeed, to borrow a geometrical
                term, Southey was eminently an
                angular mind: he did not incorporate in his
                own nature the knowledge he was constantly
                acquiring; he merely added it to what he
                already had. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Knowledge made Southey
                    learned, it made <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> wise; it enabled
                    the one to alter and illustrate, the other to
                    create and beautify; it enriched the <hi rend="italic">nature</hi>
                    of the one, but only the recollection of the
                    other. Knowledge made the author of Hamlet
                    philosophical and imaginative; it rendered
                    the writer of Thalaba prolix and
                    fanciful; it was a telescope and a microscope
                    to <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>, a mere pair of colored spectacles
                    to Southey.</hi><anchor xml:id="s4"/> We repeat, that in selecting
                    the greatest of poets for this parallel,
                    we have no wish to depreciate, but simply
                    to take the highest of each class, in order
                    to render the contrast more striking.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u3">Robert Southey, working out his own
            original nature honestly, is entitled to as
            much respect as William <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice></hi>: for</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="bottom" target="#u3">☝</note>
            <note type="footnote" xml:id="note1" place="bottom">*The Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, LL.D. Edited by his son, Rev. Charles
                Cuthbert Southey. New-York: Harper &amp; Brothers.</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00007.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">158</fw>
            <fw type="header" rend="italic" place="top">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Feb.</fw>
            <cb/><p>this we have the incontrovertible evidence
            of Holy Writ, as illustrated by the parable of
            the talents. We shall not even condemn
            him for his remarkable change of opinion
            in religion and politics: for this also he
            had the precedence of a sacred example
            in St. Paul so far as the right of search
            and change is concerned; but he had no
            authority for his malignant persecution of
            those who continued to hold the same
            opinions as he had once entertained. Surely,
            this ought to have counselled charity; but
            <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">it is a singular proof of human blindness,
            that men never hate themselves for their
            former heresies!</hi> Let us, therefore, set an
            example of charity ourselves, and suggest
            that it is merely the opinions they hate,
            after all, and not the men.</p>
            <p>We remember Sergeant Talfourd used this
            <hi rend="italic">argumentum ad hominem</hi> with great effect
            on a trial for rioting at Gloucester. Baron
            Gurney, a very able but severe judge, who
            presided, had been, during the French Revolution,
            one of the Jacobin Club in London
            notorious for its anarchical principles.
            This was well known to Talfourd, who defended
            the rebels, and who was so irritated at
            the judge's undue leaning against the prisoners,
            that in the defence he begged "his
            lordship would reflect if in his own experience
            he did not remember any one who
            had formerly been an ardent admirer and
            correspondent of Robespierre and Marat;
            one who was also a member of a club, whose
            toasts were such as, 'The heart of a king
            grilled on the ribs of his minister;' and
            whether he was not now one of the most
            distinguished ornaments of the bench; and
            what would have been his fate had no time
            been given to him to repent, and repay the
            society he had outraged," &amp;c. This had so
            great an effect, that in his charge the conscience-struck 
            Gurney directed the jury to
            acquit them, with only a severe reprimand.</p>
            <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6"/><p>Men should bear in mind that uniformity
                of opinion would soon become a dead level of
                intellect. Indeed, what diversity of scenery
                is to the picturesque, variety of mind is to
                the intellectual world.<anchor xml:id="s6"/> If all men thought
                alike, human nature would soon become a
                putrefaction of bigotry&#8212;a dead sea of idiocy.
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Heresy seems to be the gastric juice of the
                    human race. The first utterance of a new
                    doctrine is considered an offense; but in
                    time it becomes the standard of faith, and,
                    forgetful of its own youthful struggles and</hi>
            <cb/>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">sufferings, assumes in its old age the persecutor.
                    Thus, strangely as it may sound, the
                    blasphemy of one age becomes the religion
                    of the next;</hi><anchor xml:id="s8"/> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">opinions like billows roll on,
                        one after the other, swallowing each other,
                        or harmoniously subsiding into the vast
                        ocean of Truth.</hi></p>
            <p>We have thought it necessary to make
                these preliminary remarks in order that our
                readers may the better comprehend our
                view of Southey, and his aspect of society.
                It will however be advisable to glance
                hastily at his intimates and contemporaries
                before we fairly enter upon his own particular
                life and correspondence. These were
                undoubtedly some of the most remarkable
                men the world of genius has produced; we
                shall however confine ourselves to those
                most immediately acting upon his conduct
                and opinions.</p>
            <p>Coleridge, Lloyd, and Lovell were those
                who were his first intellectual associates;
                after a time, Wordsworth, Lamb, and Cottle
                were added. All these were men of a peculiar
                stamp, some of the highest powers. The
                greatest was undoubtedly Coleridge, not
                only for his attainments, imagination, and
                enthusiasm, but also on account of the eloquence
                with which he advocated any system
                he adopted; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">even his inconsistency gave
                    a poetical charm to his conduct!</hi> Ever
                the slave of impulse, but preserved from
                vice by one of the most gorgeous, and, at
                the same time, subtle imaginations vouchsafed
                to a human being, the author of
                Christabel was at once a giant and a child.
                While his comprehensive and logical mind
                detected at a glance the most plausible
                sophism of another, he was constantly bewildered
                in those of his own creation; his
                silken clue inevitably failed him in the
                labyrinth of his own planning; he was
                no Daniel in the den of his own lions!
                Coleridge was to himself throughout his life,
                what the Spectre was to the hero of one of
                Calderon's plays, the name of which we forget:
                he always found <hi rend="italic">himself</hi> opposed and
                overthrown by <hi rend="italic">himself</hi>. Like a silk-worm he
                lived in a world of his own spinning, and
                which was destined eventually to be his
                shroud. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>We have little hesitation in stating
                that we do not believe there has ever been
                an instance of a man of equal genius so entirely
                giving himself up to such flimsy delusions
                and sophisms as Coleridge did from
                his very boyhood. Lamb defined him exactly<anchor xml:id="s10"/><anchor xml:id="s12"/></p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="mid.00007.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1851.</fw>
                <fw type="header" rend="italic" place="top">Robert Southey.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">159</fw>
                <cb/><p>when he called him "the <hi rend="italic">Inspired</hi>
                    Christ School Boy." He never outgrew his
                    gigantic boyhood. Fresh from the trammels
                    of school, he longed to plant idylls and
                    eclogues on the banks of the Susquehanna,
                    of which he was to be one of the piping
                    Corydons, with some young Phillis fond of
                    throwing love-apples at him, and listening to
                    his strains, and always giving the award in
                    his favor. A variety of causes combined
                    gave a similar tendency to the more practical
                    mind of Southey. But a <hi rend="italic">fortunate</hi> want
                    of money saved them from this egregious
                    folly; for there never were two men less
                    fitted for emigration to a new world than
                    they were.</p>
                <p>Love, poverty, a vague aspiration for
                    liberty, and a restlessness, which Southey
                    finally conquered, were the motives which
                    led him to entertain the Pantisocratic scheme.
                    It is a mistake to suppose Wordsworth
                    ever for an instant was mixed up in this
                    Utopian dream; indeed, the bare suspicion
                    annoyed him so much, that on the publication
                    of Chorley's "Authors of England" in
                    1842, the old poet requested the writer of
                    this article to beg Mr. Chorley would correct
                    the mistake he had made in his life of
                    Coleridge, where Wordsworth figures as
                    one of the emigrant party.</p>
                <p>The head and front of this "Empire Plan"
                    was really Lovell; but a practical view of the
                    whole question dissipated the chimera.</p>
                <p>Both Lloyd and Lovell were singular
                    beings. The former was evidently tinged
                    with insanity even at that early period;
                    towards his middle age it showed itself so
                    unmistakably that he was placed in a Lunatic
                    Asylum, where he spent most of his remaining
                    years; he was eventually killed in endeavoring
                    to escape from one in France, no
                    many years ago. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16"/>In addition to being a
                    lunatic, he was also a poet, and he had the<anchor xml:id="s16"/>
                    honor of helping Coleridge and Southey to<anchor xml:id="s14"/>
                    fill up their first volume of poems published
                    at Bristol by their friend Cottle. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s18"/>Insanity
                    and poetry are hereditary in Lloyd's family,
                    for his eldest son, who is a scholar, a Christian,
                    a man of fortune, and an elegant poet,<anchor xml:id="s18"/>
                    has been for some years under partial
                    restraint. We know him well, and have
                    heard from him the statements we have just
                    made, and confirmed by others.</p>
            <p>Lovell was Coleridge and Southey's brother-
                in-law, the <hi rend="italic">three</hi> having married the
            <hi rend="italic">three</hi> Misses Fricker. Strange enough that<cb/>
            insanity should also develop itself in these
            ladies. Edith, Mrs. Southey, died insane
            after lingering in that state some years, and
            Mrs. Coleridge has acted so strangely through
            all her life as to cause considerable apprehension
            in her friends' minds for the ultimate
            result.</p>
            <p>Wordsworth's influence on Southey was
            small, notwithstanding the respect which he
            entertained for the great philosophical poet.
            This partly arose from their not coming
            together at Southey's plastic age; for like
            hot lava, Southey hardened very soon. This
            is curiously developed in the correspondence
            now before us; he seems at once to spring
            from Pantisocracy to common sense, in the
            commonest acceptation of the term. By-the-
            bye, while we think of it, we may ask the
            accomplished and conscientious editor why
            he has omitted a letter from his father to Coleridge
            respecting the latter's disinclination to
            marry Miss Sarah Fricker? It was written in
            reply to one from Coleridge, "in which he
            stated very weighty reasons why he should not
            marry just then, but leaving it to Southey to
            decide whether he thought he was bound in
            honor to fulfil his engagement <hi rend="italic">immediately</hi>."
            Southey's answer was lengthy and decisive,
            and determined Coleridge at once to marry,
            among difficulties amply illustrated in Cottle's
            "Recollections," and from which we
            question if he ever thoroughly emerged. The
            Gillmans, of Highgate, have a copy of this
            interesting epistle. It would throw a little
            light upon the state of Coleridge's heart,
            which might perhaps clear up the darkness
            which now apparently hangs over his long
            separation from his "besonneted Sara!"</p>
            <p>It is only due to the departed poet's
                memory to remember that his children,
            Hartley, Derwent, and Sara, were to the last
            most affectionately attached to their father,
            at the same time not forgetting their duty to
            their mother. This is a volume in Coleridge's
            favor more conclusive than any he has written
            himself; for no such three children,
            perhaps, ever came together, either for intellect,
            conscientiousness, or rectitude.</p>
            <p>After this little sketching, let us introduce
            the hero of the present drama.</p>
            <p>Southey thus records his own birth:&#8212;
            "My birthday was Friday, 12th August,
            1774; the time, half-past eight in the
            morning, according to the family Bible.
            According to my astrological friend Gilbert,
            it was a few minutes before the half hour,</p>
            <!--<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="mid.00007.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">160</fw>
            <fw type="header" rend="italic" place="top">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Feb.</fw>
            <p>in consequence of which I am to have a
                pain in the bowels when I am about thirty,
                and Jupiter is my deadly enemy, but I may
                thank the stars 'for a gloomy capability of
                walking through desolation.'" On his arrival
                the nurse declared "<hi rend="italic">he was a great ugly
                    boy</hi>." So even from the very first Southey
                had to endure unpalatable criticism.</p>
            <p>In his fourth year he was sent to a little
                daily school, where he first learned to distinguish
                the difference between "a B and a
                bull's foot," and other agreeable distinctions.
                Here he remained two years, passing most
                of his time at his aunt's, Miss Tyler, who
                seems to have been a sincere, though occasionally
                unreasonable friend, till his marriage,
                when their rupture was final. Southey
                always had a high opinion of this lady's intellect,
                and there is no telling how much he
                might owe unconsciously to her pervading
                influence, and constant association: indirectly
                she gave the bias to poetry, owing to
                her intimacy with the family of the manager
                of the Bath and Bristol theatres. We refer
                to this part of his memoirs for a very tragic
                event connected with this family. Even so
                early as his fourth year he was in the habit
                of being taken to the theatre, which fact was
                also impressed upon his mind by a reprimand
                he received for confounding the
                theatrical with the ecclesiastical terms, and
                saying after church one Sunday, "that there
                was a very full <hi rend="italic">house</hi>." The first play he
                saw was a comedy by Fielding, called <hi rend="italic">The
                    Fathers</hi>, a curious foreshadowing of the
                Fathers which in his old age occupied so
                much of his studies. At six years old he
                obtained without effort what our fair friend
                Lucretia Mott. is now desperately struggling
                for&#8212;he was breeched: his recollection must
                have been singularly vivid, for in after years
                he remembered the dress, which was <hi rend="italic">nankeen
                    trimmed with green fringe</hi>.</p>
            <p>He was now sent to Mr. Foot's, a dissenting
                minister, where he remained a year. His
                recollections of this school were very unpleasant.
                The death of the master released
                him from this bondage. He was then placed
                at Corston, a village about nine miles from
                Bristol: in a poem called The Retrospect,
                Southey in after years alludes to it with
                much pathos. After a year's domicile here
                he was taken away, and spent the time
                with his aunt, who had broken up her
                establishment at Bath, and settled at Bedminster.</p><cb/>
            <p>After a short holiday, he was placed as a
                day boarder at a school in Bristol, kept
                by a Welshman, who rejoiced in the echoing
                name of William Williams. It was at this
                time that Robert made his first attempts on
                the muse, which, he says, gave him immense
                pleasure. The first book he read
                thoroughly was <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>, and Titus Adronicus
                was his favorite drama. Before he
                was eight he had read Beaumont and
                Fletcher through.</p>
            <p>It was about this time that he announced
                to his aunt the wonderful discovery he had
                made, and one which most American authors
                think they can do, viz., write a play! Little
                Robert said, "It is the easiest thing in the
                world, aunt, to write a play!" "Is it, my
                dear?" replied the lady. "Yes," rejoined
                our little poetling; "you have only to think
                what you would say if you were in that person'
                place, and say it for them!"</p>
            <p>We are afraid upon this plan too many
                dramatists write, which will account for the
                egotistical monologues published now-a-
                days.</p>
                <p>For the gratification of those who are fond
                    of linking names together, we may as well
                    mention that Henderson, the great tragedian,
                    was an intimate friend of Miss Tyler,
                    although Southey could not remember that
                    he had ever seen him: he however cherished
                    a perfect recollection of the celebrated
                    actor Edwin, who presented him with a
                    toy.</p>
                <p>At this time a lady gave him "Hoole's
                    Tasso," which afforded him intense delight.
                    Shortly afterwards his young fancy was
                    fired by the same author's translation of
                    Ariosto. Seeing the name of Spenser in
                    the notes, he obtained a copy, and despite
                    the Old English character in which it
                    was printed, soon mastered the treasures of that
                    most poetical of poets.</p>
                <p>Southey truly says in one of his autobiographical
                    chapters, "My memory strengthens
                    as I proceed in this task of retrospection;
                    and yet, while some circumstances&#8212;a look&#8212;
                    a sound&#8212;a gesture, though utterly unimportant,
                    recur to me more vividly than the
                    transactions of yesterday, others, which I
                    would fain call to mind, are irrevocably
                    gone."</p>
                <p>To a man of perfect leisure and happy
                    circumstances, few pleasures can be comparable
                    to thus living again in the past&#8212;sorrow
                    taken from misfortune, and guilt from</p>-->
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="mid.00007.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1851.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">161</fw>
            <p>pleasure. Moore has very happily expressed
                this retrospection:</p>
                <lg type="linegroup"><l>"Sighing, as o'er the shadowy past,</l>
                <l>Like a tomb-searcher, Memory ran</l>
                <l>Lifting the shroud that Time had cast</l>
                <l>O'er buried hopes."</l></lg>
            <p>We now and then come upon pithy
                axioms, such as&#8212;(Southey is talking of his
                schoolmaster): "When his ill circumstances
                pressed upon him, he gave way perhaps
                more readily to impulses of anger; because
                anger, like drunkenness, suspends the sense
                of care, and an irascible emotion is felt as a
                relief from painful thoughts." This is however
                only half the case: anger is an excitement,
                and consequently suspends the duller sense
                of care, or any other equable state of mind;
                but Southey forgets, or perhaps never knew,
                that the real cause of the phenomenon is the
                weakness of mind, resulting from the irritation
                of the mosquito bites of buzzing animals,
                who very properly sting sleeping debtors till
                they wake and pay.</p>
                <p>We have however, a few passages further
                    on, a proof of how little a learned man is a
                    wise-one. "He would strike with a ruler
                    sometimes when his patience was greatly
                    provoked by that <hi rend="italic">incorrigible stupidity</hi>
                    which of all things, perhaps, puts patience
                    to the severest trial."</p>
                <p>Let us tell our readers that of the three,
                    the blockhead, the master, and the apologist,
                    the most incorrigible fools are the
                    schoolmaster for striking, and the Laureate
                    for defending the blow. Mr. Southey's joke,
                    too, about punishing a creole, is a proof of
                    his want of humor. We will not quote
                    the joke, having no wish "to throw a damp
                    upon a funeral."</p>
                <p>We have, however, a most serious charge
                    against the author of Kehama, and one of
                    his own convicting: we quote verbatim his
                    very words:&#8212;</p>
            <p>"One of them (evidently by his name of French
                extraction) was, however, the most thoroughly
                fiendish human being that I have ever known.
                There is an image in Kehama, drawn from my
                recollection of the devilish malignity which used
                sometimes to glow in his dark eyes, though I
                could not there give the likeness in its whole force,
                for his countenance used to darken with the blackness
                of his passion. Happily for the slaves on the
                family estate, he, though a second brother, was
                wealthy enough to settle in England; and an anecdote
                which I heard of him when he was about
                thirty years of age, will show that I have not
                <cb/>
                spoken of his character too strongly. When he
                was shooting one day, his dog committed some
                fault. He would have shot him for this upon the
                spot, if his companion had not turned his gun aside,
                and, as he supposed, succeeded in appeasing him;
                but, when the sport was over, to the horror of
                that companion, (who related the story to me,) he
                took up a large stone and knocked out tbu dog's
                brains. I have mentioned this wretch, who might
                otherwise have better been forgotten, for a charitable
                reason; because I verily believe that his
                wickedness was truly an original, innate, constitutional
                sin, and just as much a family disease as
                gout or scrofula. I think so, because be had a
                nephew who was placed as a pupil with King, the
                surgeon at Clifton, and in whom at first sight, I
                recognized a physiognomy which I hope can be
                long to no other breed. His nephew answered in
                all respects to the relationship, and to the character
                which nature had written in every lineament of
                his face. He ran a short career of knavery, profligacy,
                and crimes, which led him into a prison,
                and there he died by his own hand."</p>
                <p>The commonest observer must remark the
                    tender difference with which he treats the
                    reputation of a <hi rend="italic">living</hi> rich man, to the dead
                    memory of the poor dependent. Farther on
                    we have another phase of character: our
                    space, however, will not allow us to quote;
                    we must therefore content ourselves by requesting
                    our reader's attention to Southey's
                    account of his interview with an old schoolfellow,
                    whom he designates under the initials
                    H. O. They will find it at the close
                    of chapter xii. We question if a more singular
                    confession of feeling was ever before
                    so ingenuously given to the world.</p>
                <p>There are many <hi rend="italic">naÏve</hi> admissions in his
                    autobiography, which, for a man of the
                    Laureate's caution, strike us as remarkable.
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s19" from="#s19" to="#s20"/>In some very pertinent remarks on poetry he
                    observes: "In the earliest ages, certain it is
                    that they who possessed that gift of speech
                    which enabled them to clothe ready thoughts
                    in measured or elevated language, were
                    held to be inspired.<anchor xml:id="s20"/> False oracles were delivered
                    in <hi rend="italic">verse</hi>, and true prophecies delivered
                    in <hi rend="italic">poetry</hi>.* * * Sleight of hand
                    passed for magic in the dark ages, sleight
                    of tongue for inspiration." We can well
                    imagine how such a heretical or dangerous
                    opinion in the writings of another would
                    have drawn down his anathema as a "Quarterly
                    Reviewer."</p>
                <p>From the Welshman Southey was removed
                    to a day school at Bristol, kept by a
                    clergyman, who was a good classical scholar;
                    under his direction our poet commenced
                    "Greek and nonsense verses." This was in</p>
            <fw type="sig" place="bottom">VOL. VII. NO. II. NEW SERIES. 11</fw><!--These pages unmarked by WW.
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="mid.00007.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">164</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Feb.</fw>
            <p>to expect a savage to practise a Christianity
                he had never been taught. Had the French
                nation been capable of behaving differently
                to what they did, there would have been no
                revolution, because the motive would not
                have existed." This is of course the philosophical
                explanation, and had Southey argued
                correctly he would have recognized in
                the revolutionary harvest the frightful seed
                from whence it sprang. It is as true of a
                nation as a corn-field, that whatsoever the
                rulers sow they shall in time reap. But
                Southey had not a philosophical, nor yet a
                comprehensive mind. We doubt if he was
                even a logician in its highest signification.
                There is as much difference between the
                man of a logical and the man of a syllogistical
                mind, as there is between eloquence and
                rhetoric, poetry and verse. Indeed, one is
                founded on art, and the other on nature.
                One is a spirit and the other only a form.
                But after all the author of "Joan of Arc" was
                only a school-boy republican; he had by
                head and not by heart. It was the vague,
                idle dream of poetical imitation, and not a
                noble, glorious principle as in the breast of a
                Milton or a Washington. Listen to one of
                these absurd "day-dreams." It is in a letter
                to Horace Walpole Bedford:&#8212;</p>
                <p>"If this world did but contain ten thousand
                    people of <hi rend="italic">both sexes visionary</hi> as myself,
                    how delightfully would we repeople
                    Greece and turn out the <choice><orig>Moslem</orig><reg>Muslim</reg></choice>. I would
                    turn crusader, and make a pilgrimage to
                    Parnassus at the head of my republicans, and
                    there reinstate the Muses in their original
                    splendor."</p>
                <p>Our readers will, we think, agree with us
                    that if this be republicanism, every young
                    aristocrat fresh from Virgil or Livy is quite
                    as "good a one" as the author of " Wat Tyler."</p>
                <p>There is also at this epoch of his life a
                    discontent which developed itself in a disposition
                    to attack his fellow-creatures à la
                    Juvenal.</p>
                <p>In a letter to Bedford he thus writes:
                    "Your plan of a general satire I am ready
                    to partake when you please." Who is there
                    that has not in the outset of a classical
                    or literary life had similar vague intentions
                    of reforming or smashing human
                    nature?</p>
                <p>Even before his acquaintance with Coleridge,
                    our poet seems to have entertained
                    thoughts of an emigration to the United<cb/>
                States; for in another letter dated Dec. 14,
                1793, he writes:&#8212;</p>
                <p>"What is to become of me at ordination?
                    Heaven only knows! After keeping the strait
                    path so long, the Test Act will be a stumblingblock
                    to honesty. So chance and Providence
                    must take care of that, and I will fortify myself
                    against chance. The wants of man are so very
                    few, that they must be attainable somewhere, and
                    whether here or in America matters little. <hi rend="italic">I
                        have long learned to look upon the world as my
                        country.</hi></p>
            <p>"Now, if you are in the mood for a reverie,
                fancy only me in America; imagine my ground
                uncultivated since the creation, and see me wielding
                the axe, now to cut down the tree, and now the
                snakes that nestled in it. Then see me grubbing
                up the roots, and building a nice, snug little
                dairy with them: three rooms in my cottage, and
                my only companion some poor negro whom I have
                bought on purpose to emancipate. After a hard
                day's toil, see me sleep upon rushes, and, in very
                bad weather, take out my casette and write to
                you, for you shall positively write to me in America.
                Do not imagine I shall leave rhyming or
                philosophizing; so thus your friend will realize
                the romance of Cowley, and even outdo the seclusion
                of Rousseau; till at last comes an ill-looking
                Indian with a tomahawk, and scalps me&#8212;a most
                melancholy proof that society is very bad, and
                that I shall have done very little to improve it!
                So vanity, vanity will come from my lips, and
                poor Southey will either be cooked for a Cherokee,
                or oysterized by a tiger."</p>
                <p>How little Southey knew his own nature,
                    even if he were sincere in the sentiment we
                    have italicized, is evident to all who know
                    his after life. A man may recant his <hi rend="italic">opinions</hi>,
                    but not his <hi rend="italic">nature</hi>.</p>
                <p>Of his literary industry we have a proof
                    in a letter to Bedford of 1793: "I have
                    accomplished a most arduous task, transcribing
                    all my verses that appear worth the
                    trouble, except letters, [poetical epistles,
                    doubtless.] Of these I took one list, another
                    of my pile of stuff and nonsense, and a third
                    of what I have burned and lost. Upon an
                    average, ten thousand verses are burned and
                    lost, the same number preserved, and fifteen
                    thousand worthless. * * * I can bear
                    a retrospect, but when I look forward to taking
                    orders, a thousand dreadful ideas crowd at
                    once upon my mind. * * * The more
                    I see of this strange world, the more I am
                    <hi rend="italic">convinced that society requires desperate
                        remedies!</hi> The friends I have (and you
                    know me to be cautious in choosing them)
                    are many of them struggling with obstacles
                    which never could happen were man what
                    nature intended him. A torrent of ideas</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="mid.00007.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1851.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">165</fw>
                <p>bursts into my mind when I reflect upon
                    this subject. In the hours of sanguine expectation
                    these reveries are agreeable, but
                    more frequently the visions of futurity are
                    dark and gloomy, and the only ray that enlivens
                    the scene beams on America."</p>
                <p>So closed 1793. At the latter end of the
                    following January, he returned to Baliol
                    College, where his expenses were defrayed
                    by his uncle, the Reverend Herbert Hill,
                    chaplain to the British Factory at Lisbon,
                    who looked forward with considerable anxiety
                    to his nephew taking holy orders. To
                    this life, though Southey made no open objection,
                    he seemed to have cherished a private
                    dislike quite insuperable, which his son (himself
                    a clergyman) endeavors to apologize
                    away, by alluding to the state of the Established
                    Church at that period, hinting at
                    fox-hunting, Port-wine drinking, and a few
                    other foibles not much in the style of "Him
                    of Galilee," leaving the silent inference to be
                    drawn that had his father been a young
                    man now he would not have had his old
                    scruples.</p>
                <p>Southey's religion at this precise point of
                    his life, was, we have heard Coleridge affirm,
                    "<hi rend="italic">an empty vacuum full of mythology, and
                        craving a plenum of a comfortable income,
                        a handsome wife, and a large epic fame</hi>."
                    In a short time afterwards he grew Unitarian;
                    there was an intellectuality about it
                    which pleased him. We may as well in
                    this place relate a little anecdote of Coleridge,
                    which showed how greatly his imagination
                    entered into his "Thirty-nine Articles,"
                    even to the very last. About a fortnight
                    before the great poet died, the writer of this
                    had received a letter from Mr. Wordsworth,
                    containing a message to Coleridge, who was
                    not suspected to be so near his death as
                    eventually proved. We merely name this
                    to account for the apparent discrepancy of
                    the conversation. The "old man eloquent"
                    was in his bed-room, a chamber which commanded
                    one of the sweetest and greenest
                    views in England&#8212;being from the brow of
                    Highgate Hill, and looking over Finchley
                    towards St. Albans. As we write all seems
                    as fresh as yesterday&#8212;the broken-down
                    frame of the old poet&#8212;his large, gray,
                    fiery, yet pain-stricken eye&#8212;his flabby, pale,
                    yet heavy face&#8212;his noble brow, not bald,
                    being covered with silvery hair&#8212;his intermittent,
                    yet full, deep voice&#8212;the very
                    roll of his eye, the compressed lip, the<cb/>
                slippered feet, the snuffed old black coat,
                gorged with the titillating dust down his
                waistcoat and cuff&#8212;all stand so palpably
                now before me, that the Atlantic seems a
                rivulet, and the sixteen years that have
                nearly rolled since "the noticeable man"
                was laid in the immortality of his grave in
                the old church-yard at Highgate, a mere
                watch of the night. But we must shake off
                the reverie, or we shall bury our readers in
                sleep.</p>
                <p>Coleridge burst out as we were saying
                    "Good bye," with&#8212;"Lord Brougham has
                    been here to-day. We talked about religion.
                    Brougham said, 'Mr. Coleridge, you were a
                    Unitarian preacher once: define the difference
                    between your faith as <hi rend="italic">then</hi> and <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. I
                    shall remember it, and it may bring forth
                    seed long after you dream of.' Brougham's
                    a good man,&#8212;a kind man; his heart is
                    right&#8212;it is his over-worked brain that has
                    made him go wrong. Heaven help him&#8212;
                    he is as simple as a child!"</p>
                <p>"Well, but my dear friend," said Mrs.
                    Gillman, who had only just recovered from a
                    severe accident, "your definition?" Coleridge
                    smiled: "Dear friend, cherish that cowry
                    shell on the mantel-piece, for it has, I feel
                    assured, converted an unbelieving Chancellor,
                    the living Bacon of our Woolsack.
                    I took up the shell, my dear friends, and
                    said, 'Heaven has sent this to give me an
                    illustration. You see how exquisitely this is
                    worked, how wonderfully symmetrical; the
                    tints of the coloring are miraculously artistic:
                    on one side you have the golden flush
                    of sunset, mingling with the purple dawn;
                    and if you place it to your ear, imagination
                    supplies a voice which seems to whisper an
                    audible something, but it is only a <hi rend="italic">dead
                        shell</hi>&#8212;where is the living animal, for which
                    it was created? It is only a sarcophagus.
                    So with Unitarianism. I admire its external
                    form, the beauty of its morality, the coloring
                    of its logic. But where is the living
                    spirit of Faith? Where is Christ? You
                    have taken away the Lord, and you know
                    not where you have laid him."</p>
                <p>We shall not go into the theology of this
                    simile; we merely give it for its poetry.</p>
                <p>When Southey turned Unitarian, he became
                    more decided in all his opinions, as we
                    shall see.</p>
                <p>We must, however, devote a few lines
                    to allow the son to explain the processes
                    through which his father passed ere he be-</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="mid.00007.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">166</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Feb.</fw>
               <p>came a good Quarterly Reviewer of the
                   Tory school:&#8212;</p>
                <p>"His opinions at this time were somewhat
                    unsettled, although they soon took the form
                    of Unitarianism, from which point they seem
                    gradually to have ascended without any abrupt
                    transition, as the troubles of life increased
                    his devotional feelings, and the study
                    of religious authors informed his better judgment,
                    until they finally settled down into a
                    strong attachment for the doctrines of the
                    Church of England."</p>
                <p>Southey seems to have given the Church
                    up, that he might devote himself to Æsculapius,
                    for he announces in a letter to his
                    <hi rend="italic">fidus Achates</hi>: "Very soon shall I commence
                    my anatomical and chemical studies. When
                    well grounded in those, I hope to study
                    under Cruikshank to perfect myself in anatomy,
                    attend the clincial lectures, and then
                    commence&#8212;Doctor Southey!"</p>
                    <p>He accordingly attended for some time
                        the Anatomy School, and the Lectures of
                        the medical professors, but he soon abandoned
                        the idea as hastily as he had adopted
                        it, partly from being unable to overcome his
                        disgust tor a dissecting room, but chiefly because
                        his love for literature was too strong
                        within him.</p>
                    <p>He now turned his hopes of obtaining a
                        living towards a situation under Government,
                        as his friend Bedford had done, but
                        it was hinted that his well-known violent
                        republican sentiments, so freely and loudly
                        and unnecessarily expressed, had closed that
                        door for ever. This was a pretty situation
                        for the future Poet Laureate. We may
                        here however mention an anecdote which
                        seems to fasten upon Poet Laureates a sort
                        of political discontent. Some two years
                        before Wordsworth was appointed as Southey's
                        successor, a young English poet, a
                        friend of the Bard of Rydal sent to him a
                        sonnet written to Queen Victoria. The old
                        poet in his reply acknowledged the sonnet,
                        but rebuked him for desecrating the majesty
                        of Apollo, by bowing to crowned heads.
                        Victoria was a Whig.</p>
                    <p>Southey's reply to his friend is bold, for
                        he is evidently annoyed:&#8212;"My opinions
                        are very well known. I would have them so.
                        Nature never meant me for a negative character.
                        I can neither be good nor bad,
                        happy nor miserable, by halves. A prudential
                        silence would have sullied my integrity!"</p>
                    <p>At this precise minute he became intimate<cb/>
                        with Samuel Taylor Coleridge, who was
                        an undergraduate of Jesus College, Cambridge,
                        where he had entered in February,
                        1791. He had already given the world
                        assurance of his genius by his writings and
                        his eccentricities, having gained the golden
                        medal for his Greek Ode, and by his singular
                        lecturings. In 1793, in a fit of collegiate
                        disappointment, he enlisted in the 15th Light
                        Dragoons, under the name of Cumberback,
                        from which "warlike position" he was extricated
                        by his friends on the 10th April,
                        1794. In the June of this year, on a
                        visit to a college friend at Oxford, he was
                        introduced to Southey. They each seem,
                        like the German students of Canning's burlesque,
                        to have sworn at that instant eternal
                        friendship: they agreed in religion, politics,
                        and every thing! Southey thus writes of
                        Coleridge in the first glow of young acquaintanceship:
                        "Allen is with us daily, and his
                        friend from Cambridge, Coleridge, whose
                        poems you will oblige me by subscribing
                        to, either at Hookham's or Edwards's. He
                        is of most uncommon merit, of the strongest
                        genius, the clearest judgment, the best
                        heart. My friend he already is, and must
                        hereafter be yours!"</p>
                    <p>"Alas, for the rosy dreams of youthful hearts!"</p>
                    <p>From this meeting sprang Pantisocracy.
                        It was agreed between Lovell, Coleridge, and
                        Southey, to collect as many adventurous
                        spirits as possible, buy laud on the banks
                        of the Susquehanna, and taking out wives,
                        produce children at their leisure, to inherit
                        their estates. Stripped of all verbiage, we
                        really believe this is as nearly as possible the
                        bare idea of this loudly trumpeted Utopia.</p>
                    <p>The instigators or chief conspirators of
                        this plan to inundate the United States
                        with poets, were Robert Lovell, who had
                        lately married one of the Misses Fricker,
                        George Barrett, a fellow collegian, Robert
                        Allen, of Christ Church, Oxford, and Edmund
                        Seward: to these were soon added Southey
                        and Coleridge.</p>
                    <p>It broke up as rapidly as it had formed.
                        Seward deserted into the Established Church,
                        (an ominous beginning of the campaign,)
                        Coleridge made a pedestrian tour in Wales,
                        and Southey went to his aunt at Bath. That
                        however the two latter had not altogether
                        waked from their dream, is evident from
                        our poet's letter dated July, 1794.</p>
                    <p>"'Tis my intention to join Coleridge in</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="mid.00007.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1851.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">167</fw>
            <p>Wales, then proceed to Edmund Seward,
                seriously to arrange with him the best mode
                of settling in America. Yesterday I took
                my proposals for publishing 'Joan of Arc,'
                to the printer: should the publication be in
                any way successful, it will carry me over,
                and get me some few acres, a spade and a
                plough. My brother Thomas will gladly go
                with us. In this country I must sacrifice
                either happiness or integrity."</p>
                <p>Like all young authors, Southey had the
                    most sanguine expectation of "Joan of Arc's"
                    success; he talked of leaving it as a legacy to
                    his countiy, of its preserving his name, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>In August Coleridge returned to Bristol,
                    and, unfortunately for him, became acquainted
                    with his future wife. The tragedy called
                    the "Fall of Robespierre" was written at
                    this time.</p>
                <p>Again, too, Pantisocracy reared its head;
                    Southey thus writes to his brother who was
                    to join them:&#8212;</p>
                <p>"The Pantisocratic scheme has given me
                    new life, new hope, new energy; all the
                    faculties of my mind are dilated. I am
                    weeding out the few lurking prejudices of
                    habit, und looking forward to happiness."</p>
                <p>In October the scheme was communicated
                    to his aunt, whose anger knew no bounds.
                    It ended in her turning him from her house
                    late at night, so that he had to walk to Bath,
                    nine miles, in rain and darkness. So much
                    for the affection of a narrow-minded old woman.
                    Southey says in a letter to his brother,
                    that it was the announcement of his intended
                    marriage that most thoroughly annoyed her.
                    The aunt and nephew never met again.</p>
                <p>Two months after Lovell and Southey
                    published a small volume of poems: this
                    closed 1794.</p>
                <p>The difficulty of raising funds for emigration
                    now induced them to alter their scheme
                    from America to Wales; but after a few
                    dying reflections, even this was abandoned,
                    and poor Pantisocracy died and was buried.</p>
                <p>He now amused himself with planning
                    a magazine to be edited by him and Coleridge;
                    he also offered his services to a country
                    newspaper, which however were declined.
                    He then, in conjunction with the
                    latter, gave a course of lectures at Bristol,
                    which were well attended and much praised.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cottle now offered to publish "Joan
                    of Arc," to which Southey gladly consented.
                    He had already commenced " Madoc," which
                    he laid aside to correct his first-born epic.</p><cb/>
                <p>His uncle, Mr. Herbert Hill, being about
                    to return to Portugal, persuaded Southey to
                    accompany him. Much as he disliked the
                    idea of being separated from his fair Edith,
                    to whom he had been for some time engaged,
                    yet the idea of making the visit
                    father to a volume of travels gilded the pill
                    of separation. He however resolved to make
                    the lady his, beyond the chance of any accident
                    save death, and on the 14th November,
                    1795, they were married at Redcliffe Church,
                    Bristol, separating immediately after the ceremony.
                    A few days afterwards the virgin
                    bridegroom was on his way to Lisbon, which
                    he reached after a tedious passage, laying some
                    time wind bound at Falmouth. After an absence
                    of six months he returned, and took possession
                    of his wife and some ready-furnished
                    lodgings, and busied himself in preparing his
                    "Letters from Spain and Portugal." During
                    his absence his brother-in-law and brother
                    poet, Robert Lovell, had died, and his widow
                    soon after Southey's return went to reside
                    with them, and remained a guest during the
                    rest of her life.</p>
                <p>"Joan of Arc" had been published during
                    the author's residence in Lisbon, and had
                    fallen still-born from the press. Southey
                    says in August, 1796, "The sale of 'Joan
                    of Arc' in London has been very slow indeed;
                    six weeks ago Cadell had only sold
                    <hi rend="italic">three</hi> copies!"</p>
                <p>Mr. Wynn, his old school-fellow, had,
                    immediately on Southey's marriage, with a
                    generosity worthy of his name, settled an
                    annuity of £160 per annum on him. This
                    enabled him to work at labor he had the
                    most genius for&#8212;a great advantage; it also
                    enabled him to put some finishing touches to
                    his writings, which otherwise the daily necessities
                    of his household would have prevented.</p>
                <p>In February he came to London for a few
                    months in order to enter himself of Gray's
                    Inn. In April he returned to Bath, where
                    he remained working hard at a second
                    volume of poems, finishing "Madoc," and
                    writing for the "Morning Post," and some
                    magazines.</p>
                <p>In 1800 he commenced at Bristol his
                    "Thalaba," undoubtedly the best of his
                    longer poems; his health however had been
                    for some time failing, and in April he, accompanied
                    by his wife, set sail once more for
                    the Tagus.</p>
                <p>In June, 1801, they returned, restored</p>-->
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="mid.00007.005.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">168</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Robert Southey.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Feb.</fw>
            <cb/><p>in health, and full of renewed plans, taking
                up their residence at Bristol.</p>
                <p>Towards the close of this year he obtained,
                    through Mr. Wynn's untiring friendship,
                    the appointment of private secretary to Mr.
                    Corry, Chancellor of the Exchequer for Ireland,
                    at a salary of £400 per annum. He
                    was however only required a short time in
                    Dublin; on his return he was steadily settled
                    at London as Mr. Corry's secretary. In
                    the meantime he had published "Thalaba,"
                    the copyright of which he sold for £115.
                    In January, 1802, his mother died: this
                    was a heavy blow, as Robert Southey was a
                    man full of domestic feelings.</p>
                <p>Finding his office to be a sinecure, he,
                    with an honesty which ought to be more
                    generally followed, resigned his secretaryship,
                    and resolved to settle in the country.
                    After casting "his eyes" about him, he fixed
                    upon the Lakes of Westmoreland, to which
                    his friend Coleridge had already retired. In
                    September, 1803, immediately after the death
                    of his only child, a little girl of scarcely a
                    year old, they settled at Greta Hall. He had
                    already made the acquaintance of the Longmans,
                    and received several commissions from
                    them, which afterwards led to a connection,
                    closed only by the Laureate's death. Southey
                    had now reached his thirtieth year, and had
                    settled down in a spot from which he never
                    after removed, to devote his energies to a
                    purely literary life: perhaps we have no
                    other instance of a man so completely following
                    up that one idea without reference to
                    anything else, as the distinguished man
                    whose life we are reviewing.</p>
                <p>His industry was the most untiring of
                    any author's of modern times. In March,
                    1804, he thus wrote to his friend John
                    Rickman:&#8212;"I have more in hand than
                    Bonaparte, or Marquis Wellesley&#8212;digesting
                    Gothic Law; gleaning moral history from<cb/>
                    monkish Legends; conquering India, or
                    rather Asia, with Albuquerque; filling up
                    the chinks of the day by hunting in Jesuit
                    Chronicles, and compiling Collectanea Hispanica
                    et Gothica. Meantime Madoc sleeps,
                    and my lucre of-gain-compilation (specimens
                    of English Poets) goes on at night, when
                    I am fairly obliged to lay history aside, because
                    it perplexes me in my dreams. 'Tis a
                    vile thing to be pestered in sleep with all
                    the books in the day I have been reading
                    jostled together!"</p>
                <p>In the May of 1804 he visited London, and
                    met some new society. He however was
                    not a very "clubbable fellow," as Johnson
                    would phrase it. He was soon at his home
                    at Keswick again, in the midst of his books,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>He had now made considerable headway
                    in his History of Brazil, and looked forward
                    to another sojourn in Portugal to finish it.
                    Coleridge had been now for some time at
                    Malta, as secretary to Sir Alexander Ball,
                    and Southey's letters to him are full of
                    hints, which afterwards ripened into works&#8212;
                    Coleridge had always great theories to propound,
                    and was a most suggestive companion
                    and correspondent, as Southey and
                    Wordsworth often acknowledged.</p>
                <p>We pause at this point of the Laureate's
                    life to call the reader's attention, not alone to
                    the singular change in his political and religious
                    opinions, but also in his habits of
                    daily life. From the wild enthusiast he becomes
                    tamed town to the orthodox disciplinarian;
                    from the dreamer of Pantisocracy he
                    suddenly awakes to the realities of <hi rend="italic">L.s.d.</hi>-ism;
                    from the Lesbian heights of Pindarics' epics,
                    and Sapphics, he leaps into the level sea of
                    Routine!</p>
                <p>But we must reserve the moral we have
                    to deduce from this singular harlequinade 
                    to our next number.</p>
            <span rend="singleLine" hand="#h2" from="leaf007r"/>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2"><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Burns</hi><lb/>
                1759<lb/>
                to<lb/>
            1796</note>
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#r2">
                <q who="unknown" type="written">
            <floatingText rend="flat">
                <body>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="mid.00007.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <p>This Scotch Poet was born in 175<subst><del rend="overstrike" hand="#h2" seq="1"><gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="number"/></del><add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear" seq="2"><handShift new="#h2"/>9</add></subst><handShift new="#h1"/>.&#8212;Though
                    a ploughman originally, he rose to high poetical
                    fame. He has been called the greatest
                    untaught genius since <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>. His poems
                    glow with the real fire of feeling and passion.
                    As soon as he appeared in print he was
                    noticed and drawn from the plough to associate
                    with men of letters and opulence. But
                    the change ruined him. He indulged in licentious
                    pleasures, till his constitution gave
                    way, and the tomb received him. He died at
                    the age of 39.</p>
                </body>
            </floatingText>
                </q>
            </add>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="right">In his poems,
            Burns was faithful to
            lowly things, customs, idioms,
            Scotland, the lasses, the peasan<gap reason="cut off" extent="2" unit="letter"/>
                and to his own robust natu<gap reason="cut off" extent="2" unit="letter"/>
            He was <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear"><handShift new="#h2"/>often</add><handShift new="#h3"/> hard up, an
            improvident, free handed
            man&#8212;his poems succeeded&#8212;
            he made £500, an immense
            sum.&#8212; He took a farm,
            was appointed exciseman&#8212;
            (£75 a year)&#8212;lived two or
            three years in that way,
            drank, sickened, died.&#8212;</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>