<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00010">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="ht">Henry David Thoreau</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00010</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">On each of the final two surfaces, in an unknown hand, "x"</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Thoreau and Others on Indian Poetry and Indian Drama</title>
                    <idno type="callno"/>
                    <date notBefore="1849-01-01" notAfter="1892-05-26">After 1849</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="mid">Middlebury College Library, Special Collections</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
                    <title>A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers</title>
                    <date when="1849-01-01">1849</date>
                    <publisher>James Munroe and Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ht" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#unk" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2012-07-12">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-01-30">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-05-22">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="mid.00010.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#r1"><q who="unknown" type="written">
                <floatingText rend="flippy">
                    <body>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="mid.00010.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p xml:id="p1a" next="#p1b"><handShift new="#h1"/>It is always singular, but encouraging, to meet with
            common<add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear"><handShift new="#h2"/>x</add><handShift new="#h1"/> sense in very old books, as the Heetopades of
            Veeshnoo Sarma; a playful wisdom which has eyes behind
            as well as before, and oversees itself. It asserts their
            health and independence of the experience of later times.
            This pledge of sanity cannot be spared in a book, that is
            sometimes pleasantly reflect upon itself. The story and
            fabulous portion of this book winds loosely from sentence
            to sentence as so many oases in a desert, and is as indistinct
            as a camel's track between Mourzouk and Darfour</p>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="mid.00010.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <p>universal greenness. This sand was indeed somewhat
                        impressive and beautiful to us. A very old inhabitant,
                        who was at work in a field on the Nashua side, told us
                        that he remembered when corn and grain grew there, and</p>
                        </body></floatingText></q></add>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="right" corresp="#u1">☟
            <hi rend="underline">Menu,</hi>
            son or
            grandson
            of Brahma
            and first of
            created beings</note>
            <p xml:id="p1b" prev="#p1a">It is a comment on the flow and freshet of modern books.
            The reader leaps from sentence to sentence, as from one
            stepping stone to another, while the stream of the story
            rushes past unregarded. The Bhagvat-Geeta is less sententious
            and poetic, perhaps, but still more wonderfully
            sustained and developed. Its sanity and sublimity have
            impressed the minds even of soldiers and merchants. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">It
            is the characteristic of great poems that they will yield of
            their sense in due proportion to the hasty and the deliberate
            reader. To the practical they will be common sense,
            and to the wise wisdom; as either the traveller may wet
            his lips, or an army may fill its water casks at a full
            stream.</hi></p>
            <p>One of the most attractive of those ancient books that I
            have met with is the Laws of Menu. According to Sir
            William Jones, "Vyasa, the son of Parasara, has decided<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">4</note>
            that the Veda, with its Angas, or the six compositions
            deduced from it, the revealed system of medicine, the
            Puranas, or sacred histories, and the code of Menu, were
            four works of supreme authority, which ought never to be
            shaken by arguments merely human." The last is believed
            by the Hindoos "to have been promulged in the beginning
            of time, by <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u1">Menu, son or grandson of Brahma,"</hi> and
            "first of created beings;" and <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Brahma is said to have
            "taught his laws to Menu in a hundred thousand verses,</hi>
            which Menu explained to the primitive world in the very
            words of the book now translated." Others affirm that
            they have undergone successive abridgments for the convenience
            of mortals, "while the gods of the lower heaven,<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2" corresp="#leaf003r">Sadi
            about
            A.D. 1000</note>
            and the band of celestial musicians, are engaged in studying
            the primary code."&#8212;"A number of glosses or comments
            on Menu were composed by the Munis, or old
            philosophers, whose treatises, together with that before us,</p>
            <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2" rend="circled">over</note>
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#r1">
                <q who="unknown" type="written">
                    <floatingText rend="flippy">
                        <body>
                            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="mid.00010.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                            <p>"Yesterday, at dawn," says Hafiz, "God delivered me
                                from all worldly affliction; and amidst the gloom of night
                                presented me with the water of immortality."</p>
                                <p>In the life of Sadi by Dowlat Shah, occurs this sentence.
                                "The eagle of the immaterial soul of Shaikh Sadi shook
                                from his plumage the dust of his body."</p>
                            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="mid.00010.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                            <p>wisest, is as much more <gap reason="covered" extent="3" unit="word"/>
                            Some aspire to excellence in ths subordinate department,
                            and may God speed them. What Fuller says of masters
                            of colleges is universally applicable, that "a little alloy of</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText></q>
            </add>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00010.002a.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">154</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">A WEEK.</fw>
            <p>constitute the Dherma Sastra, in a collective sense, or
            Body of Law." Culluca Bhatta was one of the more
            modern of these.</p>
            <p>Every sacred book, successively, seems to have been
            accepted in the faith that it was to be the final restingplace
            of the sojourning soul; but after all, it is but a caravansary
            which supplies refreshment to the traveller, and
            directs him farther on his way to Isphahan or Bagdat.
            Thank God, no Hindoo tyranny prevailed at the framing
            of the world, but we are freemen of the universe, and not
            sentenced to any cast.</p>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><p>I know of no book which has come down to us with
                    grander pretensions than this, and it is so impersonal and
                    sincere that it is never offensive nor ridiculous. Compare
                    the modes in which modern literature is advertised with the
                    prospectus of this book, and think what a reading public
                    it addresses, what criticism it expects. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">It seems to have
                    been uttered from some eastern summit, with a sober
                    morning prescience in the dawn of time,</hi> and you cannot
                    read a sentence without being elevated as upon the tableland
                    of the Ghauts. It has such a rhythm as the winds of
                    the desert, such a tide as the Ganges, and <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">is as superior to
                    criticism as the Himmaleh mountains.</hi> Its tone is of such
                    unrelaxed fibre, that even at this late day, unworn by
                    time, it wears the English and the Sanscrit dress indifferently,
                    and its fixed sentences keep up their distant fires
                    still like the stars, by whose dissipated rays this lower
                    world is illumined. The whole book by noble gestures
                    and inclinations seems to render many words unnecessary.
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">English sense has toiled, but Hindoo wisdom never perspired.</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The sentences open, as we read them, unexpensively,
                    and, at first, almost unmeaningly, as the petals
                    of a flower, yet they sometimes startle us with that rare</hi><anchor xml:id="s2"/>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="mid.00010.002b.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">MONDAY.</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">155</fw>
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">kind of wisdom which could only have been learned from
                    the most trivial experience;</hi> but it comes to us as refined
                    as the porcelain earth which subsides to the bottom of the
                    ocean. They are clean and dry as fossil truths, which
                    have been exposed to the elements for thousands of years,
                    so impersonally and scientifically true that they are the
                    ornament of the parlor and the cabinet. Any <hi rend="italic">moral</hi>
                    philosophy is exceedingly rare. This of Menu addresses
                    our privacy more than most. It is a more private and
                    familiar, and, at the same time, a more public and universal
                    word than is spoken in parlor or pulpit now-a-days.
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">As our domestic fowls are said to have their original in
                    the wild pheasant of India,</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">so our domestic thoughts have
                    their prototypes in the thoughts of her philosophers.</hi> We
                    seem to be dabbling in the very elements of our present
                    conventional and actual life; as if it were the primeval
                    conventicle where how to eat and to drink and to sleep,
                    and maintain life with adequate dignity and sincerity,
                    were the questions to be decided. It is later and more
                    intimate even than the advice of our nearest friends.
                    And yet it is true for the widest horizon, and read out of
                    doors has relation to the dim mountain line, and is native
                    and aboriginal there. Most books belong to the house
                    and street only, and in the fields their leaves feel very
                    thin. They are bare and obvious, and have no halo nor
                    haze about them. Nature lies far and fair behind them
                    all. But this, as it proceeds from, so does it address what
                    is deepest and most abiding in man. It belongs to the
                    noontide of the day, the midsummer of the year, and after
                    the snows have melted, and the waters evaporated in the
                    spring, still its truth speaks freshly to our experience.
                    It helps the sun to shine, and his rays fall on its page to
                    illustrate it. It spends the mornings and the evenings,</p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="mid.00010.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">156</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">A WEEK.</fw>
                    <p>and makes such an impression on us over night as to
                    awaken us before dawn, and its influence lingers around
                    us like a fragrance late into the day. It conveys a new
                    gloss to the meadows and the depths of the wood. Its
                    spirit, like a more subtile ether, sweeps along with the
                    prevailing winds of a country, and the very locusts
                    and crickets of a summer day are but later or earlier
                    glosses on the Dherma Sastra of the <choice><orig>Hindoos</orig><reg>Hindus</reg></choice>, a continuation
                    of the sacred code. As we have said, there is
                    an orientalism in the most restless pioneer, and the farthest
                    west is but the farthest east. This fair modern
                    world is only a reprint of the Laws of Menu with the
                    gloss of Culluca. Tried by a New England eye, or the
                    mere practical wisdom of modern times, they are the
                    oracles of a race already in its dotage, but held up to the
                    sky, which is the only impartial and incorruptible ordeal,
                    they are of a piece with its depth and serenity, and I am
                    assured that they will have a place and significance as
                    long as there is a sky to test them by.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Give me a sentence which no intelligence can understand.
                    There must be a kind of life and palpitation to it,
                    and under its words a kind of blood must circulate forever.</hi>
                    It is wonderful that this sound should have come down
                    to us from so far, when the voice of man can be heard
                    so little way, and we are not now within ear-shot of any
                    contemporary. The woodcutters have here felled an ancient
                    pine forest, and brought to light to these distant hills
                    a fair lake in the south-west; and now in an instant it is
                    distinctly shown to these woods as if its image had travelled
                    hither from eternity. Perhaps these old stumps upon
                    the knoll remember when anciently this lake gleamed in
                    the horizon. One wonders if the bare earth itself did not
                    experience emotion at beholding again so fair a prospect.</p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="mid.00010.003b.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">MONDAY.</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">157</fw>
                        <!--<note type="editorial" resp="#h3" place="right">x</note>-->
                    <p>That fair water lies there in the sun thus revealed, so
                    much the prouder and fairer because its beauty needed
                    not to be seen. It seems yet lonely, sufficient to itself,
                    and superior to observation.&#8212;So are these old sentences
                    like serene lakes in the south-west, at length revealed to
                    us, which have so long been reflecting our own sky in
                    their bosom.</p>
                    <p>The great plain of India lies as in a cup between the
                    Himmaleh and the ocean on the north and south, and the
                    Brahmapootra and Indus, on the east and west, wherein
                    the primeval race was received. We will not dispute the
                    story. We are pleased to read in the natural history of
                    the country, of the "pine, larch, spruce, and silver fir,"
                    which cover the southern face of the Himmaleh range; of
                    the "gooseberry, raspberry, strawberry," which from an
                    imminent temperate zone overlook the torrid plains. So
                    did this active modern life have even then a foothold and
                    lurking place in the midst of the stateliness and contemplativeness
                    of those eastern plains. In another era the
                    "lily-of-the valley, cowslip, dandelion," were to work their
                    way down into the plain, and bloom in a level zone of
                    their own reaching round the earth. Already has the era
                    of the temperate zone arrived, the era of the pine and the
                    oak, for the palm and the banian do not supply the wants
                    of this age. The lichens on the summits of the rocks
                    will perchance find their level ere long.</p>
                    <p>As for the tenets of the Brahmans, we are not so much
                    concerned to know what doctrines they held, as that they
                    were held by any. We can tolerate all philosophies, Atomists,
                    Pneumatologists, Atheists, Theists,&#8212;Plato, Aristotle,
                    Leucippus, Democritus, Pythagorus, Zoroaster and
                    Confucius. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">It is the attitude of these men, more than
                    any communication which they make, that attracts us.</hi>
                        <fw type="sig" place="bottom">14</fw>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="mid.00010.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">158</fw>
                        <fw type="header" place="top">A WEEK.</fw><!--<note type="editorial" resp="#h3" place="right">x</note>-->
                    Between these and their commentators, it is true, there is<!-- Some writing and/or a pasteon was here before.-->
                    an endless dispute. But if it comes to this that you compare
                    notes, then you are all wrong. As it is, each takes
                    us up into the serene heavens, whither the smallest bubble
                    rises as surely as the largest, and paints earth and sky
                    for us. Any sincere thought is irresistible. The very
                    austerity of the Brahmans is tempting to the devotional
                    soul, as a more refined and nobler luxury. Wants so easily
                    and gracefully satisfied seem like a more refined pleasure.
                    Their conception of creation is peaceful as a dream.
                    "When that power awakes, then has this world its full
                    expansion; but when he slumbers with a tranquil spirit,
                    then the whole system fades away." In the very indistinctness
                    of the theogony a sublime truth is implied. It
                    hardly allows the reader to rest in any supreme first cause,
                    but directly it hints at a supremer still which created
                    the last, and the Creator is still behind increate.</p>
                    <p>Nor will we disturb the antiquity of the Scripture;
                    "From fire, from air, and from the sun," it was "milked
                    out." One might as well investigate the chronology of
                    light and heat. Let the sun shine. Menu understood
                    this matter best, when he said, "Those best know the
                    divisions of days and nights who understand that the day
                    of Brahma, which endures to the end of a thousand such
                    ages, [infinite ages, nevertheless, according to mortal
                    reckoning,] gives rise to virtuous exertions; and that his
                    night endures as long as his day." Indeed, the <choice><orig>Mussulman</orig><reg>Muslim</reg></choice>
                    and Tartar dynasties are beyond all dating. Methinks
                    I have lived under them myself. In every man's
                    brain is the Sanscrit. The Vedas and the Angas are not
                    so ancient as serene contemplation. Why will we be
                    imposed on by antiquity? Is the babe young? When I
                    behold it, it seems more venerable than the oldest man;</p>
         </body>
    </text>
</TEI>