<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00006">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Modern English Poets</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00006</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman's Manuscript Notes on Southey, Browning and Others</title>
                    <idno type="callno"/>
                    <date notBefore="1851-12-01" notAfter="1892-05-26">After December 1, 1851</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="mid">Middlebury College Library, Special Collections</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Anonymous</author> 
                    <title level="a">Modern English Poets</title>
                    <title level="j">American Whig Review</title>
                    <date when="1851">December 1851</date>
                    <!--<publisher/> 
                    <pubPlace/>-->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black-ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2012-07-23">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-01-30">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-05-22">Proofed.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-07-20">Edits per K. Price.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00006.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="top"><hi rend="underline">Bells &amp; Pomegranates</hi>, Robert Browning <lb/>
            <hi rend="underline">Casa Guidi Windows,</hi> Elizabeth Barrett Brown<gap reason="illegible" extent="3" unit="letter"/></note>
            <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h1"/>1851</fw>
            <del rend="overstrike" hand="#h2"><fw type="header" place="top">The Dallas Letter.</fw></del>
            <fw type="pageNum">461</fw>
            <cb/><delSpan rend="hashmark" hand="#h2" spanTo="#zztop"/><p>the reputation of their authors. Those who
            turn aside from the grand current of events
            to undertake the salvation or the destruction
            of the country by the propogation of
            startling issues, will continue to be cast up,
            from time to time, high and dry upon the
            beach, to learn at their leisure, that those
            who would lead public opinion must be content
            to go with it until they are not only
            assured of the superior wisdom of their own
            foresight, but that they have force enough
            to divert it into a new channel.</p>
                <p>The surest method of promoting union is
                to fix the attention upon some prospective
                good, and to labor to reach it. It has been
                wisely said, that the principle of friendly cooperation
                lies in a common interest in the
                pursuit of a common good. It is well
                enough to probe a wound to ascertain its
                nature and extent, but the probing is no part
                of the cure, and if unskilfully attempted, may
                serve to make the bad still worse.</p>
                <p>We have as a nation a work to accomplish,
                to which if we bend all our energies,
                there need be no fear of discord among us.
                Unity of heart and mind is requisite to
                the accomplishment of the task, which is no
                less than the renovation of the condition of
                human society.</p>
                <p>Europe is in a sad state. Absolutism is
                more terrible to-day than ever before; while,
                on the other hand, libety is more indispensable
                for man. The ambition of crowned
                heads is less carefully disguised by the vacant-featured 
                mask of diplomacy, and looks directly
                to its mark. A czar or an emperor
                may well burn with ambitious desire to add
                to his dominions such slaves as the men who
                wield the intellectual and moral power of
                the age. The pride of a Corsican soldier
                took fire at such a thought, and well nigh
                accomplished its most ambitious aspirations.</p>
                <p>It was vastly easier, centuries ago, to
                wrest power from the hands of kings, than at
                the present day. Until royalty learned what
                a Cromwell could do, it treated popular tumult
                with contempt, though with severity.
                But that notable example, followed by still
                more instructive lessons, has taught absolutism
                that there is no sympathy between it
                and the ideas of popular liberty. The artful
                <cb/>
                disguise which for a time served to conceal
                its hostility to popular liberty, by representing
                the design of European politics to be
                the preservation of an equipoise of power,
                is now thrown off, and open and avowed war
                is waged upon all constitutional limitations
                of royal power. Poland is absorbed; Hungary
                is stripped of its constitution; Prussia
                has the alternative of revolution or despotism;
                Germany is kept in a state of fermentation,
                as ignorant as the rest of the world
                of what are her constitutional rights, and
                who are her real masters. Even Turkey&#8212;
                alas for Europe!&#8212;has too much humanity
                for the oppressed, for the security of the
                European powers. Italy&#8212;softly Italy has
                departed; resurrection, not revolution, is the
                only hope for her. What shall be said of
                France? She presents the paradox of elective
                absolutism arm in arm with rampant
                democracy. Some dreary night, one or the
                other will be found strangled. When that
                day comes, the guillotine or the bayonet will
                have prevailed.</p>
                <p>There remains one other European power,
                seated upon what must one day have been
                the easternmost projection of the American
                continent, but, by some hankering after the
                society of royalty, betrayed into bad company,
                which entertains manly ideas of popular
                liberty. That great power has until just
                now been altogether taken up with the exhibition
                of a gigantic Punch, and with the
                practical philosophy of the Hong merchants.
                But there is hope that her mighty arm will
                be lifted over the lofty crests of the oppressors,
                for her true-hearted people have received
                with sympathy and fellowship a noble exile.</p>
                <p>That exile will soon be in our midst, and
                will be received as an ambassador, not from
                the oppressed of Hungary alone, but of all
                Europe. What may be the issue of the
                future is with Heaven alone to know; but
                the aspects of the present forebode the advent
                of events that will demand of us perfect and
                indissoluble unity, nerve and patriotism.
                For the rest, with the power and security
                which these will bring us, we may rest hopeful
                and assured of the triumph of right in
                whatever struggle gathers in the eventful
                future.</p><anchor xml:id="zztop"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="mid.00006.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top">[D]ec. 1856&#8212;Aurora Leigh, a new poem<lb/>
            by Mrs. Browning&#8212;</note>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left"><handShift new="#h1"/>462</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Modern English Poets.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">December,</fw>
            <head type="main-authorial" rend="centered">MODERN ENGLISH POETS.*</head>
            <cb/><p>MR. AND MRS. BROWNING are psychological
            curiosities. Independently of the singular
            fact of the two of the greatest poetical
            minds of the day being "united in the holy
            bonds of matrimony," there are many peculiar
            traits connected with their history which
            render them possibly the most interesting
            married couple on record. Both shrouded
            as it were from the world, and dedicated to
            the service of Apollo almost from their very
            cradle, they, like young Hannibal, have
            given themselves up to that worship which,
            though requiring a native genius, is yet more
            generally determined by some particular
            accident. In order to render their idiosyncrasy
            the more intelligible, we shall briefly
            allude to their personal history, and as a
            matter of course commence with the lady.</p>
        <p>Miss Elizabeth Barrett Barrett is the
            daughter of a gentleman of moderate fortune,
            and was born in London in 1812.
            Being of fragile health and slender frame,
            she was unable to partake of those amusements
            to which young ladies of her class in
            life are predisposed. While her friends
            sought the ball and the concert-room, the
            youthful poetess retired to her chamber, and
            studied Greek, Latin, and other Lady Jane
            Grey accomplishments. As early as her
            tenth year, she had written some verses of
            singular merit, even at that age displaying
            that peculiar style of thought and expression
            which have made her the most original
            poetess in the English language. Her
            first attempts at verse were given to the
                <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi> without any signature, or indeed
            even initial, and excited great curiosity from
            their remarkable phraseology. We question
            if any poet of so youthful an age ever so
            completely exhibited the complete <hi rend="italic">Minervaism</hi>
            as the youthful Elizabeth. A few years
            afterwards appeared her translation of Eschylus's
            "Prometheus Vinctus," which may
            challenge comparison with any translation
            of the day: indeed it may be pronounced
            <hi rend="italic">unique</hi>, not only on account of its fidelity,
            <cb/>
            but also by reason of its force and point.
            We merely give one specimen to prove our
            assertion:</p>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"Behold with throe on throe,</l>
            <l>How wasted, by this woe,</l>
            <l>I wrestle down the myriad years of Time!</l>
            <l>Behold how fast around me</l>
            <l>The New Kind of the happy ones sublime</l>
            <l>Has flung the chain he forged, has shamed and
            bound me!</l>
            <l>Woe, woe, to-day's woe, and the coming morrow's</l>
            <l>I cover with one groan. And where is found me
            A limit to these sorrows!</l>
            <l>And yet what word do I say? I have foreknown</l>
            <l>Clearly all things that should be; nothing done</l>
            <l>Comes sudden to my soul; and I must bear</l>
            <l>What is ordained with patience, being aware</l>
            <l><hi rend="italic">Necessity doth front the universe</hi></l>
            <l><hi rend="italic">With an invincible gesture."</hi></l></lg>
            <p>The two last lines are certainly of an order
            for which we must, with Mr. Willis's permission,
            invent a word, and call <hi rend="italic">Browningesque;</hi>
            for we question if, till Miss Barrett
            wrote, so singular a position were ever put,
            like a straight waistcoat, upon the universe.</p>
            <p>We will quote only one more verse of this
            really marvellous translation:</p>
            <lg type="stanza"><l>"I know that Zeus is stern;</l>
            <l>I know he metes his justice by his will;</l>
            <l>And yet I also know his soul shall learn</l>
            <l>More softness when once broken by this ill!</l>
            <l>That, curbing his unconquerable wrath,</l>
            <l>He shall rush on in fear, to meet with me,</l>
            <l>Who rush to meet with him in agony,</l>
            <l>To issues of harmonious covenant."</l></lg>
            <p>We have in this the germ of much of Mrs.
            Browning's poetry; for, without harping too
            much upon one string&#8212;for her lyre is fully
            strung&#8212;we may yet observe that very much
            of her music is set in one key, which at
            times gives a monotony to her verse which
            really belongs more to its <hi rend="italic">sound</hi> than its
            <hi rend="italic">sense</hi>. In the latter point of view, she is
            undoubtedly the most peculiar of all the
            female poets of England. But her mannerism
            is in word, not thought. There is also
            a provoking fact about her, which lends her
            the less excuse for the <hi rend="italic">tortuous</hi> style of her</p>
        <note type="footnote" place="bottom">*Sordello, Bells, and Pomegranates, &amp;c. By Robert Browning.
            Casa Guidi's Windows. By Elizabeth Barrett Browning.</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>