<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="yal.00368">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Fair Pilot of Loch Uribol</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="rb">Robert Buchanan</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>yal.00368</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>"The Fair Pilot of Loch Uribol"</title>
                    <idno type="callno">YCAL MSS 202, Folder 200</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1872-07-01" notAfter="1892-03-01">After 1872</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="yal">Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>[Robert Buchanan]</author>
                    <title level="a">The Fair Pilot of Loch Uribol: A Yachting Episode</title>
                   
                    <title level="j">The Saint Paul's Magazine</title>
                    <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                    <date notBefore="1872-07-01" notAfter="1872-12-31">July to December, 1872</date>
                    <biblScope type="pp">47-53</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#rb" medium="type"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h4" scribeRef="#unk" medium="blue-pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h5" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black-ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2011-11-29">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-10-01">Checked.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2014-11-20">Added bibliographic info.</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-05-22">Proofed.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="yal.00368.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/><div1 type="section">
                    <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1"><del rend="overstrike">return to W W</del> I have read this<lb/>
                little sketch three or four times<lb/>
                        &#8212;at intervals&#8212;sometimes when "gloomy" <lb/>
                        &#8212;&amp; every time it <hi rend="underline">sets</hi> <hi rend="underline">me</hi> <hi rend="underline">up</hi><lb/>
            Walt Whitman</note>
            <note rend="authorial" place="left" resp="#h2">602</note><head type="main-authorial"><handShift new="#h3"/>THE FAIR PILOT OF LOCH URIBOL.</head>
            <head type="sub" rend="smallcaps">A YACHTING EPISODE.</head>
            <head type="sub" rend="smallcaps">BY AN IDLE VOYAGER.</head>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <q who="William Wordsworth" type="written"><lg type="linegroup"><l>"She was a phantom of delight</l>
                <l>When first she gleamed upon my sight;</l>
                <l>A lovely apparition, sent</l>
                <l>To be a moment's ornament!"</l></lg>
                <hi rend="smallcaps">WORDSWORTH</hi>.</q>
            <p>O<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> the afternoon of a summer day, a small schooner yacht closely 
                reefed made her appearance off the mouth of Loch Uribol, a long 
                and lonely fjord in the remote Hebrides of Scotland, and while 
                beating to and fro in the open sea in the midst of the squalls from 
                the neighbouring mountains, hoisted the inverted red flag to the 
                foremast as a signal that the parties on board were in need of 
                assistance.</p>
            <p>It had been a dark, dry day, with the wind blowing fresh from the 
                west very steady and strong, and the yacht, a tiny thing of fifteen or 
                sixteen tons, with a small cock-pit, had been beating since early dawn 
                across the tossing waters of the Minch, which divides the dark, 
                serrated peaks of Skye from the far-off Outer Isles. Lightly as a 
                bird she had bounded over the great rollers of the sea, splashing 
                the foam over herself from stem to stern, but seldom taking on 
                board a drop of "green." The distance across was thirty miles, and 
                the wind was dead ahead, so that her progress westward was slow 
                indeed. The time slipt by, however; the basaltic crags of the northwest 
                coast of Skye grew fainter and fainter; and the islands of the 
                ocean, which at first had been scarcely distinguishable on the horizon, 
                had gradually loomed more and more distinct&#8212;stretching in one 
                desolate and lonely darkness from the high hills of Lewis, past the 
                faint, low-lying flats of Uist, to the dark and rocky shores which 
                fringe the cliffs of Barra. Not once in the long day had the sun 
                actually made his appearance. The atmosphere had been full of a 
                palpitating, silvern light, in which the skies seemed close to the 
                earth, and very gray, and the waves of the sea, where they did not 
                break into white foam, unusually black and threatening. Yet it was 
                "good weather," a safe, snug day for sailing, and the sombre, colourless 
                tone of all things&#8212;sea, far-off land, and sky&#8212;was not without 
                its charms for those who have learned to love the pathetic "neutral 
                tint" of the melancholy Scottish coast.</p>
<!--            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="yal.00368.002.jpg" type="verso"/>   <p> </p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="yal.00368.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> <p> </p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="yal.00368.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> <p> </p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="yal.00368.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> <p> </p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="yal.00368.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> <p> </p>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="yal.00368.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/><p> </p></div1>--></div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="yal.00368.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/><div1 type="section"><delSpan rend="hashmark" hand="#h4" spanTo="#d1"/>
                <head type="main-authorial">THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF AN IRRECONCILEABLE.</head>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <ab>I.</ab>
                    <p>"I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> the Apology which Plato gives us, as the speech of Socrates 
                        before his judges, there is this remarkable passage: 'Do not be vexed 
                        with me for telling you the truth. There lives not the man who can 
                        escape destruction if as a born antagonist he opposes you or any other 
                        popular majority and endeavours to prevent many unjust and unconstitutional 
                        things being done in the state; but it is necessary that he 
                        who will fight this battle for what is righteous, and yet, even for 
                        never so short a time, keep himself unharmed, must maintain the 
                        privacy of an individual, and take no part in public affairs.'"</p>
                    <p>Although the distinguished and very wise and humane writer who 
                        quotes this passage in his last book goes on to observe that in modern 
                        times and in Britain the Antagonist is in no such danger as the 
                        Antagonist in Athens in the days of Plato, this is by no means a true 
                        judgment. This writer does not fail, indeed, to admit that even now 
                        the Antagonist may be in danger of "persecution"&#8212;evidently not 
                        having present to his mind what a miserable burden that word 
                        carries in a compactly-formed and rapidly intercommunicating organisation 
                        like modern society. It in fact carries with it an endless 
                        scroll of threatenings; and the formula of to-day is the formula of 
                        the age of Plato&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Conform, or we will destroy you if we can.</hi></p>
                    <p>The Antagonist or Irreconcileable is not necessarily a haunter of 
                        barricades or in any recognised form a social or political conspirator. 
                        Neither of these characters would suit me, and in reading these 
                        autobiographical notes the reader will please to bear in mind that 
                        an Irreconcileable is simply an uncommitted person. He need 
                        not be cantankerous; he need not be ungentle; he need not be 
                        unsociable, when association can be made truthful. His ideals, religious, 
                        political, domestic, and other, would be found, when expressed 
                        in general terms, to be in accord with those whom most men and 
                        women agree to call good, wise, and great. But on the question of 
                        methods&#8212;that is to say, of the laws and customs directed to the 
                        cultivation of these ideals, an Irreconcileable is simply an uncommitted 
                        person; one who not only makes no show of acquiescence in 
                        these matters, but who firmly holds aloof from everything which 
                        could fairly be held to commit him to any such acquiescence.</p>
                    <p>Leaving alone the rationale of this position for the present, I will 
                        ask leave to begin these Notes with such hints of the character of 
                        my father and mother and of my own childhood as may at least help</p><anchor xml:id="d1"/></div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="yal.00368.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1 type="notes"><head type="main-authorial"><handShift new="#h5"/><hi rend="underline">"The Fair Pilot</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Loch Uribol"</hi></head>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="right">602</note>
                <ab><handShift new="#h5"/>one of my favorite stories<lb/>
                    WW</ab>
                <ab><handShift new="#h3"/>WALT WHITMAN</ab>
                <ab>CAMDEN,</ab>
                <ab>NEW JERSEY.</ab>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="yal.00368.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="bottom right">32</note>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>