<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="col.00001">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Moncure D. Conway, 17
                    February 1868</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>col.00001</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName><persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">15–16</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Moncure D. Conway, 17 February 1868</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1868-02-17" xml:id="dat1">February 17, 1868</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MS 0277</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="col">Moncure Daniel Conway Papers 1847–1907, Columbia University Libraries, Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library, New York, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Conway, Moncure D.">Moncure D. Conway</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-10-24" who="#kk">updated orgName to be consistent with other col files</change>
            <change when="2010-12-22" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-07" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington</name>, <date when="1868-02-17">February 17, 1868</date>. </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Conway,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your letter of February 1st has just come to hand. I am willing that Mr. Hotten
                should sell his English publication of my Poems in the United States, on condition
                of paying me one shilling on every copy disposed of here—&amp; hereby give
                consent to that arrangement.<ptr target="col.00001_n1"/>
                Furthermore, to save trouble, I hereby fully empower you to decide &amp; act for me
                in any matters or propositions relating to the book, in England, should any such
                arise—&amp; what you agree to is agreed to by me. If convenient I should like
                Mr. Hotten to send me two copies of the book, by mail, immediately. I should also
                consider it a special favor if you would forward me from time to time any of the
                English magazines or journals that might contain <hi rend="italic">noteworthy</hi>
                criticisms of my poems. But you must allow me to repay you the favor.</p>

            <p>William O'Connor is well, and remains employed as before. Ellen O'Connor<ptr target="col.00001_n2"/> is
                absent in Providence, but returns soon—their little daughter has been very
                ill, but is now convalescing.</p>

            <p>Our American politics, as you notice, are in an unusually effervescent
                condition—with perhaps (to the mere eye-observation from a distance) divers
                alarming &amp; deadly portending shows &amp; signals. Yet we old stagers take things
                very coolly, &amp; count on coming out all right in due time. The Republicans have
                exploited the negro too intensely, &amp; there comes a reaction. But that is going
                to be provided for. According to present appearances the good, worthy,
                non-demonstrative, average-representing Grant will be chosen President next fall.
                What about him, then? As at present advised, I shall vote for him non-demonstrative
                as he is—but admit I can tell much better about him some five years hence.</p>

            <p>I remain well &amp; hearty—occupy the same quite agreeable &amp; quiet berth in
                the Attorney General's office—and, at leisure, am writing a prose piece or
                two, (which I will send you, when printed.)<ptr target="col.00001_n3"/></p>

            <p>I wish to send my sincerest thanks &amp; personal regards to Mr. Rossetti. To have
                had my book, &amp; my cause, fall into his hands, in London, in the way they have, I
                consider one of the greatest pieces of good fortune.</p>

            <p>Mr. Morley<ptr target="col.00001_n4"/> called upon me. Did you get my piece I sent, "Democracy"? I have just
                received a letter from A. B. Alcott<ptr target="col.00001_n5"/>—he was with Mr. Emerson the previous evening, talking. </p>

            <p>Remember my request to Mr. Hotten for a couple of copies by mail—also, by your
                own kindness, any English criticisms of value should such appear.</p>

            <p>I have not yet seen the February Fortnightly<ptr target="col.00001_n6"/>—nor the book William Blake—but shall procure &amp; read both. I
                feel prepared in advance to render my cordial &amp; admirant respect to Mr.
                Swinburne—&amp; would be glad to have him know that I thank him heartily for
                the mention which, I understand, he has made of me in the Blake.<ptr target="col.00001_n7"/>
            </p>

            <p>Indeed, my dear friend, I may here confess to you that to be accepted by those young
                men of England, &amp; so treated with highest courtesy &amp; even honor, touches one
                deeply. In my own country, so far, from the organs, the press, &amp; from
                authoritative sources, I have received but one long tirade of shallow impudence,
                mockery, &amp; scurrilous jeers. Only since the English recognition have the skies
                here lighted up a little.</p>

            <p>With remembrance &amp; love to you, Rossetti, &amp; all my good friends—I
                write, for the present, Farewell. </p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>