<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00392">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, June 13
                    1870</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Charles Hyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00392</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
                    <title>Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, June 13, 1870</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1870-06-13" xml:id="dat1">June 13, 1870</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Correspondence Series, III-5A</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">The Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Charles L.">Charles L. Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-28" who="#al">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-08-17" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-07-14" who="#kk">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00392.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">Burlington</name>
                    <date when="1870-06-13">June 13 70</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Walter Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Han has received all your letters, also the Radical, containing a very complimentary testimony by a genuine woman, to your "Leaves of Grass": Yet you perceive, even the praise she bestowes, <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">i</unclear>s qualified with the general recoil, which all natures of true human sensibility experience, at your (mistaken) barbarism. The louse and the maggot know as much about procreation as you do, and when you unveil and denude yourself you descend to the level of the dog, with the bitch, merely. But I intended to write of
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00392.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
Han only. She is tolerably well. The swelling in her neck has subsided. She makes a half barbarous life for herself, however and <choice><orig>allmost</orig><reg>almost</reg> </choice> baffles all my efforts at times to humanize her. I have come to view her as a being, half child, wtih small promptings to her social obligations and no longer held her accountable for her ways. <choice><sic>Somethings</sic><corr>Some things</corr></choice> she does very well, but her speech is so vagrant, that, to use her own expression, "I must not put any meaning in her words."</p>
            
            <p>Her usual supiness, or sluggishness continues. I think it must be in the blood. It is very trying to me. Respecting her neglect in not writing to her mother, it is simply the want of inclination, but she treats her good, kind <choice><orig>neighbours</orig><reg>neighbors</reg></choice>, who came and watched over her, during 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00392.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
her last <choice><orig>dreadfull</orig><reg>dreadful</reg></choice> sickness the same way. On her recovery she never crossed the street to thank them. I need scarcely explain to you what gratitude is: Han could have done better and saved me great mortification, but her mother in Brooklyn, thwarted my <choice><orig>endeavours</orig><reg>endeavors</reg></choice>, by <choice><orig>continualy</orig><reg>continually</reg></choice> rushing in, and without sufficient occasion, advising separation. Oh! such stupid recklessness and wickedness. The <choice><orig>Allmighty</orig><reg>Almighty</reg></choice>, it seems to me, has no gift, in the Future <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">t</unclear>o amend the unnecessary and degrading experience <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">I</unclear> have endured. Nor would <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">I</unclear> enter upon such a life again, after it, were a thousand years of mortal existence promised to me, <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">(to</unclear> follow) every year to enter upon a different phase of life, each growing brighter and happier than the last, <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">s</unclear>till ascending upon a <unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">g</unclear>reater scale of grandeur 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00392.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
and felicity.</p>
            
            <p>But Han is to remain as she is and where she is. It is imperative: Any positive pressure <choice><sic>socialy</sic><corr>socially</corr></choice>, or change might prove disastrous. She is looking well, but is never feeling well—has headaches or something. She treats herself too barbarously entirely.</p>
            
            <p>Mrs Whitman rather intimates a desire to make Han another visit: She is becoming too aged, and it is as much as Han can do to take care of herself. For my part I have as much care as I desire, and more than I ever anticipated. I have just paid off the mortgage on my house and have sustained myse<unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">lf</unclear> here, not so much upon the merit or appreciation of my paintings, as by a
certai<unclear reason="margin" cert="high" resp="#kk">n</unclear> force of character, which has found sympathy among the people.</p>


            <closer>
                <salute>Yours truly</salute>
                <signed>C L Heyde</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>