<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00334">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 13 January 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00334</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">80-81</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 13 January 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-01-13">January 13, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-25">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Camp of 51st N.Y.V. near Falmouth </name>
                  <date when="1863-01-13"> Jan 13th/63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We have just come off Picket,  everything along the river and in the camp is just the same as when you left,<ptr target="duk.00334_n1"/>  I am still liveing in Capt Francis's<ptr target="duk.00334_n2"/> tent as I have not been able to get one of my own. I have been expecting every day that we would get orders to move our camp, where we could get wood and water, without going as far for it, as we have to here. Once we had orders to be ready to move the next morning but before morning came, the orders were countermanded,</p>
            <p>I have had Two letters from you since you left, and Two from home and this morning I got one from Heyde. All at home seems to be going on well, Jeff writes strong for me to resign and come home<ptr target="duk.00334_n3"/>  Heyde writes that Hannah is quite sick and almost helpless,  Poor Han I am afraid she has a hard life,  as for Heyde, he is certainly a fool, and I think a scoundrell. He writes me a great deal of stuff about Han  and among other devilish lies he says that he is told that on Han's last visit home, Mother told her She must never turn her thoughts there for a home again. The whole tenor of his letter shows that he wants to get rid of her, and I am sure she must be liveing in a perfect Hell. He says that while he was gone away she was taken worse and had to depend on the Neighbors to take care of her, and that some aquaintance of hers was about writing to her friends, to let them know how she was situated,  Walt you or Jeff must certainly go on there and see how things are, and make some arangements for bringing her home. If <hi rend="italic">you</hi> can go  write on to mother and have her send you some money and dont fail to attend to it immediately as I feel quite worried about Han.</p>
            <p>I received a Brooklyn Eagle yesterday with your letter published,<ptr target="duk.00334_n4"/>  I send you 50 cts which I wish you to buy Postage stamps with, and send them to me as soon as conveinent, as we cant buy any here. Capt Sims and all the rest are well and hearty. I got a letter from boss Rac<ptr target="duk.00334_n5"/> a few days since.</p>
            <p>Let me hear from you as soon as you get this and tell me what you propose to do in regard to Han. I will write again soon.</p>
            <closer rend="center">
               <signed>G. W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
