<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00755">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Mary Van Nostrand to Walt Whitman, 16 March
                    [1878]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Mary Van Nostrand</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00755</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Van Nostrand</author>
                    <title>Mary Van Nostrand to Walt Whitman, 16 March [1878]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1878-03-16" xml:id="dat1">March 16, 1878</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">The Trent Collection of Walt Whitman Manuscripts, Duke
                        University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Van Nostrand, Mary">Mary Van Nostrand</persName>
                </person> 
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-10-30">corrected date information</change>
            <change when="2014-09-18" who="#jyc">checked, revised</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-02-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-20" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-12-10" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-02-07" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk_am.00087_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Greenport</name>
                    <date when="1875-03-16" rend="right">Mar 16<ptr target="duk.00755_n2"/></date>
                </dateline> 
                <salute>Dear dear brother</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Again I am ashamed of myself for not writing to you before as I have received so many
                letters from you and always think I will answer but one thing and another keeps me
                from it so now I will try to tell you about myself well we jog along in about the
                old way sometimes it is nip and tuck with us sometimes nips ahead and <choice>
                    <sic>sometimees</sic>
                    <corr>sometimes</corr>
                </choice> tuck but in the main we are all right as long as I only have my health
                Ansel has been out of work for a year but has work now so we are all right I often
                hear from you through the papers and am glad enough to think you are better this
                winter <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk_am.00299_large.jpg" type="verso"/> and hope
                and pray you will entirely recover and believe you will and would like very much to
                see you whenever you feel as if you could come or any of the rest of my folks and
                will do all I can to make it pleasant for them Our family of children live here
                around us Minnie has three children and Fanny one the rest have none Greenport is
                about the same as it was when you was here only improved very much and now dear
                brother I want to thank you for the many letters cards and papers you have sent me
                and likewise for the christmas present you sent in the letter and want you to write
                whenever you can for you are the only one now since dear mother left us that ever
                writes a word to me Please when you write <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="duk_am.00300_large.jpg" type="recto"/> again mention how Eddy and <choice>
                    <sic>hannah</sic>
                    <corr>Hannah</corr>
                </choice> Jeff George and all get along as I should like to hear from them and I do
                think I will not be so long in answering again. I suppose you have almost forgotten
                how it looks here Louisa and John have built a new house opposite here and are
                living in it Minnie's husband has bought one a little further off and they are
                living in that. I <choice>
                    <sic>dont</sic>
                    <corr>don't</corr>
                </choice> know as this will interest you but I thought I would just write it. I feel
                myself growing old and failing every day but my health has been better this winter
                than usual</p>

            <p>Dear Brother one more favor I would like to ask of you that is when you have time to
                please copy our family record<ptr target="duk.00755_n1"/> and send to me <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk_am.00089_large.jpg" type="verso"/> as I really have
                forgotten how old we all are</p>
 
            <closer>
                <salute rend="right">From your affectionate sister</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Mary Van Nostrand</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
