<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00398">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Charles Louis Heyde to Walt Whitman, [20 December
                    1884]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Charles Louis Heyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00398</idno>
                <distributor>Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Charles Louis Heyde</author>
                    <title>Charles Louis Heyde to Walt Whitman, [20 December 1884]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1884-12-20" xml:id="dat1">December 20, 1884</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">The Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare
                        Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Charles Louis" ref="n0299">Charles Louis Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-24" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-06-06" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-05-20" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-02-14" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-19" who="#ss">encoded and checked</change>
            <change when="2014-12-05" who="#aa">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00398.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <note type="editorial" resp="#unk" place="top">20 Dec. '84</note>
                </dateline>
                <salute><choice><abbr>Bro</abbr><expan>Brother</expan></choice> Walt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>8 O.'clock. I have just seen Han, upstairs: <choice><sic>summond</sic><corr>summoned</corr></choice> by
                her bell, which I was expecting to hear. She was much better than I expected. I was
                very apprehensive last night. She talked strangely, and enquired in whispers to me,
                whether truly I wanted her to get well. I was with her, at her bedside repeatedly,
                and then retired, so as to leave her quiet, alone, as she desired: administered <unclear reason= "cut away" cert="medium" resp= "#if">a</unclear>
                nervine potion, which alone has effect upon nervousness. She had complained much of
                her poor head, and heart throbbing. Entreated me not to let her be taken to the
                hospital. This institution however is a place that many have preferred to be taken to, in
                sickness: where <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00398.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                perfect trained nurses are in attendance, and all uniformed cleanly; free from noise
                or care: Senator Edmunds<ptr target="n4974"/> has endowed a room there: I <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="low">believe</unclear> that his daughter was
                there. Our most experienced practicioners in surgery and medicine are daily
                examiners and prescribers. It is a beautiful situation, not very remote from our
                house, on a fine elevation. But I shall keep Han, in our own house and home. I break
                down <choice><orig>allmost</orig><reg>almost</reg></choice> to <unclear reason="margins cut off" cert="low" resp="#if"
                    >hysteria</unclear> at times, from exhaustion but my appetite remains steadfast,
                without a drop of artificial stimulant, alcohol or other. I perform all the
                housework, even to washing. Han does not; is averse to having our clothes put to
                laundry; <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#aa">their</unclear>
                condition is so bad: beside to keep my house free from <unclear reason="illegible"
                    cert="high" resp="#aa">embarressment</unclear>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00398.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> must beware of
                debt; for pay day comes at last, and my habitation is a guarantee to creditors. I
                have nursed Han though many very bad, very hard physical disorders, typhoid,
                <choice><sic>Erysipilas</sic><corr>Erysipelas</corr></choice>; spinal neuralgia, Hysteria, which is perhaps the most afflicting, and
                most incurable, possessing the mind with terrible conceits, woebegone fancies; distrust of the
                best friend. haunted; afflicting to madness.</p>
            <p>I was much encouraged yesterday, and got away from the house for a couple of hours,
                to see about the sale <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#aa"
                    >of</unclear> several of my paintings by shares or lottery: The frames cost about 60
                dollars, for which I am partly in debt: and every one seems hard pressed for money:
                There is so much extravagance in dress and living: I do not marvel: I may succeed
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00398.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                however&#8212;I can but try: I shall have to keep to the house to day: Han desires
                it: I have bought comforters and bedcloth sheets etc, and may be compelled to buy
                another stove: <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nhg">Doctor</unclear> <unclear reason= "cut off" cert="low" resp="#if">will</unclear>
                be satisfied with a painting; he visits daily, sometimes twice a generous, skilled
                man, <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#kb">has</unclear> promised to continue <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#aa"
                    >faithfully</unclear></p>
            <p>I think the public <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="high">appreciates</unclear> my professional labours and endurance; my
                devotion&#8212;yet so many have imperative <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#kb" cert="high">needs</unclear> of their. George<ptr target="duk.00425_n2"/> should
                help us, all he can: Han's friends or relatives are known: and my <choice><orig>embarressments</orig><reg>embarrassments</reg></choice>. I
                shall assist in bringing her down stairs this morning: two warm coal fires make the
                rooms comfortable&#8212;She mentions you and George: oftimes fails&#8212;can not see
                any person or talk.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>C. L. Heyde</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>If it was spring time!</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
