<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00315">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 16 March 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
<persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00315</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">45-48</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 16 March 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-03-16">March 16, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#nhg" when="2014-08-28">added sender and recipient</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-20">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
            
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Near Newbern  N.C.<ptr target="duk.00315_n100"/>
               </name>
                  <date when="1862-03-16">March 16th 1862</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We have given the Secesshers another thundering thrashing, and have gained a splendid victory. I went through the fight and did not get a scratch although the balls fairly rained around me, and several of our boys were struck down close by my side. I suppose you will get a great deal better acount of the fight, than I can give you (from the papers) but I know you will want to hear my account of it  so here it is.</p>
            <p>We left Roanoke Island March 11th and landed 16 or 18 miles below this place on the 13th. As soon as troops were all on shore we pushed on as fast as possible towards Newbern which is a nice little Citty lying up the Neuse river about 25 miles from Pamlico Sound. Our land force was about 10,000 men with 2 batteries of artilary, and the fighting part of the fleet consisted of 10 or 12 gunboats. After marching through the woods 4 or five miles we struck a railroad track leading into the citty which we followed 3 or 4 miles and as it was then getting dusk the General ordered a halt for the night,  it rained nearly all night and as we lay on the ground our blankets soon got soaked through so that we passed rather an uncomfortable night, although I managed to get 5 or 6 hours good sound sleep. The next morning we were up at daylight and after discharging and reloading our rifles which had got pretty well soaked during the night we marched on towards Newbern. We had skirmishers extending about a quarter of a mile on each side of the railroad and we had not gone more than 3 or 4 miles before they came upon the rebels in strong force behind breastworks, as usual. (We marched right up under a terible fire, formed in line of battle and went at them and fought them in splendid Style for about 3 hours, when our boys drove them from their entrenchments and the day was ours.)<ptr target="duk.00315_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Our men had 60 rounds of Catridge each when they went into action and had used it nearly all and were just about to fall back to let the 51st Pennsylvania Regt take our places (as they had not been in the fight at all) when the enemy run. Our regt went into the fight with about 650 men and as we lost about 100 in killed and wounded you may know that we had pretty hot work. One young fellow (Bob Smith Orderly Sergt of Co B.) that was killed lived in Portland Ave (in one of the brick houses below the vacant lots I think)  He was a member of Capt Spragues<ptr target="duk.00315_n3"/> Co in the old 13th Regt and was a good fellow and an intimate friend of mine. During the fight, I saw our Leiut Col. R.B. Potter<ptr target="duk.00315_n4"/> sitting on a log,   thinking he was wounded, I went up to him and asked him if he was struck, he said only with a spent ball that did not hurt him mutch, and he got up and went into the thickest of it again and did not give up untill the fighting was over which was an hour after I spoke to him, when he found a ball had struck him just above the hip and passed through his side. He is not dangerously hurt and I hope will soon be well.</p>
            <p>After the fight I found our Major C. Legendre<ptr target="duk.00315_n5"/> lying in the mud behind a log, where he had been carried after he fell,   he is very badly hurt  a ball haveing struck him in the back of the neck passing out of his cheek,   I took off the rubber blanket that I had straped on my back  put him on it, got some help and carried him about a quarter of a mile to a tent where he now lies in a very critacle condition,   The Chaplain<ptr target="duk.00315_n6"/> of our regt was killed. one Captain wounded (probaly mortaly) one Leiut killed. one Leiut had a leg taken off and 2 other Leiuts was shot through the Leg. we had 3 orderly Sergts killed and some 16 or 18 privates. I dont know what the total loss on our side is but should think about 450 killed and wounded. The rebel loss is pretty heavy but I dont beleive they lost more than us as they were well protected by their breastworks  I was talking to a darkey to day who says he saw several car loads of their killed and wounded pass through Newbern, and they left quite a number on the feild.</p>
            <p>After they retreated a part of our force followed them up but they had set fire to a bridge about 3/8 of a mile long, on which the cars cross, the river and it was some time before our folks could get boats and cross into the city, which they found nearly deserted and fired in three or four places but it did not burn mutch and we have made a good haul of Government Stores  got posession of a nice little citty that had 5 or 6000 inhabitants I beleive before they ran away. Our regt marched slowly up to the river (as we were pretty well tired) but we could not cross so we spread our blankets on the ground and had a good nights sleep,   the next morning we came to this camp, which is on the bank of the river and about 1½ miles from Newbern. The first Brigade are quartered in the City. We are very comfortably situated and will probaly stay here for some time and take it easy as our boys are pretty well used up. I went down on the battle ground yesterday and when I saw the almost impregnability of the enemys position I was almost scared. They had a chain of breastworks leading from the river, away back in the woods I dont know how far   I followed them about 2 miles and as I could not see the end I turned back,   The trees all around where our regt was engaged are perfectly riddled with balls and nearly all the small ones are cut entirely off. The enemys works on the side of the railroad where our Brigade fought, were so situated that we could not charge them, without getting up to our necks in water and they had cut down the trees and had them lying so that it was almost impassable. The feild yesterday, was quite a sight,   the dead had nearly all been buried but there were some 12 or 15 that I saw, that were not. quite a number of the enemys canon were scattered here and there and horses, that were used to draw them were lying about in the entrenchments,   From the best information I can get the enemy had more men than us and if they could not whip us with all the advantages they had in this fight they had better give it up. The nigers all say that the name of Burnsides expedition is a terror to their masters. The fleet after setting us on shore sailed up the river and walked into the rebels shore batteries in fine style  the rebels had sunk vessels all across the river but our boats got through somehow and drove them out of 4 or 5 Splendid batteries  some of them bomb proof at that.</p>
            <p>The last letter I received from home, <hi rend="italic">Mother</hi>, is dated Feb 19th   I do wish some of you would write oftener,   I had some papers too by the same mail but the last two mails have brought nothing for me. We have not been paid since the First of January, but expect to be soon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Mutch Love to all   G. W. Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>March 18th   I have not had a chance to send this letter yet but hear that the mail leaves tomorrow. I hear to night that the first Brigade leaves tomorrow on some expedition probaly to atack Beauford,<ptr target="duk.00315_n7"/>   our regt is not to go. Another mail arived here yesterday but brought me no letter, and I feel just like giveing you a good scolding, but I guess I will wait untill I get home,   I recd 2 papers however.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours V T   G W Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         </postscript>
         <postscript>
            <p>I wrote you a letter a day or two after we took Roanoke Island, did you get it.<ptr target="duk.00315_n8"/>
            </p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
