<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00320">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 9 June 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00320</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">54-56</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 9 June 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-06-09">June 9, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-12-18">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-24">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Newbern N.C.</name>
                  <date when="1862-06-09">June 9th/62</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have just received your letter of June 4th and hope you will write me oftener, I sent you a letter containing five dollars 5 or 6 days ago which I supose you received   I also sent you thirty dollars by Adams Express. Please write if you received it all right. Everything here remains quiet,  I am perfectly well and get along first rate. The Captain of our company<ptr target="duk.00320_n1"/> has a Wife, staying at his Brothers in Burlington Vermont,  he has writen to her saying I had a Sister there, and asking her to call and see her,  he received a letter to night from his wife saying, that she had been there two or three times  once Han and Heyde were out  the next time she saw Heyde who said that he and Han would call and see her,  this was a Month or 6 weeks ago,  She says in her letter that Han has never called and I am quite certain that Heyde never told Han any thing about Mrs Fancis, calling, or she would have went to see her, as she could have heard from me every week. Mrs. Francis also says that she has heard from some of Hans friends that Heyde does not treat her very well but she wrote for him not to say any thing about that to me.</p>
            <p>Mother I wish you would write to Han asking her to come home and if she wants money to come home with   I will send it to her  I want her to come very much  if I could get away I would go myself to Burlington on purpose to give that little Cuss Heyde a good square kicking.</p>
            <p>Mother dont fail to write to Han immediately and try and get her to come home and stay. If you think it would be better for Walt to go on there and see how things are I will send him some money if he will go, and then he can bring Han back if things are as we susspect.</p>
            <p>Mother you dont say any thing about your cold in the letter I got to night so I hope you are entirely over it. So Bunkum has gone Sogering too has he,<ptr target="duk.00320_n2"/> well they will have good times in Baltimore for it seems to me this war is about played out,  I have been rather doubtful about Corinth<ptr target="duk.00320_n3"/> but it seems Halleck has cleared them out of there, and if Mac,<ptr target="duk.00320_n4"/> does the clean thing at Richmond I dont see what hope will be left them</p>
            <p>I told you in my last letter of the splendid present the boys of our company made me  I am very proud of it I tell you  We have had a couple of as pretty flags as I ever saw presented to the Regt  one by the Ladies of New York and one by the City.  The New York Comon Concill when they appropriated the money for the flag they gave us said something about our exchanging (the flag that we have carried ever since we left New York) for the new one,  the Colonel one day when the Regt was out on drill, stated the case to the Boys and asked if they would exchange,  the boys let up such a yell as convinced the Colonel that the City would have a good time getting that old Flag. It has 15 or 20 bullet holes in it and the staff was shot into at Newbern, and we think a great deal of it.</p>
            <p>Well Mother I beleive that is all all I have got to say. So good night and Much Love to all</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Lieut G. W. Whitman Co D <lb/>51st Regt N.Y.V.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
