<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00375">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Reuben Farwell to Walt Whitman, 7 November 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Reuben Farwell</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00375</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">139</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Reuben Farwell</author>
               <title>Reuben Farwell to Walt Whitman, 7 November 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-11-07">November 7, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Farwell, Reuben">Reuben Farwell</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-13">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-09-03">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-10">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Dear Uncle</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="duk.00375_n100"/> received you letter of Oct 7th &amp; here I am about to write you a reply.</p>
            <p>Times here have been rather busy Together with the Mass meetings &amp; a Bridial Tour that lasted a week. This was not any of my own luck but to accompany the newly married set was all  I was on the Company. I have received only this letter Oct 7th &amp; one writen to My Father of which both reached me the same mail. One came to me from the Regiment that one I answered &amp; a reply came to me. I intend to Answer all of your Kind letters. But this one I have neglected on account of my being a way from home so long. My letter to you at the time I was Poisoned has has not affected me any that time I looked the whole City of Washington over to find you&#8212;but I looked in vain</p>
            <p>My foot is quite well so much so that one can not tell of my being hit there. Shortly after I came to the city again to be Mounted on a Horse &amp; we layed in the Defences of Washington the time the Rebels came to attack the City. Then I went up the Shanandoah Valley untill the 24 day of August where I was Discharged. There was some very heavy fighting up there under Phil Sheridan<ptr target="duk.00375_n2"/> &amp; perhaps he has warmed the Johnnys since then. This Charles Davis I have not heard from since he left for home on a Furlough<ptr target="duk.00375_n3"/>. Wether he came back or not I can not tell</p>
            <p>Dear Uncle you gave me one of your Photographs &amp; I shall always carry it with me in Remembrance of a Kind Friend &amp; one who I have thought a good deal off.</p>
            <p>I hope that you will over look this neglect of mine in not writing you before this. This is rather bad writing any how &amp; I am a fraid you will bother yourself in reading what I have scribbled. My health is very good at present  Also the same I wish to you My best wishes gose with this to you</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Yours very Respectfully</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
