<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00384">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 18 May 1860</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00384</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
                  <editor>Clarence Gohdes</editor>
                  <editor>Rollo G. Silver</editor>
                  <title xml:id="fci">Faint Clews &amp; Indirections: Manuscripts of Walt Whitman and His Family</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1949</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">215-16</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
               <title>Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 18 May 1860</title>
               <date when="1860-05-18">May 18, 1860</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Heyde, Charles L.">Charles L. Heyde</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-16">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener rend="right">
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Burlington</name>
                  <date when="1860-05-18">May 18. 1860</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt.</salute> 
            </opener>
         <p>Received your book, also a letter for Han.&#8212;Feel proud myself&#8212;the copy I<ptr target="duk.00384_n100"/> now have is just the thing to handle frequently&#8212;I like the portrait, it looks very much as you do at the present time. It has a little air of a foreign savan&#8212;however&#8212;but it is a good likeness.</p>  
            <p>I think that some of the poems open splendid&#8212;grandly&#8212;there is a fault or eccentricity however, in some, that is, they diverge too abruptly from a lofty theme or elevating imagery into common place&#8212;ordinary&#8212;and repulsive object, or subject matter&#8212;But they are poems of the thoroughfare of life passions and emotions of the universe and humanity&#8212;on all sides taken&#8212;as they approach and appear without selection&#8212;sympathies utterd and communion held with all in turn and none rejected&#8212;Poems of glorious, liberal, soul filld emotion. They will be read&#8212;they must have a place&#8212;But you'l write a perfect poem one of these days, filld with nature sublime&#8212;Your thoughts are true thoughts&#8212;Common sense is the best philosophy&#8212;Cant has too long ruled the world and judged the case of erring humanity&#8212;Your poems are sustaining&#8212;I hope that there will be a jolly good fight over them&#8212;The public are lazy&#8212;and need some disturbance to arouse them&#8212;</p>
            <p>Many thanks to you&#8212;We expected to have seen you here&#8212;Han is disappointed, but you have been detaind in Boston a long time&#8212;Our scenery here has conceald all its lofty and varied beauty and sublimity&#8212;No rain has fal'n for two months&#8212;The sun rises and sets as if it threatend to pierce the earth with its ball of fire&#8212;The atmesphere is dense and impenetrable&#8212;the mountains totaly obscured. We shall see you some time&#8212;I want Han to see her Mother&#8212;for a change. I shall come to New York for her myself&#8212;I want to visit it&#8212;I think that I shall have to return to that place or Boston or get nearer some city&#8212;Give us more poems Walt&#8212;I hope there'l be a genearl big row&#8212;in the papers&#8212;Stir em up well&#8212;I look for it.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Charlie</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>I want a handsome bound volume for a keepsake&#8212;mind that now</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
