<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00381">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 26 June 1866</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00381</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">278-279</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 26 June 1866</title>
               <date when="1866-06-26">June 26, 1866</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-24">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>,</name>
                  <date when="1866-06-26">June 26, <hi rend="italic">1866.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Well, I suppose you have the hot weather too&#8212;it has been very hot here for the last four or five days, but I have got along very well&#8212;I think of you every day, with the work &amp; the heat, &amp;c.&#8212;I believe you said that it was good air around there in Pacific st., well I should think that was one great advantage over Portland av. any how. Mother, I rec'd your letter of last week&#8212;I do not go much to the hospital this hot weather&#8212;I think I feel better than usual now for a couple of weeks past&#8212;if I can only get through the summer as well as I am, I shall be satisfied&#8212;Mrs. Grayson gives me plenty of good vegetables, peas, string beans, squash &amp; new potatoes, with fruit now &amp; then, which is better than too much meat&#8212;Old Mrs. Mix<ptr target="duk.00381_n1"/> is well as usual&#8212;the house is very pleasant this weather&#8212;as cool as it can be any where&#8212;</p>
            <p>I should like to hear from Han,<ptr target="duk.00381_n2"/> but I suppose she is getting along in the same old way&#8212;As I am writing this letter at my table, the celebrated Mrs. Cobb<ptr target="duk.00381_n3"/> has just come in, to see about some rebel pardon, some profitable job for her, I suppose&#8212;she is a great piece&#8212;she is what most people would call a very pretty little woman&#8212;dresses gay, &amp;c&#8212;but she has too brazen &amp; silly a way, ever to be taken for a lady by any one that knows&#8212;she has got lots of pardons, &amp; probably made a fortune&#8212;is half the time at the President's&#8212;is not a good character. This Washington is a great place&#8212;you see how funny the world is governed&#8212;&amp; lots of queer doings that outsiders never dream of&#8212;</p>
            <p>Well, mother, my new shirts are done, half a dozen, very satisfactory&#8212;I havn't bought any new clothes this summer except a new hat, a big brim, light drab&#8212;makes me look like a southern planter, but is very light &amp; comfortable&#8212;Mother, I wish you could sit here by the window I have so often mentioned, &amp; have the cool breeze blow on you, as it is now, &amp; the trees &amp; river &amp; hills beyond, so pleasant&#8212;</p>
            <p>Dear mother, you must try to take things moderate&#8212;because folks that worry &amp; overdo are apt to get the cholera, you know&#8212;I hope brother Jeff feels all right again<ptr target="duk.00381_n4"/>&#8212;how I should like to see him, &amp; all of you.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
