<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05112">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 4 June
                    [1881]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05112</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 4 June [1881]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1881-06-04" xml:id="dat1">June 4, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-09-29">checked, corrected</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-07" who="#ss">images added, note added</change>
            <change when="2014-06-26" who="#nhg">updated sender name</change>
            <change when="2014-02-06" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-22" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-15" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.00999_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1881-06-04">Sunday <choice>
                            <abbr>evg.</abbr>
                            <expan>evening</expan>
                        </choice> June 4.</date>
                    <name type="place">Wettiner Hof.</name>
                    <name type="place">Bad-Elster</name>
                    <name type="place">Saxony</name>
                </dateline>
            </opener>

            <p>At last I find myself able to write to you, having got myself moored in a quiet nook
                after much hurried journeying. When I received your letter with the poems, I was
                staying with a married sister<ptr target="loc.05112_n1"/> in the county Wicklow.
                Then my father got very ill &amp; I had to go down &amp; see him (he is all right now.)
                Then business in London, tedious travelling half across Europe, &amp; now my wife and
                I are fixed in a little German valley for the summer. There are mineral springs and
                baths here; she was ordered <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01000_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> to come for her health, which has not been very good
                lately&#8212;but there is every likelihood of its mending now. This is a very
                pleasant place&#8212;a long, rather narrow valley with low hills, covered with
                pinewood, at each side&#8212;at one end of it stands the village of Elster, bowered
                in dense foliage, oak and chestnut; with highroofed houses, a few large hotels, a
                rather grand looking building,&#8212;the Bath House&#8212;surrounding the mineral
                springs. When you climb to the top of a hill you see leagues on leagues of grass
                country, no mountains, but low undulations with quaintly built villages set in their
                folds, and covered often with dark tracts of pine forest. <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc_af.01001_large.jpg" type="recto"/> There are few visitors here, for
                this is not one of the fashionable watering places; our countrymen &amp; women have
                not found it out and vulgarized it yet. These Germans I admire more and
                more&#8212;if they keep their present characteristics, what a nation they will be
                sometime! Their life is simple, friendly, humane, unembarrassed; the poor have
                leisure and use it well, the rich do not strive, (as periodically in England) to "do
                their duty to the lower classes" by subscribing to benevolent schemes &#38;
                inventing elaborate machinery for the reclamation of criminals,&#8212;they meet
                their labourers, servants, &amp;c in a perfectly natural manner, as man with man and
                other bonds are established than
                those which unite the payer and the payee. As a nation, high and low, they have
                intelligence, and what is more, spirituality&#8212;life is not measured by its
                value in &#163;.s.d.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_af.01002_large.jpg" type="verso"/><p>There is much
                democracy among them, socially speaking&#8212;politically, none whatever. They
                endure a really oppressive despotism&#8212;<hi rend="underline">how</hi> oppressive
                foreigners, even aristocratic Germans, can little know&#8212;without complaint, or
                resent it only in a petty, spiteful way. And they have an innate dread and respect
                for an <hi rend="underline">official</hi>&#8212;anyone in a uniform&#8212;they
                surround him with something of the divinity that used to hedge kings when
                Shakespeare wrote. They are a people whom I love to mix with. I mean the common
                folk, the others I rarely meet with, for I scarcely see anyone, being buried a good
                deal in Greek and metaphysics, except when I take long walks in the country, which I
                do pretty often; sometimes with a <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc_af.01003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> knapsack for a fortnight, wandering
                without definite aim, finding friends, 'eating and sleeping with the earth.'</p>

            <p>In Dublin I came across a man I had heard much of but never seen before, one Standish
                O'Grady, a barrister who drifted into authorship, has written part of a History of
                Ireland, collecting, translating, piecing together, Homeric fashion, old bardic lays
                preserved from pagan times, of Irish heroes and gods. He is going to bring the
                history down to the present day.<ptr target="loc.05112_n2"/> I met him at Dowden's
                    first, often afterwards, &#38; we
                arranged for a walk on the Wicklow mountains, Dowden, O'Grady, two others &amp;
                myself. When the day came only O'Grady and I appeared at the rendezvous, &#38; we
                had a splendid day of it. I never met anyone, I think, whose mind answered so well
                to mine. We had been travelling on parallel roads of thought for some time&#8212;now
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_af.01004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> we travelled
                together. Each had help to give and each needed
                help; above all we helped each other to <hi rend="underline">realize</hi>. I love
                many persons, but him with that nearest, most contented love&#8212;him and one
                other. That other is now a schoolmaster in South Africa.<ptr target="loc.05112_n3"/>
                O'Grady in Ireland, I in Saxonland&#8212;if we three were together we would tread
                the clouds! I send you some stanzas about my day's walk with O'Grady (I found out
                shortly that he was a lover and disciple of yours, and we talked much of you).</p>

            <p>Thank you very much for the two poems.<ptr target="loc.05112_n4"/> I have put them in
                the Passage to India. It was very kind of you to try to get 'Calvin Harlowe'
                published, but I fear it is too rough. I could mend it a good deal. It was written
                quickly, the subject filled me and I hammered out the verses &#38; left them without
                a touch of the file. So too with those I send you&#8212;but I don't think I ever
                shall arrive at successful filing.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute rend="right">Yours sincerely</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>This address will find me till October&#8212;that of 'Glasshouse, Shinrone, Ireland,' always. I hope you are well.</p>
                <p>I think much might be well done in altering the arrangement of your poems &amp; prose, but I like the <hi rend="underline">two</hi> vols. <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="low">&amp;</unclear> mainly, as they are.</p>
            </postscript></div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_af.01005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
                <div1 type="enclosure">
                
                    <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date when="1881-03-24">March 24th 1881.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                    <lg type="poem"><lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>1. These to embalm a day to keep fresh its memory forever.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>2. Out of the eddying town, out of the bustle and gloom,</l>
                        <l>Relaxing the hardset grasp, dismissing knowledge and gain,</l>
                        <l>Tossing the world to the winds, wooers of sun and mountain-air,</l>
                        <l>Forth we went&#8212;thou, bard of Oscar and of the friend of outcasts,
                            the divine Cuculain,</l>
                        <l>Thou, nourisher of this land with the stalwart life, the blood of her
                            heroes dead,</l>
                        <l>I, dreamer of dreams, dilletante poet and scholar.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>3. Keen and clear, a flood of light, the March-wind blows upon the
                            Wicklow hills;</l>
                        <l>Blows from over the blue Channel, making the white waves leap at the
                            sand bank,</l>
                        <l>Sings aloft by the granite crags, the tossing heather, the miles of
                            moor.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>4. On thee we soared upborne, on paths the eagles never knew.</l>
                        <l>Far and wide the horizon fled before our gaze.</l>
                        <l>Clearly, one instant, the Real World sprang into view, and vanished like
                            a dream again&#8212;</l>

                        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_af.01006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_af.01007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

                        <l>And again the same hills and rocks, again the Sky, again the blue Channel
                            with white waves leaping;</l>
                        <l>But now, O Sea and Sky and impassive Earth, your secret is told, you can
                            mock us no longer;</l>
                        <l>Silent and mystic Nature! for once you have unmask'd to us.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>5. &#8212;And ever as we went, there hover'd near us another spirit,
                            sometimes unseen, oftener between us, holding a hand of each,</l>
                        <l>For the power of the mountains was on us that day, and the power of the
                            Sea, and of Walt Whitman, poet of comrades.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>6. Farewell, bright Day, our way through thee is ended.</l>
                        <l>Other suns shall shine for us and other skies be fair,</l>
                        <l>But thy sun and thy sky our eyes shall see no more.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>7. Yet do we not hold thee in our souls, and shall we not eternally?</l>
                        <l>All that thou gavest us, assuredly we shall keep for ever,</l>
                        <l>Day, that poured on us the power of the mountains, and the power of the
                            Sea, and of Walt Whitman, poet of comrades.</l>
                    </lg></lg>
                
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_af.01008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_af.00997_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_af.00998_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
