<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00578">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thayer &amp; Eldridge to Walt Whitman, 17 August 1860</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thayer &amp; Eldridge</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
               <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
               <orgName xml:id="wwa">Walt Whitman Archive Staff</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00578</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thayer &amp; Eldridge</author>
               <title>Thayer &amp; Eldridge to Walt Whitman, 17 August 1860</title>
               <date when="1860-08-17">August 17, 1860</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Thayer and Eldridge">Thayer and Eldridge</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-09-23">added encoding for page breaks</change>
         <change who="#jw" when="2009-09-08">Transcription revision</change>
         <change who="#bbb" when="2009-08-21">proofread</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-07-27">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-07">Encoded</change>
         <change who="#wwa" when="2006">Transcribed</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00578.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> 
                  <name type="place">Boston</name> 
                  <date when="1860-08-17">August 17, 1860</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>You will accept our<ptr target="loc.00578_n100"/> 
            <hi rend="italic">hearty</hi> thanks for your kindly advice about the S.P. &#8212; You can rely upon our keeping it secret&#8212;<ptr target="loc.00578_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps Mr. Clapp told you of our offer to take it September 1st. We rec'd a letter today from him stating he intended to visit us Monday or Tuesday to make sure arrangement with us &#8212;if possible.</p>
            <p>Now as you have been so kind as to give us a valuable hint, will you please write us per return mail stating what you know of the affairs of the S.P.&#8212;that is if it can be done without trenching upon your friendly relations with Mr. Clapp? Is the paper in debt, if so to whom; are there any liabilities incurred, which would make it subject to attachment if sold to an owned by parties not formerly connected with it.&#8212; what are Mr. Howlands' claims, <pb facs="loc.00578.002.jpg" type="verso"/>and of what nature<ptr target="loc.00578_n3"/>.  Does he help edit the paper? These questions we asked with a view to our being the sole owners of the Press with Mr. Clapp for editor.</p>
            <p>The tone of his letter indicates a determination to make a trade with us of <hi rend="italic">some</hi> kind, and therefore we wish to have any statement of his affairs he may make corroborated by others. If you have no objections to answering our queries we would esteem it a favor to hear from you by <hi rend="italic">return mail</hi>.</p>
            <p>Your suggestion as to our discerning the ownership and responsibilities of the paper we regard as the only practical thing that can be done, toward relieving Mr. C. from his difficulties. Of course we should not want it unless he was its <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi> and we could be its <hi rend="italic">business</hi> managers.  <hi rend="italic">We</hi> can make it <hi rend="italic">pay</hi> (we think) in a very short time. Besides we are deeply interested in sustaining any journal that dares <pb facs="loc.00578.003.jpg" type="recto"/>in these days of literary flunkeyism to be independent, and make the literature of a country what it should be.</p>
            <p>Now if Mr. C. can obtain a business party to do the <hi rend="italic">business</hi> of the paper (T&amp;E or some other), what a flourishing paper could be got up. But T&amp;E do not want to be subjected to any liabilities connected with the past of the S.P. and therefore proceed with caution before operating.</p>
            <p>We wrote to Mr. C. some days ago making an offer, but now we shall act having in view your suggestion.</p>
            <p>About the L of G ~ Our Mr. E. is in the country to return tonight or tomorrow. He will write you at length about the Cheap Edition as he has it in charge <ptr target="loc.00578_n4"/>~ Will Mr. Clapp use <pb facs="loc.00578.004.jpg" type="recto"/>the notice of L of G in the Cincinnati Daily Press<ptr target="loc.00578_n5"/>? If not please re-mail it to us when you have done with it. We have heard of the "Dial" notice, but could not get a copy here. We have written to the Editor for a copy<ptr target="loc.00578_n6"/>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">We</hi> too wish you could be with us in Boston for we have <hi rend="italic">so</hi> much to say; and our "fanatic" wants to get under the refreshing shelter of Walt's spirit; he does not ask Walt to talk, but only for the privilege of looking into those eyes of calm; and through them to Enter into that Soul, so deep in its Emotions, so majestic in all its thoughts&#8212;movements, and yet so simple and childlike<ptr target="loc.00578_n7"/>. Yes, Walt Whitman; though men of the world and arch-critics do not <hi rend="italic">understand</hi> thee, yet some there be among men and women who <hi rend="italic">love</hi> thee and hold thy spirit close by their own.</p>
            <p>"Among the men and women, the multitude, I perceive are picking me out by secret and divine signs&#8212; * * * * some are baffled&#8212;But that one is not&#8212;that one knows me."<ptr target="loc.00578_n8"/>
            </p>
            <p>And to Dear Walt, would we <pb facs="loc.00578.005.jpg" type="recto"/>love to seek you and learn to know you. And have we not known you?&#8212;</p>
            <p>We will try the Smithsonian House when we are obliged to represent the "Hub" in Gotham. Either Mr E or T will be in New York soon on business and will then see you, unless that you first come to Boston. Frank regretted his missing you. Perhaps the miss in this case <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a mile.</p>
            <p>We do not care one single damn for the Miss Nancys of Bookdom but shall continue to publish and <hi rend="italic">sell</hi> Leaves of Grass "so long" as Walt will have us.</p>
            
         <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Goodbye for a day or two from your genuine</salute>
               <signed>Thayer &amp; Eldridge</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <pb facs="loc.00578.006.jpg" type="recto"/>
        
         <postscript>
            <p>Dear Walt,  I wrote you in the name of T&amp;E a longer letter than I intended. Somehow I could not stop. I felt such a wondrous geniality, that I Enjoyed looking at your handwriting and imagined you were before me instead of the letter.</p>
            <p>My dear little wife wants to write you a letter, and will when the domestic gods are propitious, so that she can talk with the great Poet as she would like. She has had much ill health, but is now much better.</p>
            <p>I wish you could visit our home. The country is delightful. You would laugh and grow fat to see our blessed Jamaica Plain and enjoy its beauties. ~ Come and see us if you can.</p>
            <p>There now, some business comes in that I must attend to so I close</p>
            <closer><signed>W.W.T.</signed></closer>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
