<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03044">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 3 June
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03044</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 3 June 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-06-03" xml:id="dat1">June 3, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-14" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-04-28" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-19" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-06" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-15" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03044.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top">see notes Apr 20 1888</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1882-06-03" rend="right">June 3, 1882.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your two letters, full of memoranda, of May 28 and 30 came duly. I have "toiled
                terribly," as Cecil said of Raleigh,<!--<ptr target="loc.03044_n1"/>--> and sent off another letter to the Tribune,
                which I think will make Mr. Chadwick<!--<ptr target="00443_n2"/>--> wear a toupee, <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.03044.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> for I have snatched him
                bald-headed. It has cost me great labor, though you may not think so when you read
                it, it runs off so savagely easy; but the difficulty in a controversy of this kind
                is to mould everything so as not to lay yourself open, and to give no points to the
                enemy, and this costs <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03044.003_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> time and care. My old fencing-master, Boulet, (no better ever
                lived; he taught once at West Point,) taught me always to cover my breast with hilt
                and point, even in the lunge, and I think of his lessons when engaged in fence of
                another kind. I hope I have succeeded in being both guarded and bold <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03044.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> in this new
                encounter with Chadwick.</p>
            <p>I have freely used the memoranda you sent, and got in as much of it as I could see my
                way to employ, and as much as I dared. I think you will feel satisfied with the use
                I have made of it. Some things I thought it prudent to withhold, because <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03044.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                they might provoke replication when we are not
                in a position to defend ourselves, not being ever sure that a single organ is open
                to us.</p>
            <p>You must be very careful in this matter. Even <hi rend="underline">words</hi> must be
                carefully chosen, for the enemy is unscrupulous <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.03044.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>and uses every advantage we give
                him. I came near getting into a pretty scrape by trusting to your memorandum about
                the appearance of Emerson's letter in Cooke's memoir<!--<ptr target="loc.03044_n2"/>--> published by Osgood<!--<ptr target="hun.00047_n1"/>-->. It was a
                splendid point to make, that the letter appeared <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="loc.03044.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> verbatim in a book issued with
                Emerson's own sanction a year ago, and I worked it in and made the most of it. But
                at the last, I thought it would be prudent to see the book, and there was the letter
                sure enough, but with a lot of remarks by the editor to the effect that "it is
                understood" (the usual <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03044.008_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>sneaking lie in putting it) that Emerson had considerably
                modified his feeling, and regretted, etc., etc. Fortunately, there is not a word in
                the preface to show that the book had Emerson's sanction,&#8212;but just see the
                scrape I would have been in had I used the information in the shape you sent it!!
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03044.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                Indeed, Walt, you ought to be more careful, "A
                wild and many-weaponed throng, hang on our front and flank and rear." If I had said
                that the letter was reprinted in a book with Emerson's sanction, Chadwick would have
                had me. Our stronghold is the Emerson letter, <hi rend="underline">unretracted by
                    himself.</hi>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03044.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>Next thing we
                shall have to meet, will be the stories of what Emerson <hi rend="underline"
                    >said</hi> to this man or that man. We must deny them all, and call for proof.
                Let us admit nothing. Make the other side <hi rend="underline">prove</hi> their
                allegations.</p>
            <p>I hope my new letter will be as successful with you and the public <pb
                    xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03044.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/> as my first. My
                aim has been to shut Chadwick up for good, for I don't want to be bothered on a side
                issue by this egotistic jackass.</p>
            <p>Letters are pouring in upon me. One from John Hay,<!--<ptr target="n3080"/>--> very cordial. One from the
                Melancholy Club of New York,<!--<ptr target="loc.04616_n1"/>--> very overflowing, inviting me to a grand supper to be
                given on Saturday (this) evening <pb xml:id="leaf006v"
                    facs="loc.03044.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/> in honor of <hi rend="underline"
                    >you</hi> and of my letter! Have you been invited? And who are the Melancholy
                Club men, of Lexington Avenue? I returned them a civil letter of regret at my
                inability to be present, etc., and consoled them by offering as a toast "old
                Selden's trumpet-sentence&#8212;'Before all things, liberty!"&#8212;"words," I said
                "which are good <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03044.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                to remember when thought is menaced by law." I
                have had a number of other letters from persons unknown. One from Bucke,<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>--> quite
                jubilant over my letter, and telling me the fix I have got his book into, which is
                comic as a scene from Moliere. You will see the fun when you know <pb
                    xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03044.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/> that he had sent
                his <hi rend="underline">MS</hi>. to Osgood!! I also got a letter from John
                Burroughs,<!--<ptr target="n0129"/>--> announcing his arrival, and I at once sent him a <hi rend="underline"
                    >Tribune</hi> containing the letter. I also have a letter from Dr. Channing<!--<ptr target="loc.03044_n3"/>--> at
                Providence, red-hot for you, and proposing to reprint my "Good Gray Poet" at his
                expense!!<!--<ptr target="loc.03044_n10"/>--></p>
            <p>There has been quite a swarming of people after me. The press notices are generally
                favorable and hearty. <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.03044.015_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>I hope nothing adverse or disastrous will happen. I want the
                matter to result in your getting a publisher, as it ought.</p>
            <p>Watch the <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> for my anti-Chadwick. I hardly think it
                will fail to bring him down. At the last moment, after two days of anxious
                cogitation, I cut out of it several pages of really <pb xml:id="leaf008v"
                    facs="loc.03044.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>withering ridicule, excellent in
                itself, but possibly injurious to the main effect. You see how solely I consider
                the interests of your cause&#8212;sacrificing thereto my choicest satirical
                felicities!</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye</salute>
                <salute>Yours faithfully</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman, Esq.</salute>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
