<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05120">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 11 July
                    [1881]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05120</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 11 July [1881]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1881-07-11" xml:id="dat1">July 11, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-09-29" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-11" who="#ss">images and annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-06-26" who="#nhg">updated sender name</change>
            <change when="2014-02-07" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-23" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-07-11" who="#kc">Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_af.01059_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note resp="#ww">A valued Irish friend, a frequent traveler and resident
                on the European Continent&#8212;here is an extract from one of his late letters to
                me:<ptr target="loc.05120_n20"/></note> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_af.01060_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01061_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">bei Herrn Mauermeister M&#252;ller</name>
                    <name type="place">168 Sidonian <choice>
                            <orig>Strass</orig>
                            <reg>Strasse</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                    <name type="place">Tharandt</name>
                    <name type="place">Dresden&#8212;</name>
                    <date when="1881-07-11">July 11th</date>
                </dateline>
                <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww"><hi rend="underline">Dresden</hi>,
                    Saxony</note>
            </opener>

            <p><note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="left">&#182;"</note> There has been much
                more interest here,<ptr target="n1027"/> more sympathy and more indignation felt
                about the Presidents attempted murder,<ptr target="loc.05120_n1"/> than if he was a European sovereign. From
                all sides, I think, the world looks to America; we love our own lands as much as
                you, but we feel that the future of the race is being decided there. Political
                corruption and public dishonesty are instinctively felt to be far more significant,
                occurring in America than in Germany or England, and we have been hearing so much
                about them lately that everyone's mind <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_af.01062_large.jpg" type="verso"/>has been bent in expectation towards
                each new President, each striking turn of events in the U.S.; thinking that the time
                has come at last when something will be done to justify our hopes. We have thought
                we saw it being done since&#8212;Garfield's election&#8212;Hercules letting in the
                cleansing flood. Now, rightly or wrongly, this impression has been immensely
                strengthened. When we heard the President was dead it was as if we heard of a
                martyrdom. Now that the reports are more and more favourable everyday, it seems to
                us as if the good cause had assuredly triumphed in the first wrestle. I don't know
                how far these impressions of the state of things are true; but they have
                verisimilitude. I liked so much all I could hear of President Garfield. <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.01063_large.jpg" type="recto"/>Is it not
                wonderful and inscrutable that out of the confusion and slander and insidious
                intrigue that seems to attend every Presidential election a man like that should
                have emerged? Things look to me every way
                    as if the people were awaking.</p>

            <p>I see your friend R. M. Bucke has brought out a
                    book on 'Man's Moral Nature'&#8212;I must get it. I saw it noticed &amp; praised
                    in the 'Spectator' a few days ago&#8212;the critic said that "Mr. Bucke appeared
                    to be an ardent admirer of Walt Whitman&#8212;hence, perhaps, some of the
                    obscurities in the volume&#8212;which, we candidly confess, are beyond us."<ptr
                        target="loc.05120_n2"/> The Spectator is an excellent (weekly)
                    paper&#8212;thoughtful, honest, manly; Radical in politics, but in religion
                    belonging to <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_af.01064_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    that rather vapid sect, the Neo-Christian or Broad Church. Barring this latter
                    particular there is a very great deal in the 'Spectator' which might be written
                    out of you; and I have no doubt that if you had thrown your works into the form
                    of systematic treatises and written in a strictly refined cultured and
                    gentlemanlike way, you might have gained the approbation of the Spectator,
                    possibly even of the Saturday Review, to which latter journal you are still a
                    thorn in the flesh, of the first magnitude.<ptr target="loc.05120_n3"
                /></p> 

            <p>We have left Bad-Elster, the baths having perfectly
                    restored my wife's health to our great joy. And we are now pretty close to
                    Dresden, about half an hour by train, living in two rooms in the <gap
                        reason="cut away"/></p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
