<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05534">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, March
                    1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05534</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, March 1884</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1884-03" xml:id="dat1">March 1884</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H." ref="n1027">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt" xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-02-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected, added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-10" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded, annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01049_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <head type="main-authorial">Translation of Cleanthes' Hymn to Zeus (about 260 B.C.)<ptr
                    target="loc.05534_n1"/></head>
                
                <lg type="poem">
                    
                    <l>Most glorious of the immortals! many-named! all-powerful forever,</l>
                    <l>Zeus! ruler of nature, steering all things according to law,</l>
                    <l>Hail!&#8212;for it is the right and duty of all mortals to address
                        thee,</l>
                    <l>For we are the offspring out of thee, taking the one image of thy word,
                        as many mortal creatures as live and creep upon the earth.</l>
                    <l>Wherefore I will hymn thee and sing thy power forever;</l>
                    <l>For thee this whole universe that whirls about the earth obeys, wherever thou
                        dost lead it, and is willingly ruled by thee.</l>
                    <l>Such a servant hast thou&#8212;the two-edged, fire-breathing, ever-living
                        thunderbolt in thy invincible hands,</l>
                    <l>Under whose stroke all Nature shudders, and through which thou orderest
                        (keepest straight&#8212;in the right path) the universal Reason (<choice><sic>&#955;&#8057;&#947;&#959;s</sic><corr>&#955;&#8057;&#947;&#959;&#957;</corr></choice>) which moves through all things, and mixes itself with the
                        greater and with the lesser lights&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Nor does anything take place upon the earth without thee, O Spirit, nor in
                        the divine ethereal sky, nor in the sea,</l>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001ar" facs="loc_af.01050_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <l>Save only such things as the base &#38; wicked do in their folly&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Yet thou knowest how to make superfluous things fit where they should go, and
                        thou orderest what is without order (lit. makest cosmic what is uncosmic),
                        and things that are not dear are dear to thee.</l>
                    <l>For thus thou dost harmonize into one good things with evil; so that there
                        should be one Eternal Reason, common to all,</l>
                    <l>And this such of mortals as are evil fly from and neglect&#8212;miserables,
                        desiring ever posession of goods &#38; chattels,</l>
                    <l>Nor do they behold the universal law of God, nor hear it, which if they would
                        obey, they should have a fair and good life;</l>
                    <l>But they rush headlong, forgetful of the beautiful, some after one thing,
                        some another,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Some having an unholy thirst for fame, some turned to gain with a base
                        unrestrained lust,</l>
                    <l>Some to vice and the sweet works of the body;</l>
                    <l>&#8212;Hastening, verily, altogether, to become the contrary of these
                        things.</l>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01051_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

                    <l>But O Zeus! All-giver! Veiled in dark cloud! Lord of thunder!</l>
                    <l>Do thou save men from their miserable foolishness (lit. orig. want of
                        experience)</l>
                    <l>Which do thou, Father, scatter from their souls; and give them to find the
                        wisdom by which thou securely steerest all things, according to justice,</l>
                    <l>So that, being made honourable, they may repay thee with honour,</l>
                    <l>Hymning thy works perpetually, as is seemly for a mortal: for verily there is
                        no greater glory for mortal men or for the gods than this&#8212;to hymn
                        forever in a just heart the universal Law.</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>
            

            <div1 type="letter">

                <p>I thought you might care to see a full translation of this fine piece of ancient
                    Greek religious poetry, especially as it doesn't lie much
                    in the beaten way of readers of the classics, wherefore it may be new to you. I
                    don't think it has <hi rend="underline">ever</hi> been translated in print. I
                    have received the paper with the description of the Indian deputation, &#38;
                    also the proofs of your 'Critic' essay on Leaves <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                        facs="loc_af.01052_large.jpg" type="verso"/>of Grass, which interested me
                        <hi rend="underline">profoundly</hi>&#8212;there are materials for a big
                    volume in it.<ptr target="loc.05534_n2"/> I got too the paper with translation
                    from my essay, for which I owe the editor &#38; translator deep thanks.<ptr
                        target="loc.05534_n3"/> The translation is very good, though free&#8212;but
                    one mistake I should like to correct. I didn't say that the "beauty in L. of G.
                    worked all the deeper," &amp;c. "<hi rend="underline">because it never seemed
                        intended for any aim or purpose</hi>"&#8212;but "<hi rend="underline">because
                        it (i.e. beauty) was never made an end &#38; object in itself</hi>."<ptr
                        target="loc.05534_n4"/></p>

                <p>I have received a long &#38; interesting letter from Dr. Bucke<ptr target="n0119"
                    /> about my lecture. He is a man I should greatly like to know
                    personally&#8212;which perhaps may come about as he talks of visiting Dresden.
                    The translation of L. of G. is progressing well, though the necessity of taking
                    pupils which I am under now costs a good deal of my time.</p>

                <p>I hope all is going well with you and yours. I was very sorry to hear of the
                    death of Wendell <choice>
                        <sic>Philips</sic><corr>Phillips</corr></choice>, a good friend of Ireland.<ptr target="loc.05534_n5"/></p>

                <p>Dynamite attempts making a great stir in England now<ptr target="loc.05534_n6"/>&#8212;utterly barbarous &amp;
                    unjustifiable&#8212;but if people will sow the wind&#8212;!</p>

                <closer>
                    <salute>Yours always</salute>
                    <signed rend="right">William Rolleston.</signed>
                </closer> 

            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_af.01045_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_af.01046_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="left">early in March '84 | Cleanthes' Hymn to
                Zeus</note> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
