<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00669"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Hannah Whitman Heyde to Walt Whitman, 20 October 1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Hannah Heyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.00669</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>2019 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884200</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4200</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
                    <title>Hannah Whitman Heyde to Walt Whitman, 20 October 1884</title>
                    <date cert="low" when="1884-10-20" xml:id="dat1">October 20, 1884</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Hannah Louisa Whitman Heyde Papers, 1853&#8211;1892, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Hannah Whitman" ref="n0285">Hannah Whitman Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-04-07" who="#nhg">corrected orgName</change>
            <change when="2015-01-12" who="#kb">edited</change> 
            <change when="2014-11-26" who="#ss">encoded and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-11" who="#aa">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.00669.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Burlington </name>
                    <date when="1884-10-20">Monday Afternoon</date>
                    <date when="1884-10-20">Oct.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dearest Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>How very good you are to send me so much,&#8212;It was a great surprise, I <choice>
                    <orig>dont</orig>
                    <reg>don't</reg>
                </choice> know what to say. I <choice>
                    <orig>wont</orig>
                    <reg>won't</reg>
                </choice> try to say how grateful how much I feel your kindness</p>
            <p>What I fear is, you will have to deprive yourself of some needed comfort, and that
                worries me. Your kindness does me good, but Walt dear your health and your not
                having to feel anxious about your own needs would do me more good, your welfare and
                needs and <hi rend="underline">you</hi> I think of, more than ever since I <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.00669.002.jpg" type="verso"/>have been sick. I am
                not much sick now, feel pretty well most days. I gain but not as fast as I expected the worst
                is I cannot walk about much yet. am slow and very careful. have to be to become
                quite well. I sew &#38; do a little sitting still &#38; of course nothing like when I am
                well. I do not think it will be long before I shall be able to work again, as usual
                so you see Walt dear you need not feel in the least anxious I meant to have written,
                but supposed you thought me well, (I did not know 
                    Charlie had written until your letter came) I
                was waiting to say I was well. I mean to write dear brother before long and tell you
                everything</p> 
            <p>You are very good to me to <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.00669.003.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>say you will come to see me It would be a great pleasure and
                comfort to see you. <hi rend="underline">it</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">is</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">a</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">great</hi> comfort to know you feel so much interest in me, but
                Walt dear I shall mind fearfully your spending more money on my account, let alone
                the risk to your health. that I think of most</p> 
            <p>To do me the most good is to take care
                of yourself. I should feel badly too, your not staying here, you have done much for me, it would
                be hard to not be able to do the least thing to make it pleasant for you to have you
                come when I get well, <hi rend="underline">that</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">would</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">be</hi> something to look forward to.&#8212;I have always
                thought if I was <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.00669.004.jpg" type="verso"
                />dangerously sick, my greatest wish would be to see you.</p>
            <p>Walt dear about the money you have sent me I feel a little uneasy about your sparing
                so much. I felt bad
                yesterday. I feel afraid Charlie has been writing one of his conplaining letters. (I
                may be mistaken) I have asked him what he wrote, he gets angry, says its all right,
                must leave it to him, but Walt you must <hi rend="underline">never</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">never</hi> again send me money unless you have much more than
                you can use for your own needs. I have some money yet that you sent me that I had
                saved if needed I have used since I have been sick. I am grateful to Charlie for all
                he has done for me since I have been sick, but I wish he was different that he would
                tell me when he writes to you, I knew he wrote to you yesterday,&#8212;not what he wrote.
                he has gone out to take a long walk this afternoon. I am alone, my being sick has
                been bad for him I know</p>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww">'84</note>
         </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
