<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03315">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 26 November 1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription &#38; encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>   
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications &#38; Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03315</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom &#38; Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors
                        &#38; advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in
                        the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
                        only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 26 November 1886</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1886-11-26" xml:id="dat1">November 26, 1886</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName>
            </handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-04" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added note</change>
            <change when="2015-06-30" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-16" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-10-14" who="#ss">checked &#38; corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-06" who="#ak">transcribed &#38; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03315.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">59 Cheyne Walk</name>
                    <name type="place">Chelsea,</name>
                    <name type="place"> London. S.W.<ptr target="loc.03315_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1886-11-25">26.th Novr. '86</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have been waiting all this time for the right mood and the right day to send a
                letter to you, but I must not wait any longer now, though there is a fog outside
                &#38; a fog or something of the sort in my head. Since coming back here from the
                country three weeks ago, there has been such a lot to do that I have got out of touch
                with the natural order &#38; spirit of things, &#38; these London fogs are enough
                    to<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03315.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> make the
                animal in one turn absolute coward. With sunlight or a flying wind or a good rain I
                am happy enough, but I cannot stand these smoke-soiled days. They make me feel
                stupid &#38; wicked.</p>
            
            <p>But I ought not to grumble like this, &#38; I won't any more. For I had a splendid
                ten weeks of autumn in Wales &#38; the West of England. In North Wales&#8212;at a
                place called Llwyngwril, a primitive little village, quite away from town-<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03315.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>ways &#38;
                fashions, I stayed for four weeks with my dear friend Herbert Horne at a farm-house
                close to the sea-shore. There we bathed &#38; mountaineered &#38; drank our fill of
                mountain wind &#38; sunshine, &#38; I rambled off once right round by Snowdon to
                Carnarvon, where the remnant of the Cymric races were holding their Eisteddfod.
                There is a wonderful old castle at Carnarvon, &#38; within its walls on a bright
                September morning it impressed me strangely (being half Cymric in blood myself) to
                see those old grey-bearded, venerable fellows, <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.03315.004_large.jpg" type="recto"/>in their mystic circle, uttering
                those wonderful Druidic prayers (which are purely theistic) &#38; eloquently
                orating in a way utterly unlike our English fashion; for the Welsh orators make
                their voices almost sing sometimes, &#38; their language is much more plastic &#38;
                various, like a more southern tongue. Their improvised
                harp-songs,&#8212;Penillion-singing, are very striking too,&#8212;quaint, wild
                tunes that would delight you, I am sure, so full as they are of natural music &#38;
                feeling. Unhappily I don't know enough of the language to understand all, but I heard
                &#38; saw enough to make me feel that there was a great deal of tremendous value
                for our Saxon materialistic minds in the spirit of imaginative <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc.03315.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>idealism that underlies the Cymric
                expression of life, now as in the past. There is something to me greatly inspiring
                to think of the international elements, Celtic, Cymric, Sclavonic, Gallic, that our
                Saxon stock must assimilate to itself to new ends of human growth &#38; perfection as
                time goes by. And for this of course America is the grand field of
                development!</p>
            <p>A few days back W. S. Kennedy's<ptr target="n3039"/> new book about you arrived here
                from Chatto &#38; Windus, &#38; in reading it &#38; looking at relative passages in
                "Specimen Days" &#38; "Leaves of Grass," the thought of the American future has filled
                me with a new impetus. But I must <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.03315.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>not dwell upon this now, as there
                are other things to settle. I must just say about Kennedy's book, however, that I
                have every hope of being able to place it satisfactorily with some publisher. I am
                waiting now to hear from Fred. Wilson, of W. &#38; McCormick &#38; you may be sure I
                will do all I can for the book. There is a great deal in it about L. of G. &#38;
                about yourself intimately, which I find unspeakably stimulative &#38; tonic. It will
                cause something like a sensation when it appears,&#8212;amongst those who know L. of
                G. at any rate. Having it in my drawer or on the table as I write, it makes me feel
                as if you <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03315.007_large.jpg" type="recto"
                />yourself had been in the room, bringing health &#38; virile stimulus.</p>
            <p>This brings me to "Specimen Days" which I am proud to think will appear in the Camelot
                series. Thanks very many for letting me have it! I will get as much as I can out of
                the publishers; for as Walter Scott is one of the largest railway contractors, as
                well as a publisher, &#38; well stocked with money, I have no scruple on that score.
                It is not easy in any case to get much out of him, unfortunately. For my own sake,
                as well as yours, I wish it were! As for cutting the book down, it seems wicked to
                think of it; but it is really rather longer than they find it pays to give for a shilling,
                &#38; if you will do the emendation yourself, one may feel less sore about it.
                Including the appendix<pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03315.008_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> (which is of course in smaller type) there are about 70
                pages more than the publishers like to have in the Camelot volumes, so if you will
                revise the book to make it about 300 pages, it will answer capitally. Is
                it too much to ask you for a few fresh words of introduction as well, addressed to
                the English reader?</p>
                <p>I hope we shall soon be ready now too to print the 2nd Edn
                of the selected Leaves of Grass. In the paper you sent me I noticed your admonition
                about tampering with your full expression in them, &#38; have thought over it very
                seriously, besides asking Dr Bucke's opinion about issuing a 2nd Edn at
                all of my little book. He strongly advises the re-issue, however, looking at it, as I
                do, as an important makeshift which will help the perfect presentment to a hearing
                presently. He advises too the inclusion of "The Song of Myself" instead of some of
                the other poems. Herbert Gilchrist<ptr target="n0262"/> (whom I expect to see this
                evening) has promised me a new portrait too.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>yours, with great love,</salute>
                <signed>Ernest Rhys</signed>
            </closer>
              <postscript> 
            <p>Dr Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> has hospitably pressed me to go &#38; see him next summer,
                    holding out the inducement of your being at his place. Ah, how I should like it to
                    be possible!</p>
            </postscript>
            
            <!--The following postscript is found on the first page of the letter-->
            <postscript>
                <p>I ought<ptr target="loc.03315_n2"/> to have said with regard to "Specimen Days"
                &#38; the Camelot requirements, that the vol. of King Arthur contains a great deal
                more than the publishers can really afford to give. The first vol. they looked upon
                as a sort of pilot for the rest, &#38; put an extra amount in accordingly.</p>
            </postscript> 
            
              <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03315.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
             <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03315.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="left" resp="#unk">Rhys</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
