<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05122">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 17 September
                    1881</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05122</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 17 September 1881</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-09-17" xml:id="dat1">September 17, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-10-03">checked, corrected</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-08" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-02-11" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-23" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-21" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">The first mention of the proposed German
                translation.</note>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">? 81</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1881-09-17">September 17 '81</date>
                    <name type="place">29 Lange Strasse</name>
                    <name type="place">Dresden.</name>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            
            <p>I have been trying, since my return to Germany,<ptr target="n1027"/> to find out that essay you allude to
                in the N.A. Review article you sent me<ptr target="loc.05122_n1"/>&#8212;on the
                question 'Has America produced any great poet?' But as yet I have had no success. I
                fancy the thing fell through. There are very few ideas in Germany about American
                literature, past, present, or future. I got a few days ago a book called 'Aus dem
                Amerikanischen Dichterwald', by D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Rudolph Doehn. It has about 300 pages, &amp;
                professes, with justice, to be the first comprehensive properly historical and
                philosophical account of American literature, which <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_af.01010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>it treats in 3 periods&#8212;the
                Colonial, Revolutionary and Literary epochs. It was greatly praised in an excellent
                German weekly paper, the Gegenwart.<ptr target="loc.05122_n2"/> I was much
                disappointed with it. There seemed to be a great lack of intelligence about
                it&#8212;no recognition at all that anything particularly American was to be
                expected of American literature; just the conventional praise and blame&#8212;plenty
                of the former, for such qualities as melody, elegance, fine sentiment, &amp;c. Doehn is
                rather celebrated in Germany &amp; has lived 12 years in America. He must be a rather
                wide-minded man, for he is not very greatly offended at you. But that's just
                it&#8212;he is so appreciative that a shock scarcely affects him and a vacuity
                affects him not at all. And his tone of mind is just that of his countrymen <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_af.01013_large.jpg" type="recto"/>in general towards
                things American. He treats of you in a page, together with Stedman, Holland,
                Halpine, Winter.<ptr target="loc.05122_n3"/> Here is what he says (I translate, as
                you <choice>
                    <abbr>mayn't</abbr>
                    <expan>may not</expan>
                </choice> be familiar with German).</p>

            <q who="#Rudolph Doehn"><p>"Not to be forgotten here is Walt Whitman, born on May 31st
                    1819 in a farm village on Long Island, N. York&#8212;of whom the saying holds
                    "He bears Eagles in his head, and buries his feet in the mire" (Er tr&#228;gt
                    Adler im Haupte und steckt mit seinen F&#252;ssen tief im Kothe.) His father was
                    of English descent, his mother (Louisa van <choice>
                        <sic>Belsor</sic><corr>Velsor</corr></choice>, of Dutch origin.<ptr target="loc.05122_n4"/> His brother, George M.
                    Whitman served during the Civil War as officer in a New York Regiment. Sprung
                    from a low social position (aus niedrigem Stande) W.W. was now farmer, now carpenter, now printer. Shortly before the outbreak of the civil war he
                    composed, and set up with his own hands, his Leaves of Grass, a set of
                    mystic-democratic poems which are rough and wholly without art, but not without
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_af.01014_large.jpg" type="verso"/> strength
                    and content (Inhalt, substance). W.W. often pays no regard whatever to the
                    ordinary rules of morality and propriety (Anstand), but he does this, not from
                    attenuated deficient moral sense
                    (sittliche Verkommenheit), but because he regards the traditional observances of
                    morals and propriety as contemptible and hypocritical formalities. During the
                    civil war he was active for some time in the Sanitary Corps &amp; in the
                    hospitals; and also received a post in the Home Department;&#8212;but his
                    opponents, who saw in him a defender of "Free Love" were soon able to have him
                    removed therefrom. His "Drum Taps" appeared in 1865&#8212;are poetical
                    monologues on the war, suffer however, like almost all his compositions, from
                    over-monotony (&#252;bergro&#223;er Monotonie). Of decided poetic worth is his monody
                    on Lincoln's death, beginning "When Lilacs" (&amp;c). The same may be said of the
                    poem "Come up from the Fields, father"&#8212;in which a deep <pb
                        xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.01011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>and warm
                    feeling expresses itself in a manner which lays hold of the reader (in
                    ergreifender Weise)."</p></q>

            <p>So Herr Doehn. You see he does not even mention that in your works, for the first
                time on a large scale, English poetry is written without rhyme &amp; metre&#8212;a
                notable fact surely. (I forgot your predecessor Blake). This gives one an idea of
                his want of critical intelligence&#8212;of a large view of linked facts &amp;
                tendencies.&#8212;He touches on all American authors in this way, taking them one by
                one, giving life, and some brief criticisms; Emerson &amp; Thoreau get little mention.
                But the last division of the book consists of longer &amp; more detailed accounts of 6
                authors, viz&#8212;R. H. Dana, Whittier, Miller (Joaquin), Bryant, Longfellow,
                Bayard Taylor. Many poems are quoted in the original, and translated&#8212;but none
                of yours. <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_af.01015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>This I
                am <choice>
                    <orig>surprized</orig>
                    <reg>surprised</reg>
                </choice> at, for they would go well in German. A project I contemplate &amp; would
                carry out as soon as I could find a proper German collaborateur, is a full German
                translation of the Leaves of Grass &amp; Passage to India. I fancy it would be most
                successful here, &amp; be largely understood. I believe Freiligrath has done some?<ptr
                    target="loc.05122_n5"/></p>

            <p>I always ask Americans about you here. Sometimes they say 'Oh yes, I heard of him
                from an Englishman some time ago.' But mostly it is blank ignorance, &amp; in neither
                case, interest.</p>

            <p>I suppose 'Calvin Harlowe' was never published? I have amended it, in accordance with
                a friend's advice, &amp; sent it to Kottabos, a magazine belonging to Trinity College
                Dublin, &amp; supported by (unpaid) present &amp; past students.<ptr
                    target="loc.05122_n6"/> I write little poetry now <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="loc_af.01016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>but am trying to do a little in
                writing about German affairs for an Irish paper, &amp; give spare time to Greek &amp;
                Gaelic. My 'Encheiridion' ought to be out very soon as I have sent in the last proof
                    sheets.<ptr target="loc.05122_n7"/> I want to try &amp; get it reviewed in
                America. Should I send a copy to the 'Herald' &amp; other papers? I should be much
                obliged if you would mention the names of two or three papers to which I might send
                such a work for reviewal. And another thing I should like to hear from you, is the
                name of the author of the best yet-written history of the American Civil War. I have
                read no history of it as yet&#8212;would you recommend Draper's?<ptr
                    target="loc.05122_n8"/></p>

            <p>The address over this letter will find me for some months now.</p>

            <p>I hope you are well. I heard you were coming to England this year&#8212;I suppose
                that's not true.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute rend="right">Yours sincerely</salute>
                <signed rend="right">T W H Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_af.01012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <postscript>
                <p>If I hear of the prize essay I'll let you have it at once.</p>
            </postscript>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
