<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00476">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 27 October
               1878</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
               Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00476</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
                  the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                  copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce
                  the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals
                  for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 27 October 1878</title>
               <date when="1878-10-27">October 27, 1878</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman,
                  1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#nhg" when="2013-12-12">added image references, checked transcription against images</change>
         <change who="#nnk" when="2013-12-10">proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_ad00525_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>OFFICE OF Water Commissioner,</name>
               <name type="place">CITY HALL, (Market Street Entrance.)</name>
               <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
               <date when="1878-10-27"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>Oct 27th 1878</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My dear Walt</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Tis a long time since I have heard from any of you&#8212;but I suppose all goes about
            the same as ever. I suppose you have had all sorts of newspaper rumors in regard to the
            yellow fever in St Louis<ptr target="loc.00476_n1"/>&#8212;but the truth is that the
            stories are nearly entirely fabrications Altogether
            there has been, probably, some 35 to 40 deaths by yellow fever during the
            season&#8212;out of this number some 6 or 8 were St Louis people who had been in some
            capacity about those that had come from the South&#8212;or had been connected with the
            hospital boat that carries the sick people from the city to the fever hospital. I have
            no doubt but that had the weather continued warm for a couple or three weeks longer we
            should have had quite a touch 
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_ad00526_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            of the trouble. From what I can observe I judge the spread
            of this disease is simply a question of time That it
            always commences in the south (so far as the West is concerned at any rate) is a
            fact&#8212;that it will progress with quite a certain rate of travel&#8212;now if the
            time between its first breaking out and where it meets a heavy frost is long enough I do
            not see why it should not spread to the lakes. This season it broke out in New Orleans
            <choice>   
               <orig>abt</orig>
               <reg>about</reg>
            </choice> 6 weeks earlier than usual&#8212;we have had rather a backward season as regards
            frost and cool weather&#8212;the disease was quite bad within <choice>
               <orig>abt</orig>
               <reg>about</reg>
            </choice> 150 miles of
            us&#8212;I think more favorable conditions would undoubtedly have produced it
            here&#8212;Steamboats seem to be the home of the disease&#8212;let one of them be in the
            locality when the sickness is bad and it is pretty sure death to have anything to do
            with it&#8212;this does not seem to be the case with R. R. cars&#8212;Another thing
            seems sure and that is that with proper sanitary laws&#8212;with good energetic health
            officers&#8212;no city that is kept decently clean but what can stamp out the disease by
            taking prompt action</p>
         <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_ad00527_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <p>I do not know that you are interested in all this, but I have been pretty well exercised
            about the matter, knowing that if it did come here I should have to stop and face the
            music no matter how bad it became&#8212;We have had several cool nights&#8212;and to-day
            the weather is what might be called cold&#8212;I think we will have a decided show of
            ice to-night&#8212;and so the question of fever for this season is certainly disposed
            of.</p><!--xxx here.-->
         <p>I am getting on reasonably well have pretty good health&#8212;indeed just now it is
            extremely good&#8212;at one time&#8212;near the latter part of July I got <choice>
               
               <sic>poisened</sic>
               
               <corr>poisoned</corr>
               
            </choice> by
            the bad air of the numerous sewers, bone boiling and fat rendering establishments that I
            had to visit<ptr target="loc.00476_n2"/> and was badly off for a couple of
            weeks&#8212;and indeed did not feel well until we had a "cold wave" about two weeks
            ago&#8212;since that time I have felt the very best&#8212;and too my work has let up
            very much</p>
         <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_ad00528_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
         <p>How are you all getting on How is George and Lou and Ed and yourself&#8212;I hope you
            continue to gain&#8212;I judge from what Hattie writes that you made quite headway this
            last summer I hope so and am very glad. What is new with you are you doing anything in
            the way of books&#8212;I dont see anything in the papers<ptr target="loc.00476_n3"
            />&#8212;but then the papers I see would not be apt to say much anyhow&#8212;except in a
            mean way. Has George got through his foundry work&#8212;and if so I suppose is mostly on
            his farm<ptr target="loc.00476_n4"/>&#8212;Will you make a winter trip to your New York
            friends if so you must call and see Worthen<ptr target="loc.00476_n5"/> I have just
            had a letter from Hattie in which I learn that she is a little sick&#8212;has been laid
            off from study&#8212;I hope she is not sick to any extent&#8212;indeed I sincerely hope
            she is all right now&#8212;I have just written her to-night to let the study go and get
            well as quick as she can&#8212;I hope to hear in a day or two that she is all well
            again</p>
         <p>Give my love to all&#8212;write me when you feel like it and give me all the news.&#8212;</p>
         <closer>
            <signed rend="right">Jeff</signed>
         </closer>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
