<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00785">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 1 September 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00785</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">139-141</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 1 September 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-09-01">September 1, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-25">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-09-01">September 1 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have been thinking to-day &amp; all yesterday about the draft in Brooklyn, &amp; whether Jeff would be drafted&#8212;you must some of you write me just as soon as you get this<ptr target="loc.00785_n1"/>&#8212;I want to know, I feel anxious enough I can tell you&#8212;&amp; besides it seems a good while since I have rec'd any letters from home&#8212;Of course it is impossible for Jeff to go, in case it should turn out he was drafted&#8212;the way our family is all situated now, it would be madness&#8212;If the Common Council raise the money to exempt men with families dependent on them, I think Jeff ought to have no scruples in taking advantage of it, as I think he is in duty bound&#8212;but we will see what course to take, when we know the result &amp;c. Write about it right away.</p>
            <p>The Eagles came, this is the second time&#8212;I am always glad to get them&#8212;Jeff, wait till you get four or five, &amp; then send them with a two cent stamp&#8212;I have not had any letter from George<ptr target="loc.00785_n2"/>&#8212;Mother, have you heard any thing? did the money come? Dear mother, how are you nowadays&#8212;I do hope you feel well &amp; in good spirits&#8212;I think about you every day of my life out here&#8212;sometimes I see women in the hospitals, mothers come to see their sons, &amp; occasionally one that makes me think of my dear mother&#8212;one did very much, a lady about 60, from Pennsylvania, come to see her son, a Captain, very badly wounded, &amp; his wound gangrened, &amp; they after a while removed him to a tent by himself&#8212;another son of hers, a young man, came with her to see his brother&#8212;she was pretty full-sized lady, with spectacles, she dressed in black, looked real Velsory. I got very well acquainted with her, she had a real Long-Island old fashioned way&#8212;but I had to avoid the poor Captain as it was that time that my hand was cut in the artery, &amp; I was liable to gangrene myself&#8212;but she and the two sons have gone home now, but I doubt whether the wounded one is alive as he was very low&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, I want to hear about Andrew too, whether he went to Rockland lake<ptr target="loc.00785_n3"/>&#8212;You have no idea how many soldiers there are who have lost their voices, &amp; have to speak in whispers&#8212;there are a great many, I meet some almost every day&#8212;As far as that alone is concerned Andrew must not be discouraged, as the general health may be good as common irrespective of that&#8212;I do hope Andrew will get along better than he thinks for&#8212;it is bad enough for a poor man to be out of health even partially, but he must try to look on the bright side&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, have you heard any thing from Han since, or from Mary's folks? I got a letter from Mrs Price<ptr target="loc.00785_n4"/> last week, if you see Emma tell her I was pleased to get it, &amp; shall answer it very soon&#8212;Mother, I have sent another letter to the N Y Times,<ptr target="loc.00785_n5"/> it may appear, if not to-day, within a few days&#8212;I am feeling excellent well these days, it is so moderate &amp; pleasant weather now, I was getting real exhausted with the heat. I thought of you too, how it must have exhausted you those hot days&#8212;I still occupy the same little 3d story room, 394 L st, &amp; get my breakfast in my room in the morning myself, &amp; dinner at a restaurant about 3 o'clock&#8212;I get along very well &amp; very economical (which is a forced put, but just as well). But I must get another room or a boarding house soon, as the folks are all going to move this month&#8212;My good &amp; <hi rend="italic">real</hi> friends the O'Connors live in the same block, I am in there every day&#8212;</p>
            <p>Dear Mother, tell Mat &amp; Miss Mannahatta I send them my love&#8212;I want to see them both&#8212;O how I want to see Jeff &amp; you, mother, I sometimes feel as if I should just get in the cars &amp; come home&#8212;&amp; the baby too, you must always write about her&#8212;dear mother, good bye for present&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
