<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01491">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>  
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Edward Dowden, 18 January 1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01491</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                        <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">153&#8211;155</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Edward Dowden, 18 January 1872</title>
                    <date cert="low" when="1872-01-18" xml:id="dat1">January 18, 1872</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9, Reel 5-6</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Dowden, Edward">Edward Dowden</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-01-05" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-06" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-09-18" who="#jyc">checked,revised</change>
            <change when="2014-08-15" who="#el" >added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2010-12-01" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline> 
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington</name>
                    <date when="1872-01-18" rend="right">Jan 18, 1872.<ptr target="loc.01491_n20"/></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr Dowden,</salute>
            </opener>   

            <p>I must no longer delay writing, &#38; to acknowledge your letters of Sept 5 and Oct
                15 last.<ptr target="loc.01491_n2"/> I had previously (Aug 22)<ptr
                    target="loc.01491_n3"/> written you very briefly in response to your friendly
                letter of July 23d, the first you wrote me, accompanying copy of the Review.<ptr
                    target="loc.01491_n4"/> All&#8212;letters &#38; Review&#8212;have been read
                &#38; reread. I am sure I appreciate you in them. May I say you do not seem to stand
                afar off, but very near to me. What John Burroughs<ptr target="loc.01491_n5"/>
                brings adds confirmation. I was deeply interested in the <choice><abbr>acc'ts</abbr><expan>accounts</expan></choice> given in the letters
                of your friends. I do not hesitate to call them mine too.<ptr target="loc.01491_n6"
                    /> Tyrell<!--<ptr target="n0655"/>-->, Cross, your brother,<ptr target="loc.01491_n7"/>
                Miss West,<ptr target="loc.01491_n8"/> Todhunter,<ptr target="loc.01491_n9"/>
                    O'Grady<ptr target="loc.01491_n10"/>&#8212;Yeats,<ptr target="loc.01491_n11"/>
                    Ellis,<ptr target="loc.01491_n12"/> Nettleship.<ptr target="loc.01491_n13"/>
                Affectionate remembrance to all of them. You especially, and Mrs. Dowden, &#38;
                indeed all of you, already, I say, stand near to me. I wish each to be told my
                remembrance (or to see this letter if convenient).</p>

            <p>I like well the positions &#38; ideas in your Westminster article&#8212;and radiating
                from the central point of assumption of my pieces being, or commencing "the poetry
                of Democracy." It presents all the considerations which such a critical text &#38;
                starting point require, in a full, eloquent, &#38; convincing manner. I entirely
                accept it, all &#38; several, &#38; am not unaware that it probably afforded, if not
                the only, at least the most likely gate, by which you as an earnest friend of my
                book, &#38; believing critic of it, would gain entrance to a leading
                review&#8212;Besides, I think the main theme you exploit is really of the first
                importance&#8212;and all the rest can be broached &#38; led to, through it, as well
                as any other way.</p>

            <p>I would say that (as you of course see) the spine or verteber principle of my book is
                a model or ideal (for the service of the New World, &#38; to be gradually absorbed
                in it) of a complete healthy, heroic, practical modern <hi rend="italic"
                >Man</hi>&#8212;emotional, moral, spiritual, patriotic&#8212;a grander better son,
                brother, husband, father, friend, citizen than any yet&#8212;formed &#38; shaped in
                consonance with modern science, with American Democracy, &#38; with the requirements
                of current industrial &#38; professional life&#8212;model of a Woman also, equally
                modern &#38; heroic&#8212;a better daughter, wife, mother, citizen also, than any
                yet. I seek to typify a living Human Personality, immensely animal, with immense
                passions, immense amativeness, immense adhesiveness&#8212;in the woman immense
                maternity&#8212;&#38; then, in both, immenser far a <hi rend="italic">moral
                    conscience</hi>, &#38; in always realizing the direct &#38; indirect control of
                the divine laws through all and over all forever.</p>

            <p>In "Democratic Vistas" I seek to make patent the appalling vacuum, in our times &#38;
                here, of any school of great imaginative Literature &#38; Art, fit for a Republican,
                Religious, &#38; Healthy people&#8212;and to suggest &#38; prophesy such a
                Literature as the only vital means of sustaining &#38; perpetuating such a people. I
                would project at least the rough sketch of such a school of Literatures&#8212;an
                entirely new breed of authors, poets, American, comprehensive, Hegelian, Democratic,
                religious&#8212;&#38; with an infinitely larger scope &#38; method than any yet<ptr target="loc.01491_n14"/>&#8212;</p>
                

            <p>There is one point touched by you in the Westminster criticism that if occasion again
                arises, might be dwelt on more fully&#8212;that is the attitude of sneering denial
                which magazines, editors, publishers, "critics" &#38;c. in the U. S. hold toward
                "Leaves of Grass." As to "Democratic Vistas" it remains entirely unread, uncalled
                for here in America. If you write again for publication about my books, or have
                opportunity to influence any forthcoming article on them, I think it would be a
                proper &#38; even essential part of such article to include the fact that the books
                are hardly recognized at all by the orthodox literary &#38; conventi[on]al
                authorities of the U. S.&#8212;that the opposition is bitter, &#38; in a large
                majority, &#38; that the author was actually turned out of a small government
                employment &#38; deprived of his means of support by a Head of Department at
                Washington solely on account of having written his poems.</p>

            <p>True I take the whole matter coolly. I know my book has been composed in a cheerful
                &#38; contented spirit&#8212;&#38; that the same still substantially remains with
                me. (And I want my friends, indeed, when writing for publication about my poetry, to
                present its gay-heartedness as one of its chief qualities.)</p>

            <p>I am in excellent health, &#38; again &#38; still work as clerk here in Washington.</p>

            <p>I saw John Burroughs very lately. He is well. He showed me a letter he had just rec'd
                from you.</p>

            <p>I wish more &#38; more (and especially now that I realize I know you, &#38; we should
                be no strangers) to journey over sea, &#38; visit England &#38; your country.<ptr target="loc.01491_n15"/></p>

            <p>Tennyson<!--<ptr target="n0625"/>--> has written to me twice&#8212;&#38; very cordial &#38;
                hearty letters. He invites me to become his guest.</p>

            <p>I have <choice><abbr>rec'd</abbr><expan>received</expan></choice> a letter from Joaquin Miller.<ptr target="loc.01491_n16"/>
                He was at last accounts in Oregon, recuperating, studying,
                enjoying grand &#38; fresh Nature, &#38; writing something new.</p>

            <p>Emerson has just been this way (Baltimore &#38; Washington) lecturing. He maintains
                the same attitude&#8212;draws on the same themes&#8212;as twenty-five years
                ago. It all seems to me quite attenuated (the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> drawing
                of a good pot of tea, you know, and Emerson's was the heavenly herb itself&#8212;but
                what must one say to a <hi rend="italic">second</hi>, and even <hi rend="italic"
                    >third</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fourth</hi> infusion?) I send you a newspaper
                report of his lecture here a night or two ago. It is a fair sample.<ptr target="loc.01491_n17"/>
            </p>

            <p>And now, my dear friend, I must close. I have long wished to write you a letter to
                show, if nothing more, that I heartily realize your kindness &#38; sympathy, &#38;
                would draw the communion closer between us. I shall probably send you any thing I
                publish, and any thing about my affairs or self that might interest you. You too
                must write freely to me&#8212;&#38; I hope frequently&#8212;</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Direct</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman</signed>
                <signed rend="right">Solicitor's Office Treasury</signed>
                <signed rend="right">Washington D C</signed>
                <signed rend="right">U. S. America.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
