<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00595">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Will W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 7 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Will W. Wallace</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00595</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">210&#8211;211</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Will W. Wallace</author>
               <title>Will W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 7 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-07">May 7, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Wallace, Will W.">Will W. Wallace</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-09-04">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="loc.00595_n100"/> received your letter this morning and will not give the plea you have given. I have very little time tis true, yet I endeavor by writing rapidly to have time to keep up my correspondence more particularly with those in Washington. I am better pleased with the city than when I last wrote. I have a Hospital of 350 patients No stewards to assist me, three women to look after and Jones Hotel to run. Have I not my hands full by the way you wish to know what Jones Hotel is. It is a fine house across the way from Hospt No 3, where the Surgn Steward and women stop it has a large white Board in front with the letters contrasting in black "Jones Hotel" I have the clerks from the different Head Quarters board with me so I am well posted in what is going on in different dpts. I would be pleased to see you here. I received a letter from Col Leasur of the 100th Pa and more familiarly Roundhead Regt<ptr target="loc.00595_n2"/>  this morning stating that the 9th Army Corps was under marching orders and moving to Murfreesboro via Nashville. I wish you would come and make your headquarters with me. You could find plenty of work in your line. There is a New paper started this week by the correspondant of Forneys Press. It is making business. Here is a field of fourtune for some of them who wish</p>
            <p>I am surprised at your frenchy leaving you in such a deplorable state, but you are not alone. I had to dismiss mine to save the reputation of the Hospital and your humble servant.</p>
            <p>Nothing new here. I have the famous Miss Chase<ptr target="loc.00595_n3"/> here and she is invaluable in her assistance to me. I send my Photo and shall expect one of the Prince of Bohemia by return</p>
            <p>I will write in a few days. Come out here you will find it pleasant.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Your protegee</salute>
               <signed>Will W Wallace</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
