<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03570">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, [9 September
                    1884]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>  
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03570</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, [9 September 1884]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1884-09-09" xml:id="dat1">September 9, 1884</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 15</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H." ref="n1027">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-12" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-08-02" who="#kb">edited </change>
            <change when="2015-05-27" who="#if">edited </change>
            <change when="2015-02-14" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-18" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03570.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline> 
                    <name type="place">Glasshouse</name>
                    <name type="place">Shinrone</name>
                    <name type="place">Ireland.</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Walt&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I got your second letter yesterday, forwarded here from Dresden.<ptr target="loc.03570_n1"/> Don't be uneasy
                about the English text in the translation. I <hi rend="underline">fully</hi> see the
                advantages of it. I have mentioned it in my preface. Only as I had had no opinion on
                the subject from anyone in the publishing line I didn't know what they might not <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03570.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> have to advance
                so did not like to speak too decisively about it. I should not have given you to
                understand that a publisher's mere <hi rend="underline">opinion</hi> would weigh with me, for it would not. </p>
            <p> Now as to progress made&#8212;I have met with difficulties more serious than I expected. The
                work is ready, &amp; could go to the printer any day. But the printer is not equally
                ready for the work. I offered it to four publishers before I left Germany, agreeing
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03570.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> to pay all
                expenses myself, &amp; all refused to take it up. I sent with my <choice><abbr>M.S.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> a copy of
                Freiligrath's article,<ptr target="n0248"/> &amp; did all I could to secure a favourable hearing, but in
                vain. I am told there would probably be difficulties with the police, who in Germany
                exercise a most despotic power. Then other publishers I thought of trying are, I have
                been informed, rogues; and others again are dependent in various ways on court or
                official patronage&#8212;others would'nt touch it with it the end of a poker. So finally I
                came to a resolution a good deal <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03570.004_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> confirmed by what you said of the probable circle of readers of
                the first <choice><abbr>ed<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></abbr><expan>edition</expan></choice>&#8212;namely, to let the book appear in America, &amp; <hi
                    rend="underline">thence</hi> make its way into German circulation. Once in print
                &amp; fairly before the public it will of course weather every storm, but the thing
                is to get it fairly started. Had I been living in Germany longer I should have tried
                selling the book myself&#8212;but that I can't do from here. Now in America, where
                your position is assured, I suppose some German publisher would take it up readily
                enough. 
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03570.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            I am going then to ask you to take what steps can be taken toward finding a willing
                publisher with some German connection. No doubt D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Karl Knortz<ptr target="uva.00476_n1"/> would a useful person to
                apply to. (If you know him, &amp; could get him to glance through my proof sheets I
                don't doubt that the work would be considerably improved.) </p>
            <p> As to terms, of course if any enterprising
                publisher would give me 100 dollars or so for the book I would let him have it (it
                being understood that you &amp; I should have our way about the form of the book,
                English version, &amp;c). But I would <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.03570.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> be willing also to bear the expenses &amp; keep the copyright, if the
                former were not out of the way large&#8212;I suppose it would cost a good deal more in
                America than in Germany, where everything is very cheap, &amp; I have not much ready
                money to spare now. But I think I can rely on my father's helping me to the extent
                needed. If the book is printed in America you will be able to oversee technical
                matters connected with the printing to your own satisfaction. </p>
            <p> So the upshot of this is that I will
                send you my <choice><abbr>M.S.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> as soon as it <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03570.007_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> reaches me (it is coming in a box which was sent after me via
                Hamburg with other heavy luggage), &amp; you can do as you think well with it. Let me
                say again that I should greatly like the proofsheets, before coming here, to pass
                through the hands of some German scholar <hi rend="underline">who knows the L. of
                    G.</hi> &amp; should be grateful for any annotations he might wish to make. </p>
            <p> I was grieved to hear of your increased illness. It is very hard to be persecuted by
                such things when you ought to have peace and freedom. But I <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="loc.03570.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> know how you are 'armed with
                patience' Silence is a great comforter. </p>
            <p> We are now back in our own country for good, &amp; are greatly delighted to be so.
                The people are much more congenial to me than Germans, though these latter are more
                so than English. I was born in this house &amp; know every field &amp; nearly every tree since my
                childhood, it is wonderfully beautiful to me&#8212;a rich, undulating wooded
                land&#8212;deep grass &amp; crops, blue mountains of Slieve Bloom on the horizon,
                &amp; the stateliest trees, mostly ash &amp; beech, I ever saw. I have a great love
                for ash trees&#8212;such sinewy strength, &amp; a free, powerful method of branching,
                showing through the light foliage. What a country <pb xml:id="leaf005r"
                    facs="loc.03570.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/> this is! or would be but for
                savage misgovernment, and Protestant bigotry. The Orangemen in the north are a source of much
                evil, &amp; will be of more, unless some miracle should turn them into human
                sympathetic Irishmen. There was a time when I thought that Ireland could never be
                set free from English rule because the Catholic Church would instantly become
                dominant and inaugurate a system of religious tyranny which would crush liberties
                more important than <hi rend="underline">national</hi> liberties. Now I begin to see
                that this would not be so for long. The Irish are much less Catholic than they were&#8212;dogmatic religion is loosening its hold
                upon them in a very remarkable way, &amp; hatred for <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03570.010_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> Protestant England as Irelands ruler is a most potent cause at
                present in supporting the Catholic religion here. This is felt even by the more
                cultivated &amp; farseeing of the clergy, who consequently oppose the national
                movement as far as they dare. I have no doubt that in a free Ireland the Church would
                persecute as naturally as a 
                    wasp stings, but I am equally certain that a revulsion of feeling would come which (though attended
                perhaps with terrible struggles) would mark a real moral &amp; intellectual advance
                such as seems out of our reach at present. The people about us here are very poor, <pb
                    xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03570.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/> reckless,
                friendly "full of reminiscences" both of good &amp; evil. My father is greatly loved
                far &amp; wide because when County Court Judge of Tipperary he protected the tenants
                as far as the laws allowed against the rapacity of the landlord class. He is a man
                you would like to see! He is over 70 now, more than average height even for our
                family, where the men grow very tall&#8212;(about 6 <choice><abbr>ft</abbr><expan>feet</expan></choice> 4 inches)&#8212;&amp; still sturdy. At
                present he is suffering form a strain got a few days ago while riding a restive
                horse. They tell me that a few days before I came there was a storm, and a fine
                sycamore <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03570.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/> he was
                fond of, near being blown down&#8212;they saw the roots heaving through the loosened
                earth&#8212;and my father sat down upon them until heavy weights could be brought to keep
                them down till the storm blew out, a device which was perfectly successful. 
                He &amp; my mother are greatly delighted with the two grandchildren we have brought
                them home. I'll send you a photograph of them soon, which has been done in Dresden
                just before we left. </p>
            <p> I will leave the poems arranged in the order I find best but you of course may wish
                to alter my arrangement, in which case I shall have nothing to object. </p>
            <p> &#8212;I couldn't make out what '<hi rend="underline">teff wheat</hi>' is&#8212;(Salut au Monde)&#8212;is there a German
                equivalent? I have written Teff-Weizen.<ptr target="loc.03570_n2"/> </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours,</salute>
                <signed>T.W.R.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
