<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00457">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 8 December 1872</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00457</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">147-150</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 8 December 1872</title>
               <date when="1872-12-08">December 8, 1872</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis </name>
                  <date when="1872-12-08">Dec 8th 1872</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your various letters were received. I was up to Chicago<ptr target="loc.00457_n1"/> when they arrived and thus Mattie did not get [them] for a few days after they came to the office. Mattie is pretty sick  she has had a great deal of trouble with her right arm and hand&#8212;a[nd] is not able to use it to write just now&#8212;for the last few days she has suffered the torments of Hell in being blistered&#8212;she had four large strong blisters on her at once and this morning I had to thake them off or I feared she would go crazy&#8212;she is some easier now&#8212;yet suffers much from the terrible places places left by these blisters  It seems to have helped her arm and hand some and perhaps her lungs a little yet she coughs a grat deal  Since the receipt of your letter saying that you would not come out here Mat has about given up her idea of going East&#8212;at any rate just now she is altogether too sick to think of such a thing. She has had quite a sleep this (Sunday) morning the first since Wednesday last. As soon as the places heal up a little I hope she will be comfortable&#8212;yet my dear Mother it is no use to try and think she is getting better&#8212;she is failing all the time&#8212;yet by care and attention and all that I hope she will get through the winter and if she does I shall try and get her to go out towards California or into the Rocky Mountains<ptr target="loc.00457_n2"/>  As good luck would have it we have been more than fortunate in regard to help&#8212;Mat had two girls, sisters, one a good cook and the other [a] house girl  some fellow came out from Jersey City and married the house girl and the cook thought she would leave but as she had another sister also a cook Mat made an arrangement by which the second cook came to us as cook and our old one took the place of the married one  so you see we are in good condition for eating&#8212;they do splendidly and Mat has not the least care of either house or house keeping</p>
            <p>The children are perfectly well and go to school regularly  Jess has just begun to take lessons in music and they both go to dancing school<ptr target="loc.00457_n3"/>&#8212;so all this&#8212;with the marketing and going to the stores&#8212;occupies all their time&#8212;indeed they seem to work as hard as anyone</p>
            <p>I have just had to stop and go over to the bed and dress these blister sores with sweet oil&#8212;Mat is suffering very much&#8212;you may know how much when I tell you that for the first time she cannot restrain groaning&#8212;I do not know whether the Dr will like my taking off the blisters or not&#8212;but I do know that Mat could not have stood it many hours longer</p>
            <p>We have just commenced with the horse sickness here<ptr target="loc.00457_n4"/> and it is quite an interesting thing to see how quickly people in a big city will adapt themselves to circumstances&#8212;only a few days ago and all the affairs and business that the horse entered into were progressing the same as usual&#8212;to-day not one hundretth of the horses are out&#8212;oxen quite plenty&#8212;last night a fire broke out&#8212;the fire engines were on the spot pretty near as soon as usual&#8212;but drawn in the old fashioned way by men.</p>
            <p>My own horse is sick but not very bad&#8212;yet bad enough to make me feel mighty sorry for him&#8212;I hav'nt had him out since last Tuesday&#8212;I hope he will not be out of use more than a week</p>
            <p>I was up to Chicago last week  Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00457_n5"/> came down from Milwaukee to see me, we had a few hours of good old fashioned talk and I was extremely glad to see him&#8212;he looks first rate, certainly coming west was a good move for Lane</p>
            <p>We noted what you said about receiving a letter from Jo Barkeloo<ptr target="loc.00457_n6"/>&#8212;and nothing would give Mat more pleasure than to make them a visit&#8212;but she cannot think of such a thing now&#8212;I hope she may be able to accept the invitation next season</p>
            <p>I am well, have a good deal to do but still manage to get along well enough&#8212;the works progress well and we have just worked through a pretty bad season&#8212;but we got through without much trouble after all</p>
            <p>How do you do, dear Mammy  How goes it with you? What sort of wine did you get and how do you like it?<ptr target="loc.00457_n7"/> How is George and Loo and Ed&#8212;how I would like to see you all&#8212;does George still have plenty of work&#8212;What do you hear from Han&#8212;I suppose Walt comes to see you now and then&#8212;Has Ed found a church in Camden to his liking&#8212;it must be quite a draw back to the Bedford Av affair, Ed's leaving  have they had to shut up the shop on account of Ed's moving away from Brooklyn</p>
            <p>Do you ever get over to Philadelphia, and if so how do you like it? and a thousand other things I would like to ask you if I could see you</p>
            <p>Do you ever hear from Brooklyn? I suppose George does tell him to drop me a line and tell me how things go there since the new dispensation<ptr target="loc.00457_n8"/>
            </p>
            <p>Well dear Mammy I guess I will consider this a dose for this time&#8212;you must write whenever you can&#8212;all send love&#8212;Mat and I and the children too are much very much, disappointed that you do not think well of coming out and staying the winter with us&#8212;did you know how easy the travel is you would not mind that part of it</p>
            <p>All send love to Loo and George and Ed&#8212;I will try and write a little more frequently</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
