<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00777">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 15 July 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00777</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">117-118</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 15 July 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-07-15">July 15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-03-04">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-24">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-07-15">Wednesday forenoon July 15 | 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>So the mob has risen at last in New York<ptr target="loc.00777_n1"/>&#8212;I have been expecting it, but as the day for the draft had arrived &amp; every thing was so quiet, I supposed all might go on smoothly&#8212;but it seems the passions of the people were only sleeping, &amp; have burst forth with terrible fury, &amp; they have destroyed life &amp; property, the enrolment buildings &amp;c as we hear&#8212;the accounts we get are a good deal in a muddle, but it seems bad enough&#8212;the feeling here is savage &amp; hot as fire against New York, (the mob&#8212;"<hi rend="italic">copperhead mob</hi>" the papers here call it,) &amp; I hear nothing in all directions but threats of ordering up the gunboats, cannonading the city, shooting down the mob, hanging them in a body, &amp;c &amp;c&#8212;meantime I remain silent, partly amused, partly scornful, or occasionally put a dry remark, which only adds fuel to the flame&#8212;I do not feel it in my heart to abuse the poor people, or call for rope or bullets for them, but that is all the talk here, even in the hospitals&#8212;</p>
            <p>The acc'ts from N Y this morning are that the gov't has ordered the draft to be suspended there&#8212;I hope it is true, for I find that the deeper they go in with the draft, the more trouble it is likely to make&#8212;I have changed my opinions &amp; feelings on the subject&#8212;we are in the midst of strange &amp; terrible times&#8212;one is pulled a dozen different ways in his mind, &amp; hardly knows what to think or do&#8212;Mother, I have not much fear that the troubles in New York will affect any of our family, still I feel somewhat uneasy&#8212;about Jeff, if any one, as he is more around&#8212;I have had it much on my mind what could be done, if it should so happen that Jeff should be drafted&#8212;of course he could not go, without its being the downfall almost of our whole family, as you may say, Mat &amp; his young ones, &amp; a sad blow to you too, mother, &amp; to all&#8212;I didn't see any other way than to try to raise the $300, mostly by borrowing if possible of Mr Lane&#8212;mother, I have no doubt I shall make a few hundred dollars by the lectures I shall certainly commence soon, (for my hospital missionary purposes &amp; my own, for that purpose) &amp; I could lend that am't to Jeff to pay it back&#8212;May be the draft will not come off after all&#8212;I should say it was very doubtful if they can carry it out in N Y &amp; Brooklyn&#8212;&amp; besides it is only one chance out of several, to be drawn if it does&#8212;I dont wonder dear brother Jeff feels the effect it would have on domestic affairs. I think it is right to feel so, full as strongly as a man can. I do hope all will go well, &amp; without such an additional trouble falling upon us, but as it can be met with money, I hope Jeff &amp; Mat &amp; all of you, dear mother, will not worry any more about it&#8212;I wrote to Jeff a few lines last Sunday, I suppose he got<ptr target="loc.00777_n2"/>&#8212;Mother, I don't know whether you have had a kind of gloomy week the past week, but somehow I feel as if you all had, but I hope it has passed over&#8212;How is dear sister Mat, &amp; how is Miss Mannahatta &amp; little black head&#8212;I sometimes feel as if I <hi rend="italic">must</hi> come home &amp; see you all, I want to very much&#8212;</p>
            <p>My hospital life still continues the same&#8212;I was in Armory all day yesterday &amp; day &amp; night before&#8212;they have the men wounded in the railroad accident at Laurel station (bet[ween] here &amp; Baltimore) about 30 soldiers, some of them horribly injured at 3 o'clock a m last Saturday by collision&#8212;poor, poor, poor men&#8212;I go again this afternoon &amp; night&#8212;I see so much of butcher sights, so much sickness &amp; suffering I must get away a while I believe for self preservation&#8212;I have felt quite well though the past week&#8212;we have had rain continually&#8212;Mother, I have not heard from George since, have you? I shall write Han to-day &amp; send George's letter&#8212;if you or Jeff has not written this week I hope Jeff will write on receiving this. Good bye for present, dearest mother, &amp; Jeff &amp; Mat.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Mother, the army is to be paid off two months more, right away. Of course George will get two months more pay. Dear mother, I hope you will keep untouched &amp; put in bank every cent you can. I want us to have a ranch somewhere by or before next spring.</p>
         </postscript> 
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
