<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05770">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 17 December
                    1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05770</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">230&#8211;232</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 17 December 1884</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1884-12-17" xml:id="dat1">December 17, 1884</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 10, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-24" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-06-06" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-26" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-02-14" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-16" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Keats Corner</name>
                    <name type="place">Hampstead</name>
                    <date when="1884-12-17">Dec. 17, '84.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute> Dearest Friend:
                </salute>
            </opener>
            <p> At last I have extracted a little bit of news about you from friend Carpenter,<ptr
                    target="n0141b"/> who never comes to see us and is [as] reluctant to write
                letters as&#8212;somebody else that I know. That you have a comfortable, elderly
                couple to keep house for you was a good hearing&#8212;for "the old shanty" had risen
                before my eyes as somewhat lonely, &amp; perhaps the cooking, &amp;c., not well
                attended to.&#8212;There seems a curious kind of ebb and flow about the recognition
                of you in England&#8212;just now there are signs of the flow&#8212;of a steadily
                gathering great wave, one indication of which is the little pamphlet just published
                in Edinburgh&#8212;one of the "Round Table" Series<ptr target="loc.05770_n2"/>&#8212;no doubt a copy has been
                sent you. If not and you would care to see it, I will send you one. On the whole I
                like it (barring one or two stupidities)&#8212;at any rate, as compared with what
                has hitherto been written. My poor article has so far been rejected by
                editors&#8212;so I have laid it by for a little, to come with a fresh eye &amp; see
                if I can make it in any way more likely to win a hearing&#8212;though I often say to
                myself, "If they have not ears to hear you, how is it likely one can unstop their
                ears?" But on the other hand there is always the chance of leading some to read the
                Poems who had not else done so.&#8212;Percy &amp; Norah and Archie,<ptr
                    target="n0263"/> now grown a very sturdy active little fellow, are coming to
                spend Xmas with us, which is a great pleasure. </p>
            <p> I am deep in Froude's last volumes of "Carlyle's Life in London".<ptr
                    target="loc.05770_n1"/> Folks are grumbling that they have had enough &amp; too
                much of Carlyle &amp; <hi rend="italic">his</hi> grumblings and sarcasms. But he is an inexhaustibly
                interesting figure to me, &amp; will remain so in the long run to the world, I am
                persuaded. It grieves me that he should have been so cruelly unjust to himself as a
                husband&#8212;that remorse, those bitter self-reproaches, were undeserved, were
                altogether morbid: he was not only an infinitely better husband than she was wife:
                he was wonderfully affectionate &amp; tender &amp; just&#8212;&amp; as to his temper
                &amp; irritable nerves, she knew what she was about when she married him. Herby was
                walking through the British Museum the other day with a friend when a group, a
                ready-made picture, struck him&#8212;it was a young student-sculptress, a graceful
                girl high on a pile of boxes modelling in clay a copy of an antique statue, &amp;
                standing below, looking up at her, was a young sculptor in his blouse, criticising
                her work with much animation &amp; gesture; the background of the group, a part of
                the Elgin Marbles. So this is what Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> is painting &amp; I
                think he will make a very jolly little picture out of it. I have been much a
                prisoner to the house with bad colds ever since I returned from Wolverhampton, but
                am beginning to get out again&#8212;which puts new life into me. I have never envied
                anything in this world but a man's strong legs &amp; powers of tramping, tramping,
                over hill &amp; dale as long as he pleases&#8212;legs would content me and a sound
                breathing apparatus! I am in no hurry for wings. Giddy's voice, too, is just now
                eclipsed by cold. </p>
            <p> I hope you have escaped this evil and are able to jaunt to &amp; fro on the ferries as freely as
                ever. And I hope the pleasant Quaker friends are well&#8212;and Mr. &amp; Mrs.
                    Whitman<ptr target="n1046"/> and Hattie<ptr target="n0911"/> &amp; Jessie<ptr
                    target="n1055"/>&#8212;there is a fellow student of Giddy's<ptr target="n0890"/>
                at the Guild Hall music school who so reminds her of Hattie. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Love from us all, dear friend. Most from me.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
