<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00413">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 12 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00413</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">56-57</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 12 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-12">May 12, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-21">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-12">May 12th 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Bro. Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mr. Lane recd. your letter this morning<ptr target="loc.00413_n1"/> and would have probably answered it to-day but has had to go out in the country (to Jamaica) to make some arrangements for a visit that the Common Council and Water Board intend to make over the works. In his behalf I return thanks for your kindness as regards Horace.<ptr target="loc.00413_n2"/> Mr Lane however has heard from him  He was in the thickest of the fight but was not harmed although he had some pretty narrow escapes  He says that some of the rebs took pretty good aim at him</p>
            <p>Dear Walt, your letter has given me a great deal of pleasure, so it has Mr Lane in regard to Hooker and his movements.<ptr target="loc.00413_n3"/> I am so glad to understand that he is going in again. Tis sure that he could not have been badly whipped or he could not have done that, And Lee as you say must have been badly hurt or he would never let Hooker come across the river without molestation  I wish you could send me letters oftener. I like to get your ideas of matters and also hear what the people down in Wash'tn think. Twas rather blue here for a few days, almost every one thought it was another bad defeat.</p>
            <p>We are all thriving as usual. Mother is about the same as ever, somewhat lame with the rheumatism but not much  the rest are all well. Andrew had a letter yesterday from Jim Cornwell,<ptr target="loc.00413_n4"/> enclosing him $50 and telling him to come immediately to Suffolk,<ptr target="loc.00413_n5"/> at the bottom was a transportation order from Frank Spinola.<ptr target="loc.00413_n6"/> Cornwell said if he did not come to give the money to his (Cornwells) wife, but to come sure if possible. I think Andrew very foolish not to go, as Ruggles<ptr target="loc.00413_n7"/> says he certainly will never get <hi rend="italic">well</hi> of his throat here. Andrew was to come for me and we were going to see the Dr. to-day abt his going but he did not come and mother thinks that he has concluded <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to go. I think it would be much better for him to go  I think it would be better for his health, dont you? They must intend to give him a pretty good show or they would not send "<hi rend="italic">surely come</hi>" for him. We do not here from either Han or George do you? Hattie is the same as ever ever wanting to be out doors and wonders if Uncle Walt will never come and take her out on "<hi rend="italic">Ft. Greene</hi>."<ptr target="loc.00413_n8"/> She seems to remember you first rate and George too. What abt the pictures, shall I send them? The letter does not come out in the Eagle and probably will not but to make again sure I will call to-morrow and look over their file for some weeks back to see if I have possibly overlooked it. All send their love</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
