<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00780">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Hugo Fritsch, 7 August 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00780</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">125-127</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Hugo Fritsch, 7 August 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-08-07">August 7, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Fritsch, Hugo">Hugo Fritsch</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-03-12">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-25">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Hugo,<ptr target="loc.00780_n3"/>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I rec'd a letter from Bloom yesterday&#8212;but, before responding to it (which I will do soon) I must write to you, my friend. Your good letter of June 27th was duly rec'd&#8212;I have read it many times&#8212;indeed, Hugo, you know not how much comfort you give, by writing me your letters&#8212;posting me up.</p>
            <p>Well, Hugo, I am still as much as ever, indeed more, in the great military hospitals here. Every day or night I spend four, five, or six hours, among my sick, wounded, prostrate boys. It is fascinating, sad, &amp; with varied fortune of course. Some of my boys get well, some die. After I finish this letter (and then dining at a restaurant), I shall give the latter part of the afternoon &amp; some hours of the night to Armory Square Hospital, a large establishment &amp; one I find most calling on my sympathies &amp; ministrations. I am welcomed by the surgeons as by the soldiers&#8212;very grateful to me. You must remember that these government hospitals are not filled as with human débris like the old established city hospitals, New York, &amp;c., but mostly [with] these good-born American young men, appealing to me most profoundly, good stock, often mere boys, full of sweetness &amp; heroism&#8212;often they seem very near to me, even as my own children or younger brothers. I make no bones of petting them just as if they were&#8212;have long given up formalities &amp; reserves in my treatment of them.</p>
            <p>Let me see, Hugo. I will not write any thing about the topics of the horrible riots of last week,<ptr target="loc.00780_n4"/> nor Gen. Meade, nor Vicksburgh, nor Charleston&#8212;I leave them to the newspapers. Nor will I write you this time so much about hospitals as I did last. Tell Fred his letter was received&#8212;I appreciate it, received real pleasure from it&#8212;'twas a true friend's letter, characteristic, full of vivacity, off hand, &amp; below all a thorough base of genuine remembrance &amp; good will&#8212;was not wanting in the <hi rend="italic">sentimental</hi> either&#8212;(so I take back all about the <hi rend="italic">apostate</hi>, do you understand, Freddy, my dear?)&#8212;&amp; only write this for you till I reply to that said letter a good long (especial) missive to yourself.</p>
            <p>I<ptr target="loc.00780_n5"/> meant to [tell] Nat Bloom that if he expects to provoke me into a dignified not mentioning him, nor writing any thing about him, by his studious course of heart-breaking neglect, (which has already reduced me to a skeleton of but little over 200 lbs &amp; a countenance of raging hectic, indicating an early grave), I was determined not to do any thing of the sort, but shall speak of him every time, &amp; send him my love, just as if he were adorned with faithful troth instead of (as I understand) beautiful whiskers&#8212;Does he think that beautiful whiskers can fend off the pangs of remorse? In conclusion I have to say, Nathaniel, you just keep on if you think there's no hell.</p>
            <p>Hugo, I suppose you were at Charles Chauncey's<ptr target="loc.00780_n6"/> funeral&#8212;tell me all you hear about the particulars of his death&#8212;Tell me of course all about the boys, what you do, say, any thing, every thing<ptr target="loc.00780_n7"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Hugo, write oftener&#8212;you express your thoughts perfectly&#8212;do you not know how much more agreeable to me is the conversation or writing that does not take hard paved tracks, the usual &amp; stereotyped, but has little peculiarities &amp; even kinks of its own, making its genuineness&#8212;its vitality? Dear friend, your letters are precious to me&#8212;none I have received from any one are more so.</p>
            <p>Ah, I see in your letter, Hugo, you speak of my being reformed&#8212;no, I am not so frightfully reformed either, only the hot weather here does not admit of drinking heavy drinks, &amp; there is no good lager here&#8212;then besides I have no society&#8212;I expect to prove to you &amp; all yet that I am no backslider&#8212;But here I go nowhere for mere amusement, only occasionally a walk.</p>
            <p>And Charles Russell&#8212;how I should like to see him&#8212;how like to have one of our old times again&#8212;Ah Fred, and you, dear Hugo, &amp; you repentant one with the dark-shining whiskers<ptr target="loc.00780_n8"/>&#8212;must there not be an hour, an evening in the future, when we four returning concentrating New York-ward or elsewhere, shall meet, allowing no interloper, &amp; have our drinks &amp; things, &amp; resume the chain &amp; consolidate &amp; achieve a night better &amp; mellower than ever&#8212;we four?</p>
            <p>Hugo, I wish you to give my love to all the boys&#8212;I received a letter from Ben Knower, very good&#8212;I shall answer it soon&#8212;Give my love to Ben&#8212;If Charles Kingsley<ptr target="loc.00780_n9"/> is in town same to him&#8212;ditto Mullen&#8212;ditto Perk,<ptr target="loc.00780_n10"/> (I hope to hear that sweet, sweet fiddler one of these days, that strain again.)</p>
         <p>I wish to have Fred Gray say something from me, giving my love to his mother &amp; father&#8212;I bear them both in mind&#8212;I count on having good interviews with them when I see New York.<ptr target="loc.00780_n100"/>
         </p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
