<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01452">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 27 July
                    1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01452</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 27 July 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-07-27" xml:id="dat1">July 27, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas">Thomas Dixon</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-09-22" who="#el">transcribed and encoded letterhead</change>
            <change when="2010-12-15" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-01" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01452.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                    <handShift rend="printed"/>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine rend="center">15. SUNDERLAND STREET.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Sunderland</name>,
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                    <date when="1871-07-27">July 27 <handShift rend="printed"/>18<handShift rend="manuscript"/>71</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>


            <p>I see from the Westminster Review of our Country, that you have issued a new Edition
                of your Poems. I want to know if the new Poems are to be purchased separate. I would
                fain make my own Copy complete to the present times, so would thank you for a line
                giving me some particulars respecting the new Poems so that I may know how to order
                them from by Bookseller.—</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01452.002.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>I note that in them you have been in New York lately and that its ways and people
                don't please you. <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">even</unclear>
                these changes in people are precisely of that character that I thought you had
                already expected such and in fact are of the greatest feature in your Poems to me,
                was your acknowledgement of the existence of such peoples, and also your indication
                how such peoples originated in such States as your States. Now the question to me is
                this. Can these people help themselves being that which they are? Does not the
                artificial Life in all large Towns create and breed such people? You who have seen
                &amp; may write almost <hi rend="underline">all People</hi>, <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01452.003.jpg" type="verso"/> and have watched the growth of these
                changes seems to consider all such changes as inevitable, and that also is marked
                too in your Poems. So I pray you someday give us a clear estimate on this question
                of Life. What Life is the best for People? A Town one with every so called comfort,
                and Art and Luxury? But why need I ask when I see now before my minds eye several
                passages in your Poems that answer all the questions and that too in an emphatic
                way. yet I like yourself still keep putting the Questions to all I Know and to
                myself whenever I wander in the Streets or mix with those that Farm the lands or
                till There. Well over and above all I often have been wondering how the Books I sent
                you turned <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01452.004.jpg" type="recto"/> out as you
                read them, how did the curious Book on Indian Philosophy? answer the yearning you
                seem to have to know something about them, how did the Life of Bewich or Carlyle
                please you, to it make you feel an interest in these men? How did the Indian Theists
                utterance with its mixture of Western ideas meet your own thoughts on his Themes.
                How did Mazzinis small but yet great Book tally with your own teachings of your own
                people. There was so much representative ideas in these small Books that I yearn to
                know how it all appeared to you, and if it was to you the truth it seems to have
                been to me in thus sending to you, as my feeling was they would be as dear to you
                also.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01452.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>Since last I wrote you again as war and even Revolution once more been tried in
                France in the attempt to found a new Social State the Dream it seems to me of
                Humanity in all Ages. There is not a Literature I have read that some such a Social
                State was not foreshadowed by some of its great Men in their writings. And also how
                sorrowful to write after all the bloodshed this noble idea is still a Dream, except
                in as far as your Land proves it not so, by the few noble and successful
                associations that seems to grow and flourish in same portions of your great
                Country—                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01452.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                proving
                the idea is no dream but a veritable Truth awaiting the full growth of Humanity in
                all its true fulness for the fulfillment of
                such a truly noble form of Social Life for all Peoples!!—true comrades men
                and women such as you sing in your Poems. there again you see I find fresh spirit for my dream in your own work and that our latest
                utterance of hope for us in Human Life. I know that all these months of horror will
                have been often pondered over so wonder if in these ponderings speech or written
                thought has been made thereon.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Yours Thankfully,</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Thos. Dixon</hi></signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>