<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00609">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Byron Sutherland to Walt Whitman, 5 September 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Byron Sutherland</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00609</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">197</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Byron Sutherland</author>
               <title>Byron Sutherland to Walt Whitman, 5 September 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-09-05">September 5, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Sutherland, Byron">Byron Sutherland</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-11">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#bbb" when="2008-08-17">updated annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-18">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Your letter of Aug 26th reached me<ptr target="loc.00609_n100"/> in due time.<ptr target="loc.00609_n2"/> I had began to think (allmost) that you had forgotten me. Then I imagined that some press of work had prevented your writing me sooner. Well as for myself (And I have nothing elese to write about) I am at work on a Farm at present. And managing to save $30.00 per month. Considerable leisure time, entertaining Books, good company. My employer is at home but a very small portion of his time. Have enjoyed myself pretty well (Hard times when I cannot) considering that I am Just from so much excitement when compared with this. Have been reading, Our Old Home (by Nathaniel Hawthorne,) Home and Abroad (by B. Taylor) Color Guard (by J. R. Hosmer) all light reading but entertaining, for news I have the Buffalo Express (daily). So you see dear friend that I am pretty well provided for. I should like very much to see you and be with you.</p>
            <p>Corry is a pretty rough place. Property is very valuable. it is the Junction of three R.R. Atlantic &amp; Great Western, Pa &amp; Erie and Oil Creek. Large Refineries, Saw Mills, Manufactorys are located here and doing a flourishing Business. Lots with the stumps &amp; logs on are sold at the rate of $40.00 per foot.</p>
            <p>This winter I shall either learn a trade of go to School, I shall be governed by circumstances.</p>
            <p>The Weather is very warm for this time of the season considerable rain has fallen lately but the weather is quite pleasant nevertheless.</p>
            <p>Seems to me you are about to leave Washington in its most pleasant season. I was allways delighted with the fall of the year in that climate.</p>
            <p>Dont have any good pictures here. People are thinking more of money here than of Beauty.</p>
            <p>Sometimes I have disputes with the detested Copperheads. I treat them rather uncivilly. Havent any special regard for them.</p>
            <p>I hope you will write me a long letter. Your letter was very interesting to me&#8212;very valuable. Well Good Old Friend I must bid you good night.</p>

         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
