<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01591">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 17 October
                    [1868]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01591</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">60–62</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 17 October [1868]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1868-10-17" xml:id="dat1">October 17, 1868</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2011-08-01" who="#el">updated WWA ID referring to Doyle's letter</change>
            <change when="2011-03-07" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-23" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Providence R. I.</name>
                    <date when="1868-10-17" rend="right">October 17</date>.
<ptr target="loc.01591_n1"/>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Pete,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>According to announcement in my last, I have made a movement &amp; change of base,
                from tumultuous, close-packed, world-like N. Y., to this half-rural, brisk,
                handsome, New England, third-class town. I came on here last Thursday. I came as
                guest of Thomas Davis, formerly M. C. from this city—arrived between 8 and 9
                o'clock at night—found his carriage at the depot waiting for me—at the
                house (a sort of castle built of stone, on fine grounds, a mile &amp; a half from
                the town) a hearty welcome from his hospitable wife, &amp; a family of young ladies
                &amp; children—a hot supper, a tip-top room &amp;c. &amp;c.—so you see,
                Pete, your old man is in clover. I have since been round the city &amp; suburbs
                considerably. I am going down to Newport before I return. Invitations &amp;c. are
                numerous. I am, in fact, already dividing myself between two hospitalities, part of
                the time with Mr. &amp; Mrs. Davis, and part with Dr. &amp; Mrs. Channing, old
                acquaintances of mine in another part of the city. I stopt last night at the house
                of the latter. It is on a high &amp; pleasant hill at the side of the city, which it
                entirely overlooks. From the window of my room, I can look down across the city, the
                river, and off miles upon miles in the distance. The woods are a real spectacle,
                colored with all the rich colors of autumn. Yesterday it was beautiful &amp; balmy
                beyond description, like the finest Indian summer. I wandered around, partly
                walking, partly in a carriage, a good part of the day. To-day there is an entire
                change of scene—As I sit writing this—what do you think,
                Pete?—great flakes of <hi rend="italic">snow</hi> are falling, quite a thick
                flurry—sometimes the wind blows gusts—in fact a real snow storm has been
                going on all the forenoon, though without the look or feeling of actual winter as
                the grass &amp; foliage are autumnal, &amp; the cold is not severe yet. Still it
                [is] disagreeable &amp; wet &amp; damp &amp; prevents me from going out. So I will
                make it up by writing a couple of letters—one to mother,<ptr target="loc.01591_n2"/> &amp; one to you,
                telling you about things. Providence is a handsome city of about 70,000
                inhabitants—has numerous manufactories in full operation—every thing
                looks lively. From the house up here, I can hear almost any time, night or day, the
                sound of factory bells &amp; the steam whistles of locomotives half a mile distant.
                Then the lights at night seen from here make a curious exhibition. At both places I
                stop, we have plenty of ripe fresh fruit and lots of flowers. Pete, I could now send
                you a bouquet every morning, far better than I used to, of much choicer flowers. </p>

            <p>And how are you getting along, dearest comrade? I hope you are well, &amp; that every
                thing is going on right with you. I have not heard from you for a good while, it
                    seems.<ptr target="loc.01591_n3"/> I suppose
                you got my last letter, 14th, from N. Y. I expect to return to N. Y. about the 22d.
                Should you feel to write after receiving this, you might direct to 331 East 55th st.
                as before. I am well as usual. I am luxuriating on excellent grapes. I wish I could
                send you a basket. At both places I stop they have vineyards, &amp; the grapes are
                very good &amp; plenty this year. Last night, when I went up at 11 o'clock to my
                room, I took up three great bunches, each as big as my fist, &amp; sat down and eat
                them before I turned in. I like to eat them this way, &amp; it agrees with me. It is
                quite a change here from my associations &amp; surroundings either in Washington or
                New York. Evenings &amp; meal times I find myself thrown amidst a mild, pleasant
                society, really intellectual, composed largely of educated women, some young, some
                not so young, every thing refined &amp; polite, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> disposed
                to small talk, conversing in earnest on profound subjects, but with a moderate
                rather slow tone, &amp; in a kind &amp; conciliatory manner—delighting in this
                sort of conversation, &amp; spending their evenings till late in it. I take a hand
                in, for a change. I find it entertaining, as I say, for novelty's sake, for a week
                or two—but I know very well that would be enough for me. It is all first-rate,
                good &amp; smart, but too constrained &amp; bookish for a free old hawk like me. I
                send you my love, dear Pete. <hi rend="italic">So long</hi>. Will write from N. Y.
                soon as I return there.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">W W</signed>
            </closer>

            <postscript>
                <p>P.S. Just after 12 o'clock—noon—as I am just finishing, the storm
                    lightens up—I am sure I see a bit of blue sky in the clouds—yes,
                    the sun is certainly breaking out. </p>
            </postscript>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>