<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00418">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 19 July 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00418</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">65-67</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 19 July 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-07-19">July 19, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-20">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-07-19">Sunday [July] 19th /63<ptr target="loc.00418_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We have passed through a wonderful week for our New York. A week that I think will eventually be productive of great good to our country, but had at a fearful cost. From my own personal observations I think that the newspapers would give one the most perverted kind of an idea of the riot. The big type, the general "skeery" look of the articles, was something that did not make its appearance on the public face. I guess the only wonderfully frightened men were Opdike and Seymour, if we perhaps except the Copperhead dem.'s that incited the rioters on and then deserted them.<ptr target="loc.00418_n2"/> Opdike though was awfully frightened. In the flashy, sensation style the papers were all far from the truth, ahead, but when it comes to the killed, they are fa[r]ther from the truth, behind. Undoubtedly we shall never know the full number but I have it from the very best authority&#8212;an eye witness of most of the fights, that there are now more than 400 rioters that have paid their lives for their plunder  The papers are not allowed to publish this<ptr target="loc.00418_n3"/>  I suppose it is much better not to let it be known, but the lesson was fearful and thorough to these men. Yesterday I saw them taking coffins out of the shanties on 2nd Av. piling them on carts and driving right to the cemetery  I understand they have been doing this ever since Monday night. The police covered themselves with glory. They certainly made a splendid fight. They deserve great credit. God only knows where the city of New York would have been had we had Wood's police.<ptr target="loc.00418_n4"/> They did well also in Brooklyn. The scoundrels thought to commence operations in Brooklyn, and did set fire to a couple of grain elevators, but the thing has gone no further. I think that rioting in these parts has received its quietus mostly from that Reg of Michigan boys that the War Dept. were kind enough to send us. I hear that they made fearful havoc with the irish ranks. Twas better so&#8212;they did not have that "citizen feeling" that our militia would have had. The only feeling I have is that I fear that they did not kill enough of 'em Walt. I'm perfectly rabid on an Irishman  I hate them worse than I thought I could hate anything. Their conduct for the past week has made me do it. The papers say that the draft is to go on in a day or two in New York &amp; Brooklyn  this is right, I think, and will be a victory over a certain portion of the rebel army. I want, if possible to make a suggestion to this man Fry or whoever has char[g]e of this thing, of a manner in which, I think, the draft can be enforced in these larger cities without endangering riots. My idea is this, to make a certain portion of the city, say certain wards that make a district, not too large, and make the draft, carry the thing out complete, <hi rend="italic">get the men in the field</hi> and every thing done before drafting in any other part of the same city. The advantages, I think, would be these, you could get along with a much smaller police (military) force as their would be no tendency to mob except in the one district, and when (and this I think would be the great point.) you got all through, the men in the field, the remainder of this whole district would be on the side of the draft and would help enforce it in the next, so that in a short time a majority of the city would <hi rend="italic">want</hi> it enforced in the parts where it had not yet been done. The same should be done in Brooklyn  Being the first thing of the kind almost that has ever happened in this country I think a little policy would not come amiss. Another thing I think bad is the publishing of the list of names of the drafted men. This should not be done  I have reasons to suppose that had this not been done in New York they would not have had this organized mob headed by a drafted democratic Alderman<ptr target="loc.00418_n5"/> and a lot of drafted irishman. Would it be possible for you to do anything in this matter. I mean suggest these ideas to those having the matter in charge. It strikes me Walt that if they could be carried out twould save a great deal of innocent blood  I go in for enforcing the draft at all hasards, and that too without giving in the least to the mob, but if a little politician thing of this kind would help, I think it ought to be done. Won't you try to do something about the matter. Of course all that can be done would be to bring it to the notice of the right parties. Twould defeat the entire thing by giving it publicity. My theory is that before the people found out the thing drafting would be over, and like the fellow that had the tooth out when he had taken laughing gas they would think it a good joke</p>
            <p>Yesterdays Herald stated that the 9th Corps were sent in pursuit of Johnson. To-days Times says that they have arrived back in Kentucky. Tis hard to say which is right, perhaps both&#8212;more likely neither.<ptr target="loc.00418_n6"/>&#8212;We want to hear from George much.&#8212;Heard from Han 'tother day. She was getting better. heard through Heyde.&#8212;Abt. the $300. I'm a little afraid that I shant be able to raise it through Mr Lane as he has been a little unfortunate lately, but still I keep a bold front<ptr target="loc.00418_n7"/>  I lately got a position where I am getting $90 per month. (through Mr Lane, Tis on the Water Works)  This will be permanent (as long as Mr Lane is here, perhaps for years.) and with such a certain prospect of paying it back in a few months, I think that George would lend me the money. I, by sailing very close, think I could pay him in five months. Dont you think he would be willing? Walt will you write me at once  I want to hear from you, often. All well at home, first-rate. Hope you will come home soon.</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
