<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03230">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">George Parsons Lathrop to Walt Whitman, 20 April 1878</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>George Parsons Lathrop</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="vm">Vince Moran</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03230</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>George Parsons Lathrop</author>
                    <title>George Parsons Lathrop to Walt Whitman, 20 April 1878</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1878-04-20" xml:id="dat1">April 20, 1878</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Lathrop, George Parsons">George Parsons Lathrop</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-06" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-10-08" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-16" who="#ab">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-06" who="#ej">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-12-03" who="#vm">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03230.001.jpg" type="recto"/><!-- The following note is in Traubel's hand, at the top of the page: <note type="editorial" place="top">See notes Sept 11 1888</note>-->
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">41 Bowdoin St.<ptr target="n0885"/></name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Cambridge, Mass.</name>
                    <date when="1878-12-03" rend="right">April 20. 1878.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I saw Mr. Burroughs<ptr target="n0129"/> in New York, lately, &amp; he encouraged me to believe that I might get from you some news of your new book. I am anxious to see some proofs or early sheets, in order to write an account of it to the London Academy. If it is possible, will you oblige me in this matter?</p>
            
            <p>I have confessed to Burroughs my admiration of the spirit you have breathed into the air, to enlarge &amp; stimulate the after-         
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03230.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            comers, the young writers of America. At times, I have had an intense longing to express my gratitude to you yourself; &amp; it was a sharp disappointment to me that I could not come down to Mrs. Gilchrist's,<ptr target="n0259"/> last summer, with the young Englishman, Carpenter,<ptr target="n0141b"/> to meet you.</p>
            
            <p>But I am not gifted with the faculty of praising. Where I greatly admire I am most likely to be silent; &amp; I never felt it quite the time to speak to you. Well, this time is not come now; it hardly comes at all. The secret of our reluctance to make
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03230.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            acknowledgement to those whom we owe much in the spiritual way is, probably, that we know it is impossible ever to give adequate utterance to such matters; &amp; to speak at all is almost to obscure the sentiment instead of revealing it. If I myself could choose, &amp; had done anything, I would by preference take silent recognition, though personal expression of appreciation is certainly a great balm, at times.</p>
            
            <p>In writing, now, I have another project to advance, besides that of seeing your new book. I am getting up a volume of poems to be published anonymously by Messrs. Roberts Brothers,<ptr target="n0886"/> of Boston. Of course these are of the
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03230.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            older &amp; prevalent fashion. They are by a number of poets, some of whom are very well known. I don't know whether you will feel like participating in this scheme; but there are some advantages about it which may strike you. If they do, I would greatly like to have you send me two or three short pieces with a view to insertion in this book. Owing to the general character of the collection, however, your contribution would have to conform to the more usual rhythms at least as far as "Captain, my Captain!"<ptr target="n0887"/> Have you anything lying by you&#8212;especially of a patriotic tone?</p> 
            <p>There is time enough yet; the copy will not be prepared for the printers until September. But, if you look favorably on the plan, please let me know before long.</p>
           
            <p>Meanwhile, the new book.</p>         
            
            <closer>
                <salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
                <signed>G.P. Lathrop.</signed>
            </closer>
            <!-- The following postscript is on the recto of the first page (nhg) -->
            <postscript><p>I think you have corresponded with Albert Otis, a lawyer of Boston, whom I know. You have more appreciators here than you suspect.</p></postscript>  
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
