<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00789">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 15 September 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00789</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">146-149</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 15 September 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-09-15">September 15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-03">hid self-referencing hyperlink</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-27">proofread and modified; need to return to address query</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-26">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-09-15">September 15 1863<ptr target="loc.00789_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letters were very acceptable&#8212;one came just as I was putting my last in the post office&#8212;I guess they all come right&#8212;I have written to Han &amp; George, &amp; sent George papers&#8212;Mother, have you heard any thing whether the 51st went on with Burnside, or did they remain as a reserve in Kentucky<ptr target="loc.00789_n2"/>&#8212;Burnside has managed splendidly so far, his taking Knoxville &amp; all together, it is a first class success&#8212;I have known Tennessee union men here in hospital, &amp; I understand it therefore&#8212;the region where Knoxville is, is mainly union but the southerners could not exist without it, as it is in their midst&#8212;so they determined to pound &amp; kill &amp; crush out the unionists&#8212;all the savage &amp; monstrous things printed in the papers about their treatment are true, at least that kind of thing is&#8212;as bad as the Irish in the mob treated the poor niggers in New York<ptr target="loc.00789_n3"/>&#8212;we north[erners] dont understand some things about southerners, it is very strange&#8212;the contrast&#8212;if I should pick out the most genuine union men &amp; real patriots I have ever met in all my experience, I should pick out two or three Tennesse &amp; Virginia unionists I have met in the hospitals, wounded or sick&#8212;one young man I guess I have mentioned to you in my letters, John Barker,<ptr target="loc.00789_n4"/> 2d Tennessee Vol. (union)&#8212;was a long while a prisoner in secesh prisons in Georgia, &amp; in Richmond&#8212;three times the devils hung him up by the heels to make him promise to give up his unionism, once he was cut down for dead&#8212;he is a young married man with one child&#8212;his little property destroyed, his wife &amp; child turned out&#8212;he hunted &amp; tormented, &amp; any moment he could have had any thing if he would join the confederacy&#8212;but he was firm as a rock&#8212;he would not even take an oath to not fight for either side&#8212;they held him about 8 months&#8212;then he was very sick, scurvy, &amp; they exchanged him &amp; he came up from Richmond here to hospital, here I got acquainted with him&#8212;he is a large, slow, good natured man (somehow made me often think of father), shrewd, very little to say&#8212;wouldn't talk to any body but me&#8212;his whole thought was to get back &amp; fight, he was not fit to go, but he has gone back to Tennessee&#8212;he spent two days with his wife &amp; young one there &amp; then to his regiment&#8212;he writes to me frequently, &amp; I to him&#8212; he is not fit to soldier, for the rebels have destroyed his health &amp; strength (though he is only 23 or 4), but nothing will keep him from his regiment, &amp; fighting&#8212;he is uneducated, but as sensible a young man as I ever met, &amp; understands the whole question&#8212;well, mother, Jack Barker is the most genuine Union man I have ever yet met&#8212;I asked him once very gravely why he didn't take the southern oath &amp; get his liberty&#8212;if he didn't think it was foolish to be so stiff &amp;c&#8212;I never saw such a look as he gave me, he thought I was in earnest&#8212;the old devil himself couldn't have had put a worse look in his eyes&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, I have no doubt there are quite a good many just such men&#8212;he is now down there with his regiment, (one of his brothers was killed)&#8212;when he fails in strength, he gets the Colonel to detach him to do teamster's duty for a few days, on a march till he recruits his strength&#8212;but he always carries his gun with him&#8212;in a battle he is always in the ranks&#8212;then he is so sensible, such decent manly ways, nothing shallow or mean, (he must have been a giant in health, but now he is weaker, has a cough too)&#8212;Mother, can you wonder at my getting so attached to such men, with such love, especially when they show it to me&#8212;some of them on their dying beds, &amp; in the very hour of death or just the same when they recover, or partially recover&#8212;I never knew what American young men were till I have been in the hospitals&#8212;</p>
            <p>Well, mother, I have got writing on&#8212;there is nothing new with me, just the same old thing&#8212;as I suppose it is with you there&#8212;Mother, how is Andrew, I wish to hear all about him&#8212;I do hope he is better, &amp; that it will not prove any thing so bad&#8212;I will write to him soon myself, but in the mean time you must tell him to not put so much faith in medicine, drugs I mean, as in the true curative things, namely diet &amp; careful habits, breathing good air, &amp;c&#8212;you know I wrote in a former letter<ptr target="loc.00789_n5"/> what is the cause &amp; foundation of the diseases of the throat, &amp; what must be the remedy that goes to the bottom of the thing&#8212;sudden attacks &amp;c are to be treated with applications &amp; medicines, but diseases of a seated character are not to be cured by them, only perhaps a little relieved, (&amp; often aggravated, made firmer)&#8212;</p>
            <p>Dearest mother, I hope you yourself are well, &amp; getting along good&#8212;About the letter in the Times,<ptr target="loc.00789_n6"/> I see ever since I sent it they have been very crowded with news that must be printed&#8212;I think they will give it yet. I hear there is a new paper in Brooklyn,<ptr target="loc.00789_n7"/> or to be one&#8212;I wish Jeff would send me some of the first numbers without fail, &amp; a stray Eagle in same parcel to make up the 4 ounces&#8212;I was glad to hear Mat was going to write me a good long letter&#8212;every letter from home is so good, when one is away&#8212;(I often see the men crying in the hospital when they get a letter)&#8212;Jeff too I want him to write whenever he can, &amp; not forget the new paper&#8212;we are having pleasant weather here, it is such a relief from that awful heat&#8212;(I can't think of another such seige without feeling sick at the thought)&#8212;Mother, I believe I told you I had written to Mrs. Price&#8212;do you see Emma? Are the soldiers still on Fort Greene?<ptr target="loc.00789_n8"/>
            </p>
            <p>Well, mother, I have writ quite a letter&#8212;it is between 2 &amp; 3 o'clock&#8212;I am in Major Hapgood's all alone&#8212;from my window I see all the Potomac, &amp; all around Washington&#8212;Major &amp; all gone down in the Army to pay troops &amp; I keep house&#8212;I am invited to dinner to-day at 4 o'clock at a Mr Boyle's<ptr target="loc.00789_n9"/>&#8212;I am going&#8212;(hope we shall have something good)&#8212;dear Mother, I send you my love, &amp; same to Jeff &amp; Mat &amp; all, not forgetting Mannahatta (who I hope is a help &amp; comfort to her grandmother)&#8212;well I must scratch off in a hurry, for it is nearly a hour later than I thought&#8212;good bye for present, dear mother&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
