<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00819">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 26 April 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00819</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">211&#8211;213</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 26 April 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-04-26">April 26, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2009-09-04">linked to George Washington Whitman's letter of April 16, 1864 (note 2)</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-03">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-03">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1864-04-26">April 26 1864</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Burnside's army passed through here yesterday&#8212;I saw George &amp; walked with him in the regiment for some distance &amp; had quite a talk&#8212;he is very well, he is very much tanned &amp; looks hardy, I told him all the latest news from home&#8212;George stands it very well, &amp; looks &amp; behaves the same good &amp; noble fellow he always was &amp; always will be&#8212;it was on 14th st.&#8212;I watched three hours before the 51st came along&#8212;I joined him just before they came to where the President &amp; Gen Burnside were standing with others on a balcony, &amp; the interest of seeing me &amp;c. made George forget to notice the President &amp; salute him&#8212;he was a little annoyed at forgetting it&#8212;I called his attention to it, but we had passed a little too far on, &amp; George wouldn't turn round even ever so little&#8212;however there was a great many (more than half the army) passed without noticing Mr Lincoln &amp; the others, for there was a great crowd all through the streets, especially here, &amp; the place where the President stood was not conspicuous from the rest&#8212; The 9th Corps made a very fine show indeed&#8212;there were I should think five very full regiments of new black troops under Gen Ferrero,<ptr target="loc.00819_n1"/> they looked &amp; marched very well&#8212;It looked funny to see the President standing with his hat off to them just the same as the rest as they passed by&#8212;then there [were] Michigan regiments, one of them was a reg't of sharpshooters, partly composed of indians&#8212;then there was a pretty strong force of artillery&#8212;&amp; a middling force of cavalry, many New York, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, R[hode] I[sland], &amp;c reg'ts&#8212;all except the blacks were veterans, seen plenty of fighting&#8212;Mother, it is very different to see a real army of fighting men, from one of those shows in Brooklyn, or New York, or on fort Greene&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, it was a curious sight to see these ranks after ranks of our own dearest blood of men, mostly young, march by, worn &amp; sunburnt &amp; sweaty, with well worn clothes &amp; their bundles &amp; knapsacks, tin cups &amp; some with frying pans, strapt over their backs, all dirty &amp; sweaty&#8212;nothing real neat about them except their muskets, but they were all as clean &amp; bright as silver&#8212;they were four or five hours passing along, marching with wide ranks pretty quickly too&#8212;it is a great sight to see such a big Army, 25 or 30,000, on the march&#8212;they are all so gay too, poor fellows&#8212;nothing dampens their spirits&#8212;they all got soaked with rain the night before&#8212;I saw Fred McReady &amp; Capt Sims, &amp; Col LeGendre<ptr target="loc.00819_n2"/> &amp;c&#8212;I dont know exactly where Burnside's army is going&#8212;among other rumors it is said they [are] to go [with] the Army of the Potomac to act as a reserve force, &amp;c&#8212;another is that they are to make a flank march, to go round &amp; get Lee on the side &amp;c&#8212;We know nothing&#8212;I havn't been out this morning &amp; dont know what news, only that there is without doubt to be a terrible campaign here in Virginia this summer, &amp; that all who know deepest about it, are very serious about it&#8212;Mother, it is serious times&#8212;I do not feel to fret or whimper, but in my heart &amp; soul about our country, the army, the forthcoming campaign with all its vicissitudes &amp; the wounded &amp; slain&#8212;I dare say, Mother, I feel the reality more than some because I [am] in the midst of its saddest results so much&#8212;Others may say what they like, I believe in Grant &amp; in Lincoln too&#8212;I think Grant deserves to be trusted, he is working continually&#8212;no one knows his plans, we will only know them when he puts them in operation&#8212;Our Army is very large here in Virginia this spring &amp; they are still pouring in from east &amp; west&#8212;you dont see about it in the papers, but we have very large army here&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, I am first rate in health, thank God, I never was better&#8212;dear mother, have you got all over that distress &amp; sickness in your head? You must write particular about it&#8212;Dear brother Jeff, how are you, &amp; how is Matty?&#8212;&amp; how the dear little girls&#8212;Jeff, I believe the devil is in it about my writing you, I have laid out so many weeks to write you a good long letter, &amp; something has shoved it off each time&#8212;never mind, mother's letters keep you posted&#8212;you must write &amp; don't forget to tell me all about sis, is she as good &amp; interesting as she was six months ago? Mother, have you heard any thing from Han? Mother, I have just had my breakfast, I had it in my room, some hard biscuits warmed on stove, &amp; a first rate bowl of strong tea, with good milk &amp; sugar&#8212;I have given a Michigan soldier<ptr target="loc.00819_n3"/> his breakfast with me, he relished it too, he has just gone&#8212;Mother, I have just heard again that Burnside's troops are to be a reserve to protect Washington, so there may be something in it&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>It is very fine weather here yesterday &amp; to&#8211;day&#8212;the hospitals are very full, they are putting up hundreds of hospital tents&#8212;</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
