<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03510">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Frederick York Powell to Walt Whitman, 1 November
                    1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Frederick York Powell</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03510</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Frederick York Powell</author>
                    <title>Frederick York Powell to Walt Whitman, 1 November 1884</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1884-11-01" xml:id="dat1">November 1, 1884</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 14</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Powell, Frederick York" ref="loc.03510_n1">Frederick York Powell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-05-27" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-25" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-02-14" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-17" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03510.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Christ Church</name>
                    <name type="place">Oxford</name>
                    <date when="1884-11-01">1. 11. 84</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I wish to thank you most heartily for your gift to me which I have just received
                from Mrs Wharton.<ptr target="loc.03510_n2"/> </p>
            <p> I could not have received anything from America which I should prize as I do this
                Volume of the Leaves of Grass. </p>
            <p> Since I first read your poems years ago now they have always had a great influence
                on my thoughts and wishes. I should have liked to <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.03510.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> write to you then, but I did not
                think I had a right to, and I wished to see you and talk to you, but I never had
                the opportunity. Your gift has given me at least the right to thank you now not only
                for it but for the great good I have got form your work. Every man I suppose worries
                out some idea of the right life for himself, but your books have helped me much in
                getting a truer view of things than I started with. I have found out the truth of
                your words too from my short <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03510.003_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> experience of life in deed as well as in thought. You have many
                more worthy listeners but none more gratified than myself. Your Leaves of Grass I
                keep with my Shakespeare and my Bible and it is from these three that I have got
                more sympathy than from any other books. </p>
            <p> I should like to tell you too that you have many more friends here than you can ever
                have heard of by letter or paper, men and women who have got a good hold of your
                poems and their pith. </p>
            <p> If you should ever come to the Old <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03510.004_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> Country how pleased we should be, I wish it may yet be possible
                for you to do so. </p>
            <p> You will not I hope think that I wish to give you the trouble of sending or writing
                any answer to these few lines. I have not written for that at all, but simply
                because I wanted you to know that I am very grateful to you and that I am yours
                faithfully </p>
            <closer>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">FredkYork Powell</hi></signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
