<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00440">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 16 July 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00440</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">113-115</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 16 July 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-07-16">July 16, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-11">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.,</name>
                  <date when="1865-07-16">July 16th 1865</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We duly received your letter<ptr target="loc.00440_n1"/>&#8212;We of course all felt very indignant at the way you had been treated&#8212;but<ptr target="loc.00440_n2"/> when I came to the statement that Harlan was a parson<ptr target="loc.00440_n3"/> of course his conduct was to be expected  From that class you can never get anything but lying and meanness&#8212;I hope you do not allow it to have any effect on you  you must not&#8212;The poor mean-minded man&#8212;If Christ came to earth again and did'nt behave different from what he did when he was here he would have a mighty poor show with Harlan would'nt he&#8212;</p>
            <p>The most outrageous thing was published in the Eagle<ptr target="loc.00440_n4"/>  If you have any curiosity abt it I will send it to you  It was perfectly in keeping with the paper and I'v no doubt was considered a very good thing by little Van<ptr target="loc.00440_n5"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>I see by the papers that the 51st will probably be mustered out in a few days<ptr target="loc.00440_n6"/>  How does George feel about it<ptr target="loc.00440_n7"/> I wonder&#8212;I still think if he wishes he could get in the regular army&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother had yesterday a letter from Heyde&#8212;10 pages&#8212;of the most disgusting trash<ptr target="loc.00440_n8"/>&#8212;the vilest and meanest things that he could get together  He says he shall leave Han, and go out west<ptr target="loc.00440_n9"/>&#8212;I wish he was in Hell&#8212;Mother of course is considerably exercised about it&#8212;and thinks she will go on there and bring Han home&#8212;thinks she will go next week  Of course it is foolish for Mother to attempt any thing of the kind and I dont mean to let her go&#8212;I am in hopes that George will get home next week and then he could go&#8212;I am sure that Mother would never live to get there and back let alone bringing Han&#8212;I read Heyds letter through and it is plain to me that they have had a quarrel abt some women that Heyde had in his room&#8212;they had a big row and Heyde has written to mother while the thing was fresh in his cussed head<ptr target="loc.00440_n10"/>&#8212;I suppose mother will get another letter soon rather taking the edge of[f] of this one&#8212;I've no doubt that Han has a most outrageous existance&#8212;and that she had better leave Heyde but I certainly dont think that Mother&#8212;old as she is can think of going there&#8212;she can hardly move in the morning till she gets some coffee with Mat&#8212;You must write her that she had better not go till George comes home and he can go with her&#8212;or something of that kind&#8212;dont fail to write mother&#8212;</p>
            <p>Everything is going as usual with me&#8212;all keep about the same  Mattie and the children are well  the baby is a little down just now&#8212;but I guess she will be all right again in a few days&#8212;My friend Davis<ptr target="loc.00440_n11"/> has got back from Peru&#8212;he spent 3 or 4 days with me last week&#8212;</p>
            <p>Write to me</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
