<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00396">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 13 January 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00396</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">22-24</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 13 January 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-01-03">January 3, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#nhg" when="2014-09-22">corrected date</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-11">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-25">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
               <opener>
                  <dateline rend="right">
                     <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                     <date when="1863-01-13">Jan 13th 1863</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00396_n1"/> handed me your note yesterday and I enclose the within $6, $5 from myself and $1 from Mother.<ptr target="loc.00396_n2"/> I wish Walt that I could do more and will try to collect a little something. I have made one or two attempts already but failed, entirely. Have you written to any of your driver friends,<ptr target="loc.00396_n3"/> if you could strike them I should think you might get something. Probasco<ptr target="loc.00396_n4"/> sent you $5 yesterday and Mr Lane would have sent you some to-day but I told him that I thought that it would be better for all concerned if we put a little time between the letters. I am in hopes to raise a few dollars more in a week or two which I will send you. I wish you would take either Lane's or Probasco['s] money and keep an exact account of what it does and send them the particulars of just the good it does. I think it would assist them (and the rest of us) in collecting more  You can understand what an effect twould have, twould give us an opportunity to show what immense good a few shillings even will do when rightly applied  besides twould please the person sending the money hugely twould bring his good deeds under his nose</p>
               <p>We have had some two or three letters from Heyde, directed to you. He talks like a d&#8212;m fool. He says that he saw that your feelings and sympathies were excited by the things that you saw and says that he would desire to call them a little nearer home, and then follows a lot of stuff ending with the request that you will come on and get Han and bring her home, as he cant paint. The miserable skunk. I would like to get a fair chance at his ugly mug.<ptr target="loc.00396_n5"/> Mother has written to him that Mat will come on after Han, and we are now waiting a reply. The day after each letter came to you mother would get one from him, stating that he was under the influene of quinine and soda, and that he had boils, on his rump bone, and that his blood was bad (d&#8212;m his blood) and that he couldn't paint) and that charity, public charity, would have to relieve them, and a hell of a lot of other things all <hi rend="italic">meaning</hi> that he wants to shake Han off. Undoubtedly we shall have her home before long. He says she is sick, but I think that if she was she would write home herself. It makes mother feel pretty bad. that combined with all her other troubles, I think, shows on her. She of course is with Mat and I most of the time and we try to make things as pleasant as possible  Ed and Jess are the same as usual</p>
               <p>Mr Lane says that we ought to do something to help you to get a situation there  If we can do any thing in the way of letters let us know. Lane thinks that you might do something with Dana.<ptr target="loc.00396_n6"/> Can you? Did you get the papers that I sent you, I sent 15 copies.<ptr target="loc.00396_n7"/> Walt write me as often as possible as you cannot imagine how interesting they are to me. We all read them, Lane Probasco &amp;c &amp;c. They make us see things through new eyes</p>
               <p>Mother is about as well as usual. Mattie ditto. Sis is growing more interesting than ever, and more mischiefous than the old dickens  she talks of you and Uncle George quite often  Mother and Mat send their love. Mat says she is much obliged for her letter and will answer it herself soon.<ptr target="loc.00396_n8"/> What are you doing and how are you getting along? Things the same as usual with me. Write me soon and often  We had a long letter from George to-day  He says he thinks that he will try for a furlough and that if they wont let him have it that he may resign. I rather think Walt that he is more tired than he lets us know. I wish to God that he would come home, I think that it would add 10 years to Mothers life. Write him. With love from all dear brother  Good night</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>Jeff.</signed>
               </closer>
            
            <postscript>
               <p>P.S. Botsford<ptr target="loc.00396_n9"/> also got his note and will send you something before long. George wrote for $10. which I sent him to-day</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>T. J. Whitman</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
