<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04056">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 2 February 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04056</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">173&#8211;174</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 2 February 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-02-02" xml:id="dat1">February 2, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Herbert">Herbert Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-02" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">New York<ptr target="n0262"/></name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">112 Madison Avenue</name>
                    <date when="1879-01-27" rend="right">February 2nd, 1879.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Darling Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I read your long piece in the Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> with ever so much interest, &#38; with especial delight the delicately told bit about the dear old Pond, artistic, because so true.<ptr target="n3011"/> I know that it will please you to hear that I have gained tenfold facility with my brush since the autumn. It has agreed uncommonly well with me having enlisted under such an experienced &#38; able painter as Chase;<ptr target="n1510"/> as a manipulator of the brush he is agreed by the experts (Eaton)<ptr target="upa.00172_n3"/> to have no rival. I may yet be able to paint a head of you in <hi rend="italic">one</hi> sitting that will do justice to you. Three of my pictures are nicely hung at the Water Colour Exhibition Academy of Design, the first time that I have exhibited in New York. We had two &#38; three engagements every night (with one exception) last week, &#38; go to Mrs. Croley's to-night. Your friend John Burroughs<ptr target="n0129"/> called last Wednesday&#8212;came to try Turkish baths for his malarious trouble, but it seemed to bring on his attacks of neuralgia worse. I am sorry that I can report but poorly of his health, so painfully excruciating was his neuralgia about his arms at times that a Dr. was sent for &#38; morphia injected in his wrist, but I am glad to say he reported himself a little better. He hopes that you will come and give the lecture on Lincoln this winter; why not, confound it, it would be most interesting.</p>

            <p>Quite often we go to Miss Booth's<ptr target="n3017"/> receptions. Saturday evening, they are gay &#38; amusing. Met Mr. Bliss, the gentleman that talked like "a house afire" one Sunday at your house last winter, you remember.</p>
            
            <p>Last Wednesday I, mother, Giddy,<ptr target="n0890"/> &#38; Kate Hillard<ptr target="n0302"/> went to Mrs. Bigelow's<ptr target="n1509"/> reception. Miss H. was asked to recite &#38; she recited the "Swineherd" (<choice><sic>Anderson</sic><corr>Andersen</corr></choice>'s)<ptr target="n0041"/> charmingly, &#38; "The Faithful Lovers," which took every one. "Walk in" Miller<ptr target="n0412"/> was there (I can't spell his name) &#38; lots more.</p>
            
            <p>This morning being Sunday, I took my skates to the Park. The wind was high &#38; whirled us about fantastically; ladies seated in wicker chairs were pushed rapidly along the Pond's smooth icy surface by their gentlemen escorts, tall men kissed the ice or sprawled full length on their backs, while others flew by like swallows; all this with a church spire peeping behind hills dappled with snow &#38; sunshine: what more inspiriting than this?</p>
            
            <p>And now dear Walt.</p>
                     
            <closer>
                <salute>Good-bye for the present.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Herbert H. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
