<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00765">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 31 March 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00765</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">85-87</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 31 March 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-03-31">March 31, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2012-05-22">footnote two revised; see changelog</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-24">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-16">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-03-31">March 31, 1863.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have not heard from George, except a note he wrote me a couple of days after he got back from his furlough&#8212;I think it likely the regiment has gone with its corps to the west, to the Kentucky or Tennessee region <ptr target="loc.00765_n1"/>&#8212;Burnside at last accounts was in Cincinnati&#8212;Well it will be a change for George, if he is out there&#8212;I sent a long letter to Han last Saturday, enclosed George's note to me. Mother, when you or Jeff writes again, tell me if my papers &amp; <hi rend="smallcaps">MSS</hi> are all right&#8212;I should be very sorry indeed if they got scattered, or used up or any thing&#8212;<hi rend="italic">especially</hi> the copy of Leaves of Grass covered in blue paper, and the little MS book "Drum Taps," &amp; the MS tied up in the square, spotted (stone-paper) loose covers&#8212;I want them all carefully kept.</p>
            <p>Mother, it is quite a snow storm here this morning&#8212;the ground is an inch and a half deep with snow&#8212;and it is snowing &amp; drizzling&#8212;but I feel very independent in my stout army-boots, I go any where. I <hi rend="italic">have</hi> felt quite well of my deafness and cold in my head for four days or so, but it is back again bad as ever this morning.</p>
            <p>Dear mother, I wrote the above, in my room&#8212;I have now come down to Major Hapgood's office. I do not find any thing from home, and no particular news in the paper this morning&#8212;no news about the Ninth Army Corps, or where they are. I find a good letter from one of my New York boys, (Fifth Avenue)&#8212;a young fellow named Hugo Fritsch,<ptr target="loc.00765_n2"/> son of the Austrian Consul General&#8212;he writes me a long first-rate letter this morning&#8212;he too speaks about the opera, (like Jeff) he goes there a good deal&#8212;says that Medori,<ptr target="loc.00765_n3"/> the soprano, as Norma, made the greatest success ever seen&#8212;says that the whole company there now, the singers, are very fine&#8212;all this I write for Jeff &amp; Mat&#8212;I hope they will go once in a while when it is convenient&#8212;</p>
            <p>It is a most disagreeable day here, mother, walking poshy and a rain and drizzle&#8212;</p>
            <p>There is nothing new with me&#8212;no particular sight for an office, that I can count on. But I can make enough with the papers, for the present necessities&#8212;I hear that the paymaster, Major Yard,<ptr target="loc.00765_n4"/> that pays the 51st, has gone on West. I suppose to Cincinnati, or wherever the brigade has gone&#8212;of course to pay up&#8212;he pays up to 1st of March&#8212;All the Army is going to be paid up to 1st March every where.</p>    
            <p>Mother, I hope you are well and hearty as usual&#8212;I am so glad you are none of you going to move&#8212;I would like to have the pleasure of Miss Mannahatta Whitman's company, the first fine forenoon, if it were possible&#8212;I think we might have first rate times, for one day at any rate&#8212;I hope she will not forget her Uncle Walt<ptr target="loc.00765_n5"/>&#8212;I received a note from Probasco,<ptr target="loc.00765_n6"/> requesting me not to put his name in my next letter&#8212;I appreciate his motive, and wish to please him always&#8212;but in this matter I shall do what I think appropriate&#8212;Mother, I see some very interesting persons here&#8212;a young master's mate, who was on the Hatteras, when surprised &amp; broadsided by the Alabama, Capt. Semmes<ptr target="loc.00765_n7"/>&#8212;he gave me a very good acc't of it all&#8212;then Capt. Mullin,<ptr target="loc.00765_n8"/> U. S. Army (engineer), who has been six years out in the Rocky Mt's, making a gov't road, 650 miles from Ft. Benton to Walla Walla&#8212;very, very interesting to know such men intimately, and talk freely with them&#8212;Dearest mother, I shall have great yarns to spin, when I come home&#8212;I am not a bit home sick, yet I should [like] to see you &amp; Mat, very very much&#8212;One thinks of the <hi rend="italic">vimmen</hi> when he is away.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Shall send the shirts in a day or two.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
