<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00436">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 7 February 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00436</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">105-107</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 7 February 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-02-07">February 7, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-03">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.,</name>
                  <date when="1865-02-07">Feb 7th 1865</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours received<ptr target="loc.00436_n1"/>&#8212;We are all very joyful over what you wrote in regard to George&#8212;It seemed to put new life in mother&#8212;I went to see the Dr<ptr target="loc.00436_n2"/> to-day&#8212;He said immediately that he would go and see Swinton<ptr target="loc.00436_n3"/> and talk with him about the matter and urge him to write to Gen Grant  The Dr. thinks that Swinton will do it and that Grant will grant the request&#8212;He seemed to feel very sanguine about it&#8212;Oh I so hope that we will prove successful in getting George exchanged</p>
            <p>I was glad to see that Mason<ptr target="loc.00436_n4"/> made a response to your asking him to send supplies to George&#8212;I intend to send a box this week if I can</p>
            <p>The enclosed letter<ptr target="loc.00436_n5"/> came to the house for you  Mother opened it&#8212;I thought I would send it to you and you could tell me if any more of the same style came whether to send them to you or not&#8212;</p>
 
            <p>We are now having quite a snow storm&#8212;it looks as if it would be quite deep&#8212;I am rather sorry to see it for it looks hard for the soilders  I feel disappointed in regard to the peace talks.<ptr target="loc.00436_n6"/> I was in hopes that we had had war enough  It seems almost impossible that the south can keep up the fight much longer&#8212;however I think the president showed a great deal of cuteness in going down to see them and if he only told them that the Union was all he asked [he showed] more statesmanship than I ever gave him credit for  I see that a great many here have not yet given up the idea but what there is something more to come&#8212;the desire for a peace on the basis of the Union alone seems so far as I can see meets with universal applause</p>
            <p>Well Walt so you have gone to keeping house<ptr target="loc.00436_n7"/> have you  You must be car[e]ful or you will get sick again&#8212;I fear you do not live well&#8212;I think the great cause of good health is good eating&#8212;Keep up the supply of good things&#8212;Do you have about the same experience in the Hospitals as you used to&#8212;were the men glad to see you back&#8212;were any remaining that you used to visit  if so I know they were glad to see you&#8212;and it must seem like old times for you to go among them&#8212;Do you see many of the friends that you used to know then&#8212;I suppose you visit the Hospitals once a day&#8212;are there as many in them as there used to be&#8212;I hope not&#8212;tis so long since we have had any very large battles that I should suppose the Hospita[l]s were not full<ptr target="loc.00436_n8"/>
            </p>
            <p>What is it about the Exchange of prisoners&#8212;do you know it looks to me as if they were trying to delay the exchange and yet talk about it as if they were going to do it and wished to do it all the time&#8212;I was very glad to have you write that Hichcock said Butler lied<ptr target="loc.00436_n9"/>&#8212;I thought as much but did not dare to believe it either  I do hope that Grant will make an exchange&#8212;The people seem almost to demand it&#8212;Do talk it up&#8212;Walt&#8212;write it up if you have a chance&#8212;One thing I think I see and that is that whoever does delay it that they are pretty well frightened about it and want to humbug the people with the idea that they are going to exchange at once&#8212;I was almost overjoyed a few nights since to see a dispatch that the President had ordered a complete and general exchange&#8212;but alas it turned out to be nothing</p>
            <p>Mother is quite well&#8212;Mat and the babies are well and all send their love&#8212;the baby often calls "Walt" to come  Write me</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
