<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03043">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 29 May
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03043</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 29 May 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-05-29" xml:id="dat1">May 29, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-14" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-04-25" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-14" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-06" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-14" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03043.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1882-05-29" rend="right">May 29, 1882.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:<!--<ptr target="n2002"/>--></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got your cordial letter of the 25th.<!--<ptr target="loc.03043_n1"/>--> Congratulations and approval, personal and
                from the press, are pouring in upon me, but I shall get nothing worth so much as
                your heartful "God bless you," flashing from
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03043.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     the finale of your postscript.
                Next best, is your admiration of my lightnings. It fills me with measureless content
                to know that what I have written is not merely a success with the public, but with
                <hi rend="underline">you</hi>.</p>
            <p>I had given the letter up and was taken aback by its appearance. Of course, I was
                delighted, for my article puts
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03043.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                     the matter just in the shape I wanted it to appear&#8212;gives us
                the ground to fight <hi rend="underline">from</hi>&#8212;a <hi rend="underline">base</hi> for operations. It
                cost me immense labor, for I had to be very guarded and very bold at once, blending
                composure with fury, and was anxious not to lay myself open to the disingenuous
                enemy. I am satisfied. Let <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03043.006_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> Oliver Stevens and Osgood<!--<ptr target="upa.00201_n2"/>--> get over this if they can. It will
                stick.</p>
            <p>It is probably the beginning of a fight and we will comport ourselves according
                to events. Let Stevens or Marston dare to reply! I will exterminate them. After the
                affair has gone its full length, some of us&#8212;perhaps <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc.03043.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                I&#8212;will have the grand
                closing word, solemn as life, copious as the tempest, in the North American Review.
                Mr. Rice<!--<ptr target="loc.02206_n4"/>--> will give us a hearing.</p>
            <p>The moment I get John Burroughs'<!--<ptr target="n0129"/>--> address abroad, I will mail him a copy of the <hi
                    rend="underline">Tribune</hi>, which I have
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03043.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     reserved for him. I think John
                will be delighted with my sword-play. Besides, I want him to know the facts, so that
                he can fire up the literati abroad.</p>
            <p>I wish the article I wrote for Bucke<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>--> could appear, because a part of it was devoted
                to
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03043.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                the recent
                critiques on your new edition, and every sentence was a blister. I wrote one in
                particular on the Rev. Higginson,<!--<ptr target="nyp.00440_n9"/>--> which I was going to add when Bucke sent me the
                proof, and which will make Higginson wish he was in another and a better world. I have
                not yet found out from Bucke why his book<!--<ptr target="loc.05148_n3"/>--> is delayed.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03043.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>I earnestly hope the matter will bear fruit in your getting another publisher. If
                there is one publisher in this country who has the least sense, he will take
                advantage of the conspicuity the District Attorney has given you, and come forward
                with an offer to publish.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03043.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>&#8212;I had written thus far when your letter of the 28th came, containing the
                article of the Rev. Chadwick<!--<ptr target="nyp.00443_n2"/>--> in the Sunday Tribune, which I had not seen. Of course
                I shall answer this clerical blackguard, who has the audacity to accuse me of
                wilfully and consciously lying, and I shall do my best to answer him with blasting
                effect, but I am truly sorry to have to turn aside to the discussion of veracity
                with such a fly as this. The harm I foresaw from your equivocal statement in the <hi
                    rend="underline">Critic</hi> and The N. A. <hi rend="underline">Review</hi>, <pb
                    xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03043.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/> and of which I
                warned you, has come in this letter of Chadwick's. I feared that the enemy would
                make this use of your language. "Howandiver," as Father Tom says, we must endeavor
                to turn the disaster to the best advantage, and make something by the operation.</p>
            <p>I
                shall certainly try to weave in all the memoranda you send me.</p>
            <p>I had a comforting letter, with yours, from <pb xml:id="leaf006r"
                facs="loc.03043.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/> Whitelaw Reid,<!--<ptr target="n0500"/>--> very cordial
                and friendly, and evidently pleased with me, and the poignant and perfumed little
                note of thanks I sent him after the appearance of my letter. He says: "I took great
                pleasure in printing your letter, because it was so cleverly done, and because
                besides, I could not help having some sympathy with it." I was glad to get this
                letter, for the assurance of innings at the <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> office which it gives me.</p>
            <p>I had a splendid letter from Mr. Walter P. Phillips,<!--<ptr target="n3079"/>--> <pb xml:id="leaf006v"
                    facs="loc.03043.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/> the head of the Associated Press
                here, ranking you among "the greatest of living men" and thanking me, although a
                stranger, for the "taste, eloquence and strength" of my defence. It is very
                consoling, and shows a real gentleman. Doubtless we shall hear much more.</p>
            <p>If we can only send Chadwick to the moon in fragments! My task is to do this, and
                thoroughly, the first time. No after claps. If I fail, his abominable letter will
                give us trouble.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Goodbye</salute>
                <salute>Faithfully,</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03043.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="left"><hi rend="underline">May 29 '82</hi></note>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="inline">see notes Dec 11th 1910</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03043.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
