<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00775">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 7 July 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00775</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">114-116</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 7 July 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-07-07">July 7, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-03-04">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-20">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <date when="1863-07-07">Tuesday afternoon.<ptr target="loc.00775_n1"/>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Mother, it seems to be certain that Meade<ptr target="loc.00775_n2"/> has gained the day, &amp; that the battles there in Pennsylvania have been about as terrible as any in the war&#8212;O what a sight must have been presented by the field of action&#8212;I think the killed &amp; wounded there on both sides were as many as eighteen or twenty thousand&#8212;in one place, four or five acres, there were a thousand dead, at daybreak on Saturday morning&#8212;Mother, one's heart grows sick of war, after all, when you see what it really is&#8212;every once in a while I feel so horrified &amp; disgusted&#8212;it seems to me like a great slaughter-house &amp; the men mutually butchering each other&#8212;then I feel how impossible it appears, again, to retire from this contest, until we have carried our points&#8212;(it is cruel to be so tossed from pillar to post in one's judgment).</p>
            <p>Washington is a pleasant place in some respects&#8212;it has the finest trees, &amp; plenty of them every where, on the streets, &amp; grounds. The Capitol grounds, though small, have the finest cultivated trees I ever see&#8212;there is a great variety, &amp; not one but is in perfect condition&#8212;After I finish this letter I am going out there for an hour's recreation&#8212;The great sights of Washington are the public buildings, the wide streets, the public grounds, the trees, the Smithsonian Institute &amp; grounds&#8212;I go to the latter occasionally&#8212;the Institute is an old fogy concern, but the grounds are fine<ptr target="loc.00775_n3"/>&#8212;Sometimes I go up to Georgetown, about two &amp; a half miles up the Potomac, an old town&#8212;just opposite it in the river is an island, where the niggers have their first Washington reg't encamped&#8212;they make a good show, are often seen in the streets of Washington in squads&#8212;since they have begun to carry arms, the secesh here &amp; in Georgetown (about 3/5ths) are not insulting to them as formerly.</p>
            <p>One of the things here always on the go, is long trains of army wagons&#8212;sometimes they will stream along all day, it almost seems as if there was nothing else but army wagons &amp; ambulances&#8212;they have great camps here in every direction, of army wagons, teamsters, ambulance camps, &amp;c. Some of them are permanent, &amp; have small hospitals&#8212;I go to them, (as no one else goes, ladies would not venture)&#8212;I sometimes have the luck to give some of the drivers a great deal of comfort &amp; help. Indeed, mother, there are camps here of every thing&#8212;I went once or twice to the Contraband Camp,<ptr target="loc.00775_n4"/> to the Hospital, &amp;c. but I could not bring myself to go again&#8212;when I meet black men or boys among my own hospitals, I use them kindly, give them something, &amp;c.&#8212;I believe I told you that I do the same to the wounded rebels, too&#8212;but as there is a limit to one's sinews &amp; endurance &amp; sympathies, &amp;c. I have got in the way after going lightly as it were all through the wards of a hospital, &amp; trying to give a word of cheer, if nothing else, to every one, then confining my special attentions to the few where the investment seems to tell best, &amp; who want it most&#8212;Mother, I have real pride in telling you that I have the consciousness of saving quite a little number of lives by saving them from giving up &amp; being a good deal with them&#8212;the men say it is so, &amp; the doctors say it is so&#8212;&amp; I will candidly confess I can see it is true, though I say it of myself&#8212;I know you will like to hear it, mother, so I tell you&#8212;</p>
            <p>I am finishing this in Major Hapgood's office, about 1 o'clock&#8212;it is pretty warm, but has not cleared off yet&#8212;the trees look so well from where I am, &amp; the Potomac&#8212;it is a noble river&#8212;I see it several miles, &amp; Arlington heights&#8212;Mother, I see some of the 47th Brooklyn every day or two&#8212;the reg't is on the Heights&#8212;back of Arlington House, a fine camp ground&#8212;O, Matty, I have just thought of you&#8212;dear sister, how are you getting along? Jeff, I will write you truly&#8212;Good bye for the present, dearest mother, &amp; all&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
