<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05151">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 26 December
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05151</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 26 December 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-12-26" xml:id="dat1">December 26, 1882</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-10" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-06-03" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-04-29" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-24" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-19" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-12-12" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01037_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww">'82</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1882-12-26" rend="right">Dec. 26.</date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">29 Lange Strasse <lb/>Dresden</name>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Your card of Dec. 10 received<ptr target="n1027"/>&#8212;together with printed sheets
                of L. of G., from which I shall work in future. I have been reading your <hi
                    rend="underline">Specimen Days</hi> with great delight since it came.&#8212;I
                had not seen so strong an utterance as yours <add rend="unmarked"
                    place="supralinear">in S. D.</add> on the subject of Hegel before, though of
                course I conjectured out of the L. of G. that you <del rend="overstrike">had</del>
                appreciated him.<ptr target="loc.05151_n2"/> I have not read anything of the man
                himself yet&#8212;though I find that my reading &#38; thinking for long past has
                been, more or less consciously, of the nature of a gradual investment of his
                stronghold&#8212;preparation for a vigorous attack. You put the gradual but sure
                evolution of good out of evil as his keynote, and that must surely be the keynote of
                any sane philosophy. But what good? and when? and where? For suppose all the good
                    <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">(qu&#226;, moral)</add> imaginable,
                realized in the world, would there not be a blank still&#8212;would we not be
                inclined to say "and is that all"? I don't know whether the difficulty is an
                insurmountable one, but I cannot help feeling that the reign of universal <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01038_large.jpg" type="verso"/> virtue would not
                be any improvement on the present state of things, since so much of the beauty and
                power of virtue is only thinkable when existing in the midst of evil, &#38; seen on
                that background. Here then is a strange frame of mind, yet common to us all&#8212;we
                feel it an imperious duty or a thrilling impulse to take part on the right side in
                the great conflict, and fight therein on the principle of 'No Surrender,' yet we
                think at the same time that the victory we strive for is never to be gained, is not
                even conceiveably gainable. What is the justification of this seeming absurdity! I
                suppose it must be this, that the Good we are really striving for transcends our
                powers of concrete imagination: in the strife we fix our minds on something definite
                and practical &#38; make that our ostensible aim, while really working,
                unconsciously, perhaps, most of us, for a Good not to be expressed in terms of
                practical virtue. What private soldier of Frederick the Great, storming Torgau under
                the fire of 400 cannon, felt&#8212;<hi rend="underline">or if he felt could have
                    articulately said</hi>&#8212;that he was working for that most wonderful
                accomplishment, <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.01039_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                as yet not nearly gauged in its true significance, the establishment of a German
                nation. The ridge of a bushy hill, which he should leave tomorrow, never to see
                again, represented for him that great object.</p>
            <p>Now that I am on speculative matters, I will tell you of an important judgment on
                Darwinism recently delivered by the highest European authority on such subjects,
                viz, Professor Virchow.<ptr target="loc.05151_n3"/> He is a wide minded man, of
                strong character (a leader of the Radical politicians in Germany) &#38; of immense
                knowledge in all domains of science, particularly anthropology. His judgment is that
                of a serious thinker, who will take 20 years to make up his mind rather than say an
                unconsidered word, and he is said to exercise, in scientific matters, a mind of
                absolute impartiality and clearness. Recently then, <add rend="insertion"
                    place="supralinear">some 2 months ago, I think,</add> he has delivered an
                address before the German Anthropological Soc. at Halle, which takes Darwinism as
                its subject, and utters an unqualified condemnation of that theory. He says it is an
                illustration of the pernicious 'Naturphilosophie' which tries to force theories on
                Nature, and supposes that scientific truth can be reached by mere speculation,
                instead of by patiently studying the facts of physical life. When the theory was
                first proposed he was not carried off his feet by the waves of enthusiasm around
                him. He was content to wait, taking the theory for what it was worth, for the proof
                or disproof which the researchers <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc_af.01040_large.jpg" type="verso"/> of the next few decades (dominated
                as they have been by the desire to find facts bearing on that theory) would
                certainly bring. Now he <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">feels
                    himself</add> entitled to say that the proof has not been forthcoming, and the
                disproof has. And he is confirmed by seeing that a perceptible 'disillusionment' has
                already made its appearance among many who were the most vigorous supporters of
                Darwinism. It must be remembered that the 'Darwinism' here sentenced to death is not
                synonymous with evolution. The latter doctrine existed, of course, before
                D.&#8212;he only offered an explanation of it&#8212;&#38; that explanation consisted
                in the putting forward of the <hi rend="underline">merely mechanical law</hi> of
                'Natural Selection of the (physically) Fittest' as the <hi rend="underline"
                    >only</hi> cause needed to explain <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the phenomena
                of organization. This cause does doubtless work, but V. denies that it accounts for
                    <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the facts, and if it does not account for all, it
                is by no means of the importance at first supposed. Such an utterance as this of
                Virchow's ought to go far towards abating the dogmatic intolerance with which most
                Darwinists regard all who refuse to take their doctrine as the central pivot for all
                thinking.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you have already heard of Virchow's speech, in which case, pardon this
                Mittheilung. If you didn't know of it I expected it would interest you.</p>
            <p>I hope you have had a pleasant Christmas and are well.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
                <signed rend="right">T. W. Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
