<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03311">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 7 July 1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03311</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 7 July 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-07-07" xml:id="dat1">July 7, 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-24" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-05-20" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-01" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-02" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-25" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03311.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">59 Cheyne Walk.</name>
                    <name type="place">Chelsea,</name>
                    <name type="place">London, S.W.</name>
                    <date when="1885-07-07">7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July, 1885.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p> More than a month back I addressed a letter to you, which misfortune of one kind or
                another may have overtaken, or which you may not yet have had time or inclination to
                    answer.<ptr target="n6101"/> It was referring to the scheme of a new
                edition of your Poems in England here, but I'm afraid was not clear enough as to the
                rights &amp; reasons of such an edition, or the way it would be carried out. In the
                letter I explained something of <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03311.002_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> this, but not enough; and it was careless of me to do this &amp;
                then expect you to reply to an insufficient proposal, when you must have already
                more to do in this way than can be easily compassed. For fear too that the letter
                never reached you at all, it will be better to state the whole matter afresh. </p>
            <p> A series of poets was last year begun by Walter Scott<ptr target="loc.03311_n2"/> the
                publisher under the occasional editorship of my friend, Joseph Skipsey, poet &amp;
                former coal-miner;<ptr target="loc.03310_n4"/> (I have been a coal-miner&#8212;a
                mining engineer that is&#8212;myself; hence the connection!) and in their list a
                month or two after my arrival in London as a student of life &amp; letters this
                year, I saw rather to my astonishment your name <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc.03311.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> amid the rest, &amp; feeling that
                in some ways I had a special right &amp; knowledge I ventured to write in, offering to
                prepare the <choice>
                    <abbr>vol.</abbr>
                    <expan>volume.</expan>
                </choice> Skipsey's influence did the rest. </p>
            <p> At first it seemed rather out of place to have your work in a series of this kind
                called, rather stupidly, "The Canterbury Poets," and got up in a cheap &amp;
                prettified fashion, with red lines, &amp;c. But afterwards it struck me that there
                might be gain in the end through it. Now I have succeeded in one hope: the
                publishers will give up the red lines &amp; trivial design of cover. Next will be to
                have your Poems issued in a different shape&#8212;quite square I should like to have
                it&#8212;so as to give your long lines full play! And the very <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.03311.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> including of <hi rend="underline"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> in a series like this gives them a chance of reaching people who
                would otherwise never see them. What I&#8212;&amp; many
                young men like me, ardent believers in your poetic initiative&#8212;chiefly feel
                about this is however, that an edition at a price which will put it in the reach of
                the poorest member of the great social democracy is a thing of imperative
                requirement. You know what a fervid stir &amp; impulse forward of Humanity there is
                to-day in certain quarters, and I am sure you will be tremendously glad to help us
                here, in the very camp of the enemy, the stronghold of caste &amp; aristocracy &amp;
                all selfishness between rich &amp; poor! </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03311.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p> Some people want to claim you as the property of a certain literary clique,&#8212;a
                    <hi rend="underline">rara avis</hi>, to be carefully kept out of sight of the
                uneducated mob as not able to understand &amp; appreciate the peculiar qualities of
                your work. This does harm in many ways, &amp; it would be a very good thing to make
                a fair trial of the despised mob. The price of Wilson &amp; McCormick's edition<ptr
                    target="loc.03311_n3"/> &#8212;half-a-guinea&#8212;practically damns the popular
                circulation of the book, &amp; gives colour to the notion of its being a luxury only
                for the rich. What we want then is an edition for the poor, &amp; this proposed one
                at only a shilling would be within reach of every man willing &amp; caring to read. </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03311.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p> I did not know until a week or so back that Wilson &amp; McCormick had any direct
                authorisation for their Ed<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>, or should certainly have
                advised Walter Scott to communicate his intention to them. Now someone has written
                on their behalf resenting&#8212;very naturally&#8212;his appearance in the field.
                But this difficulty might be easily settled by Scott paying, say ten guineas outright
                or a certain royalty per copy, to them on your account, if W. &amp; McC. would not
                like a new contract with you by Scott. The fact of the new proposed ed<hi
                    rend="superscript">n</hi> being one of smaller scope [the <choice>
                    <abbr>vol.</abbr>
                    <expan>volume</expan>
                </choice> would not hold more than &#8532;<hi rend="superscript">rds</hi> of the
                poetry;] would no doubt weigh with them too, reference being clearly made to the
                complete works to which this would serve as a pilot for <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="loc.03311.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> the time being, &amp; increase the
                sale in the end. </p>
            <p> As for my own share, all I really care about is to procure a serviceable popular
                edition, giving all the help an earnest &amp; enthusiastic sympathy can devise. On
                mere literary grounds I have very little claim, but I have a great love &amp; desire
                to help the struggling mass of men, to be a true soldier in "The War of liberation
                of Humanity." I should strive to just say what would best bring your Ideal to the
                hearts of such as the coal-miners &amp; shepherds of the North&#8212;dear friends of
                mine many of them, many consciously, all unconsciously&#8212;and being a young
                man myself to make Leaves of Grass potent for comradeship and chivalry &amp;
                manliness all through in the young men who are in the forefront to-day. <pb
                    xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03311.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> I feel very much
                inclined to say a great deal more about my hopes and ideals, but to-night perhaps it
                is better not. One thing though I must say a word about,&#8212;how much in noblest
                knowledge &amp; inspiration I have to thank you for, in life &amp; religion &amp;
                poetry &amp; manhood, a debt it will not suffice to pay in words at all, but which
                someday you will see, I hope, may be fairly written off the score. Meanwhile,
                receive the greeting of one more follower on this side the Atlantic,&#8212; </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>very earnestly&#8212;</salute>
                <signed>Ernest Rhys.</signed>
            </closer>

            <postscript>
                <p> Any suggestions or directions as to the scheme &amp; scope of the book I will
                    thank you for most heartily, and will furnish fuller details as they are
                    arranged. </p>
            </postscript>

        </body>   
    </text> 
</TEI>
