<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03700">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">W. L. Shoemaker to Walt Whitman, 7 July 1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>W. L. Shoemaker</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt> 
                <idno>loc.03700</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>W. L. Shoemaker</author>
                    <title>W. L. Shoemaker to Walt Whitman, 7 July 1886</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1886-07-07" xml:id="dat1">July 7, 1886</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 15</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>  
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Shoemaker, W. L." ref="n4109">W. L. Shoemaker</persName>
                </person> 
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-28" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-06-26" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-16" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-11-21" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-15" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03700.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date when="1886-07-07">3116 P Street: Georgetown, D.C., July 7. '86.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute> Dear Sir:&#8212; </salute>
                </opener>
                <p> Spending a few weeks in Merchantville, in "the leafy month of June," I took
                    occasion, one bright Sunday morning, to call and pay my respects to you. I had
                    previously, on visiting Philadelphia, two or three times taken the same liberty
                    and enjoyed the same pleasure; once with my friend E. J. Loomis, of the Nautical
                    Almanac Office. For you had yourself, in certain "Messenger Leaves," extended an
                    invitation to persons unknown to you to hail you and exchange a few words with
                    you, if they felt an impulse so to do. </p>
                <p>
                    <q>"Stranger! if you, passing, meet me, and desire to speak to me, why should
                        you not speak to me, why should you not speak to me? And why should I not speak
                        to you?"</q>
                </p>
                <p> Had I received such a Leaf in Washington, years ago, where I often saw you, I
                    think I should have hailed you and wished you w<unclear reason="damage" resp="#smb" cert="high">ell</unclear>, 
                    even in the public street; for I even then desired to speak to you. I remember that once, taking a stroll
                    over the hills beyond the Anacostia, I gathered a small bunch of wild-flowers,
                    and, on returning home, finding you seated in the same car, I was impelled to
                    offer you the little bouquet&#8212;a spontaneous, simple tribute to "the good
                    gray poet"&#8212;which you accepted very courteously, with thanks. </p>
                <p> On my last visit to you, I was glad to see you so, apparently, much better in
                    health than I had anticipated finding you. Though you expressed yourself as
                    calmly and patiently awaiting the summons to "emigrate" into the great Unknown,
                    I hope that the summons may be deferred for may years to come, and that, daring
                    them, such vigor of mind and body may remain to you as that life be not a burthen. </p>
                <p> I promised to send you an epigram which on a certain occurrence in 1882&#8212;a
                    proceeding disgraceful to one of These States&#8212;my indignation impelled me
                    to pen. I gave a copy of it to your valorous champion, O'Connor,<ptr target="n2002"/> but I do not
                    know whether he ever sent it to you. </p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03700.003_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

                <p> I have a dim remembrance that I also sent it to <hi rend="underline">Puck</hi>,
                    with a clipping from the <hi rend="underline">Evening Star</hi>. I do not think,
                    however, that it was ever printed. It may perchance amuse you. At any rate I
                    have promised to let you have it, and you will find it transcribed herein. </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I remain, my dear <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ss" cert="high">S</unclear>ir,</salute>
                    <salute>very truly, your friend, (if you allow me to call you so,)</salute>
                    <signed><gap reason="damage" quantity="1" unit="char"/> L. Shoemaker.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03700.002_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <head rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">Epigram.</hi></head>
                <lg>
                    <l>On the attempted Suppression</l>
                    <l>of "an American, one of the Roughs, a Kosmos,"</l>
                    <l>and "Yawped over the roofs of the world."</l>
                    <l><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/></l>
                    <l>To the District Attorney for Suffolk County, Mass.</l>
                    <l><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/></l>
                    <l>'Tis a most rema<unclear reason="damage" resp="#smb" cert="high">rk</unclear>able want of wit, man&#8212;</l>
                    <l>The attempt to put down the poet Whitman.</l>
                    <l>An attempt to suppress an attorney were better,</l>
                    <l>Who thinks the free flight of the soul to fetter.</l>
                    <l>Your essay is doomed to ignoble miscarriage.</l>
                    <l>An effort to quell youth, love, courtship, and marriage,</l>
                    <l>Would be quite as wise. Now, by way of variety,</l>
                    <l>Just try it yourself, with you dainty Society;&#42;</l>
                    <l>And if you should fail, an absurder sch<unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="high">oo</unclear> quit, man:&#8212;</l>
                    <l>What! chain up winged speech, and bold song, and staunch Whitman?</l>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared"/>
                    <l>Arrest, if you can, from a bow shot, an arrow,</l>
                    <l>And confine and hold steam in a compass to narrow,</l>
                    <l>Then thought-check, when once it is printed on paper.</l>
                    <l>Far more strong than shot shaft or mere watery vapor,</l>
                    <l>Is thought: and when that has set out on its journey,</l>
                    <l>It <choice><abbr>ne'er</abbr><expan>never</expan></choice> can be stopped by a District Attorney.</l>
                </lg>
               
                <p> <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-left"/></p> 
                    <p>&#42;The Society for the Suppression of Vice, (a Society no <gap
                        reason="illegible" quantity="2" unit="char"/> quite indispensable in
                    Massachusetts.) </p>
              <p><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-left"/></p>
                <signed>W. L. Shoemaker.</signed>
                <dateline>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Georgetown, D.C.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <date when="1882-06-12">June 12, 1882.</date>
                  </dateline>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/></p> 
                    <p>Transcribed for Walt Whitman</p>
                    <p>July 7,1886</p>
                <signed>W.L.S.</signed></postscript>
                <postscript>
            <p>
             <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/></p>
                </postscript>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03700.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="right">WL Shoemaker</note>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
