<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00403">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 21 March 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00403</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">36&#8211;40</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 21 March 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-03-21">March 21, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-24">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-03-21">March 21st 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have not written to you for the last day or two thinking that I would wait till I could send the prints that you wanted,<ptr target="loc.00403_n2"/> and I also wanted to send a large picture of George with them. Harrison<ptr target="loc.00403_n3"/> promised me them to-day and upon calling he told me that he had spoiled the large ones in the printing. However I got a dozen of the kind (I send you a specimen) and I think it's good, dont you  I shall get the large ones by the middle of next week and I will send you one immediately. I wish you could have been home when George was here, 'twas a great pleasure to be with him. I'm sure he enjoyed himself well and I know that we all did. The bundle of shirts &amp;c that you sent to him were first rate and although we had hard work to make him take them all yet I packed them all in his "traps" almost without his knowing it. By the way Walt in regard to those wollen shirts that I sent down to George by you I am real sorry that I did not know that you or he was not using them for I have wanted them pretty bad myself and should have got you to send them to me before. They were all that I had and I had wore them up to the time that you went away. If you do not use them, and you dont think George will want them for the present, (my reason for thinking that George will not want [them] is that we had such hard work to get him to take all that you sent him) I wish you would send them back to me. Understand me Walt, if you do not use them yourself  if you do, why they will do me as much good as if I had them  In regard to moving, I have given up all ideas of building for the present. I had several bids on the plan for a little house that I had made and they wanted 22 &amp; 23. hundred dollars to build it, so I caved. Things go along with me about as usual. Everything in the way of eating and wearing is awful high, but I manage to make enough to keep my head above water yet. I think (am quite confident) that I shall manage to hold on to the lot without trouble and if I do shall be perfectly satisfied. Undoubtedly we shall all live right along just the same as usual, Browns<ptr target="loc.00403_n4"/> and all.</p>
         <p>I have been quite often lately to the <hi rend="italic">Opera</hi>  Rather queer and expensive for these hard times aint it? But I take a small dose every time (25 or 50¢ worth)  Walt I wish you could hear a man that is singing here by the name of Bellini.<ptr target="loc.00403_n5"/> He plays the same parts that Amodio used to but possesses the (to me) most wonderful voice, with the single exception of Bertina<ptr target="loc.00403_n6"/> (of old) that I ever heard  He is in looks and acting almost a likeness of Bertina [(]the tenor whom we used to admire so much) and indeed his voice is almost the same, just a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> lower, but fully having all those wonderful qualities of pathos and feeling  He certianly would carry you back to the old Castle Garden and Bertina singing "Spirit O'Gentil"<ptr target="loc.00403_n7"/>  The tenor (Mazzoleni) is excedingly good. An immense <hi rend="italic">quantity</hi> of rather an unfa[i]ling voice, with a little overdosing the action, and a constant "tremolo" (rather of the hand organ style) but after all <hi rend="italic">good</hi> and following on the heels of Brignoli, who has by not singing when advertised and cutting the work, and lazy action, he has made an immense success in New York  The woman<ptr target="loc.00403_n8"/> is just the same, only a little more so, and they both make an immense point in letting themselves out in all the choruses, more so than I ever heard before. In Verdi's<ptr target="loc.00403_n9"/> music it is wonderfully grand  I most particularly hope you will hear Bellini.<ptr target="loc.00403_n100"/>
         </p>
            <p>Monday Morning&#8212;At the same time that I mail this I also mail the bundle of Engravings and papers directed as usual.<ptr target="loc.00403_n10"/> We are all well and jolly as usual. We are having glorious spring weather and sissy wants to know if I wont write and tell Uncle Walt to come home and take her out on Fort Green<ptr target="loc.00403_n11"/>  I took her out yesterday P. M. and after walking around a while took the car and went over to New York, returning she walked from the ferry all the way home. Good for less than a 3 year old wasn't it? Let me hear from you soon. All send their love,</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>&#8212;Affectionately Brother Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
