<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03351">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William Harrison Riley to Walt Whitman, 5 March 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William Harrison Riley</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03351</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>           
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William Harrison Riley</author>
                    <title>William Harrison Riley to Walt Whitman, 5 March 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-03-05" xml:id="dat1">March 5, 1879</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Riley, William Harrison">William Harrison Riley</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-01-05" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-07" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-06" who="#ak">corrected transcription and encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-10-06" who="#no">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03351.001.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">St. George's Farm, Totley, near Sheffield <lb/> England,</name>
                    <date when="1879-03-05">5.3.79.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Friend and Master,</salute>
                
            </opener>
            <p>About twelve years since, I was in Boston and looking at the books of an old book-stall in a passage of Washington St. when I saw your "Leaves of Grass", opened the book, and saw <hi rend="underline">a Revelation</hi>. I was 'poor', the book was 'expensive', but I felt that whatever the 'cost' I must <choice><sic>posses</sic><corr>possess</corr></choice> it. No words will serve to indicate the value your living words have been to me. In all my troubles and successes I have been strengthened by
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03351.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                your divine teachings. You are not only inspired yourself, but you inspire others. Though most of the people I have read extracts, or lent your book, to have utterly failed to appreciate you, I have never faltered in my faith and love, and have always esteemed you as the Messenger of this age. (My <hi rend="underline">words</hi> seem utterly paltry and drivelling, and I am thoroughly ashamed of them. But you know what I desire to utter.)</p>
            <p>A few years since, I

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03351.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            met a lady, named Miss Bernard, in London. She was from Washington, and was personally acquainted with you, and she promised to send me your photograph. I have never received it, and wish <hi rend="underline">you</hi> to send it, and also to send me, <hi rend="underline">if you can</hi>, a copy of your <hi rend="underline">original edition</hi> of 'Leaves of Grass'. (I lent mine, and it was <hi rend="underline">lost</hi>, and the copy I now have is dated 1872&#8212;and includes additional poems)</p>
            <p>You will know of John Ruskin,&#8212;'Professor Ruskin'. He is indeed a Master,
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03351.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                and a Man eminently Just and Brave. He is an inspired Man, and his utterances are always classical, and mostly divine. A few days ago I sent a few extracts of your poems to him, and&#8212;though he was ill&#8212;he at once answered as follows:&#8212;</p>
            
            <q who="John Ruskin">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <opener>
                            <salute>'Dear Riley</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>These are quite glorious things you have sent me.<ptr target="loc.03351_n1"/> Who <hi rend="underline">is</hi> Walt (Walter?) Whitman, and is much of him like this!</p>
            
                        <closer>
                            <salute>Ever gratefully yours</salute>
            
                            <signed>J Ruskin'</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            
            <p>Please know that Ruskin is esteemed as the greatest critic
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03351.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
            of scripture, sculpture, and painting that we have any knowledge of, and that he is extremely careful not to use adjectives unsuitably. He writes 'glorious', and, by that, means <hi rend="underline">really</hi> the utmost degree of excellence. I never knew him use the word before, except as describing some scenery or valorous action. It is <hi rend="underline">very seldom indeed</hi> that he has used the word&#8212;though his 'works' are so many that a complete set costs about &#163;120. The book and photograph I wish to forward to Ruskin. The money cost shall be remitted&#8212;by or for him. He will be greatly pleased
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03351.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                to receive (and thank you for) your kind acquiescence to this request.</p>
            
            <p>As for <hi rend="underline">myself</hi>&#8212;since I read your book I have been striving to work as a good Pupil and Companion. You have sent me through poverty and many cruel tribulations, but I have never whined over my work. I joined the 'International' and published and 
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03351.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                edited the only paper it has had in England. I stuck to it, while I had 'a shot in the locker' and never once was tempted to utter a cowardly, sneaking, or treacherous word. Out of the strife, through the poverty, and despite the offers of bribes, and attempts to intimidate I came out clean handed and clean hearted&#8212;always supported by your great teachings.</p>
      
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03351.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>My dear Master&#8212;<hi rend="underline">do</hi> write to me&#8212;your faithful pupil and lover. My <hi rend="underline">words</hi> will not prove my love, but could you have seen my <hi rend="underline">work</hi> since I first read your divine Message&#8212;you would <hi rend="underline">know</hi> I loved you, and that you had gained one more loving soldier for your campaign.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>William Harrison Riley</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03351.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03351.010.jpg" type="verso"/>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
