<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01819">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 19 October
               1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
               Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.01819</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
                  the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                  copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce
                  the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals
                  for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
               <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 19 October 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-10-19">October 19, 1865</date>
               <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                  Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n4992">William D. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2015-06-14" who="#ss">annotated</change>
         <change who="#kmp" when="2015-05-14">blessed</change>
         <change who="#nhg" when="2015-01-28">corrected image names, transcription</change>
         <change who="#ak" when="2015-01-16">added images, corrected transcription, removed
            biblStruct</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2011-10-27">updated archive id</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-11">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-17">annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-17">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
         <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03023.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <div1 type="section">
            <opener rend="right">
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">New Ipswich</name>
                  <name type="place">New Hampshire.</name>
                  <date when="1865-10-19">October 19, 1865.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The article you sent Nelly<ptr target="loc.01819_n3"/> from the London Leader is in
               my possession. Good! I shall incorporate it. Part of it is very fine.</p>
            <p>I wonder if young William Allingham wrote it.<ptr target="loc.01819_n4"/> The Leader
               is the paper he is on. He is a poet, you remember&#8212;one of the most promising of
               the young British choir. He is an Irishman <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                  facs="loc.03023.002.jpg" type="verso"/>and a reverent lover of Emerson's genius. I
               shouldn't wonder if he wrote this critique.</p>
            <p>Anyhow it's good and I shall put a great deal of it in.</p>
            <p>If, ever since I have been here, I had not had the worst cold I ever had in my
               life&#8212;a cold which has made me really sick and spoiled the pleasure of my
               visit&#8212;I should doubtless have ere this sent off the <hi rend="underline"
                  >MS</hi> to Curtis.<ptr target="loc.01819_n5"/> It will probably go soon. It is
               just as well and even better that I have delayed it, for <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                  facs="loc.03023.003.jpg" type="recto"/>in the first place it will be enriched with
               this quotation and besides you will like it better by the excision of nearly all the
               personality, new light having come to me on this point as time has passed and the
               sweet country air and relief from labor cleared and refreshed my poor boiled
               brains.</p>
            <p>On my way through New York I enquired at <hi rend="underline">Harpers</hi> for Curtis
               and found he was out of town. So I brought the <hi rend="underline">MS</hi> with me
               up here. Then came Curtis' answer; of which I <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                  facs="loc.03023.004.jpg" type="verso"/>send you a copy that you may see how true
               the reply this splendid gentleman and noble heart sends back to my call.</p>
            <p>I really did not expect so much from Curtis. I relied on his literary chivalry, but
               did not look for the rest. As George would say, he has "elements."</p>
            <p>I have written to him saying that I want him to endeavor to find me a publisher and
               mentioning Hurd &amp; Houghton: also saying that in a few days I shall send him the
                  <hi rend="underline">MS</hi>.</p>
            <p>I wish you could come <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03023.005.jpg" type="recto"/>up
               here. The landscape is exquisite. Fields, farms, the quiet rustic town, the gorgeous
               foliage, the Temple and Peterboro' hills enclosing all. And then, drive out a few
               miles and lo! Monadnoc! O Walt, what a sight! A purple breadth of mountain, spreading
               calm in sleepy light and filling the landscape with grandeur. It is the finest
               mountain I have seen. Its characteristic is breadth.</p>
            <p>I am staying here <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03023.006.jpg" type="verso"/>at the
               house of Miss Jenny Bullard, a friend of whom I believe I have spoken to you.<ptr
                  target="loc.01819_n6"/> I wish you knew her. You would like her. She is handsome,
               bountiful, generous, cordial, strong, careless, laughing, large, regardless of dress
               or personal appearance, and appreciates or likes <hi rend="underline">Leaves of
                  Grass</hi>. The first thing she read in the book was <hi rend="underline">Enfans
                  d'Adam</hi>, which she cordially liked and wondered how anyone could mistake its
               atmosphere and purport. She is a very particular friend <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                  facs="loc.03023.007.jpg" type="recto"/>of mine. I wish you knew her. She told me
               today that she wanted me to invite you to come up here for a few days before I go,
               but I said I wouldn't because I knew you wouldn't come.</p>
            <p>I shall probably leave here about the twenty fifth and go to Boston. Then, home.</p>
            <p>Spite of dear friends and respite from the treadmill and the superb October scenery,
               I have had considerably of a bad time, chiefly owing to the horrible cold I have had
               and <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03023.008.jpg" type="verso"/>the weary state I
               have been in. But I am better now and the world looks brighter.</p>
            <p>Now I hope to be able to announce to you that the <hi rend="underline">MS</hi> has a
               publisher. But oh, Walt, the literary shortcomings of it oppress me. It is not the
               thing that should be said of your book&#8212;not the thing that it is in even me to
               say,&#8212;as I feel.&#8212;However.</p>
            <p>Good bye. I will write you again.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Your faithful</salute>
               <signed>W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div1>

         <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03024.001.jpg" type="recto"/>

         <div1 type="section">
            <note type="authorial" place="top">(Copy.)</note>
            <opener rend="right">
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Ashfield, Mass.</name>
                  <date when="1865-09-30">30 Sept. 1865.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear O'Connor:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Here, up among the Autumn hills, I get your interesting letter of the 20th and you
               may be very sure that I will do all I can to redress the wrong of which you
               speak.</p>
            <p>The task you undertake is not easy, as you know. The public sympathy will be with the
               Secretary for removing a man who will be considered an obscene author and a free
               lover. But your hearty vindication <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03024.002.jpg"
                  type="verso"/>of free letters will not be the less welcome to all liberal men.</p>
            <p>Personally I do not know Whitman; and while his "Leaves of Grass" impressed me less
               than it impressed many better men than I, I have never heard anything of him but what
               was noble nor believed anything of him but what was honorable. That a man should be
               expelled from Office and held up to public contumely, because of an honest book which
               no candid mind can truly regard as hurtful to public morality, <pb xml:id="leaf006r"
                  facs="loc.03024.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
               <hi rend="underline">is</hi> an offence which demands exposure and censure.</p>
            <p>I know Carleton but he has several times asked of me favors which I could not grant
               and I do not believe your offer would be strengthened if made through me.<ptr
                  target="loc.01819_n7"/> If you think otherwise, I shall most cheerfully go to
               him,&#8212;but would it not be better for you to write to him and refer him to me,
               saying, if you choose, that you had asked me to call upon him? Think of it and let me
               know.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03024.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>It was very pleasant to see your comely chirography again, altho' I wish I could
               think of you as having had some vacation. We have been here for two months, far from
               railroads, telegraphs and gossip and are just going home. My wife returns your
               friendly remembrance and yours, I hope, has not forgotten me. I should be glad, too,
               if I thought you felt as cheerfully as I feel at the real gain in the Good Fight made
               by the war. Andy may Tylerize, but the country will not. The wave may be lower, but
               the tide is rising.</p>
            <p>Good bye. Let me hear as soon as you will. You <pb xml:id="leaf007r"
                  facs="loc.03024.005.jpg" type="recto"/>know how gladly I shall serve you and how
               truly I am</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Your friend</salute>
               <signed>G. W. Curtis.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03024.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
         </div1>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
