<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00586">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Silas S. Soule to Walt Whitman, 8 January 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Silas S. Soule</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00586</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">187</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Silas S. Soule</author>
               <title>Silas S. Soule to Walt Whitman, 8 January 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-01-08">January 8, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Soule, Silas S.">Silas S. Soule</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-20">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#bbb" when="2008-07-20">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-07">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> 
</dateline>
               <salute>Friend Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Perhaps you have forgotten a wild farmer scarecrow and man who used to linger around Thayer &amp; Eldridge Publishers office Boston in the spring of 1860. But he still remembers you and has been waiting very patiently for a volume of Leaves of Grass which was to be sent to Lawrence Kansas. Perhaps you think I<ptr target="loc.00586_n100"/> am writing rather familiar for almost a stranger and writing to a distinguished poet but I think I have made a sufficient appology and I tell you I have been in the Rocky Mountains for almost two years where every man is an old acquaintance if you never saw him before.</p>
            <p>When I left Boston I went to Kansas and from there out here among Grizzly bears, Indians, Yankees and almost every other species of man and beast that inhabit the globe. I have lived on venison and I have lived on bread I have gone hungry for many a day and have had plenty to eat for many more, and for all the hard life I have seen it suits me   I like it   I enjoy myself hugely and I think you would do the same.</p>
            <p>I now hold the position of Ist Lieut of Co K Ist Reg Col[orado] Vols.<ptr target="loc.00586_n2"/> I suppose I shall be soldier for the next few years.</p>
            <p>I have often heard Leaves of Grass highly spoken of away out here but have never seen a volume and a few days ago the man who has that will not dispose of that possession he brought out with him to this country.</p>
            <p>I am in an old dog shanty to night away up in the mountains about forty miles from the valley the wind blows a perfect hurricane and it is cold as Greenland. I am writing by the light of a pitch fire for it is past twelve oclock and I must go to bed as I must march for the valley in the morning &amp; dont want you to forget to do this. Good night.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Yours &amp;c</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
