<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00438">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 14 May 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00438</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">109-111</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 14 May 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-05-14">May 14, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-09">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.,</name>
                  <date when="1865-05-14">May 14th 1865</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your letter<ptr target="loc.00438_n1"/> in due time. I am indeed glad to hear that you are so well and get along so nicely&#8212;We are all well as usual&#8212;and time slides along as usual&#8212;a day or two ago I to[ok] Mat and Hattie out on the line for a ride&#8212;very pleasant&#8212;and Mother said the little one was as good as she could be&#8212;indeed I think Mother rather likes to have her all to herself&#8212;When you come on again we must certainly take a ride or two out&#8212;The country looks splendid&#8212;everything is growing as finely as can be</p>
            <p>We had a letter from George a few days ago&#8212;Mother tells me that George is wanting to get a position as Captain in the regular Army&#8212;I have though[t] considerably about it and have made up my mind if we all go to work it could be done quite easy<ptr target="loc.00438_n2"/>&#8212;Jule Mason<ptr target="loc.00438_n3"/> was at my house yesterday and I had a long talk with him about it&#8212;he said that just now there was no way&#8212;as the regulations only admitted officers that had graduated at some military school&#8212;but said that undoubtedly that in a very short time that objection would be removed&#8212;he said that he could help us in the matter a good deal and would do all in his power with pleasure&#8212;he said he (George) ought to go about it at once by getting a <hi rend="italic">good first</hi>class endorsement from the officers he had served under&#8212;all that he could&#8212;and then bring what ever other influence he could on the Sec of War and Gen Grant&#8212;He said in his duties he was brought sometimes (quite often) in such intercourse with Gen Grant that he could (and it would come in good too&#8212;not far-fetched) speak a recommendation for George  I spoke with Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00438_n4"/> and he said that he knew very intimately the new senator from California (Bidwell)<ptr target="loc.00438_n5"/> and that he was certain he could get him to give his influence to the thing and would willingly do anything in his power&#8212;And then there is John Swinton<ptr target="loc.00438_n6"/> I am sure he would help&#8212;perhaps by writing a letter to Stanton<ptr target="loc.00438_n7"/>&#8212;and we ourselves could get Congress man Bergen<ptr target="loc.00438_n8"/> to aid the matter&#8212;thinking it all over I am sure that if the restriction prescribing those not educated in a military school is removed George can get the same position in the regular army that he now has&#8212;but for God-sake dont let him think of enlisting in the army with the expectation of being promoted  that is too dangerous&#8212;Will you give the matter some attention and see how the matter stands&#8212;Mason is stationed in Washingt[on]  hunt him up and talk the matter over&#8212;he can and will help us if we will only make the effort</p>
            <p>I am going to try all in my power to come on to Washington at the time of the review<ptr target="loc.00438_n9"/>&#8212;if I can possibly leave I shall come&#8212;I want very much to see something that will make me remember the war&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother received a letter from you Friday<ptr target="loc.00438_n10"/>&#8212;I heard that Worthen<ptr target="loc.00438_n11"/> had sent a letter to you containing $25. did you get it? When you see George give my love to him&#8212;talk over the matter that I have written abt. and see what he thinks of it. All send their love</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
