<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00948">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 17 October 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00948</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 17 October 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-10-17">October 17, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">added encoding for page breaks</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-17">annotations</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00948.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Washington.</name>
                  <date when="1865-10-17">Oct. 17/65. Tuesday.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I was very glad to hear from you.<ptr target="loc.00948_n100"/> The letter came promptly last Friday with one from Wm. &amp; I wrote him yesterday, &amp; sent the book review. I think it is an admirable criticism, almost the best of Leaves of Grass that I have ever seen.</p>
            <p>William tells me that in the letter Curtis promises to do all he can, &amp; is very much interested, but most likely he has written you all about it.<ptr target="loc.00948_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>How comes on Drum Taps? <pb facs="loc.00948.002.jpg" type="verso"/>How is the little girl? I was more pained than I can tell you to learn that she was ill, and with one of those dreadful fevers. The poor little thing! Isn't it s pitiful thing to see a child sick? To me far more appealing than the sickness of a grown person.</p>
            <p>The critical time was Sunday last you said, now it is Tuesday, I hope she is better. Try to send me a line to say how she is.</p>
            <p>I am sorry for your sake, dear Walt, <pb facs="loc.00948.003.jpg" type="recto"/>that your mother is away. I know how you would miss her. But perhaps by this time you have gone for her. I hope you will go, &amp; will have a pleasant journey and visit.</p>
            <p>I have delayed writing that I might give you the latest news of Mrs. Ashton &amp; baby, but Charley went in there &amp; Ashton had gone home to see them.<ptr target="loc.00948_n3"/> Speed had returned, I think he was gone for a week. Mr. Pleasants said they were well when Ashton left for Philadelphia.<ptr target="loc.00948_n4"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00948.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </p>
            <p>We miss you and William <hi rend="italic">immensely,</hi> Charley &amp; I speak of you daily.</p>
            <p>Miss Howard's sister Sallie is very sick, I think typhoid fever, &amp; I have been out to-day trying to get a nurse for her.<ptr target="loc.00948_n5"/> So far Garaphelia has taken care of her night &amp; day, &amp; she looks worn out.</p>
            <p>We are well, so is Charley. Jeannie sends love. She was very sorry &amp; sympathizing about little California. I trust the little thing is better.</p>
            <p>My sister Jeannie's little Mary is very sick with typhoid <pb facs="loc.00948.005.jpg" type="reco"/>fever too, but they hope not dangerously so.</p>
            <p>We shall be glad to welcome you back, but while you are away I hope you will have a good time, &amp; get very well.</p>
            <p>Good by.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With love always</salute>
               <signed>Nelly.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
