<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05584">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Alfred Janson Bloor to Walt Whitman, 7 June
                    1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Alfred Janson Bloor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05584</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine> 
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Alfred Janson Bloor</author>
                    <title>Alfred Janson Bloor to Walt Whitman, 7 June 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-06-07" xml:id="dat1">June 7, 1879</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 3-4 Reel 2-3</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Bloor, Alfred Janson">Alfred Janson Bloor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-13" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-08-04" who="#ss">checked, corrected, annotated</change>
            <change when="2014-07-23" who="#bbb">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_ej.00611_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="center">
                    <name type="place">New York</name>
                    <date when="1879-06-07">7th June 1879</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
 
            <p>My recollection of what Miss &#8212; told me on the Friday evening,<ptr
                    target="med.00639_n2"/> just one week after President Lincoln's murder, and of
                the diagram she took out of her pocket in illustration, is as follows:<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05584_n1"/>--></p>

            <p>The <choice>
                    <orig>Pres<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></orig>
                    <reg>President</reg>
                </choice> &amp; Mrs. Lincoln called for her &#38; her escort at the house of her
                father, Senator &#8212;, on their way to Ford's Theatre. As the four drove thither, Miss
                &#8212; was struck, she said, with the uncommon hilarity of the <choice>
                    <orig>Pres<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></orig><reg>President</reg></choice>. He laughed &#38; joked &#38; was evidently bent on having a jolly
                evening. On getting to the theatre, and after some preliminaries as to position for
                the chairs, the party was finally arranged as shown on the diagram.<ptr target="loc.05584_n1"/></p>

            <!--<list>
                <item><space dim="horizontal"/> Theatre Box<ptr target="loc.05584_n2"/>
                    <space dim="horizontal"/><space dim="horizontal"/>1. <choice>
                        <orig>Pres<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></orig>
                        <reg>President</reg>
                    </choice> Lincoln 2. Mrs. Lincoln.</item>
                <item/>
                <item><space dim="horizontal"/>(4)(3)<space dim="horizontal"/>(1)(2)<space
                        dim="horizontal"/>3. Miss __ 4. Major __</item>
                <item/>

            </list> I opted to add this information as a note; it doesn't display particularly well as a list.-->


            <p>The play was "Our American Cousin." I do not remember whether <choice>
                    <sic>Sothern</sic>
                    <corr>Southern</corr>
                </choice> was in it or not, but I recollect she said Miss Laura Keene was. I knew
                the play very well, &#38; recollect asking Miss &#8212; at what point in it the tragedy
                occurred, but her answer has escaped my memory. Mr. Lincoln laughed heartily at the
                comical situations &#38; dialogue of the play, and paid close attention to it (as he
                always did when I had an opportunity of seeing him at the theatre. Senator Sumner
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_ej.00612_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_ej.00613_large.jpg" type="recto"/> told once me that in a conversation the
                day before with Mr Lincoln, the latter had defended the <choice>
                    <sic>practise</sic>
                    <corr>practice</corr>
                </choice> of habitual joking, and said that if he had not the opportunity to get out
                of himself by jests and an occasional visit to the theatre, he thought he should go
                crazy.)</p>

            <p>Miss &#8212;<ptr target="loc.05584_n2"/> was leaning forward, she said, to catch some
                by-play that was going on at the back of the stage when suddenly she heard a pistol
                shot, and felt the odor of gunpowder. She felt too, she said (though she was by no
                means a sentimental young lady) that there was "a thrill in the air" and that
                "something dreadful was happening"; though nevertheless she imagined confusedly that
                the pistol shot must be part of the play, though she could see nothing <choice>
                    <sic>&#224;propos</sic>
                    <corr>apropos</corr>
                </choice> to it in the stage situation. Instead of discovering that the shot was
                fired behind her, she thought it was from the front. She therefore leaned still
                further out of the box, and recollected that she saw Miss Keene on the stage,
                evidently in great excitement.</p>

            <p>While she was telling me the story, she left me several times for a few minutes to go
                into the adjoining room, telling me her step-brother, (whom she afterwards married)
                was lying there suffering from the effects of a wound or other hurt (I don't
                remember with what weapon or missile) received on the occasion, but whether from
                Wilkes Booth, or from some one else in the <choice>
                    <orig>m&#234;l&#233;e</orig>
                    <reg>melee</reg>
                </choice> that followed, I can't recall, though she must have told me.</p>

            <p>Neither can I now, on reflection, say positively whether it was from her (though I am
                pretty sure it was) or afterwards from the press, I got the impression that even
                when Booth had jumped on the stage from her very side (for it must have been from
                the ledge of the box between <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_ej.00614_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_ej.00615_large.jpg" type="recto"/> her &#38; Mr.
                Lincoln that he jumped) &#38; had shouted his cry of "Sic semper tyrannis" &#38; run
                off the stage, she still thought it was part of the play; and had not recognized
                that he had leapt from her box at all. Certainly this would naturally be so, if her
                mind was filled, as she said, with the notion that the excitement originated on the
                stage, and if she was stretching herself out of the box, to find out what it
                was.</p>

            <p>But this I do remember as from herself: though the time that elapsed between the
                shot and her recovery from her dazed condition to an appreciation of the real
                circumstances must in reality have been very short indeed (take out your watch, look
                at the index of the minute dial go round for sixty seconds &#38; you will probably
                say it must have been within that
                time) the brief moments seemed to her "like an age," and there was something she
                could not explain, that made her feel "as if the world was coming to an end." A
                clever girl who had carried on, all through a stirring episode of history, a good
                part of her senator father's correspondence, and who had her own political &#38;
                sectional prepossessions,&#8212;it might very well be that her own emotions, on
                realizing what had just been accomplished, colored her perceptions, but
                psychologists would probably say that this inexplicable something, portentious
                     of destruction &#38; death, was none the less a reality for being
                invisible &#38; intangible&#8212;that it was in truth a magnetic
                wave of aggregated human passion from those who looking up at the immediate scene of the tragedy
                had, unlike her, seen its action &#38; at once appreciated its consequences&#8212;it
                was a shock of wonder &#38; doubt&#8212;a flood of horror, awe, fury&#8212;a mute
                despairing call for succor that could not come&#8212;a wild outcry for vengeance that
                could not restore.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_ej.00616_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_ej.00617_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p>After her description of her feelings just preceding, and on her realization of, the
                tragedy, the rest of the young lady's story was simply an anti-climax. She
                accompanied Mrs. Lincoln from the theatre &#38; was with her, I think she said, a
                good part of the night. One thing she told me however, in answer to a question of
                mine, interested me, for there was much gossip &#38; scandal afloat about Mrs.
                Lincoln's temper &#38; her abuse of her husband, &#38; part of the stories told I
                knew from competent &#38; trustworthy sources &#38; also, in a small measure, from
                my own observation, to be true. But it was also said, though it by no means followed
                as a corollary, that she did not love her husband&#8212;that she only valued him as
                the means to her ambition&#8212;and that this abuse was studied &#38; habitual. Miss
                &#8212;, in answer to several questions from me, said in substance that if ever a woman
                showed genuine grief on personal grounds, and apart from that arising from a mortal
                blow to her ambition, Mrs. Lincoln did so that fateful night.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed>A.J.B.</signed>
            </closer>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_ej.00618_large.jpg" type="verso"/>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
