<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03046">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 19 June
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03046</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 19 June 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-06-19" xml:id="dat1">June 19, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-04-28" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-19" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-12" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-15" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03046.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Life Saving, <lb/>Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1882-06-19" rend="right">June 19, 1882</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have yours of yesterday, and am happy in the thought that you find my second letter
                telling. I think it indicates the line to stick to, and I don't see how Chadwick can
                climb over it. The enemy would give much <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.03046.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>to be able to break down the
                Emerson letter. That is what they will try to do, and my reply to Chadwick will make
                it harder than ever for them. When we get them fairly shut up on that point, we will
                proceed to further action.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, be careful not to make any unguarded admissions,
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc.03046.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>so as to call for defence We must
                not be detained on side issues. I burn to resume the thunder and let the levin fly
                at Marston. He need not think he is going to escape. At present I am only perplexed
                by the problem how to make the other side fight. So far, the affair is too much one
                way, and they seem
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03046.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                cowed. O if you only had a publisher! What a chance for advertising is slipping
                by.</p>
            <p>I am anxious not to be dragged away from the main question into the discussion of
                side issues, and am therefore in doubt whether to reply to "Sigma." Of course, it is
                a fine chance for the <choice><sic>catawampous</sic><corr>catawampus</corr></choice>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc.03046.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                chaw, as this bogus "experienced
                critic" will find out if I go for him, but it seems too much like being drawn away
                from the trail. On the other hand, The Tribune invites my attention to Sigma's
                "assertion" about the "disgusting Priapism," which is, of course, a disgusting lie,
                and I 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03046.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>I have to
                make up my mind whether the point is worth scoring. I have been talking today with
                Professor Loomis who was up at Concord when Emerson's letter was published, and
                heard him talk on the subject. He says Emerson's enthusiasm about the book was
                great,
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03046.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>and that
                he never said a word, nor assumed any tone, pointing to any discount or
                qualification. Emerson's prominent consideration about Leaves of Grass was its absolute <hi
                    rend="underline">newness</hi>. He spoke of it as absolutely a new manifestation of literature&#8212;a fresh revelation.
                Professor Loomis is very
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03046.010_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>strong about the impossibility of Emerson ever having gone back
                upon his letter. The tone he took, he says, precluded this. He says that undoubtedly
                Emerson was <hi rend="underline">subsequently</hi> much annoyed at what the
                publication of the letter brought upon him&#8212;the swarm of "trippers and
                <pb
                    xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03046.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                askers" that
                surrounded him with demands as to how he could defend such a passage as this, and
                what had he to say to such an expression as this, etc, etc., and that he may have
                expressed his annoyance, said petulant things, wished you more than once at the
                devil, etc.,
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03046.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>but
                this was all, and that he never qualified his original utterance&#8212;never! This
                is Professor Loomis' view&#8212;a distinguished man, a witness&#8212;and it has
                weight and force at this time.</p>
            <p>Thoreau, he said, was equally, or nearly equally, strong in favor of Leaves of Grass,
                and so were the other
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03046.013_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> Concordians. All this knocks the "disgusting Priapism" assertion
                endways. Of course we must expect all sorts of hardy lying, but we must allow
                nothing and demand proof of everything alleged.</p>
            <p>Another question is as to the genuineness of the Sigma letter. The 
                <pb
                    xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03046.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>Tribune
                editorial shows a desire to put in something as a makeweight, and to seem biased
                against me, while admitting my letters and letting me do all the mischief I can, and
                Whitelaw Reid's notes to me have a cordial tone which sustains this view. Hence, the
                Sigma letter
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03046.015_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                may
                be got up as a counterpoise. At any rate, it is let in in sham equity. If genuine,
                who wrote it? Sigma is the Greek letter S, which might stand for Spofford, the
                librarian of Congress, who is unfriendly to you, and a great squirt and jackass
                generally.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03046.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I will decide soon whether to answer this serpentine signature.</p>
            <p>Apropos, Professor Loomis says he wrote to you for a copy of your book, which he is
                anxious to get. I wish you would let me know the price, as I have enquiries on this
                point, and can only suppose
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.03046.017_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>it is &#36;2, like the Osgood.</p>
            <p>I sent John Burroughs one of yesterday's Tribunes, which I hope will reach him.</p>
            <p>The day here is bad for heat, and I sit soaked, after a sleepless night, not fit to
                write a letter nor anything else. Congratulatory epistles continue to flow. All taffy
                so far, except
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.03046.018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                "Sigma," whose lucubrations make me think of dear old Gurowski's phrase of
                objurgation&#8212;"Sir, you are an asinine assish ass!" This is too mild, but
                nevertheless it faintly describes Sigma.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Goodbye</salute>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Mr. Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
