<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01689">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 28
                    September 1869</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01689</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">89–90</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 28 September 1869</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1869-09-28" xml:id="dat1">September 28, 1869</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-03-08" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-11-01" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="center">Attorney General's Office</name>, <name type="place" rend="right"><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></name>, <date when="1869-09-28" rend="right">Sept 28, <hi rend="italic">18</hi>69</date>.<ptr target="loc.01689_n1"/>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear William O'Connor:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>As you were interested in Mr. Parton's money-borrowing
                item about me, I enclose you the receipts signed &amp; given me by his Attorney at
                the time, (June, 1857.)<ptr target="loc.01689_n2"/> The sum borrowed by me of Mr. Parton was Two hundred
                dollars. He had, just before, kindly volunteered the loan himself, without the least
                request or hint from me. I then declined, but afterward borrowed the money, &amp;
                gave a short-time Note. I felt soon, &amp; feel now, that it was a great impropriety
                on my part, &amp; it has caused me much compunction &amp; real unhappiness since.
                Any how when the time for paying the note came, I had no money. Mr. Parton then put
                the matter in the hands of his Attorney, Mr. Oliver Dyer, who sued. My recollection
                is that I confessed judgment, &amp; proposed to Mr. Dyer that he should receive
                payment in goods. He came by appointment to my room in Classon avenue, Brooklyn,
                June 17, 1857, talked over the matter, behaved very kindly, positively accepted
                there &amp; then, &amp; conveyed away, goods to the amount of One hundred and eighty
                one dollars, and receipted for them, on account. He also, for the balance,
                conditionally accepted other goods, (which he also conveyed away with him,) on the
                agreement between us that if they, when more deliberately examined, proved
                acceptable, they would requite the balance, &amp; the debt would be considered paid;
                otherwise they would be returned, &amp; the balance would still stand against me.
                These goods he retained, and subsequently told me that they had proved acceptable,
                and consented to give me a receipt in full, &amp; satisfaction paper—but, (I
                think,) said the latter would require the signature of Mr. Parton. This was a
                meeting either in the street, or on the Brooklyn ferry. On meeting him afterwards in
                a similar way, once or twice, I mentioned the matter of a receipt in full, but never
                pressed it—never procured such receipt, nor the original note either.</p>

            <p>I consider the debt <hi rend="italic">paid</hi>—(though if I had wealth,
                to-day, I should certainly pay it over again, in cash.) Among the goods rendered I
                remember an oil painting, an original, of marked beauty &amp; value, by Jesse
                    Talbot,<ptr target="loc.01689_n3"/> illustrating a scene
                from Pilgrim's Progress, worth from four to five hundred dollars. This I put, if I
                remember right, at one hundred dollars. I presume Mr. Dyer or Mr. Parton has it yet.</p>

            <p>The enclosed receipt, marked 1,<ptr target="loc.01689_n4"/> was, on turning over the goods,
                written by me &amp; signed, by Mr. Dyer, who then remarked that he would also give
                me one in more technical form, and wrote, signed, &amp; handed me the receipt marked
                    2<ptr target="loc.01689_n5"/>—I presume, (but do not know for
                certain,) that Mr. Dyer considers the debt fully paid.</p>

            <p>(The balance of thirty five dollars mentioned, besides the one hundred &amp; eighty
                one includes sixteen dollars as Mr. Dyer's fee, or more probably costs of suit, over
                &amp; above the original two hundred.) </p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>