<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05140">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 12 July
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05140</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 12 July 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-07-12" xml:id="dat1">July 12, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-25" who="#nhg">added images, updated transcription</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-16" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-27" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-12-03" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03284.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top right">see notes Nov 18 1888</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1883-07-12">July 12, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have been so ill, and so burdened with the office charge, being scarcely able to
                hold my head up, that I have too long kept your <hi rend="underline">Critic</hi> article, which I return. It
                is splendid. What other American poet has earned, or will ever earn, the proud
                distinction of having an article upon him, like Dr. Popoff's, suppressed by the
                knout-empire!</p>
 
            <p>Did you note how the N. Y. Post (same as the <hi rend="underline">Nation</hi>) in itemizing the article, took
                out its essential features. Contemptible wretches.</p>
            <p>There was a vile review 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03284.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                of
                Bucke's book in the <hi rend="underline">Nation</hi> of July 26. I did not see it until this week, and
                have sent a reply&#8212;quiet but scathing&#8212;which I hope may get into print.</p>
            <p>As
                for Mathilde Blind's (Blinnd, they pronounce it, as rhyming to <hi rend="underline">dinned</hi>,) report of
                George Eliot's attitude toward <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice>, it is a precious war-weapon, when you consider the immense
                estimation in which George Eliot is held, especially by the enemy (an undue
                estimation, though she certainly was a woman of genius). It is high jinks for us
                when she, whom they are even ranking 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03284.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                with Shakespeare, should put <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr>
                    <expan>Leaves of Grass</expan>
                </choice> among the few modern books she read, and declare that she found it
                "<hi rend="underline">good for her soul</hi>!" This must be wormwood to some of our moral literary
                ghosts&#8212;ghosts, indeed, since they have, if you'll believe them, got rid of
                their bodies before death&#8212;who are always retching over <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice>, and purring like cats over <hi rend="underline">Adam Bede</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Middlemarch</hi>. A careful
                advertisement ought to be prepared for McKay, giving a few of the <hi rend="underline"
                    >best</hi> opinions on <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice>, with this prominent among them. The effect would 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03284.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                be considerable. How
                poor Sidney Lanier would wince over this testimony! He had a savage (and silly)
                attack on you in his lectures, coupled with sky falutin eulogy of George
                Eliot. To see his idol prostrate in worship before his <hi rend="underline">bete
                    noir</hi>, would have been a stinger. But, rest his soul! he's dead, and
                gone where he knows what an ass he made of himself.</p>

            <p>I have just read Specimen Days, and seen the splendid compliment you pay me. To be
                remembered in connection with Ossian and on an Ossianic night, is the 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03284.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                highest
                tribute possible.</p>

            <p>The book is all sweet and sane and immortal. When I get well (I am slowly mending) I
                am going to read it carefully and slowly&#8212;not, as now, with a weak and whirling
                head. I noticed on page 317 what seemed a plate breakage&#8212;NOTES LEFT
                OVEP&#8212;"ovep" for "over."</p>

            <p>Apropos of corrections, I wish, if Bucke's book comes to a second edition, that you
                would substitute something else for the <hi rend="underline">fac simile</hi> piece about Garfield's
                assassination. First, because, despite the 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03284.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                poor fellow's horrible death, he does not
                deserve such commemoration. Garfield was a bad fellow. I knew him well. He was one
                of the worst types of an intriguing politician&#8212;personally and politically
                base. His death has canonized him, although the glamor is fading. Any knowing
                politician, who will be confidential with you, will tell you that Dorsey's
                allegations are strictly true. Three or four of them, I myself <hi rend="underline"
                    >know</hi> to be true. A second reason for suppressing the piece, or relegating
                it to a back 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03284.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                seat, is that the first line&#8212;"The sobbing of the bells"&#8212;is
                one of Edgar Poe's best-known verses, original with him too. You will find it
                in "The Bells."</p>

            <p>I got the 25 copies from McKay, and will settle soon.</p>

            <p>I have found that the "office editor" of the N. A. Review is named Metcalf. As ill
                luck would have it, he is away, as Rice is. I have an article there which I am
                anxious to get published, but fear they will reject it. Grant White had a dastardly
                mass of lies and perversions
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03284.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
                in the <hi rend="underline">Atlantic</hi> in April anent of Mrs. Pott's
                publication of Bacon's <hi rend="underline">Promus</hi>&#8212;a strong anti-<choice><orig>Shakespere</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> document&#8212;which
                hurt the book immensely, and my article is a reply in which I take Mr. White's hide
                off, and "hang the calf-skin on his recreant limbs." Although Rice welcomes
                both sides, the Shakespeare prejudice is so strong, that I am afraid of not getting
                a hearing, and I wanted to make things even by bringing a little influence to bear
                on the office editor, in Rice's absence.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03284.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I am glad you stand so well in Rice's favor, though I am surprised he should have
                rejected your Carlyle article, which seems to me so rich and grand.</p>

            <p>I wrote to Montgomery by way of attaching him, and had a very cordial and
                friendly reply. He has lots of talent, but a vicious way of
                temporizing&#8212;qualifying his statements, which he ought to get over. His
                letter, too, gave me an unpleasant impression of pertness and 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03284.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
                conceit. I fear he is
                an ineradicable sophomore, but he is friendly to us, and we need friends.</p>

            <p>I wrote to Sloane Kennedy, and had a fine reply. He is a good fellow.</p>

            <p>Your Santa Fe letter is superb. It strikes a great chord. I have long looked
                with distrust on the Spanish boojum manufactured for us. After all, the true
                Spain&#8212;the real, essential Castilian spirit&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03284.011.jpg" type="recto"/>is in Cervantes. Surely, it
                is not dark and cruel there. Apropos, here's a nice little fact. The Spanish
                Inquisition, according to the indictment of its deadliest enemy, its secretary,
                Llorente, destroyed in 400 years, 30,000 people. The whole
                Protestant world howls and roars, properly enough, over this dreadful record.
                Yes&#8212;but in the single reign of Henry the Eighth, Defender of the faith and typical
                Protestant, according to Lord Chief 
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03284.012.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Justice Campbell, a Protestant and a Scotchman,
                there were 72,000 people who suffered bloody and violent
                deaths! It is funny that History shrieks over the 30,000 it took 400 years for the Inquisition to destroy, and is quite mum over the
                72,000 who perished in the single reign of the English
                Bluebeard. "Give a dog a bad name."</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye</salute>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed>WD O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman</salute>
            </closer>
            
            <postscript>
                <p>(Don't forget to return my <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> article sometime.)</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
