<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00400">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 3 March 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00400</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">31-34</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 3 March 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-03-03">March 3, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-27">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-03-03">March 3rd/63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yesterday I received your letter of Sunday.<ptr target="loc.00400_n1"/> I was real glad to hear from you and began to wonder what had happen [to] you  About the house. I had my plan fixed up as I wanted it and left it with some three or four carpenters and got bids on it. much to my astonishment I found that what I was supposed would cost at 11 or $1200 could not be done for less than 20 or $2100  after thinking the matter over pretty thoroughly I have come to the conclusion that the best thing I could do would be to hold on to the lot and wait for cheaper times. I hardly would be willing to spend that amount of money in a house of that kind and I think it would be much better to wait till the character of the avenue is settled before building. And again, I find (by calculation) that the prospect is that the difference in prices in, say two years, will more than pay rent for that time and then there would be the interest money to pay besides. Dont you think I have acted wisely. I sent word to Blake<ptr target="loc.00400_n2"/> word this morning that I would remain as I was and he sent back word that he would call and see me this week. That she bitch of Hell, the Brown, is trying her strongest to clear us out and I honestly think Walt that I shall just take and belt old Johny<ptr target="loc.00400_n3"/> under the eye if he attempts any of his last summers games</p>
            <p>To day the bitch could do nothing better than spend an hour or two in getting the lid of the cistern up and has left it in the old dangerous style half on and half of[f] the hole  Mother tells me that Blake is altogether "on their side"  one thing is sure that if he attempts any of his games I shall most certainly clear out. I rather think that Mother would rather that we would move as Brown is continually at her about Mats conduct and keeps her in continued hot water. Everything is going on as usual. I wish you would let me hear from you at least twice a week. I guess that I have received all your letters  Mother got your letter enclosing the $1.00 and is still like Oliver Twist.<ptr target="loc.00400_n4"/> She has had some 3 letters from you with money in it.</p>
            <p>We had received the letter from George (that he spoke of in his letter to you) just before we got yours<ptr target="loc.00400_n5"/>  Mother wrote to George also Han yesterday. I wish you would tell George that if he cannot possibly get his furlough (if he should make his clothes look awful they might let him home to get a new suit) and will send on his measure we will have them made in good style and sent to him. As regards the money in the Bank, there is plenty left for that purpose. Mother had a letter from Han on Saturday  she seemed about the same although Heyde wrote in the latter part of the letter that she was not so well  the exertion of writing was too much for her<ptr target="loc.00400_n6"/>  Sissy is very well and is growing finely  She is great on the mischief, she is just getting at that age where she does it with "malice aforethoughts"</p>
            <p>I shall write you oftener hereafter  I have been so busy with plans specifications &amp;c &amp;c that I have not been able to write you as ofen as I would like. I think that I have a good bargain in my lot if I can manage to hold on to it. They are now asking $1500 for lots in the immediate neighborhood that are not as well located as the one I have bargained for</p>
            <p>How do you get along with your office hunting  do you meet with any encouragement. It must be a new life to you. Are you writing for any paper outside of Washington, if so what?<ptr target="loc.00400_n7"/> You must have pretty good times generally, dont you  I should much like to see you for a good talk. Your note book will certainly have a good many strange things in it. What are they going to do to reinforce the army, will they have to enforce the conscript bill<ptr target="loc.00400_n8"/>
            </p>
            <p>We have not been able to send you any money lately but hope that we shall before long. do you get any from any other source? Twill be hard for you to go to the Hospitals if you cant give the poor young heroes something. I think that it would be a good idea for you to write Mr Lane, tell him that you are out, and ask him if he could not get the young men around the office to subscribe 50 <hi rend="superscript">cts</hi> a month.<ptr target="loc.00400_n9"/> I will, if he puts "the questions" amend that it be made a dollar, and should not wonder that we could send you quite a little sum every month. Of course you wont say I suggested it.</p>
            <p>We are all quite well and getting along as well as usual  will write you again in a few days. Dear Walt receive love from all and a kiss from Hattie</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
