<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02407">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Newton Johnson to Walt Whitman, [30?] August
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Newton Johnson</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02407</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John Newton Johnson</author>
                    <title>John Newton Johnson to Walt Whitman, [30?] August 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-08-30" xml:id="dat1">August 30, 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 11, Reel 7</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Johnson, John Newton" ref="n0914">John Newton Johnson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-05" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-07-05" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-06-05" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-12" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-04" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-20" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02407.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Mid P.O. Alabama<ptr target="loc.02407_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1885-09">August 1885</date>
                    <name type="place">(Sent from Guntersville)</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Something very near a Soliloquy.</salute>
                <salute>(John Newton Johnson)</salute>
            </opener>

            <p> What revelations of the last 18 months! </p>
            <p> How soul-sickening! </p>
            <p> What "joy of suffering" there from! In the summer of '80, my oldest son (of this, my
                second wife,) being then a well-grown, strong, and healthy boy of 17 years 4 months,
                took a notion he must go to Texas. He did tolerably well then for two years. He
                become large sized and extra strong.....A woman 2 years his senior, a sort of
                "heiress" (in a small way,) began to think she must have a husband; and after a
                failure to get another young fellow (a kinsman of ours) to come from there,) opened up a correspondence with our
                boy. At the same time she coquetted with another young man nearer home. Our boy came
                home, and seemed to become crazed for <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.02407.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> a person of no accomplishments or
                charms (whatever) unless a seductive pretence or fancy of attachment&#8212;while the
                very climax of indecision and inconstancy. In spite of all I could say&#8212;in
                spite of the "Body Electric" with its grand "old man, a common farmer"&#8212;in
                spite of all a "philosopher" could say or plead (from stores of reading &amp;
                reflection) they married&#8212;or rather consorted. Straightway he went to hardest
                work like the wildest fanatic. Building, building, &amp;c&#8212;not too much tho'
                except that his foundation was&#8212;SAND! 20 months hardest work (and
                wretchedness.) 20 months supreme idling, "gadding", tales to "Ma!" To
                others&#8212;"he would be good to me if I would let him." <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc.02407.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> Result&#8212;a deliberate,
                soldier-like suicide! He kept his troubles almost entirely concealed from his
                parents&#8212;we thoughts things were going just a little bad. The woman's people
                knew much more. Her four brothers of whom two were larger men, one as large, and
                one smaller, were a lot of jealous, stingy, envious fellows, who concealed their
                ill-will. (They had before maltreated a brother-in-law and a stepfather, and it
                doubtless mortified them for people to know they could'n't do the muscular and
                giant-willed young lion in the same way.) He was kind to them as if they were
                babies! They had to have their revenge (after his death) on <hi rend="underline">his
                    creditors</hi> and his innocent father. <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                        facs="loc.02407.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>  They made the widow repudiate all
                of his debts&#8212;tho' universally known that his improvements on her land were
                worth as much as the debts, and there was much added to her personal effects. </p>
            <p>
                
                After long and patient reasoning the "old man" defied one of them to combat (with
                nature's weapon's)&#8212;he accepted&#8212;then weakened, "wilted", then took up a
                fence rail (having once killed a man with one at a single blow,) and made a most
                deliberate, long-continued attempt to kill. Well! he didn't kill, frighten or
                drive&#8212;and in all ways exhausted himself. Never was a sublimer scene. </p>
            <p> Yet the most manifest, unblushing corruption (official and semi-official)<ptr target="loc.02407_n2"/> and a
                total lack of manliness all around us seems about to excuse the offender </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02407.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p> I am at our Circuit Court&#8212;been here some days. Since that young man was taking
                a <hi rend="underline">law</hi> advantage of myself and other creditors of my dead
                son, after he went back on his agreement for a pugilistic encounter, I determined to
                only parry his many blows with steadfast demeanor 'till reflection <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#kb" cert="low">could</unclear> stop him;
                but he stopped only from exhaustion, (as proven by his retreat within a gate in
                search of more effective weapons&#8212;and finding nothing but one something to
                throw at me, he left off, the picture of a miserable despair.) Yet with all his and
                his folks' subsequent wretchedness, they could not master their niggardliness to do
                anything for anybody except a few least needy creditors. These last got vague and
                indirect promises&#8212;doubtless to prevent or secure <choice><sic>inffuence</sic><corr>influence</corr></choice>. </p>
            <p> What a miracle or strange happening&#8212;that <hi rend="underline">he</hi> should be <hi rend="underline"
                    >drawn</hi> and <hi rend="underline">passed</hi> as a grand juror at the court
                succeeding! Some other suggestive and ugly facts. </p> 

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.02407.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p> The cold-hearted young widow who had witnessed and consented to her handsome (and
                for her, every way noble) husband boring a hole through his own broad and generous
                breast with a double load of buckshot, also witnessed without any remonstrance the
                attempt to demolish the gray-haired father-in-law. </p>
            <p> After brutal insults put on me in his brother's house, and in presence of two of his
                big and silent brothers (when I was still reasoning the matter,) and some months
                more of waiting, I went to his (bachelor) home, to challenge him. The corrupt and
                the unmanly make this their excuse, and say a petit jury would (as they fear) fail or refuse to execute the plain letter and
                spirit of the law. </p>
            <p> My kin, always recognized as of superior honesty, have shown themselves in all this
                matter immeasurably sluggish and spiritless (as I wrote you some years ago that they
                were.) </p>
            <p> Dear Walt, write to me at "Mid." </p>
            <postscript><!--this is written upside down at the top of pages 4 and 6 of the letter-->
                <p>My kin are much allied with those bad people by marriages. Our broad estates are all
                    adjoining.<ptr target="loc.02407_n3"/></p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.02407.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.02407.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww">from John Newton Johnson (suicide of his son)</note>


        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>
