<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01360">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe to Walt Whitman, 17
                    January 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01360</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe</author>
                    <title>Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe to Walt Whitman, 17 January 1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-01-17" xml:id="dat1">January 17, 1887</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 8, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Costelloe, Mary Whitall Smith" ref="loc.02189_n1">Mary Whitall Smith
                        Costelloe</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-25" who="#smb">final check</change>
            <change when="2015-07-14" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-24" who="#ss">annotated</change>
            <change when="2014-10-14" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-02" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01360.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <handShift rend="printed"/>
                    <name type="place">40, GROSVENOR ROAD,</name>
                    <name type="place">THE EMBANKMENT.S.W.</name>
                    <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                    <date when="1887-01-17">January 17th '87</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Many thanks for thy card of the 3rd which came on Saturday, just too late for me to
                catch the return mail. I am afraid by a curious fatality all thy biographers want to
                make thee out <hi rend="underline">too good</hi> for thy liking! Has thee never
                thought of expanding the Specimen Days into Autobiographical sketches? Then thee
                could tell the world thy wickedness to the full, which <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.01360.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> thy friends are so
                uncomprehending as not to see! I wonder if thee knows Mr. Norman personally? He is
                a charming fellow, very clever and full of American pluck. He is always so busy that
                one seldom gets a chance of seeing him in the seething side of affairs in this great
                city, but I am going to make my husband look him up again, now that I know he is a
                friend of thine. </p>
            <p>We have had nothing here but a succession of thick fogs, and today when I saw the
                flush of the real sun in the sky, I thought it was a fire!
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01360.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                In pursuance of the course of reading I wrote to thee about, I have begun to take
                Greek lessons and to read Plato's Republic. In our spare moments (which are alas!
                none too many) we are working out our idea of the ideal State, as a sort of
                supplement and corrective to Socialism. But life rushes along too fast here to give
                one time for many wayside reflections, I am afraid, and too often I find whole days
                filled up with <hi rend="underline">things</hi>&#8212;thoughts being crowded out.
                Perhaps it is good to live an intensely practical life for <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.01360.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> a while. </p>
            <p>I am very grateful for thy little slip anent Tennyson's latest, although I don't
                agree with it at all. Tennyson struck me as a man great <hi rend="underline">in
                    spots</hi>, and the cracks filled in with inferior stuff. I think this latest
                outburst of cynical pessimism comes from one of the gaps in the greatness of his
                nature. Perhaps thee will think this the hasty &#38; impulsive judgment of youth. I
                will begin to reconsider it when I find thee issuing a latest edition of Leaves of
                Grass with all the optimism <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01360.005_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> and faith and kindliness left out. I should have been glad to die
                before I had left <hi rend="underline">such</hi> a message as my last utterance, the
                final outcome of a long life of experience and thought. I can't join with thee in
                thanking him for his "Sixty Years After"!<ptr target="loc.01360_n1"/> I judge people by different standards from
                those which one uses towards Nature, for I think the gulf between natural evolution
                &#38; moral responsibility is <hi rend="underline">infinite</hi>, and if the present
                poems of Tennyson are the result of his point of view all along, then I think he is
                responsible for taking such a point of view <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">&#38; for</unclear><pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.01360.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> working it out to this
                disheartening issue.</p>
            <p>But I am disobeying my doctor, who has forbidden long letters for the present. It is
                always a temptation to chat with thee&#8212;I only wish I were near enough to do it
                    <hi rend="underline">really</hi>. Thee can't think what a refreshment to soul
                and body it is to read Leaves of Grass, or even to think of thee, in the midst of
                this artificial town life. I hope thee is well and cheerful; I am always silently
                sending thee good wishes across the ocean. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Thy friend,</salute>
                <signed>Mary Whitall Costelloe</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
