<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02192">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 20 August
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02192</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 20 August 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-08-20" xml:id="dat1">August 20, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 10, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Herbert">Herbert Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-29" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-12" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-13" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-12-05" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02192.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Post Office, <lb/>Griff, Nuneaton <lb/>Warwickshire <lb/>
                        England</name>
                    <date when="1882-08-20">August 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1882</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dearest friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am staying for a couple of weeks in the country 98 miles N.W. of London. At George
                Eliot's native place &#38; I see traces of the great novelist everywhere.</p>
            <p>The workman&#8212;<unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ss" cert="low">M
                    Alton</unclear>&#8212;<choice><orig>withom</orig>
                    <reg>with whom</reg>
                </choice> I am lodging, says his father remembers seeing G. Eliot's father walk into Griff
                with a bag of tools
                slung over his shoulder&#8212;a carpenter, one who could read &#38; write, a rare
                thing for a workman in those days; soon he came to be made a land steward for a large estate,
                &#38; got on like a "house on fire" now his son Isaac Evans lives in 
                Griff house &#38; is a rich country gentleman. The character of Adam Bede is a
                portrait of her father, I will send it to you if you have not already read it? Tell
                me in your next letter. G Eliot was very fond of her father, and the only time he
                was severe with her, was
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02192.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    once, when, she was a young woman at the time, a great student,
                and I suppose after a great deal of reflection and conning G Eliot came to the conclusion that
                to go to church and mumble a creed you no longer believed in was intolerable, and so, she told her
                father, for the first time, that she could not go to church any more; so Old Mr.
                Evans said 'you shall not live in my house then' she was greatly distressed but finally
                agreed to go to church. I am sketching her house, and a bit of her garden that she was particularly fond of, it makes quite
                a pretty little picture. I wish that I could show it to you, albeit, I can't.</p>
            <p>Am also
                sketching her house covered with creepers, ivy blue Japanese creeper sweet-peas and
                    the rest a large <gap
                    reason="illegible" extent="1 words" quantity="5" unit="chars"/>-tree on the
                lawn. George Eliot's brother inhabits this house, and is very friendly and
                hospitable to me, whilst I am at work on these sketches, considering that I have never
                seen him before; Miss Nelly
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02192.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                George Eliot's Niece) has just returned from the Highlands; a fresh, lively, candid, pleasing,
                plain woman, rather churchy, but not obtrusively so; altogether very good fun. I
                had a jolly game of tennis on their lawn,&#8212;a lawn such as you Americans <choice>
                    <orig>dont</orig>
                    <reg>don't</reg>
                </choice> dream of!!&#8212;with them.</p>
            <p>I went to Astley church this morning, an ancient church. The church
                was nearly empty, the clergyman was late&#8212;presently, I heard a scuffle in the
                    belfry, I turned and saw a big raw
                country-bumpkin boy hastily donning his <hi rend="underline">white surplus</hi>! He strides up the aisle; buries his face in his
                hands, on kneeling, with the exception of one eye which squints at the <choice><orig>new comer</orig><reg>newcomer</reg></choice>, who is busy trying to find his place in the prayer book. The <unclear
                    reason="illegible" resp="#nnk" cert="low">raw</unclear> young Rector reads with a
                musical voice a curious contradiction to his face. I afterwards learned that he
                hunts (an unusual thing for a parson.) and on occasion can swear ably.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02192.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>There is a jolly <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="low">moated</unclear> castle quite close to this little church
                whither I shall wend next week, and sketch!</p>
                
                <p>I am writing by this
                post to Eustace Conway,
                my lawyer friend in New York, a gay young spark, a fine constant friend of mine of whom I have mentioned in other letters
                to you. I have told him that "I shall try and look him up in New York some day" he
                tells me that he has a spare bedroom for me whenever
                I like to go. And now goodbye Love to Debbie Ruthie Joe Mont: Van: Georgie: Ed: Where
                is Ed now? &#38; Hal and yourself.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Herb: Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
            <!--This postscript is on the first page of the letter.--><postscript><p>Send your letter to London as usual.</p></postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
