<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00399">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 12 February 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>

               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00399</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">29&#8211;31</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 12 February 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-02-12">February 12, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-13">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2006-11-21">added figure</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            
               <opener>
                  <dateline rend="right">
                     <name type="place">Brooklyn,</name>
                     <date when="1863-02-12">Feb. 12th 1863</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I mailed a letter to you either last Friday or Saturday, containing $11. 10 from Hill &amp; Newman and $1. from Henry Carlow  On Tuesday I again wrote you, sending you $4…$2 from Theo. A. Drake and 2 from "Cash" through John D. Martin<ptr target="loc.00399_n1"/>  The enclosed $5 is from our friend Mr. E. Rae.<ptr target="loc.00399_n2"/> He gave it to me last night   I left him a couple of letters to read and I want you to write him one of the same kind of letters asking him to show it to some of his friends and if they have anything to devote to the purpose for him to send it directly to you or through me. Walt, I know Rae is a liberal hearted man and through his friends he could do a great deal and I am confident that he could be more earnestly interested in the matter if you write him directly. Please acknowledge the receipt of this and the others (if received) so that I may be positive that the money is reaching you. Ive no doubt we shall keep dribbling along, a few dollars at a time, for some time yet.</p>
               <p>We are all about the same at home as when I last wrote. Mother is of course quite worried about the moving of the 9th Army Corps and very much disappointed that George will not have an opportunity to come home and see us.<ptr target="loc.00399_n3"/> We are all getting well of our colds, last night Mother had a very bad sore throat but I made her some "hot stuff" and she was much better this morning. Mat and Sis have nearly recovered and are all right I guess. In George's letter he speaks of wanting $20. We think of sending it to him by Capt. Simms,<ptr target="loc.00399_n4"/> who is now here, and I think it will be the better and safer way.</p>
               <p>I am really much disappointed that George should have to go in the thickest of the danger. I certainly feel that he is doing wrong if there is any possible way for him to avoid it. However I try to put as good a face on the matter as possible and sincerely hope for the best  Tis too bad that he should just have got his hut done and then have to go away and leave it.<ptr target="loc.00399_n5"/>
               </p>
               <p>How goes matters with you Walt? Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00399_n6"/> will send you the letters I spoke of in a day or two. I wish you could make it so that you could visit George before they leave Fortress Monroe  Do if you possibly can. I am having a plan for a small 2 Story house (22 x 32) made and shall try to get Rae to build it for me. the only question that I am not clear on and am wanting advice is the position that I shall put on the lot, front or rear. I have almost made up my mind to set it so that a 65 or 70 x 20 foot lot can at any time be made in front, and the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> objection to placing it in that position is the location of the privy in the next yard, which in this case would be right abreast of the center of the house thus<ptr target="loc.00399_n7"/>  I do not fear that it would amount to anything unless 'twould damage the cellar in some manner. Unless I am convinced that it will be some damage <hi rend="italic">via</hi> the
                  <figure facs="loc.00399.001.jpg">
                     <head type="main-authorial"/>
                     <figDesc>Jeff Whitman's sketch, reproduced here from a scan of the photocopy of the original. The sketch shows the layout for the plot of land on which he plans to build the house described in the letter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  cellar I shall place it as above. Let me know what you think of it. (The above sketch is not at all in proportion, but may convey an idea to you what I mean)  The front lot will be quite ample, I think, (65 x 20) when you take in consideration that there will neither have to be a privy or cistern in the yard, and you will be able to have a gate in the ally which is quite an advantage. Mr Lane compliments me highly on my bargain and says I have done <hi rend="italic">well</hi>. I hope I have but I am as ignorant about these matters as a baby. However I am bound to go through with it now, sink or tother thing.</p>
               <p>Dear brother write me. If you see dear dear Brother George tell him how fondly we looked for his coming home and assure him that we were <hi rend="italic">all</hi> much, very much disappointed. All send their love to you and you may be assured you are never absent from our minds.</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>Affectionately Jeff</signed>
               </closer>
            
            <postscript>
               <p>The enclosed letter Mr Lane gave me to send you, wishing me to say that undoubtedly this Mr Webster<ptr target="loc.00399_n8"/> could help you and if he did it would be with the idea that it would help him somehow at some future period, That you must use him (Webster) if you can. Mr Lane sends his respects to you</p>
               <p>At Dinner time to-day Mother told me that Andrew had been discharged from the yard. Tis too bad but I presume it is on account of his not being there much of the time. I hardly know what Nancy<ptr target="loc.00399_n9"/> is to do with her two children.</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>Jeff</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
