<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03701">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Elizabeth J. Sharpe to Walt Whitman, 16 July
                    1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Elizabeth J. Sharpe</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03701</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Elizabeth J. Sharpe</author>
                    <title>Elizabeth J. Sharpe to Walt Whitman, 16 July 1886</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1886-07-16" xml:id="dat1">July 16, 1886</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 15</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Sharpe, Elizabeth J." ref="n4104">Elizabeth J. Sharpe</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-28" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-06-27" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-16" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-10-14" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-13" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03701.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1886-07-16">Camden 7. 16. 1886.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I was shown the new type so kindly given by you to Miss Grace Hunter<ptr
                    target="loc.03701_n2"/> a day or two ago, and I think it, by far, the finest I
                have seen of you in any form. I am so pleased that I write immediately to beg of you
                to reserve one for me, if it so happen you have another to spare. I leave the city
                to day for 2 or 3 months (Marlton N.J. Your friend Mr. Stafford<ptr target="n0590"/> is at the station
                there) as I am in very <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03701.002_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> delicate health, but will call for it, if you will allow me, on my
                return in the fall, provided of course that you are disposed to favor me so highly. </p>
            <p> I have seen Mr. Hunter two or three times daily for months&#8212;when both in the
                city&#8212;and I spent last evening with him and his daughter. He read "Eidolons"; Mr. H&#8212; several times. I am
                not prepared to say that I have arrived at its best significance as yet and intend
                giving full study. Other poems were also read and I think Mr. H is fully impressed
                he shall like them more and more as he allows a better and more familiar
                acquaintance. For myself, I have held for years that you are the greatest <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03701.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> "master of
                words" in the language, and although the source is humble you will appreciate from
                the fact that the prophet is so rarely duly appraised in his own country, and that
                in local circles my opinion as a wide reader and a student is not without its own
                little influence. </p>
            <p> I have been begging Mr. Hunter to bring me to call with him&#8212;fearing otherwise
                I should infringe upon your time&#8212;but he is very selfish and comes by himself.
                I am sure he thinks you will get all the compliments and it is best for himself to
                leave me at home. Yet, oh yes, he is very <hi rend="underline">very</hi> good and
                has my interests, literary and <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03701.004_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> otherwise, quite at heart, so it is not so very hard to forgive
                him, only&#8212;well, I should have liked very much to have come, and trust you will <choice>
                    <orig>comission</orig>
                    <corr>commission</corr>
                </choice> me the pleasure sometime after the Canadian trip which I understand it is
                now your intention to take. </p>
            <p> Wishing you every benefit form the occasion, and a safe and hearty return. I am </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Very Truly Yours</salute>
                <signed>Elizabeth J. Sharpe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p> P.S. I have been collecting every little item pertaining to you for the past 2
                    or three years that I find afloat; shall continue for the next ten if I
                    live. I am now 28. I trust my ability may equal the time &amp; material before me to compile
                    judiciously and in <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#if">worthiness</unclear> the
                    subject, as it is my desire to do <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#smb">sl</unclear> <gap reason="illegible" quantity ="2" unit="word"/>.
                </p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
