<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00432">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 11 March 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00432</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">93&#8211;95</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 11 March 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-03-11">March 11, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1864-03-11">March 11th 1864</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> The enclosed $5 is contributed for the wounded men by Moses Lane<ptr target="loc.00432_n1"/>
            </p>
            <p>I am at a stand to know whether to beg pardon for not writing you before or to scold you for not writing to me.<ptr target="loc.00432_n2"/> I have been away for nearly three weeks, down in Conn. making surveys for an "Iron Co." and only returned last Monday night. since then I have been very much engaged in getting my work up so that I have not, lately, really had an opportunity to write you  We have had, and are having, considerable excitement in relation to moving and the house. Just so soon as I had got away in the country, the next day, Mrs Brown<ptr target="loc.00432_n3"/> informed Mother that they had hired the house and that she could remain by paying $8 per month ($3 a month increase) but that our rooms they should rent to other parties, would not allow us to have them anyhow &amp;c&#8212;This came rather hard on Mat and Mother, for we thought sure that things would go on as they had the last year, only with a slight increase of rent. On my return Mat told me all about it. On Tuesday, the next day some masons &amp;c came with their tools to make repairs to the rooms and house. I told Mat, (she was going to take up her stair carpet oil cloths&#8212;clear out closets &amp;c) to not touch a thing, informed the men that I paid rent for the rooms that they were abt fixing that I didn't want them fixed and should charge the landlord with all damage done. In the afternoon I went to New York to see Travis<ptr target="loc.00432_n4"/> (the new landlord) to give him legal notice about it. After talking with him awhile I found that the Browns had lied to us and lied to him.&#8212;that they had not hired it, but merely talked of it&#8212;that they had offered to get a tenant in our place that Travis had told them that the rent of the house would be $400 and that if it returned that to him they might have it if they wanted it and if I was not going to stay &amp;c. In the mean time the Browns were trying to let our room to Jim Jourdan's wife.<ptr target="loc.00432_n5"/> Mr Travis said that he would just as soon have us stay as they. Travis sent them a note not to let the house till they saw him. They both went over in the evening to see Travis and lied again by telling him that they had rented it but as they had not passed any papers he would not let them have it.&#8212;The increase of rent is $52&#8212;$36 of this they were going to fasten on Mother&#8212;I offered Travis that I would pay $18 a month for the rooms that Mother and I had&#8212;that would leave them to pay 15 1/3 a month increasing our rent $3 and theirs $1 1/3 or if they would not agree to that, that I would take the whole of it at $400.&#8212;He is to decide this week which&#8212;if either&#8212;he will do  in the mean time they are moving everything to get Mat and I out.&#8212;I think the chances are about even whether they succeed or not. Rents are very high in Brooklyn  for that floor over Browers<ptr target="loc.00432_n6"/> (cor of Cumberland st. and Myrtle) they ask $350 for one floor and 275 for the third story.&#8212;There is a story around that Travis bought the house we live in for $3000, but I can hardly think of it. If so I wish I had known it  I would have tried to get it myself</p>
            <p>Mr Crany's<ptr target="loc.00432_n7"/> address would be best "care of Moses Lane Box 192 Brooklyn P.O." I wish you would write me a letter to show Mr W. E. Worthen<ptr target="loc.00432_n8"/> of New York  I think I could raise you some $20 or $25 per month out of him  He is the man I went down to Springfield to work for.&#8212;he spoke of it himself&#8212;said that he thought he could do something out of his friends,&#8212;although poor himself</p>
            <p>We suppose that George is at Camp Nelson<ptr target="loc.00432_n9"/> again but we have not heard from himself since he went away. Sims<ptr target="loc.00432_n10"/> is here yet, got a recruiting office.</p>
            <p>Mother is not well. I think she has the worst cold that I ever knew of  I wish she could be made to think that she must not wash scrub and clean house.&#8212;I had quite a time with her this morning about it  after exhausting every excuse she said she "could not afford to hire it done"&#8212;She is foolishly worrying herself about George&#8212;thinking that he does not want her to use so much of his money  She says that when he went away he did not say as usual "Mammy dont want for anything"  If he didn't God knows he meant it. To me his whole life and actions home seemed to say so. But Mother seems to feel quite bad about it. Several days after he first went away she was either crying or planning how to take "boarders" and make her own living. Poor Mother, how foolish her dear old heart gets sometimes. Mat has been quite sick but is well again. the little one is quite well and Hattie too. Matters are going on about as usual. I wish you could find time to write me a good long letter. also one to Lane, and the Dr<ptr target="loc.00432_n11"/> too you said you would write.</p>
            <p>I will write again soon</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Yours affectionately Jeff.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
