<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04058">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 18 March 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04058</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">177&#8211;178</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 18 March 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-03-18" xml:id="dat1">March 18, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-02" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">112 Madison Ave.</name>
                    <date when="1879-03-18" rend="right">March 18, 1879.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I hope you are enjoying this splendid, sunshiny weather as much as we are&#8212;the atmosphere here is delicious.<ptr target="n0259"/> In the morning Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> and I set at home busy with needle work, letter writing, and reading. After lunch we go out for a walk or to pay visits&#8212;and of an evening very often to receptions (but they are not half so jolly as our evenings at Philadelphia). Still we have a lively, pleasant time. I like Miss Booth<ptr target="n3017"/> very much, with her kindly, generous character and active practical mind. So I do Mrs. Croly<ptr target="n1507"/>&#8212;she is more impulsive and enthusiastic. Kate Hillard<ptr target="n0302"/> often goes with us, &#38; she is always good company. I had a note from Edward Carpenter<ptr target="n0141b"/> the other day brought by a lady who had been living near him at Sheffield&#8212;an American lady with two very fine little girls who has lately lost her husband in England and was on her way back to her parents' home in Pennsylvania&#8212;somewhere beyond <choice><orig>Pittsburg</orig><reg>Pittsburgh</reg></choice>. She is one who loves your poems, &#38; has great hopes of seeing you in New York. She told me her little girls were so fond of Carpenter he of them&#8212;he is first rate with children. I hope you will not put off coming to New York till we are returning to Philadelphia, which will be some time in May. I find Beatrice<ptr target="n0260"/> is so anxious to get further advantages for study in England or Paris before she begins to practise, and Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> is so strongly advised by Mr. Eaton,<ptr target="upa.00172_n3"/> of whose judgment &#38; experience he thinks very highly, to study in Duron's Studio in Paris for a year, that I have made up my mind to go back, for a time at any rate, this summer; but I shall leave my furniture here, and the question of where our future home is to be, open. Herby is making great progress. I wish you could see the head of an old woman he has just painted&#8212;and I wish he had had as much power when he had such splendid chances of painting you. I cannot tell you how vividly and pleasantly Chestnut St. on a sunny day rose before me in your jottings. Love from us all. Tell your sister I often think of her &#38; shall enjoy a chat ever so.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">A. G.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
