<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00940">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 10 November 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00940</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 10 November 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-11-10">November 10, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">added encoding for page breaks</change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00940.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Washington.</name>
                  <name type="place">400 L Street.</name>
                  <date when="1863-11-10">Nov. 10.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
         <p>Did you arrive home safely, dear Walt?<ptr target="loc.00940_n100"/> and did you vote? did you vote seven time as the Count did when he first become a citizen of these United States?<ptr target="loc.00940_n2"/> If not in your own person, I hope that you caused as many as seven raving democrats to vote right this time, however as the result was all right we argue that you did your part.</p>
            <p>Now, now, Walt, are you aware that your ten days expire to-morrow! Not that I at all expect to see you then for ten days would be a short time to stay at home after nearly a year's absence, but we have <pb facs="loc.00940.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00940.003.jpg" type="recto"/>been counting the days in the <hi rend="italic">very faintest</hi> hope that you might come then.</p>
            <p>M. Eldridge comes as usual every evening, and we always ask each other - "have you heard from Walt?"<ptr target="loc.00940_n3"/> He has sent you two letters, one the next day after you left, and one since. We have drank your health on several occasions, and in a variety of liquids, <hi rend="italic">tea</hi> on one occasion.</p>
            <p>By the way, all of the Piatts including the sweet Patsy &amp; the baby have dined with us since you left.<ptr target="loc.00940_n4"/> I shall save all details to tell you when you come. But you were asked for, and we all wished you present.<pb facs="loc.00940.004.jpg" type="recto"/> Of course Mr. Eldridge &amp; Mrs. Cooper formed two of the dinner party.<ptr target="loc.00940_n5"/> Mrs. C. is still with me, being detained much longer than she expected to be, for which I am very glad. I shall not know how to get along without her, especially while you are gone. She is very bright and keeps us alive, she knows how to cook nice things too, and has exercised her genius for me several times, and if you will come back before she is gone, we will have a nice dinner for you.</p>
            <p>I fully intended to be able to tell you something about your boys in hospital, but I have had so bad a cold since you left <pb facs="loc.00940.005.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00940.006.jpg" type="recto"/>and such an annoying troublesome cough with it that I have not been able to go to see them. They must miss you sadly, poor boys, I pity them.</p>
            <p>How did you find all of home? Did your good mother look as when you left her? &amp; did you remember to give her my love? How did little Hattie look? Had she grown much? &amp; what do you think of the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> baby? Did you kiss them both for me? If not you must.</p>
            <p>How about all the other members of the family? I hope you found all better than you expected. You know I feel personally acquainted with each <pb facs="loc.00940.007.jpg" type="recto"/>member of your family.</p>
            <p>And what about your New York boys? Of course you have seen all, and have had that great <hi rend="italic">time</hi> which we are to hear all about when you come back. Indeed, won't you have "lots" to tell us! You know you must come back prepared to give us a full account.</p>
            <p>Have you seen Mrs. Price.<ptr target="loc.00940_n6"/> I wrote her the very day you left. Do you find her much worse than when you left last year?</p>
            <p>And Walt, have you seen Mr. Howells?<ptr target="loc.00940_n7"/> If not I beg that you will, and with all the skill and talent of which you <pb facs="loc.00940.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00940.009.jpg" type="recto"/>are master do what you can to disenchant him with those people. I know more about it than when you were here, and I assure you that you will be rendering a service not only to Mrs. H. &amp; the family, but to all who care for them if you can only get him out of this. If he could but know the real truth in regard to "the great head" and leader of the reform it would surely open his eyes. He evidently thinks Mr. A. a "great light" &amp; a saint of a man, sincere and true. Oh! can't he be enlightened? It is awful, and unless his eyes are soon opened I don't see what will be the end. I depend on you<pb facs="loc.00940.010.jpg" type="recto"/> Walt, to see him, at any rate, &amp; your own intuition will tell you whether you can do more, but I feel that you can. He has great regard for your opinions of people and things.</p>
            <p>William is well as usual, he is at the office or would send lots of love.<ptr target="loc.00940_n8"/> Mrs. Cooper has gone in to the other house to dress for dinner, or she too, would send love. Do you know that in the innocence of her heart she fully believes that you are going to stop and see her in your return through Philadelphia, and <hi rend="italic">I</hi> have not the heart to undeceive her, and tell her what a <hi rend="italic">promising</hi> youth you are <pb facs="loc.00940.011.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00940.012.jpg" type="recto"/>so I don't see but that you really must make the promised visit, &amp; you would have a very good time, I assure you of that beforehand. She wants me to go home with her, but I doubt if I shall. Can't afford it.</p>
            <p>By the way, one bit of intelligence in regard to our dear friend and neighbor Gwynne I must tell you.<ptr target="loc.00940_n9"/> They think of moving &amp; renting the house up here, &amp; a lady whom I know came to look at it. G. was much pleased at the idea of moving such a nice family as hers for tenants, &amp; offered to rent it for <pb facs="loc.00940.013.jpg" type="recto"/>one hundred dollars a month unfurnished. The lady politely declined &amp; told him that she rents her present house 
<hi rend="italic">furnished</hi> for that sum. Mrs. G. &amp; the new baby are well. I can't think of any more news to tell you.</p>
            <p>To tell you that we miss you <hi rend="italic">awfully</hi> would not be news would it? You expected that, but I do have a most uncomfortable sense of "goneness" all the time, &amp; I shall welcome you home here <hi rend="italic">very heartily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can I do any thing for you in your absence?</p>
            <p>Don't forget the three things you were to bring for my especial <pb facs="loc.00940.014.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00940.015.jpg" type="recto"/>benefit. The picture, letter, &amp; "Drum Taps-"</p>
            <p>Now good bye - and very much love from us all. I have said nothing of Jeannie, she is not as well as I want to see her looking, she is out playing, or I would ask her what message to you. She asks for you often, and hopes you will soon be back.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With love always,</salute>
               <salute>Yours,</salute>
               <signed>Nelly O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Do write <hi rend="italic">very soon,</hi> &amp; direct to corner of 14th &amp; L Sts. The two letters Mr. E. has sent you, are letters that come for you. How is your head now? Your hearing? Better I hope.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nelly.</signed>
            </closer>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
