<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01448">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 9 April
                    1870</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01448</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 9 April 1870</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1870-04-09" xml:id="dat1">April 9, 1870</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas">Thomas Dixon</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-02-17" who="#al">Checked</change>
            <change when="2010-09-22" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-09-22" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01448.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>15 Sunderland Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Sunderland</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <date when="1870-04-09">April 9 1870</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have sent you a small Box of Books carriage Paid to your address in Washington. I
                expect it will leave Liverpool on Wednesday the 13th so I expect you will have it
                very soon after the arrival of this letter. I regret I could not send you some
                Indian Books I had in view when I wrote you some time ago. I mean the Bhagavad
                Gita—and the Vedas. the last is a work at present only published for the
                Scholars and Students it is in <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">8</unclear> large octavo volumes.—<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01448.002.jpg" type="verso"/> and will not all be published this year.
                However the Collection is a representative one as you will find on looking over the
                list. I have few of them so relating to our <choice>
                    <orig>modren</orig>
                    <reg>modern</reg>
                </choice> Literature as you will observe they are by men whom I highly esteem though
                I do not endorse or hold by all they teach two of the Books are connected with my
                own thoughts and Studies. Time &amp; Tide and the progress of the Working Classes
                from 1832 to 1868, compiled by two warm advocates of the working Classes. the memoir
                of Bewick is also a work I love and esteem and one that i think will be <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01448.003.jpg" type="recto"/> read by you with
                pleasure and also delight, as the utterances of a real noble honest soul, free from
                all pretensions of culture or Book-making, a truly representative Man, and lover of
                Nature, and natural Life. it is a Book I would fain see more known here and in
                America, it is so brimful of good sound sense. There is also a Portrait of Dante
                &amp; Milton both photographed by admirers of your works, and reading <choice>
                    <orig>Pamphelets</orig>
                    <reg>pamphlets</reg>
                </choice> by <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="5"/> other warm admirers of your Book, and lastly
                there is 2 remarkable Indian <choice>
                    <orig>Pamphelets</orig>
                    <reg>pamphlets</reg>
                </choice> Jesus Christ Europe &amp; Asia by Chunder Sen, an <choice>
                    <orig>Hindoo</orig>
                    <reg>Hindu</reg>
                </choice>—and one on Beneficent Government also written by an <choice>
                    <orig>Hindoo</orig>
                    <reg>Hindu</reg>
                </choice> Philosopher</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01448.004.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>Also 4 numbers of the Cooperator containing L. Napoleon's remarkable work the
                Extinction of Pauperism to me a very remarkable production despite his none fullfilment of it now
                that he is in power and position—The last I will name is the Dabistan a very
                remarkable Book by a Persian on the Schools of Religion in the East a Book after
                your own heart I think one that will be dear to you indeed, or I am much mistaken in
                your love of Books, interspersed with fine stanzas of oriental Poetry, altogether in
                my opinion a real Book. and then the <choice>
                    <orig>Sacconitala</orig>
                    <reg>Sacontala</reg>
                </choice> &amp; Indian Drama—the Flowery Scrawl, a Chinese Novel. These few
                fragments I hope will help to lift the Veil of the East to thee.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Yours Truly</salute>
                <signed>T. Dixon</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01448.006.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <postscript>
                <p>P.S.<lb/> In Emerson's new Book Society and Solitude, the Essay upon Books makes
                    references to several oriental Books. I hope that notice of them will promote
                    their publication by some Publisher or else some Society will be formed to do
                    it. people who are lovers of the Writings of Emerson &amp; Mazzini ought to take
                    the matter in hand and do it effectually. then we would possess the necessary
                    works for a proper study of Humanity in all ages and in all Countries.</p>

                
                

                <p>P.S. Friends here would like <hi rend="underline">a Portrait of your without your
                        Hat</hi>.—a Card would do—</p>
                <p>I got the 2 Newspapers you sent <hi rend="underline">me all safe</hi></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01448.005.jpg" type="recto"/>

                <p>Small Box of Books as follows, per Suttons Parcel Dispatch. addressed W. Whitman,
                    Attorney General's Office, Washington D. C. U. S. America.—<list>
                        <item>Dabistan 3 Vols Cloth—</item>
                        <item>Sacontala 1—cl<lb/></item>
                        <item>Time &amp; Tide 1——</item>
                        <item>Mazzini's Duties of Man—</item>
                        <item>Carlyle a Choice of Books.</item>
                        <item>Working Classes 1832. 1868.</item>
                        <item>Memoir of Thomas Bewick</item>
                        <item>Flowery Scrawl Chinese Novel</item>
                        <item>Words of a Believer. Lamenais</item>
                        <item>Christ Europe &amp; Asia</item>
                        <item>Beneficent Government</item>
                        <item>Cooperator with Napoleon on Pauperism</item>
                        <item>Portraits of Dante &amp; Milton</item>
                        <item>What is a Christian J. C. Street</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </postscript>



        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>