<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00947">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 30 November 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00947</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 30 November 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-11-30">November 30, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change when="2013-12-11" who="#el">added transcription/encoding of byline, title for poem enclosure</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-13">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>         
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00947.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <div1 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete">
               <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Washington.</name>
                  <date when="1864-11-30">Nov. 30. 64.</date>
                  <name type="place">400 L Street.</name>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>How I wish you were with us this beautiful day! It is so warm that I sit here with three windows wide open. I have a little fire in the stove, and the sun pours in full and strong. It is a perfect day, &amp; seems more like May than November.</p>
            <p>How are you? &amp; is there any hope of your coming this way this winter? I have hoped you would but I begin to despair of it, as you have not come yet, and we have not heard from you. <pb facs="loc.00947.002.jpg" type="verso"/>We have been feeling very blue at the prospect of losing Charley Eldridge.<ptr target="loc.00947_n1"/> The Major is to be ordered to Boston, so they hear, tho they have not got their orders yet, and of course Charley goes with him. It is two weeks since they first heard a rumor of it, but I think they will go before Christmas. As soon as he told us, I thought that that lost us one more chance of seeing you, as he had asked you to stay with him at his room. How lonely we shall be with both you &amp; Charley gone! I don't think of it any more <pb facs="loc.00947.003.jpg" type="recto"/>than I can help.</p>
            <p>Every evening we talk of you, &amp; wish you were here, &amp; almost every evening we read from Leaves of Grass, read &amp; admire. I don't believe, dear Walt, that you have in all the world, two heartier lovers &amp; appreciators than William &amp; Charley.<ptr target="loc.00947_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>What news of your brother George? I think of him very often. How is your mother now? &amp; are the babies well?</p>
            <p>I presume you have seen Mr. Howells, if so you know that he has moved his family to New York.<ptr target="loc.00947_n3"/> He has <pb facs="loc.00947.004.jpg" type="verso"/>a position in the Custom House, &amp; still retains, or was to retain his room where we called on him. Ms. Wood has not come back, &amp; the Dr. talks of leaving, if he does, I shall miss Ms. Wood, for I still hope that she will come.<ptr target="loc.00947_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>John Johnson was wounded the last of Sept. and is at home now. His arm was shot below the elbow. He come in the other day &amp; sat an hour with me. He asked for you. He was seventeen years old yesterday, &amp; has been in service more than a year, he is very impatient to get well &amp; go <pb facs="loc.00947.005.jpg" type="verso"/>back to his company.</p>
            <p>We had a letter from Mr. &amp; Mrs. Croffut, they both asked for you, you know they live in Rochester now. </p>
            <p>Do you remember Mrs. Balch who dined with us once last spring? She &amp; her husband are to live up stairs. We expect them this week from Boston. I was so glad to know that Mrs. Ginnaty was not to be my neighbor.</p>
            <p>The Gwynnes live in their own house now, &amp; I guess very much in the old way.<ptr target="loc.00947_n5"/>
            </p>
            <p>I don't know any more news to tell you. Just now I am very <pb facs="loc.00947.006.jpg" type="verso"/>well, but I was quite sick soon after I got back &amp; thought I had lost all - I had gained, but I am much better again, &amp; find that I am very much better than I was last autumn. Jeannie is well, though she, too, has had an ill turn, she is just learning to read. I teach her every day now. William has a terrible cold just now, &amp; sore throat, but has been very well &amp; vigorous, as hearty as ever.</p>
            <p>We got home very well, and had a good journey. I am glad that we had the day with you, it was some sati<pb facs="loc.00947.007.jpg" type="recto"/>sfaction to see you for even so short a time.</p>
            <p>The election passed-off well, didn't it? &amp; I am so glad that we are to have a better Congress next time. The Woods out, &amp; some others like them. This three months will soon go.</p>
            <p>We feel very hopeful about Sherman, especially as this fine weather will help him so much. Do you think Grant will do any thing this fall?</p>
            <p>The Count asks for you every time that he sees William or Charley.<ptr target="loc.00947_n6"/> He says he wants to see you, &amp; sends love.<pb facs="loc.00947.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </p>
            <p>We wished for you on Thanksgiving day. We had a quiet day, no one with us but Charley, he dined with us, &amp; we all wished that you were here.</p>
            <p>William sees Mr. Leventen sometimes, I have not seen him yet.</p>
            <p>What about your poems? Are you at work on them now? &amp; what about publishing? Have you done any thing since we came on?</p>
            <p>Write, won't you? I want to hear from you very much. I have spoken of writing every day since I came back, but have hardly touched <pb facs="loc.00947.009.jpg" type="recto"/>a pen at all.</p>
            <p>Tell me what you hear from your brother.</p>
            <p>I have not yet been in any hospital since I came home, but I mean to go.</p>
            <p>Enclosed I send you the little poem that we spoke of by Ms. Beach.<ptr target="loc.00947_n7"/>
            </p>
            <p>William says every day that he is going to write you, &amp; he will soon.</p>
            <p>How is Ms. Price?<ptr target="loc.00947_n8"/> My love to your mother, &amp; very much to you, always, dear Walt, from</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your friend</salute>
               <signed>Nelly O'Connor</signed>
            </closer>
         </div1>
         
         
         <div1 type="enclosure">
            <pb facs="loc.00947.010.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <q who="Ms. Beach">
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <note type="newspaper-editorial" rend="center">[From the New York Leader.]</note>
                     <lg type="poem">
                        <head type="main-authorial" rend="center">CLAIRE.</head>
                        <milestone unit="absent" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                        <byline rend="center">By JULIETTE H. BEACH.</byline>
                        <milestone unit="absent" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                           <l>Come, sweet, I will sing you to sleep;</l>
                           <l>Too tired, little darling, to creep?</l>
                           <l>Then lift your white hands, and my arms</l>
                           <l>From harms</l>
                           <l>And troubles the baby will keep.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                           <l>You've a musical name, baby Claire,</l>
                           <l>And the color of gold is your hair,</l>
                           <l>And your beautiful eyes, when they smile,</l>
                           <l>Beguile</l>
                           <l>The heart of your mother from care.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                           <l>You are dimpled, and dainty, and sweet,</l>
                           <l>From your head to your pink and white feet,</l>
                           <l>And they talk in your curious tongue</l>
                           <l>Among</l>
                           <l>The angels you need to meet.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                           <l>You have been with us - is it a year</l>
                           <l>Since we welcomed you first, little dear?</l>
                           <l>A year since the angels have kissed</l>
                           <l>And missed</l>
                           <l>The beauty that blesses us here!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                           <l>Fall, snowy lids, over sweet eyes,</l>
                           <l>Sweet eyes blue as midsummer skies!</l>
                           <l>Sink, pretty one, into your nest,</l>
                           <l>And rest</l>
                           <l>Dear truant from Paradise! </l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div1>
         
      </body>
      
   </text>
</TEI>
