<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03297">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 2 October
                    1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03297</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 2 October 1884</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1884-10-02" xml:id="dat1">October 2, 1884</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 14</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-24" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-05-19" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-02-14" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-17" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03297.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top">see notes May 19 '88</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1884-10-02">October 2, 1884.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I got yours of the 29th ultimo, with the slip from The <hi rend="underline"
                    >Critic</hi>.<ptr target="loc.03297_n1"/> It is a magnificent compliment, and
                was inexpressibly comforting. John Burroughs<ptr target="n0129"/> told me when he
                was here, and has since written to the same effect, that what I say on the question
                does not touch him at all, and although one <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.03297.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> does not mind such things at
                first, yet gradually, and especially when they are only part of one concurrent
                voice, they more than half persuade one that he is a visionary jackass, and have a
                deeply disheartening effect&#8212;all the more, I think, when one's convictions on
                the matter are clear and deep. There is nothing more evident to me than what
                Machiavel in <hi rend="underline">The Prince</hi> did for tyranny&#8212;i.e. sow
                death for it by <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03297.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                simply showing it up without bias and with perfect candor&#8212;Bacon (i.e.
                Shakespeare) did for feudality. It is the old story of the basilisk&#8212;if you see
                him first, he dies. In the plays&#8212;the historical plays especially&#8212;Bacon
                sees the basilisk in all his nature and proportions. </p>
            <p> I regret I am not free of office life, for I am sure I could make Bacon's part in
                all this matter so evident that Time would remember it. <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.03297.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> Criticism on Shakespeare has not
                yet begun, nor can it ever begin, until the coincidence with the Baconian
                movement&#8212;the divine conspiracy of the <hi rend="underline">Novum Organum</hi>
                against false civilization&#8212;is recognized. So far comment on Shakespeare has
                been merely esthetic. But the relation of that drama to that age&#8212;that
                marvellous "time-bettering age"&#8212;<hi rend="underline">that</hi> is the main question. </p>
            <p> I am extremely gratified <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03297.005_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> at the reinforcement your article brings. In this connection,
                please read <hi rend="underline">Coriolanus</hi>. The impersonation of the feudal military spirit in the hero
                is perfect, and there are scenes&#8212;notably that of the conference between the
                tribunes when they plan "to darken him forever"&#8212;which are revelations. </p>
            <p> I have an article before the <hi rend="underline">Manhattan</hi> which <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03297.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> I now hope more
                than ever they will publish, for it has some things about Bacon I would like you to
                read. </p>
            <p> There is a noble picture of him, from the painting by Vandyck, in the October <hi
                    rend="underline">Harper</hi>. Look at it, and ask yourself whether that face
                belongs to one who was "the meanest of mankind"! Nothing refutes a slander like a
                good portrait. </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03297.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p> I have been over today to the Surgeon General's Office to see about data for you. I
                know Dr. Huntington, the Acting Surgeon General, very well. I am afraid that the
                quest will be fruitless. The only matter they have is the "Medical and Surgical
                History of the War", now in process of publication. What you want&#8212;i.e.
                hospital matter&#8212;will be in the third volume, and this is now being made up,
                and will not be ready, <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03297.008_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> unfortunately, for a year. I am sorry. However, I will go down
                tomorrow, to the Medical Museum, and, (as Dr. Huntington suggested to me] talk with Dr.
                Wild, the librarian, and see if he can give me anything. I fear it is
                unlikely&#8212;the publications being inchoate. You shall hear duly. </p>
            <p> I am crushed with work at present. The weather is simply infernal. I wish you were
                better, and hope the coming coolness of October will revive you. More anon.<ptr target="loc.03297_n2"/></p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Faithfully,</salute>
                <signed>W.D.OC.</signed>
                <salute/>
                <salute>W.W.</salute>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>(I hope you got the little Hearn book. The thieves song in the Polynesian story
                    is wonderfully fine.<ptr target="loc.03297_n3"/></p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 
