<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01518">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 21 August [1869]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01518</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">83–85</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 21 August [1869]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1869-08-21" xml:id="dat1">August 21, 1869</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-03-08" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-29" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                    <date when="1869-08-21" rend="right">Saturday evening—Aug. 21</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Pete—</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have been very sick the last three days—I dont know what to call it—it makes me prostrated 
                &amp; deathly weak, &amp; little use of my limbs.<ptr target="loc.01518_n1"/> I have thought of you, my darling boy, very much of the time. 
                I have not been out of the house since the first day after my arrival. I had a pleasant journey 
                through on the cars Wednesday afternoon &amp; night—felt quite well then. My Mother &amp; folks are all well. 
                We are in our new house—we occupy part &amp; rent out part. I have a nice room, where I now sit writing this. 
                It is the latter part of the afternoon. I feel better the last hour or so. It has been extremely hot here 
                the last two days—I see it has been so in Washington too. I hope I shall get out soon. 
                I hanker to get out doors, &amp; down the bay.
            </p>
            
            <p>And now, dear Pete, for yourself. How is it with you, dearest boy—and is there any thing different with the face?<ptr target="loc.01518_n2"/> Dear Pete, you must forgive me for being so cold the last day &amp; evening. 
                I was unspeakably shocked and repelled from you by that talk &amp; proposition of yours—you know what—there by the fountain. It seemed indeed to me, (for I will talk out 
                plain to you, dearest comrade,) that the one I loved, and who had always been so manly 
                &amp; sensible, was gone, &amp; a fool &amp; intentional murderer stood in his place. 
                I spoke so sternly &amp; cutting. (Though I see now that my words might have appeared 
                to have a certain other meaning, which I didn't dream of, insulting to you, never for 
                one moment in my thoughts.) But I will say no more of this—for I know such thoughts must 
                have come when you was not yourself, but in a moment of derangement—&amp; have passed away like a bad dream.</p>
            
            <p>Dearest boy, I have not a doubt but you will get well, and entirely well—&amp; we will one day look back on these drawbacks &amp; sufferings as things long past. 
                The extreme cases of that malady, (as I told you before) are persons that have very 
                deeply diseased blood, probably with syphilis in it, inherited from parentage, 
                &amp; confirmed by themselves—so they have no foundation to build on. <hi rend="italic">You</hi> are of healthy stock, 
                with a sound constitution, &amp; good blood—&amp; I <hi rend="italic">know</hi> it is impossible for it to continue long. 
                My darling, if you are not well when I come back I will get a good room or two in some quiet place, 
                (or out of Washington, perhaps in Baltimore,) and we will live together, &amp; devote ourselves 
                altogether to the job of curing you, &amp; rooting the cursed thing out entirely, 
                &amp; making you stronger &amp; healthier than ever. I have had this in my mind before, 
                but never broached it to you. I could go on with my work in the Attorney General's office 
                just the same—&amp; we would see that your mother should have a small sum every week to keep the pot a-boiling at home.
            </p>
            
            <p>Dear comrade, I think of you very often. My love for you is indestructible, 
                &amp; since that night &amp; morning has returned more than before.
            </p>
            
            <p>Dear Pete, dear son, my darling boy, my young &amp; loving brother, don't let the devil 
                put such thoughts in your mind again—wickedness unspeakable—murder, death &amp; disgrace here, 
                &amp; hell's agonies hereafter<ptr target="loc.01518_n3"/>—Then what would it be afterward to the mother? What to <hi rend="italic">me</hi>?—</p>
            
            <p>Pete, I send you some money, by Adam's Express—you use it, dearest son, &amp; when it is gone, 
                you shall have some more, for I have plenty. I will write again before long—give my love to Johnny Lee,<ptr target="loc.01518_n4"/> my dear darling boy, I love him truly—(let him read these three last lines)—Dear Pete, <hi rend="italic">remember</hi>—</p>
            
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Walt</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>