<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00773">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 9 June 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00773</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">107-109</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 9 June 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-06-09">June 9, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-03">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-20">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-16">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington,</name>
                  <date when="1863-06-09">Tuesday morning | June 9th 1863.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Jeff's letter came yesterday &amp; was very welcome, as I wanted to hear about you all&#8212;I wrote to George yesterday &amp; sent Jeff's letter enclosed. It looks from some accounts as though the 9th Army corps might be going down into East Tennessee, (Cumberland Gap or perhaps bound for Knoxville.) It is an important region, &amp; has many southern unionists &#8212;the staunchest union man I have ever met is a young southerner in the 2d Tennessee (union reg't)&#8212;he was ten months in southern prisons, came up from Richmond paroled about ten weeks ago, &amp; has been in hospital here sick until lately&#8212;he suffered every thing but death, he is the one they hung up by the heels, head downwards, &amp; indeed worse than death, but stuck to his convictions like a hero&#8212;John Barker,<ptr target="loc.00773_n1"/> a real manly fellow, I saw much of him &amp; heard much of that country that can be relied on. He is now gone home to his reg't.</p>
            <p>Mother, I am feeling very well these days&#8212;my head that was stopt up so &amp; hard of hearing seems to be all right. I only hope you have had similar good fortune with your rheumatism, &amp; that it will continue so&#8212;I wish I could come in for a couple of days &amp; see you&#8212;if I should succeed in getting a transportation ticket that would take me to New York &amp; back, I should be tempted to come home for two or three days, as I want some MSS &amp; books, &amp; the trunk, &amp;c. But I will see&#8212;Mother, your letter week before last was very good&#8212;whenever you feel like it, you write me, dear mother, &amp; tell me every thing about the neighborhood, &amp; all the items of our family. And sister Mat, how is she getting along&#8212;I believe I will have to write a letter especially to her &amp; Sis, one of these times.</p>
            <p>It is awful dry weather here, no rain of any consequence for five or six weeks&#8212;we have strawberries good &amp; plenty, 15 cents a quart, with the hulls on&#8212;I go down to market sometimes of a morning &amp; buy two or three quarts, for the folks I take my meals with&#8212;Mother, do you know I have not paid, as you may say, a cent of board since I have been in Washington, that is for meals&#8212;four or five times I have made a rush to leave the folks &amp; find a moderate priced boarding house, but every time they have made such a time about it, that I have kept on&#8212;it is Mr. &amp; Mrs. O'Connor, (he is the author of "Harrington")<ptr target="loc.00773_n2"/>&#8212;he has a $1600 office in the Treasury, &amp; she is a first rate woman, a Massachusetts girl&#8212;they keep house in a moderate way&#8212;they have one little girl, (lost a fine boy about a year ago)&#8212;they have two rooms in the same house where I hire my room, &amp; I take breakfast (½ past 8) &amp; dinner (½ past 4) with them, as they will have it so&#8212;that's the way it has gone on now over five months, &amp; as I say they won't listen to my leaving&#8212;but I shall do so, I think&#8212;I can never forget their kindness &amp; real friendship &amp; it appears as though they would continue just the same, if it were for all our lives. But I have insisted on going to market, (it is pleasant in the cool of the morning,) and getting the things, at my own expense, two or three times a week lately&#8212;I pay for the room I occupy now $7 a month&#8212;the landlord is a mixture of booby, miser &amp; hog, his name is Gwin<ptr target="loc.00773_n3"/>&#8212;the landlady is a good woman, Washington raised&#8212;they are quite rich&#8212;he is Irish of the worst kind&#8212;has had a good office for ten years until Lincoln came in&#8212;They have bought another house, smaller, to live in, &amp; are going to move (were to have moved 1st of June)&#8212;they had an auction of the house we live in yesterday, but nobody came to buy, so it was ridiculous&#8212;we had a red flag out, &amp; a nigger walked up &amp; down ringing a big bell, which is the fashion here for auctions.</p>
            <p>Well, mother, the war still goes on, &amp; every thing as much in a fog as ever&#8212;&amp; the battles as bloody, &amp; the wounded &amp; sick getting worse &amp; plentier all the time. I see a letter in the Tribune from Lexington, Ky., June 5th, headed "the 9th Army Corps departing for Vicksburgh"<ptr target="loc.00773_n4"/>&#8212;but I cannot exactly make it out, on reading the letter carefully&#8212;I don't see any thing in the letter about the 9th corps moving for Vicksburgh&#8212;at any rate I think the 2d division is more likely to be needed in Kentucky (or as I said, in Eastern Tennessee) as the secesh are expected to make trouble there&#8212;But one can hardly tell&#8212;the only thing is to resign onesself to events as they occur&#8212;it is a sad &amp; dreary time, for so many thousands of parents &amp; relatives, not knowing what will occur next&#8212;Mother, I told you I think last week that I had wrote to Han, &amp; enclosed George's last letter to me&#8212;I wrote a week ago last Sunday&#8212;I wonder if she got the letter&#8212;About the pictures, I should like Jeff to send them, as soon as convenient&#8212;might send 20 of the big head, 10 or 12 of the standing figure, &amp; 3 of the carte visite.</p>
            <p>I am writing this in Major Hapgood's office&#8212;it is bright &amp; pleasant, only the dust here in Washington is a great nuisance. Mother, your shirts do first rate. I am wearing them&#8212;the one I have on today suits me better than any I have ever yet had. I have not worn the thin coat the last week or so, as it has not been very hot lately.</p>
            <p>Mother, I think something of commencing a series of lectures &amp; readings &amp;c.<ptr target="loc.00773_n5"/> through different cities of the north, to supply myself with funds for my Hospital &amp; Soldiers visits&#8212;as I do not like to be beholden to the medium of others&#8212;I need a pretty large supply of money &amp;c. to do the good I would like to&#8212;&amp; the work grows upon me, &amp; fascinates me&#8212;it is the most affecting thing you ever see, the lots of poor sick &amp; wounded young men that depend so much, in one ward or another, upon my petting or soothing or feeding, sitting by them &amp; feeding them their dinner or supper, some are quite helpless&#8212;some wounded in both arms&#8212;or giving some trifle (for a novelty or a change, it isn't for the value of it,) or stopping a little while with them&#8212;nobody will do but me&#8212;So, mother, I feel as though I would like to inaugurate a plan by which I could raise means on my own hook, &amp; perhaps quite plenty too. Best love to you, dearest mother, &amp; to sister Mat &amp; Jeff.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
