<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05094">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 28
                    November [1881]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05094</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Horst Frenz</editor>
                        <title xml:id="hf">Whitman and Rolleston: A
                            Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Bloomington</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Indiana University Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1951">1951</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">43&#8211;47</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 28 November [1881]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-11-28" xml:id="dat1">November 28, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>



        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H.
                        Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-03" who="#nhg">updated sender name</change>
            <change when="2014-02-18" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-31" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-02" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1881-11-28">Nov. 28 [1881]</date>
                    <name type="place">29 Lange Strasse</name>
                    <name type="place">Dresden<ptr
                            target="loc.05094_n1"/></name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yesterday I received all your dispatches&#8212;viz, a postcard&#8212;a letter&#8212;a
                circular (with scraps)&#8212;a copy of <choice><abbr>L of G</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice>&#8212;and a set of
                proofsheets of ditto. Shall find them very useful. For all of which things, many
                thanks&#8212;I am delighted to see your new <choice>
                    <abbr>edn</abbr>
                    <reg>edition</reg>
                </choice> in such grand form, and spent all yesterday reading it.<ptr target="loc.05094_n2"/> Sometimes I missed
                regretfully a familiar rhythm and was sorry to see 'Respondez' cut up and scattered
                about the book&#8212;most of it summarily suppressed. It was, of course, rather a
                gritty poem to read straight through. Still I am very glad that I have it complete
                in my old <choice>
                    <abbr>edn</abbr><reg>edition</reg></choice>.<ptr target="loc.05094_n3"/> Nearly always I have come to think your many alterations, improvements.
                This volume, with its new poems, etc. offered a field of "pleasant exploration" and
                renewed my sense of wonder and delight at your works. It is a splendid thing to have
                given them final form in this way&#8212;resumed them all in this noble volume. I
                like many of your new poems immensely, especially perhaps 'Spirit that form'd this
                scene'&#8212;a Riddle Song, and the Dalliance of the Eagles. The Riddle Song puzzled
                me&#8212;I could only think of (for the 'two words')<ptr target="loc.05094_n4"/> the end of a sonnet of W. B.
                Scott</p>

            <p><q who="Scott"><lg type="linegroup"><l>For we know nought of that dark sun, the True,</l>
            <l>Whose latent heats create our spiritual year.<ptr target="loc.05094_n5"/></l></lg></q>

            Yet I don't feel as if this could be it.&#8212;</p>
            <p>I am very glad you like the idea of a German translation. I have had a reported
                admirer of yours, as collaborateur in my eye for some time, but I find now he is
                only a rather pedantic old savan, and that his knowledge of and admiration for you
                are both of a very limited character. However I will go on by myself at present and
                have a good mass of work ready for revision when I find the right man. The work
                shall certainly be done, and done as well as my pains and the best German help can
                do it. From attempts I have made I am convinced that a very impressive, quite
                satisfactory translation of your <choice><abbr>L of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice> might be made in German. It is
                a language, which, as Germans well know, offers extraordinary facilities for
                translation especially poetic, from foreign tongues, e.g. a Greek play, which is a
                bald affair in the best English, can be put into German with all the choral metres,
                etc. accurately preserved, and lose little of its freshness and energy. Of course
                the <choice>
                    <abbr>transl.</abbr>
                    <reg>translation</reg>
                </choice> would be complete&#8212;a reproduction of your new <choice>
                    <abbr>vol.</abbr>
                    <reg>volume</reg>
                </choice> just as it is.</p>
            <p>I think a <hi rend="italic">Russian</hi> translation is also probable (and certainly
                at least as desirable as the German). A friend and countryman of mine named Lee,<ptr target="loc.05094_n6"/>
                living here, is an ardent Russian scholar and intimate with many men of that nation,
                living here and in Servia, etc. They are mostly exiles, which means, speaking
                generally, men of unusual ability and thoughtfulness. I have made Lee acquainted
                with the <choice><abbr>L of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice> which he appreciates, and he has just written for your
                new <choice>
                    <abbr>edn</abbr><reg>edition</reg></choice>. And I think (though I have not broached the subject yet) that he would be
                likely to undertake a Russian translation, and that he could get the best possible
                help for it. I shall get him to lend his book to some of his Russian friends, and
                work on this as much as I can. The book would doubtless be prohibited by Government
                but that would not hinder its spread much, rather the contrary.<ptr target="loc.05094_n7"/> I shall have one or
                two things to ask you about with reference to the German <choice>
                    <abbr>transl</abbr><reg>translation</reg></choice>. Can now only think of the word 'equals' in <hi rend="italic">To him that
                    was Crucified</hi>. I take this (contrary to the general opinion as far as I
                know) <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to imply that the little band of teachers are equal
                among themselves (there seems little significance in saying this) but rather that
                they are the equals of all other men&#8212;able to put themselves on common footing with
                all they meet, and establish free, healthy relations with them&#8212;as the
                Answerer&#8212;"the mechanics take him for a mechanic"&#8212;etc. etc. In this sense
                I should be inclined to translate the word.&#8212;Indeed though, as far as the
                translation goes, the word could be literally rendered in German and have both
                meanings open, as in English, and this of course would be the right thing to do.</p>
            <p>Are you sure about the double text of English and German? It seems to me as if it
                would give the book a formidably scientific appearance. Did anyone ever get much
                comfort out of one of those polyglot bibles with the Greek, Hebrew, Latin, English, <choice>
                    <sic>Objibbeway</sic>
                    <corr>Ojibwe</corr>
                </choice> etc., all arranged in parallel columns? And would people buy largely a
                book of poems of which half was in an unknown tongue? I see the advantages of the
                plan&#8212;but, at present at least, it appears to me that the disadvantages
                preponderate, especially as your works could be rendered, I think, with full
                accuracy in German&#8212;really reproducing both form and matter.&#8212;I believe
                the work would strike root <hi rend="italic">deeply</hi> in Germany and might be of
                vast importance.</p>
            <p>Did you see that the Fortschritt<ptr target="loc.05094_n8"/> ( = more or less Girondist) party have had great
                successes at the last elections here?</p>
            <p>I have ordered my book to be sent to the American papers you mentioned. I shall be
                here for a year certainly. Will always let you know my movements and about the
                translation, etc.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
                <signed>W. Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>You should have <choice>
                        <abbr>recd.</abbr>
                        <reg>received</reg>
                    </choice> a copy of my Encheiridion by this.</p>
            </postscript>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
