<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01943">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Charles Warren Stoddard to Walt Whitman, 2
                    March 1869</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Charles Warren Stoddard</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01943</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Charles Warren Stoddard</author>
                    <title>Charles Warren Stoddard to Walt Whitman, 2 March 1869</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1869-03-02" xml:id="dat1">March 2, 1869</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Stoddard, Charles Warren">Charles Warren Stoddard</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-08-08" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-05-02" who="#al">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-04-04" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01943.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1869-03-02"><hi rend="underline">1869</hi></date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Honolulu. Hawaiian Islands.</name>
                    <date when="1869-03-02">2nd <hi rend="underline">March</hi>.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>To <hi rend="underline">Walt Whitman</hi>.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>May I quote you a couplet from your "Leaves of Grass"?
                
            <q who="Walt Whitman">
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"Stranger! If you, passing, meet me,</l>
                            <l>"and desire to speak to me, why</l>
                            <l>"should you not speak to me?</l>
                            <l>"And why should I not speak to you?"</l>                            
                        </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
            
            —I am the stranger who, passing, desires to speak to you. Once before I have done so, offering you a few feeble verses. I do not wonder you did not reply to them. Now my voice is stronger, I ask, <hi rend="underline">why will</hi> you not speak to me?</p>
            
            <p>So fortunate as to be traveling in these very interesting islands I have done wonders in my intercourse with these natives.
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01943.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                
For the first time I act as my nature prompts me. It would not answer in America, as a general principle, not even in California where men are tolerably bold. This is my mode of life:—At dusk I reach some village, a few grass huts by the sea or in some valley. The native villagers gather about me, for strangers are not common in these parts. I observe them closely. Superb looking, many of them. Fine heads. Glorious eyes that question, observe and then trust or distrust with an infallible instinct. Proud, defiant lips, a matchless physique, grace and freedom in every motion. I mark one, a lad of eighteen or twenty years who is regarding me. I call him to me, ask his name 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01943.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
               
                
giving mine in return. He speaks it over and over, manipulating my body unconsciously, as it were, with bountiful and unconstrained love. I go to his grass-house, eat with him his simple food, sleep with him upon his mats, and at night sometimes waken to find him watching me with earnest, patient looks, his arm over my breast and around me. In the morning he hates to have me go. I hate as much to leave him. Over and over I think of him as I travel: he doubtless recalls me some times, perhaps wishes me back with him. We were known to one another, perhaps twelve hours. Yet I cannot forget him. Any thing that pertains to him now interests me.</p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01943.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
           
            
            <p>You will easily imagine, my dear sir, how delightful I find this life. I read your Poems with a new spirit, to understand them as few may be able to. And I wish more than ever that I might possess a few lines from your pen. I want your personal magnetism to quicken mine, how else shall I have it? Do write me a few lines for they will be of immense value to me.</p>
            
            <p>I wish it were possible to get your photograph. The small <hi rend="underline">Lithograph</hi> I have of you is not wholly satisfactory. But I would not ask so much of you. Only a page with your name &amp; mine as you write it–Is this too much?</p>
            
            <p>My address is San Francisco, Cal <hi rend="italic">Box 1005. P. O.</hi> I shall immediately return there.</p>
            
            <closer rend="right">
                <salute>In all places I am the same to you.</salute>
                <signed>Chas. Warren Stoddard..</signed>
            </closer>        

        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>