<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05118">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 5 June 1881</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05118</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page, &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">200&#8211;202</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 5 June 1881</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-06-05" xml:id="dat1">June 5, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Herbert">Herbert Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-04-16" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-02-04" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-23" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-18" who="#kc">Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Keats Corner, Well Road</name>
                    <name type="place">North London</name>
                    <name type="place">Hampstead, England</name>
                    <date when="1881-06-05">June 5th, 1881, Sunday afternoon</date>
                    <date when="1881-06-05">5 P. M.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>MY DEAR WALT:<!--<ptr target="n0262"/>--></salute>
            </opener>

            <p>You don't write me a letter nor take any notice of my magnificent offers concerning
                "Pond Musings",<!--<ptr target="pml.00050_n9"/>--> etc. however, I will forgive you this oft-repeated
                offence. I often think of you, very often of America and things generally there, and
                nearly always with pleasure.</p>

            <p>My mother<!--<ptr target="n0259"/>--> is away staying with Beatrice<!--<ptr target="n0260"/>--> in Edinburgh city, recruiting her health,
                which has most sadly needed it of late. So I and Grace<!--<ptr target="n0890"/>--> &amp; a new Scotch lassie,
                one Margaret, who officiates as servant most efficaciously too, I can tell you (such
                scrubbing &amp; cleaning as you never saw the like) we three, I say, are alone at
                Keats Corner; cool sitting here in our long drawing-room (hung with
                innumerable pictures as of yore), although it has been scorchingly hot this past
                month. The morning I spend sketching on Hampstead Heath, which is lovely just now,
                all the May-trees are in full bloom the gorse &amp; broom are a blaze of
                yellow, the rooks fly constantly by a quarter of a mile (seemingly) overhead,
                the sly fellows giving some side like dart when you look up at them even at that
                height. I am painting one of them; so I have to look up pretty often. In the
                early morning the nightingale sings, oh, so sweetly, long trills &amp;
                roulades in the most accomplished manner.</p>

            <p>Last Wednesday Miss Ellen Terry,<!--<ptr target="n3051"/>--> whose name you are doubtless familiar with as being
                the leading actress in London, well, she called upon me to ask my advice or opinion
                of a drawing connected with my father's book. Ellen Terry expressed herself highly
                interested in our house, pictures, decorations and so forth. Her manner was a little
                stagey, but graceful to the extreme, and you could see peeping out of this theatric
                manner a kind, good heart, oh, so kind, I feel as if I would do anything for her,
                her manners were so winning. "Will you come to the stage entrance of the
                Lyceum some day soon and you shall have stalls for two; now will you come? Do."
                Were her last words to Grace. I called on her at Kensington last week, returning the
                drawing, and I was so charmed with two beautiful children of hers, a tall, fair
                girl, a pretty mixture of shyness and self-possession that quite won me. She
                too I should fancy will be a great actress some day, she has such a bright face, The
                boy, Master Ted,<!--<ptr target="n3052"/>--> was nice too.</p>

            <p>Well, I gave Ellen Terry a proof of a drawing that I have just completed for Dr.
                Bucke's<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>--> book&#8212;a job I got through Buxton Forman,<!--<ptr target="n0240"/>--> a great friend of Bucke's,
                done <hi rend="italic">con amore</hi> on my part. This drawing has been beautifully
                reproduced by the new photo intaglio-process.<!--<ptr target="n3053"/>--> I hope Dr. Bucke will like it,
                but I should not expect great things from him in that line, judging from the
                twopenny hapenny little pen &amp; ink sketch by Waters which he sent over in the
                first instance; however, Forman rescued him from that &amp; so far he has been
                guided by his friend. Whether he will when he sees my drawing, we neither of us
                know; but both feel to have done our best in the matter. I said that Ellen Terry
                must ask for you when she goes to America, which she contemplates some day. I have
                sold the last drawing I made in New York of you for &#163;10. 10s to Buxton Forman
                (&#36;50. odd). Church bells have just commenced chiming in the distance, a sound I
                like better than the parsons. I hear that the young American artists are
                doing capitally filling their pockets. My cousin Sidney Thomas is, or was, in
                America, a good deal lionized, I understand. If at any time you favour me with a
                letter let it be a letter and not a postcard please. I have been reading Carlyle's
                reminiscences&#8212;good stuff in them, brilliant touches, but dreadfully morbid,
                don't you think? &amp; one shuts the book up with a feeling that in some respect
                one Carlyle<!--<ptr target="n0139"/>--> is enough in the world: &amp; yet in some respects a million
                wouldn't be too many. I often think of your remark to us one day that tolerance is
                the rarest quality in the world.</p>

            <p>Interested in those Boston scraps you send my mother. You have always been pretty
                well received in Boston, have you not&#8212;I mean in the Emerson days? Pity
                that when Emerson is no more there will be no fine portrait of him in
                existence; there was a nobility stamped upon his face that I never saw the like
                of, and which should have been caught and stamped forever on canvas.</p>

            <p>We all see something of the Formans &amp; all like them; they have so much
                character, rather unusual in literary folk of the lighter sort, I fancy; but
                there is something very fresh and original about Forman. Nice children they have,
                too. Miss Blind<!--<ptr target="n0092"/>--> is bringing out a volume of poems; why will people all imagine
                they can write poetry? William Rossetti<!--<ptr target="n0522"/>--> is writing a hundred
                sonnets&#8212;writes one a day; one about John Brown is not bad: and many
                are instructive, but are in no sense poems. I am going down to tea &amp; must not
                keep Grace waiting any longer. Love to you.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">HERBERT H. GILCHRIST.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
