<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03042">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 20 May
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03042</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 20 May 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-05-20" xml:id="dat1">May 20, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-04-29" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-18" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-12" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-05" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-10" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03042.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1882-05-20" rend="right">May 20, 1882</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:<!--<ptr target="n2002"/>--></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have yours of the 17<hi rend="superscipt">th</hi>, and also your picture, for which many thanks.<!--<ptr target="loc.03042_n1"/>--> It is a fine
                presentment.</p>
            <p>My article has gone to the <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi><!--<ptr target="n3077"/>--> with a note to Whitelaw Reid,<!--<ptr target="n0500"/>--> and we await the
                result. I hope, if it appears, you will like it. Of course, you are not in any way
                responsible for it, and <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03042.004_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> this is the position for you to take. Learning the facts, I use
                the independent privilege of a friend, and of a citizen, to criticise the offenders.
                    <hi rend="underline">I alone am responsible.</hi></p>
            <p>I composed the article under great affliction, for as the devil would have it, there
                were several days of shocking raw weather, followed by five consecutive days of
                rain, and I got the influenza, <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03042.005_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> and was half dead with headache, a racking cough and all the
                accompaniments. Nothing therefore was right for composition but the heart. Despite
                conditions, Charley Eldridge, who got here from California in time to read what I
                have written, and of whose cool-headedness and judgmatical quality I think highly,
                considers it the best thing I have done, <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.03042.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> which I hope will prove true. At
                all events, if it gets printed, it will be the opening gun in a tremendous
                cannonade, and we will have war on the enemy in England at any rate, which is what
                will hurt Oliver Stevens<!--<ptr target="upa.00201_n2"/>--> and company here.</p>
            <p> My object is to smoke the hidden movers in this business out of their holes, and I
                kept this in mind through the whole composition. <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc.03042.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                Hence, although I knew that
                Marston was behind the Boston attorney, I took care not to even mention his name,
                but focussed all my fire right upon Oliver Stevens, who, you know, is the only one
                that appears officially in the transaction. He will never endure to be exclusively
                blistered <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03042.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> in
                this way, but will in defence inculpate the State Attorney General. The minute he
                brings him forward, I will give them both the devil. In the present article, I have
                been very guarded, and have interwoven fury with moderation, but when we get Marston
                to the front, there will be augmented <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="loc.03042.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/> fire for his hide, and I hope to
                make it so intolerable for him, that he will in self-defence peach on the holy
                citizens who have egged him on. Then, when we get their names, will be the time for
                punishment, memorable and terrible. They shall never be forgotten. The whole gang
                shall hang in chains for <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03042.010_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> all time.</p>
            <p>This must be our object&#8212;to discover the history of this persecution&#8212;the
                names of the subterranean movers. You must help me in this all you can. Perhaps
                Lathrop<!--<ptr target="sjs.00016_n6"/>--> can discover.</p>
            <p>You are quite right in feeling as you do toward Osgood &#38; Co.,<!--<ptr target="loc.03477_n1"/>--> besides being
                magnanimous, but <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03042.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                it is not for me, nor for anyone else to approve their course, which has simply
                been on the lowest plane of huckster prudence. You had grounds against them for an
                action for damages. They solicited your book, they knew its character, they agreed
                to non-expurgation, and at the first breath of <pb xml:id="leaf005v"
                    facs="loc.03042.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/> trouble, they flunked. It is all
                right for you to take such an attitude as you do toward them&#8212;for <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
                personally; but my part, and the part of all your friends, is to whale them. You, of
                course, are not responsible.</p>
            <p>I have a strong suspicion that when the truth comes to be known, <pb
                    xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03042.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/> the Rev. Thomas
                Wentworth Higginson<!--<ptr target="nyp.00440_n9"/>--> will be found behind the State Attorney General as an
                instigator. His tone toward you, in the <hi rend="underline">Woman's Journal</hi>
                article (and the <hi rend="underline">Nation</hi> was probably his,) shows extreme
                venom. I know him, and know just where he is vulnerable, and will in due time plant
                a javelin where it will do him good.</p>
            <p>I have seen and <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03042.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                read twice your article in the N. A. Review.<!--<ptr target="nyp.00441_n5"/>--> It is splendid, and cannot fail to do
                good. I only wish the style was a little clearer. I like better your earlier manner,
                so free from sub-clauses, involutions, parentheses&#8212;so direct and simple. In
                this country, in this age, when the necessity is upon us of addressing the whole
                people, and <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03042.015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                not
                the college professors or bookmen merely, I set extreme value upon communication. To
                be readily apprehended by your auditory is, the truth being yours, the whole
                battle.</p>
            <p>Your position in the Review article is impregnable. Gibraltar is less strong. It only
                remains to show the relations of poetic statements to these <pb xml:id="leaf007v"
                    facs="loc.03042.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/> didactic truths. With many
                excellent people, especially when devoid of imagination, the trouble is to accept a
                passional expression, though they are quite willing to accept one simply
                descriptive, as in a physiological treatise. We live in a cursed abyss of society.
                Everything is sophisticated, everything polluted. To <pb xml:id="leaf008r"
                    facs="loc.03042.017_large.jpg" type="recto"/> a sane man or woman it is simply
                monstrous that the august and tender supra-mortal experience of a nuptial night,
                <hi rend="underline">cannot</hi> be put into living poetry.</p>
            <p>&#8212;I hope my <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> letter will appear and be satisfactory to you. It cost me great
                pains, as I had to move gingerly and with audacity at the same time. You will see how
                I have worked <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.03042.018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Emerson's letter against Stevens like an engine.</p>
            <p>You must be careful in what you say of Emerson's position toward your amative
                passages. You have often told us that in his talk with you on the Common he had
                nothing to say on intrinsic grounds against these passages, but only on commercial
                or popular grounds. I remember your telling me that it was the saddest thing you
                ever heard that Emerson had <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc.03042.019_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>
                nothing to urge in all his vehement talk, but that the exclusion
                of these passages would make the book sell better. Nor could he have had. These
                passages are capable of the most unanswerable vindication on purely intellectual
                grounds merely, not to go deeper, and this Emerson knew. In his <pb
                    xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc.03042.020_large.jpg" type="verso"/> letter to you he
                approves them. What else does his panegyric on your "<hi rend="underline">courage of
                    treatment</hi>" mean?&#8212;I mention this because I have thought from your way of
                mentioning the matter, that the enemy might say that you had allowed that Emerson
                was opposed to these passages on <hi rend="underline">moral</hi> grounds, which
                would be untrue.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good-bye,</salute>
                <salute>Yours faithfully</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="loc.03042.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="loc.03042.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
