<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01816">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 13 August 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
               Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.01816</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
                  the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                  copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce
                  the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals
                  for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
               <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 13 August 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-08-13">August 13, 1864</date>
               <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                  Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
               Traubel</persName></handNote>
         </handNotes>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n4992">William D. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2015-06-14" who="#ss">added more annotations</change>
         <change when="2015-05-14" who="#kmp">blessed</change>
         <change when="2015-05-12" who="#nhg">moved correspondent note up to ref</change>
         <change when="2015-01-22" who="#nhg">checked, corrected, updated image names</change>
         <change who="#ak" when="2015-01-16">added images, checked trancriptions, removed
            biblStruct, merged to loc id</change>
         <change when="2014-11-06" who="#nhg">added date to biblStruct</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-12">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-03">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-17">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03022.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <opener rend="right">
            <dateline>
               <name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>
               <date when="1864-08-13">August 13, 1864.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My dear Walt:</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am enraged and ashamed with myself to have never sent you a word responsive to your
            letters of July 5th &amp; 24th. Believe that I have thought of you much, however, and
            for the last fortnight I have talked of you incredibly, saying superb things all the
            time, to Mr. Channing<ptr target="loc.01257_n1"/> whom you know, and to Miss Griffith
            whom perhaps you have not heard of. She is a handsome and heroic Kentucky girl, who
            several years ago impoverished herself by liberating her slaves, (seven of them, I
            think,) and then came North to live, the South being hateful to her on account of
            slavery. She lives in New York, but has come on here for a time and <pb
               xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03022.004.jpg" type="verso"/>is staying with her sister
            in Georgetown. She had heard much of you and was anxious to hear about you from me, whom
            she likes (of course!!!). So I told her much, painting you as the gigantesque angel of
            valor, compassion, and poetry that you are, and reciting moreover all the splendid
            passages from your book that I could remember, besides numerous excerpts from your
            forthcoming volume! This, you see, involved considerable conversation about you and you
            must admit that I have kept you well in mind.</p>
         <p>I am indeed glad to know from your letter and from a recent report from Howells that you
            are getting better. I have felt very anxious about you. At times I had dreads <pb
               xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03022.005.jpg" type="recto"/>that I did not like to own
            to myself. But the sky now seems clearing if not all clear and I can trust to see you
            well again and strong.</p>
         <p>The heat of the last fortnight has been fearful, but tonight, thank goodness, there has
            been a rattling thunder storm, flash and crash, with a deluge of rain and the moon now
            shines through broken clouds on an earth drenched and cool. It was such rain as we have
            often seen here from my windows, only this time I saw it all alone.</p>
         <p>I drill every day between three and four in the afternoon. It is fine exercise and good
            for me, though what with the torrid sun (for we drill <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
               facs="loc.03022.006.jpg" type="verso"/> out of doors) and the weight of a sixteen
            pound rifle with accoutrements, it is pretty severe.</p>
         <p>Glad you got the Report on Armored Vessels. I thought it might yield hints for poems. At
            all events, it gives one a good idea of what the Monitors are and can do. They are, as I
            once said to you, an upheld finger of warning to all despotocracy. The Dictators will
            prove a clenched hand of menace to the same. Soon America can defy all outward foes.</p>
         <p>I want very much to hear that "Drum Taps" are printing. I have many misgivings about
            your plan of getting out the book yourself. I want it to have a large sale, as I think
               <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03022.007.jpg" type="recto"/> it well might, and I am
            afraid that this sort of private publication will keep it from being known or accessible
            to any considerable number of people. Such a volume ought to make your fame secure and
            with a good publisher I think it would. How I wish Eldridge was in the field!</p>
         <p>Are you going to get it done by subscription? I want to know because I want to help as
            much as I can. The rascally Congress taxes me in September fifty dollars in a lump,
            besides my usual income tax, so that I shall not be able to do as well as I intended,
            but if subscription is the order of the day, I mean to give as much as I can. So let me
            know.</p>
         <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03022.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
         <p>Eldridge<ptr target="loc.00943_n2"/> is down at Petersburgh paying troops. Alas, Walt!
            There is no hope of Richmond. The campaign has proved a failure. Every thing shows that
            Grant is coming back and the next fighting will probably be in the Shenandoah Valley if
            not in Ohio or Pennsylvania. It is sad to think of the eighty thousand men, veterans,
            lost so fruitlessly.&#8212;I think Mr Lincoln's chances for the next presidency are very
            small. Victory at Atlanta is possible, and may save him, but the signs are that the
            party will withdraw him and run some other man.&#8212;I see New York had one of her
            oceanic meetings for McClellan lately. I fear he will be our next President.</p>
         <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03022.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <p>I am glad your brother continues unscathed. I think of him whenever there is
            fighting.</p>
         <p>Howells<ptr target="loc.00944_n2"/> gave me splendid accounts of your mother.<ptr
               target="n0705"/> I hope I shall yet know her.</p>
         <p>Ashton<ptr target="duk.00644_n4"/> is away at Schooley's Mountain, New York,
            vacationizing. I am quite alone here, save for the society of Miss Griffith, whom I go
            to see pretty often. The house is awfully lonely with Nelly<ptr target="duk.00602_n1"/>
            away, and I don't like to stay in it.</p>
         <p>The Count<ptr target="med.00324_n2"/> I have not seen for several weeks. The last time I
            saw him, he abused me frightfully&#8212;for the first time! I happened to say, very
            quietly, that the Rebels would probably repeat their raid into Maryland very soon. (A
            week afterward they did so and burned Chambersburgh). <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
               facs="loc.03022.010.jpg" type="verso"/>Whereupon the Count clutched his straw hat
            down upon his head with both hands, danced like a demon on the pavement, howled out "You
            are an <hi rend="underline">ass</hi>!" and, in a word, behaved like a maniac. Indeed his
            conduct convinced me that he is a madman with lucid intervals. I seriously mean it. No
            one could burst into such tempests of rage and abuse on so slight an occasion and be
            sane. A few nights afterward, he undertook to discipline the firemen with a pistol,
            during a conflagration, because they did not move quickly enough, for which freak he
            suffered fine and imprisonment.</p>
         <p>I hope you will come back here this Fall, dear Walt, and that our former days and nights
            may be renewed. For this time, good bye.</p>
         <closer rend="right">
            <salute>Your faithful</salute>
            <signed>W.D.O'C.</signed>
         </closer>
         <postscript>
            <p>I will send your letter to Nelly!</p>
         </postscript>
         <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03022.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <note resp="#ht" type="editorial" place="top">see notes Dec 17th 1888</note>
         <note resp="#ww" type="editorial" place="left">W D. O'Connor | Washington Aug 13
            1864</note>
         <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03022.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
