<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00442">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 29 September 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00442</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">116-117</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 29 September 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-09-29">September 29, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.,</name>
                  <date when="1865-09-29">Sept. 29th 1865</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We hav'nt heard from you for some time<ptr target="loc.00442_n1"/>&#8212;you say the bundle was not the right one&#8212;I read the label and thought it read the same as you described in your letter&#8212;would you like me to send the other or right one if I can find it&#8212;Mother told me she knew the one you meant and that she would put it on the table for me<ptr target="loc.00442_n2"/>&#8212;that is the one I sent</p>
            <p>We had a letter from Mother to-day&#8212;she seems pretty well&#8212;talks a little of coming home but does not say when&#8212;I have just written her this eve&#8212;We are all as well as usual&#8212;the baby has a bad boil on its forehead but I suppose it will get well in a day or two and then she will be all right again&#8212;it looks just now though about as bad as anything of the kind I ever saw  by-the-way it was me that had the "run around" on the finger<ptr target="loc.00442_n3"/>&#8212;and I have just got well of it&#8212;and a cussed bad time I had of it too&#8212;it accounts for my not writing you before&#8212;</p>
            <p>George is getting along first rate I guess&#8212;He dont say any more about getting a position in the Custom House&#8212;I hope he wont try but I am quite sure that if he can keep devoted to his present undertaking he will make a handsome fortune in 8 or ten years<ptr target="loc.00442_n4"/>&#8212;he certainly has the prospect of it&#8212;there is an immense amount of building in the city this season&#8212;though material is wonderful high&#8212;brick $12 per thousand&#8212;should be abt 5 or 6&#8212;I have given up all thought of building this fall&#8212;at one time I thought I would sure  perhaps next spring will be better</p>
            <p>Matters about Brooklyn are much the same&#8212;with me just the same&#8212;Mr Kirkwood<ptr target="loc.00442_n5"/> has been on a visit to Brooklyn and just gone back to St. Louis&#8212;I think it more than likely that he will build the water works of that city&#8212;if so it will be as large a job as the Brooklyn works</p>
            <p>The Doctor<ptr target="loc.00442_n6"/> returned from the country last week&#8212;he looks first rate&#8212;says he had a wonderfully good time&#8212;he was spending the summer up in Vermont near Burlington&#8212;speaks of it as being a splendid place to live&#8212;</p>
            <p>In her letter to-day Mother says she wants either you or George to come on and come home with her<ptr target="loc.00442_n7"/>&#8212;so I suppose she begins to think of coming home</p>
            <p>Mattie and the children desire to send their love to you&#8212;the child[ren] are growing first rate&#8212;</p>
            <p>I wish you would write me  I want to know how things are going with you</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
