<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01588">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 6 October [1868]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01588</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">55–56</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 6 October [1868]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1868-10-06" xml:id="dat1">October 6, 1868</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2011-08-01" who="#el">updated WWA ID referring to Doyle's letter</change>
            <change when="2011-03-07" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-21" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1868-10-06" rend="right">Oct 6</date><ptr target="loc.01588_n1"/>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Pete,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>There is nothing special with me to write to you about. The time slips away mighty quick. 
                It seems but a day or two since I left Wash, yet I am now on the fourth week of my furlough. 
                Last night was about the greatest political show I ever saw, even in New York—a grand 
                Democratic meeting &amp; torch-light processions. I was out in the midst of them, to see the sights. 
                I always enjoy seeing the city let loose, and on the rampage, as it was last night 
                to the fullest extent. I cannot begin to tell you how the Democrats showed themselves 
                by thousands &amp; tens of thousands. The whole city was lit up with torches. 
                Cannons were fired all night in various parts of the city. As I was on my way home 
                in a 2d av. car between 12 &amp; 1 o'clock we got blocked in by a great part of the returning procession. 
                Of course we had to just stand &amp; take it. I enjoyed it hugely from the front platform. 
                They were nearly an hour passing us, streaming both sides. In the procession were all sorts of objects, 
                models of ships, forty or fifty feet long, full-manned, cars of liberty with women, 
                &amp;c &amp;c. The ranks spread across the street, &amp; every body carried a blazing torch. 
                Fireworks were going off in every direction. The sky was full of big balloons, 
                letting off rockets &amp; Roman candles, 'way up among the stars. The excitement, the rush, 
                &amp; the endless torches, gave me great pleasure. Ever &amp; anon, the cannon, some near some distant. 
                I heard them long after I got to bed. It sounded like a distant engagement. 
                I send you the Herald with a sort of account of the show, but it doesn't do 
                half justice to it.<ptr target="loc.01588_n2"/> The speeches were of no account at all.
            </p>
            
            <p>I suppose you got a letter &amp; paper from me Saturday, Oct 3. I rec'd your welcome letter of Oct 1,<ptr target="loc.01588_n3"/> also the Star.<ptr target="loc.01588_n4"/> I read Mr. Noyes<ptr target="loc.01588_n5"/> 
                western letters with pleasure. So you have something new in RR—new officers &amp; rules. 
                The RR business here is very different. They go through these long routes 
                on the rush—no mercy to cattle. The 3d av. RR. lost 36 horses in one day 
                last summer, one of those hot days. We are having pleasant weather just now, 
                seems like Indian summer. So long, dear Pete. From your loving comrade.
            </p>           
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>