<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00588">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen Eyre to Walt Whitman, 25 March 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Ellen Eyre</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00588</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ellen Eyre</author>
               <title>Ellen Eyre to Walt Whitman, 25 March 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-03-25">March 25, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Eyre, Ellen">Ellen Eyre</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-12-15">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-20">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-07-28">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-07">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline><!-- <name type="place">DR G P WIKSELL. 410 HOTEL PELHAM. BOSTON.</name> --><!-- This information was on the hotel stationary. -->
                  <date when="1860-02-10">Tuesday Mar 25 1862</date>
                  <name type="person">Walt Whitman</name>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Mr. Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="loc.00588_n100"/> fear you took me last night for a female privateer. It's true that I was sailing under <hi rend="italic">false colors</hi>.&#8212;But the flag I assure you covered nothing piratical&#8212;although I would joyfully have made your heart a captive.</p>
            <p>Women have an unequal chance in this world. Men are its monarchs, and "full many a rose is born to blush unseen and waste its sweetness in the desert air."<ptr target="loc.00588_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Such I was resolved should not be the fate of this fancy I had long nourished for you.&#8212;A gold mine may be found by the Divining Rod but there is no such instrument for detecting in the crowded streets of a great city the [unknown?] mine of latent affection a man may have unconsciously inspired in a woman's heart. I make these explanations in extenuation not by way of apology. My social position enjoins precaution &amp; mystery, and perhaps the enjoyment of my friend's society is heightened which in yielding to its fascination I preserve my incognito; yet mystery lends an ineffable charm to love and when a woman is bent upon the gratification of her inclinations&#8212;She is pardonable if she still spreads the veil of decorum over her actions. Hypocrisy is said to be "the homage which sin pays to virtue," and yet <hi rend="italic">I</hi> can see no vice in that generous sympathy with which we share our caprices with those who have inspired us with tenderness,&#8212;</p>
            <p>I trust you will think well enough of me soon to renew the pleasure you afforded me last P.M., and I therefore write to remind you that there is a sensible head as well as a sympathetic heart, both of which would gladly evolve wit &amp; warmth for your direction &amp; comfort.&#8212;You have already my whereabouts &amp; my hours&#8212;It shall only depend upon you to make them yours and me the happiest of women.</p>
            <closer rend="right">

                  <salute>I am always</salute>

                  <salute>Yours sincerely,</salute>

                  <signed>Ellen Eyre</signed>
               
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
