<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00420">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 5 September 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00420</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">69-71</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 5 September 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-09-05">September 5, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-25">proofread and modified; need to return to address queries</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1863-09-05">Sept 5 1863<ptr target="loc.00420_n1"/>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mother gave me the enclosed letter to send you some days since but I forgot to mail it till now. We received your letter<ptr target="loc.00420_n2"/> last night. The money from George came all safe  I sent you another letter from George about last Monday, also sent George a letter with the money in it. Andrew has been away in the country but returned yesterday, very much worse.<ptr target="loc.00420_n3"/> He came in to see me this morning and it has made me feel quite down-spirited.  He can neither eat nor drink without the greatest agony. He looks very thin and emaciated. I think that if I had the same sickness that I could get the best of it,<ptr target="loc.00420_n4"/> but Andrew seems to put his whole faith in thinking that some Dr can give him something that will set him all straight. I am going to see the Dr with him this P.M. and I also want him to consult Ruggles<ptr target="loc.00420_n5"/> if he will. I fear the worst for Andrew. I wish you was on here. I think that your advice would be a great thing for him. Cant you come. You speak of coming home. I wish you could come just now. Mother is of course much worried about him. Nancy dont seem to amount to much when trouble comes. You would hardly know Andrew. He is thin weak and generally sickly looking  We have heard nothing from Han lately that I know of  Mother and Heyde keep writing letters to one another but what about I know not. At last the great draft has come and gone and I was not one of the elected. I feel thankful  In our ward the screws were put rather tight. out of a little over 3000 names they drew 1056 nearly one in three, while in other wards the proportion was 1 in 6 and 1 in 7 and in the 9th ward 1 in 10. Tom Geere,<ptr target="loc.00420_n6"/> Tom McEvoy,<ptr target="loc.00420_n7"/> Pat Hughes<ptr target="loc.00420_n8"/> two or three in Amermans<ptr target="loc.00420_n9"/> house, were all hit. It seems to have avoided the Water Works, only one or two out of the whole 40 or 50 employed were hit while in Husted &amp; Carls store<ptr target="loc.00420_n10"/> 7 out of 10 were taken. If this is the last of it I feel thankful but I believe Uncle Abe left off some on account of Seymour,<ptr target="loc.00420_n11"/> if so I suppose there will be another spurt. However we wont worry till the time comes  The enclosed $5 is from Mr Moses Lane.<ptr target="loc.00420_n12"/>
            </p>
            <p>We have what remains of [three?] old Reg. on the hills by our house. They are fine looking and well behaved men, and look as if they would do their duty any where. If you was home you could have grand times talking with them  One Reg. is from Min. one from Mich. and one from Ohio. What do you think about coming to Brooklyn  I think you better, for awhile any way. I wish you would write to Andrew. He seems to feel wonderfully cast down  Aint the Administrat[ion] got wit enough to see that now is the hour to end the war by whipping the rebels. Dont they know enough to know that unless it is ended in 6 months they will have a hard time to get men to fill the places of what they have now. I fear not.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
