<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00811">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 2 March 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="br">Bev Rilett</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00811</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">200-201</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 2 March 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-03-02">March 2, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#br" when="2009-08-31">proofed and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-03">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington |  </name>
                  <date when="1864-03-02">March 2 1864</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You or Jeff must try to write as soon as you receive this &amp; let me know how little Sis is, tell me if she got entirely over the croup &amp; how she is&#8212;also about George's trunks,<ptr target="loc.00811_n1"/> I do hope he recovered them, it was such a misfortune&#8212;I want to hear the end of it, I am in hopes I shall hear that he has got them&#8212;I have not seen in the papers whether the 51st has left New York yet&#8212;Mother, I want to hear all about home &amp; all the occurrences, especially the two things I have just mentioned, &amp; how you are, dearest mother, you must write me exactly how you are for somehow I was thinking from your letters lately whether you was as well as usual or not&#8212;write how my dear sister Mat is too, &amp; whether you are still going to stay there in Portland av. the coming year&#8212;Well, dear mother, I am just the same here, nothing new, I am well &amp; hearty, &amp; constantly moving around among the wounded &amp; sick&#8212;there are a great many of the latter coming up&#8212;the hospitals here are quite full&#8212;lately they have [been] picking out in the hospitals all that had pretty well recovered, &amp; sending them back to their regiments, they seem to be determined to strengthen the army this spring, to the utmost&#8212;they are sending down many to their reg'ts that are not fit to go, in my opinion&#8212;then there are squads &amp; companies &amp; reg'ts too passing through here in one steady stream going down to front, returning from furlough home&#8212;but then there are quite a number leaving the army on furlough, re-enlisting, &amp; going north for a while&#8212;they pass through here quite largely&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, Lewis Brown is getting quite well, he will soon be able to have a wooden leg put on, he is very restless &amp; active, &amp; wants to go around all the time&#8212;</p>
            <p>Sam Beatty<ptr target="loc.00811_n2"/> is here in Washington&#8212;We have had quite a snow storm, but is clear &amp; sunny to-day here, but sloshy, I am wearing my army boots&#8212;any thing but the dust&#8212;Dear mother, I want to see you &amp; Sis, &amp; Mat &amp; all very much&#8212;if I can get a chance I think I shall come home for a while&#8212;I want to try to bring out a book of poems, a new one to be called "Drum Taps" &amp; I want to come to New York for that purpose too&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, I havn't given up the project of lecturing<ptr target="loc.00811_n3"/> either&#8212;but whatever I do, I shall for the main thing devote myself for years to come to these wounded &amp; sick, what little I can&#8212;Well good bye, dear mother, for present&#8212;write soon&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
