<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00454">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 5 April 1869</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00454</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">140-141</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 5 April 1869</title>
               <date when="1869-04-05">April 5, 1869</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
               <opener>
                  <dateline rend="right">
                     <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
                     <date when="1869-04-05">April 5th 1869</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear brother Walt</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>A few days since I received from Mr O'Connor<ptr target="loc.00454_n1"/> six of the little pamphlets<ptr target="loc.00454_n2"/> that I wrote to you about  They came in just right and have enabled me to make some very important changes in our work&#8212;I also received a letter from him yesterday saying that he would visit the U.S. Engineers office and pick up what he could for me&#8212;I do so hope he will&#8212;for they are just the books that do me the most good&#8212;and books that you cannot buy  Matters are about the same with us. Mattie is not so well for a week or so back&#8212;but I think it is the weather and then we are not so happily situated as we were before we left our room over the beer house<ptr target="loc.00454_n3"/>&#8212;nor do we live so well&#8212;I am trying to get a house and must succeed in a week or so then if Mattie dont get better I shall try and send her and the children up to Min. or Wis.<ptr target="loc.00454_n4"/> for some four or five months. I hope and feel pretty sure that when we get to housekeeping and Mat has a better time and better food she will get all right again&#8212;she is not near as bad as she was in Brooklyn but she is not as well as she was when she had been here a few weeks. The children are well and are learning to read and write and all that sort of thing&#8212;they behave well and get along nicely&#8212;yet they are not as comfortably situated [as] I hope to have them after awhile.</p>
               <p>We hav'nt heard from home in a long time  I suppose matters are going as usual there however. I shall try and send George some money to-day<ptr target="loc.00454_n5"/>&#8212;I hope he will succeed and get his houses done before the 1st of May<ptr target="loc.00454_n6"/> so that Mother can get into one of them. I see that they are having some sort of a turn about in regard to the political offices in Brooklyn<ptr target="loc.00454_n7"/>&#8212;I hope that they wont reach Lane<ptr target="loc.00454_n8"/> both for his own sake and for George's&#8212;It would be too bad to have any change in the Water Dept&#8212;The city would suffer more than could be calculated.</p>
               <p>There is a series of papers called "Papers on Practical Engineering, published by the Engineer Dept."<ptr target="loc.00454_n9"/> that I would like very much to get&#8212;I have seen no 5 and no 7 of them&#8212;they are of some 30 to 40 pages each, unbound&#8212;but give what of all things is the best for me&#8212;how certain works were constructed and the difficulties that they had to overcome. If Mr O'Connor or you can send me some of them I hope you will do so. Anyway the one he sent ("Memoir &amp;c") gave me information so that I changed some portions of our work and I guess got me out of what might have turned out to be a bad fix&#8212;on the question of foundations. I shall write Mr O'Connor to-morrow&#8212;in the meantime please thank him for me&#8212;</p>
               <p>How does the new administration affect you<ptr target="loc.00454_n10"/>&#8212;I hope that it will not be to your detriment. Are you still living the same as when I was at Washington<ptr target="loc.00454_n11"/> and do you get along well.</p>
               <p>By the way, in my last I forgot to tell you abt the "bitters" and to thank you for them&#8212;Mat likes them first rate and I think they do her good. I would like to get a gallon or two of them if I could&#8212;Will you ask the party making them if they can be kept in a jug and if so write me how much it will cost to get a one or two gallon demijohn and fill it and I will send you the money. Mattie takes them regularly and her appetite is kept up thereby</p>
               <p>All send love to you&#8212;and hope to hear from you soon</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>Affectionately yours Jeff</signed>
               </closer>
            
            <postscript>
               <p>Or can I buy the bitters here  if so, and you can learn where, it will do as well</p>
            </postscript>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
