<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00444">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 23 May 1867</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00444</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">120-122</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 23 May 1867</title>
               <date when="1867-05-23">May 23, 1867</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
                  <date when="1867-05-23">May 23rd 1867<ptr target="loc.00444_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours I received yesterday  I also had a lettr from Mat to-day<ptr target="loc.00444_n2"/>  As you can imagine I am very glad to get news from home&#8212;I was glad you sent me Mothers letter&#8212;</p>
            <p>In regard to the house I think too that it is far better to do as you propose and build on George's lot&#8212;twill be a home and a good one too I think for Mother<ptr target="loc.00444_n3"/>&#8212;I see from Matts letter that they are going to be turned out from their place there&#8212;that Olmstead<ptr target="loc.00444_n4"/> and all the rest are a mean set of cusses as ever lived&#8212;there is no need of their wanting the house</p>
            <p>I hav'nt written to Kingsly<ptr target="loc.00444_n5"/> yet&#8212;am thinking of perhaps some other way of raising the money&#8212;anyway I am pretty sure&#8212;indeed <hi rend="italic">am</hi> sure that it can be had&#8212;how soon will you want it? write me about it&#8212;</p>
            <p>I am glad you went home<ptr target="loc.00444_n6"/>  I guess it did Mother and all of them a great deal of good&#8212;Mat writes that she is going out to hire rooms as soon as she can  It seems to me d&#8212;m mean that they manage to want the whole of that big house  It looks more like being a little ugly than anything else&#8212;I wish Mattie would be a little stiff with them&#8212;the Bullards<ptr target="loc.00444_n7"/> I mean the people that are going to move in&#8212;the d&#8212;m cusses shant have my water pipe unless the[y] behave decent&#8212;yet I suppose the Park people are mean enough to prevent my taking it up&#8212;</p>
            <p>Matters are beginning to get into shape with me&#8212;I am in need of Davis<ptr target="loc.00444_n8"/> very much&#8212;I have been urging him to come as soon as possible but received a letter to-day saying that he could not possibly get here before the 15th of June if then&#8212;I hope however that he will certainly get here by that time.</p>
            <p>Mr Kirkwood<ptr target="loc.00444_n9"/> left me this morning&#8212;he has been here since Saturday&#8212;The Board of Commis[sio]ners I like very much&#8212;they do just whatever I ask&#8212;at once&#8212;indeed almost too much so.<ptr target="loc.00444_n10"/> I begin to feel as if I should get along if I have decent luck&#8212;Yet it is hard to say what will turn up&#8212;</p>
            <p>I manage to get the N. York papers pretty regularly now. I had the Times of Friday while eating my Breakfast on Sunday&#8212;that is pretty well isnt it. The weather is quite cool&#8212;but nevertheless vegetation is getting forward fast&#8212;and just out side the city&#8212;where we are to build part of our new works, matters look perfectly beautiful. I hope you will be able to come on here and make me a visit if I stay here long&#8212;I begin to like the city better&#8212;Yet it dont come up to B[rooklyn] by a long chalk&#8212;</p>
            <p>Give my regards to Mr and Mrs O'Connor<ptr target="loc.00444_n11"/>&#8212;write me as often as you can</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
