<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04057">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Beatrice Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 16 February 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Beatrice Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04057</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">175&#8211;176</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Beatrice Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Beatrice Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 16 February 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-02-16" xml:id="dat1">February 16, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Beatrice">Beatrice Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-02" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">33 Warrenton St.</name>
                    <date when="1879-02-16" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Feb.</abbr><expan>February</expan></choice> 16, 1879.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Although not in word, I have thanked you for your letter &#38; papers by enjoying them thoroughly.<ptr target="n0260"/></p>
            
            <p>Down at this Dispensary<ptr target="n1512"/> we work just as hard as at the Hospital, but our spare minutes are our own (no records to write out); our work is under our own control; we are out in fresh air half the day, sometimes half the night, making intimate acquaintance with all sorts of people &#38; places &#38; with far distant parts of Boston.</p>
            
            <p>We have all the responsibility that it is good for young doctors to have, i. e., in all difficult or obscure &#38; dangerous cases we are obliged to call in older heads &#38; are obliged to report verbally to the visiting physician of the month all our cases &#38; our treatment. Only two students live at the Dispensary&#8212;Dr. Wiley<ptr target="n3010"/> (the coloured Philadelphia student you saw) &#38; myself. In tastes we have much in common &#38; on the whole I prefer to live with her rather than with any of the other students. We share rooms. We have a bedroom, a drug-room, a treatment room, waiting room for patients, &#38; take our meals in the kitchen.</p>

            <p>A widow woman with two children housekeeps.</p>
             
            <p>I think Boston a very beautiful city. The public Gardens &#38; Commons in the busiest part, sloping down from the gilt domed state house on Beacon hill, threaded by paths in all directions, traversed by the business men, the fine ladies, the beggars, etc., etc. One broad, sloping path is given up to the boys who want to coast, temporary wooden bridges being thrown over the cross paths. Then, crossing South Bay to South Boston is a beautiful walk I take from one to four times a day. South Boston looks rather dingy; it is inhabited mostly by artisans &#38; mill hands &#38; fishermen, but walking up 3rd St., as you cross the lettered streets A, B, C, D, etc., you look down upon the harbour&#8212;on bright days bright blue, &#38; a few sails to be seen&#8212;at sunset the colours of course are reflected gorgeously.</p>
    
            <p>Somehow or other the sea looks doubly beautiful set in dingy S. Boston.</p>
                
            <p>Far over in the West End too we have patients. Last Tuesday I had twins all by myself; only one, however, was born alive; the other had been dead a week. How delightful that you are feeling so much better. Shall you not be coming to Boston sometime before I leave, 1st June?</p>
               
            <p>The Boston I know is not the Boston I knew in books; I am as far off from that as if I lived in England&#8212;is not the "hub"&#8212;I was reminded of that last Sunday when I had time for once to go to church &#38; went to hear Mr. E. E. Hale<ptr target="n1514"/>  preach and went home to dinner with him....</p>
            
            <p>I like his daughter whom we knew in Philadelphia. She is a clever young artist. Dr. Wiley is very popular with her patients, far more so than I.</p>
            
            <p>Please remember me to all the Staffords<ptr target="n1009"/> &#38; give my especial love to Mrs. Stafford. Also to Mrs. Whitman.<ptr target="n0368b"/></p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours affectionately,</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Beatrice C. Gilchrist</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
