<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01236">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 1 July 1881</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                    <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01236</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
                    <title>Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 1 July 1881</title>              
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-07-01" xml:id="dat1">July 1, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-04-24" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-02-04" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-24" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-08" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01236.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Broadway</name>
                    <name type="place"><choice><abbr>nr</abbr><expan>near</expan></choice> Sheffield</name>
                    <date when="1881-07-01">1. July.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I think you would like to see Robert Sharland's letter so I enclose it.<!--<ptr target="n0141b"/>--> I have just got Bucke's<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>--> 'Moral Nature'<!--<ptr target="loc.04081_n4"/>-->&#8212;at least Mrs. Gilchrist<!--<ptr target="n0259"/>--> lent me a copy some time ago, but I have bought two copies now. It is very interesting, I think&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01236.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>it seems to explain to me the relation of animals to man,&#8212;the smallness of their <hi rend="underline">brains</hi> does not really constitute a gap&#8212;even physiologically....I was going to ask you a question about the <hi rend="underline">soul</hi>, but the more I think about it the less can I make out what it was I was going to ask! It was something about whether the sympathetic comes <hi rend="underline">next</hi> to it, or whether it is inside it or outside it, or behind it or before it: or what? or is it 
                It?&#8212;but<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01236.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> I fear such conversation is unprofitable.</p>
            
            <p>It is so jolly living in this farmyard. Our landlord is a farmer and our little cottage is only divided from it by a low wall over which the cows come &amp; put their noses, and there are the fowls and a pig and an old horse, and cats &amp; ducks &amp; things. The other side of the yard is an orchard, cherry apple &amp; pear, with the farm house. We are high here, I daresay 800 <choice><abbr>ft</abbr><expan>feet</expan></choice> above the
            
            
             <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01236.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>sea, and the land is clayey &amp; cold&#8212;the farmers mostly a slow going shrewd sort&#8212;saving more out of their land than putting into it; the country all the same breaks away into beautiful valleys &amp; the wild moors are close at hand&#8212;Charles Fox our landlord is very friendly. He is about 35, unmarried, a great reader (or has been so), but so quiet, homely, clodhopping like that few people suspect him
                
             <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01236.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>of it. He is very anxious to travel but a good deal tied down at present. The farm, about 30 acres, belongs to him; and I suppose he represents a class of small proprietors, farmers, that used to be common in these parts, but there are not so many now. Everything is <hi rend="underline">rented</hi> now in this country.</p>
            
            <p><hi rend="underline">Our</hi> household consists of Albert Fearnehough,<!--<ptr target="n3063"/>--> his wife, and Annie a bright girl of 13. There is also a boy George who is apprenticed to a joiner in Sheffield. He
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01236.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>comes home only on Saturdays &amp; Sundays: and is always welcome. Now my lectures are over I am spending the summer helping in the garden and any odd jobs about the place&#8212;and am doing also a good deal of writing. I pretty well live out in the open air &amp; don't feel as if I <choice><abbr>sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr><expan>should</expan></choice> ever manage indoor life again. It is possible that Albert &amp; I might take a small farm, but we shall see. I feel that I <hi rend="underline">must</hi>
                
                
             <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01236.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>write, at present.&#8212;I can't keep my fingers off it&#8212;but still that takes only a small fraction of the week &amp; leaves plenty of time for other work.</p>
            
            <p>These friends that I have here and my more natural open air life seem to have made a difference to me. I feel as if I had touched the bottom at last, and had something firm to go upon&#8212;after floundering about so long. Thanks for all that also to you.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01236.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>I hear that Herbert Gilchrist<!--<ptr target="n0262"/>--> is painting a portrait of you for Dr Bucke. Is it for the book? Dr B. asked me for some contribution&#8212;but I have never sent anything&#8212;I <choice><orig>dont</orig><reg>don't</reg></choice> exactly know why, but chiefly because I wasn't sure how the Gilchrists <choice><abbr>wd</abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> like their names appearing so freely in what I had written.</p>
            
            <p>Remembrances to the Staffords<!--<ptr target="n1009"/>--> when you see them and to John Burroughs<!--<ptr target="n0129"/>--> if you see him.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Your friend</salute>
                <signed>Edward Carpenter</signed>
            </closer>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01236.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <!-- front of envelope --> <note resp="#ww" type="editorial" place="top">good letter from Edward Carpenter July 1 '81</note> <!-- Envelope transcription: Walt Whitman 431 Stevens Street Camden New Jersey U.S. America -->
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.01236.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
