<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00594">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Will W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 5 April 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Will W. Wallace</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00594</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">208-210</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Will W. Wallace</author>
               <title>Will W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 5 April 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-04-05">April 5, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Wallace, Will W.">Will W. Wallace</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jw" when="2008-09-08">Transcription revision</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-08-28">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> </dateline>
               <salute>Friend Walter</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="loc.00594_n100"/> have not forgotten you in the wanderings from Washington here.  After five days and nights jolting in the cars I reached this point and was put on duty instanter&#8212;And such duty!  Why I have worked night and day and it appears there is more to do now than when I came.</p>
            <p>They only allow one steward to each Hospital, and it is an irksome office when such is the case. I am doing finely and in the course of a few weeks I think will have some leisure time. The Hospitals here were in a destitute condition, compared with those of the North. When I came to this Hospital they had no clothes to change <hi rend="italic">one fourth</hi> of the patients. I immediately appealed to my lady friends and patriots in Philadelphia, and they have sent me on a fine lot of sanitary stores, yet not enough for the wants of the many admitted. Our Hospt is a large five story building and accommodates between 300 &amp; 400 patients, most of whom are wounded in the continual skirmishing about Murfreesboro and Franklin.</p>
            <p>I have never had better health in my life, perhaps I can explain it to you. I have five young ladies who act in the capacity of nurses&#8212;i e, <hi rend="italic">one of them is French</hi>, young and beautiful to set your eyes upon. Can you not visit us and note for yourself? I think a change of climate will be beneficial.</p>
            <p>How are Jack and Amos?<ptr target="loc.00594_n2"/> I wish you would give me Amos's address, as I have lost the one he gave me. My regards to them and hope they are out of Campbell Hospital. What became of poor Dick?</p>
            <p>I have been so busy I have neglected all correspondence so you will readily forget the seeming neglect</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Hoping to hear from you at an early period I remain</salute>
               <salute>Very respectfully</salute>
               <salute>Your humble</salute>
               <signed>Will Wallace</signed>
               <salute>To the Prince of Bohemians Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>P..S. Send me that promised photograph and as soon as I find out your quarters I will return compt Will</p>
            <p>I will tell you of the many secesh at the next writing</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
