<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05696">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Herbert H. Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 29 April
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Herbert H. Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05696</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">213&#8211;214</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Herbert H. Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Herbert H. Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 29 April 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-04-29" xml:id="dat1">April 29, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Herbert H.">Herbert H. Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-18" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-14" who="#no">checked, corrected last sentence to new paragraph</change>
            <change when="2014-11-10" who="#ak">corrected transcription and encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-07-19" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded and annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Keats Corner</name>
                    <name type="place">Well Road, Hampstead, London, England</name>
                    <date when="1883-07-30">April 29th, '83.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your card to hand last night,<!--<ptr target="n0262"/>--> with its sad account of dear Mrs.
                Stafford's health;<!--<ptr target="loc.05696_n1"/>--> but what the doctor says is cheering.
                I wonder, though, what the doctor would call good weather&#8212;mild spring, I
                suppose.</p>

            <p>Very glad, my dear old Walt, to see your strong familiar handwriting again; it does
                one good, it's so individual that it is next to seeing you. Right glad to hear of
                your good health&#8212;had an idea that you were not so well again this winter. John
                    Burroughs<!--<ptr target="n0129"/>--> was very violent against my intaglio; on the
                other hand, Alma Tadema<!--<ptr target="n3083"/>-->&#8212;our great painter
                here&#8212;liked it very much. I take violent criticism pretty philosophically, now
                that I see how unreliable it nearly always is. John Burroughs has got a fixed idea
                about your personality, and that is that the top of your head is a foot high and any
                portrait that doesn't develop the "dome" is no portrait.&#8212;Curious what eyes a
                man may have for everything except a picture. I finished lately a life-size portrait
                of James Simmons, J.P., a hunting (fox) squire of the old school&#8212;such a fine
                old fellow. My portrait represents him standing firmly, in a scarlet hunting-coat
                well stained with many a wet chase, his great whip tucked under his arm whilst
                buttoning on his left glove, white buckskin trousers in shade relieving the scarlet
                coat, black velvet hunting cap, dark rich blue background to qualify and cool the
                scarlet. I wish you could see it. Then I have painted a subject "The Good Gray
                Poet's Gift." I have long meant to build up something of you from my studies, adding
                colour. You play a prominent part in this picture&#8212;seated at table bending
                over a nosegay of flowers, poetizing, before presenting them to mother. I am
                standing up bending over the tea-pot, with the kettle, filling it up; opposite you
                sits Giddy;<!--<ptr target="n0890"/>--> out of the window a pretty view of Cannon place,
                Hampstead. Mater thinks it a pretty picture and a good likeness of you, just as you
                used to sit at tea with us at 1729 N. 22nd St. Now I am going out for a stroll on
                Hampstead Heath. Have just come in from a long ramble over the Heaths&#8212;a lovely
                soft spring day, innumerable birds in full song. I think J. B. is right when he says
                that your birds are more plaintive than ours&#8212;it's nature's way of
                compensating us for a loss of sunshine: what would England be without the merry
                lark, the very embodiment of cheeriness. Are not the Carlyle<!--<ptr target="n0139"/>-->
                &#38; Emerson<!--<ptr target="n1044"/>--> letters interesting? It seems to me to be one of
                the most beautiful and pathetic things in literature, C's fondness for E. But all
                Englishmen, I must tell you, are not grumblers like Carlyle; he stands quite alone
                in that quality&#8212;look at Darwin!<!--<ptr target="n3075"/>--></p> 
            
              <p>I should be grateful for another postcard.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>With all love,</salute>
                <signed>Herb. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
