<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01445">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 23 December
                    1869</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Dixon, Thomas</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01445</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 23 December 1869</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1869-12-23" xml:id="dat1">December 23, 1869</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas">Thomas Dixon</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-10-17" who="#el">added underlining to postscript</change>
            <change when="2011-02-17" who="#al">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-11-02" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-09-20" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01445.003.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <address>
                    <addrLine rend="right"><name type="place">15 Sunderland Street</name>.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine rend="right"><name type="place">Sunderland</name>.</addrLine>
                </address>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <date when="1869-12-23">Dec 23, 1869</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir and <hi rend="underline">Friend</hi></salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Thy letter and the photograph is to hand all safe. <hi rend="underline">Newspaper</hi> seems to have been appropriated on the way either by thy people
                or by mine. let us hope to <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#al">above</unclear> the
                two lots hath fallen it may be profitable to <hi rend="underline">body and
                Soul</hi>. I have had news from Sister. Some letters hath gone astray sent by me, 
                and also by me. Such accidents I suppose is <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01445.004.jpg" type="verso"/> uncommon in the Post Office when one
                considers the amount of letters sent the wonder is that some more does not go
                astray. when one thinks of the quantity of letters sent it seems really amazing how
                few seems to miss there destination! However I trust no more Books to their care in
                future. A Parcel of a few I will send you in a few weeks. I delay simply because
                when I do send you I wish to send you really representative Books? and shall send
                them by parcel <choice>
                    <orig>Despatch</orig>
                    <reg>dispatch</reg>
                </choice> then they are answerable for their delivery or Value thereof. I write you
                in haste because I wish to save you trouble in <choice>
                    <orig>enquiring</orig>
                    <reg>inquiring</reg>
                </choice> respecting Sister, who is now in communication with us <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01445.005.jpg" type="recto"/> all again, and who
                will recieve what I hope will enable her to buy some piece of your Native Land, and
                to then Have for herself and husband and Family. Thy recognition of my loss goes to
                my heart. I feel in thee <hi rend="underline">a friend</hi>. my love for thee
                through thy printed utterances has been more then recompenced by thy <hi rend="underline">kind words</hi>. My parcel and its contents will speak to thee
                more then I can write thee. I love nearly all the Men thou lovest and all the Books
                and thoughts that seem congenial to thee long hath been to me. I gaze on the Sea
                while I eat my food and think of thee in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="5" unit="chars"/>  of summer I gaze on the sea, and in the morning also—<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01445.006.jpg" type="verso"/> and often while I gaze
                thereon I think of thee, and how thou loves that sea, and how to thee it hath been
                more then to me. I love also those on the Sea, as the small matters sent to thee
                does prove how dear they are to me. again even now my eldest Lad is now in Japan is
                second voyage to <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">Celina</unclear>  and yet only 16 years old—my youngest is also now
                learning a trade are that I suppose you know well too. (<hi rend="underline">House
                    Joiner</hi>.) He I hope someday will visit your Land. my two lads I would like
                to see settled there on Land, only I do not know if it may ever be. Such is their
                fathers Hope. <hi rend="underline">Your Books</hi> still are out on Loan they have
                made many a journey since they came to me, they are as follows. Burroughs W. W. the
                Man &amp; the Poet. Connor's Good Gray Poet.—                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01445.007.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                Conway's Notice in Fortnightly. Your Poems in Tinsley &amp; Broadwood. these go from hand to hand here in my town and in
                the district amongst all sorts of people—Unitarian Ministers, Joiners,
                Carpenters, Ship Carvers, Watchmakers, Potters, <gap reason="unclear" extent="four letters" quantity="4" unit="chars"/>latters, Shipwrights, Boiler Makers,
                Blacksmiths and others, even amongst Quakers in Manchester too has your Books now
                become Known . . <hi rend="underline">all love</hi> you simply because you seem to <hi rend="underline">love all</hi>. I have long wished for someone to arise that
                would once again through the Spirit working upon them, open the hand of fellowship
                to all Humanity—<hi rend="underline">the poor,</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">the outcast, the learned, the unlearned</hi>, you seem in your Life to have done this so
                we love you—as a true Manifestation amongst us 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01445.008.jpg" type="verso"/> once again of the Spirit of the Great
                Teacher, and by your actions and your teachings you compell us to love and admire
                you, because in your Life you have lived that which you have written for us. Ah! how few that love
                Christ and his teachings see or apprehend that to do them is really what He meant when
                he asked them to become His disciple. I hope these few scratches may convey to you
                why I love you, and why we all love you, and why we long for your Portrait. <hi rend="underline">Many,</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">Many</hi> thanks for it, and thy kind letter, and noble
                recognition of us all. May thou long be spared to the people and our people too likewise. </p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Thine, thankfully</salute>
                <signed>Thomas Dixon</signed>
            </closer>
            
            <postscript>
                <p><hi rend="underline">In the Good deeds</hi> of Humanity is the true Unity
                    of God made <hi rend="underline">Manifest to Humanity</hi>. Nations, Peoples, tongues, or speeches are but
                    segments of a great <hi rend="underline">All</hi>.</p>
            </postscript>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>