<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00398">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 10 February 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>

               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00398</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">26-28</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 10 February 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-02-10">February 10, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2011-08-08">Seward footnote</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-13">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2006-11-21">added table for monetary amounts in first paragraph</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1863-02-10">Feb. 10th&#8212;1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your letter of yesterday morning.<ptr target="loc.00398_n1"/> I am glad to hear that you are still visiting the hospitals and doing so much good. We are trying to do what little we can to furnish you with the necessary funds (in a small way to be sure) and the only thing that we are sorry about is that we cannot do more. The enclosed money is contributed by</p>
            
            <p>
               <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>Theo. A. Drake<ptr target="loc.00398_n2"/></cell>
                  <cell>$2.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>"<hi rend="italic">Cash</hi>" through John D Martin<ptr target="loc.00398_n3"/></cell>
                  <cell><hi rend="italic">$2.</hi></cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>&#160;</cell>
                  <cell>$4</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            </p>
         
           <p>both of whom are employed on the work under Mr Lane.<ptr target="loc.00398_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr Lane has written a letter to <hi rend="italic">Mr Webster</hi>
               <ptr target="loc.00398_n5"/> the clerk of Seward<ptr target="loc.00398_n6"/> that I spoke to you about and will send you a letter of introduction to him immediately. He tells me that he (Webster) is a "politician" and that he will help you without doubt provided that he thinks that it will not interfere at all with him. Or that is about the idea of what he said.</p>
            <p>We are all getting well at home  Sis has almost entirely recovered  Mat's throat is still quite sore and mothers cough <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a great deal better, till she went and caught more but she is again getting well. We do not hear any more from Heyde so I presume that Han is getting better again and perhaps will soon be home. I hope so anyway</p> 
            <p>I hope that George may be successful in getting his furlough.<ptr target="loc.00398_n7"/> I saw Capt. Simms<ptr target="loc.00398_n8"/> Sunday night, he had left George and the rest on Thursday morning. He was then well and engaged in building his hut. Simms looks very well indeed. My old friend Bill DeBevoise<ptr target="loc.00398_n9"/> is home sick with "<hi rend="italic">weakness</hi>" I suppose you might call it. He can hardly walk alone  He has been home about 2 weeks and has got so he can just get about a little. My friend J. W. Mason,<ptr target="loc.00398_n10"/> (used to be in my party on the Water Works) was in Brooklyn on Saturday  He was then on his way to his fathers at Towando, Pa. and promised that he would call on you when he returned to the army  He is now a Capt. in the regulars. (5th Cavalry)</p>
            <p>I think I shall take a few of your letters and give them to George Wright<ptr target="loc.00398_n11"/> (of the ferry) and let him see if he cannot collect a few dollars from the ferry hands  dont you think it would be a good idea. I think that he might be able to collect something quite handsome. I have not seen any of the ferry hands since you went away.</p>
            <p>We often wish that you and George could pop in on us just as we were about to sit down to dinner, particularly when we have "Turk" as sis calls it. Mother eats with us at almost every meal and I think living well is about all that keeps her up through all the trouble and worry that she goes through, for work and worry she will and I dont think the power of man can prevent it. Mat is nearly the same as usual  she is not very well and sometimes has to give up for a little while, but she soon buckels in again. Sis of course when she is well is just as big a little scamp as ever, more mischief-making than ever, if that is possible. Jess and Ed are I guess, in every respect are just the same. I met Andrew Rome,<ptr target="loc.00398_n12"/> 'tother day, he wanted to know how soon you would be in Brooklyn again  I told him I did not know and asked him to write you. How would it do for you to write to Wilke,<ptr target="loc.00398_n13"/> detailing what you are doing, what we have contributed so that he might strike some of the big-bugs that he moves among or shall I give him the letters that you have written to us. advise me about it</p>
            <p>Mr Lane has about finished his reports and wishes me to tell you that he will now have some time to devote and thinks he will be able to raise some more money, however he will write you himself before long, a day or two.</p>
            <p>What about your chances for the "position" and what kind of a position do you expect to get. I sincerely hope that you might succeed and get detailed to New York.<ptr target="loc.00398_n14"/> Try for it Walt and dont be discouraged if you do not succeed at first</p>
            <p>Do you write to dear brother George often, I wish he could honorably get out of it. Would'nt it be good if he was home just now to build my "house"  I should like much to have it done by him, let him get a gang of men and pay him by the day. However I suppose it cannot be done in that manner and shall have to do it in some other.</p>
            <p>Dear Walt let me hear from you soon. All send their love to you and receive my best wishes for your health and success  I remain as ever your affectionate brother</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
