<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01083">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amelia W. Bates to Walt Whitman, 18 January
                    [1881]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amelia W. Bates</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01083</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amelia W. Bates</author>
                    <title>Amelia W. Bates to Walt Whitman, 18 January [1881]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1881-01-18" xml:id="dat1">January 18, 1881</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Bates, Amelia W.">Amelia W. Bates</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-04-13" who="#nhg">corrected date, added annotation</change>
            <change when="2015-01-05" who="#kmp">corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-15" who="#mc">corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-09" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-11" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01083.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">Came to-day from a
                Wisconsin lady, a stranger</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name>Mrs. Amelia W. Bates</name>
                    <name type="place">710 Astor St.</name>
                    <name type="place">Milwaukee,</name>
                    <date when="1880-01-18">Jan. 18, 1880.</date><ptr target="loc.01083_n1"/>
                </dateline>   
                <salute>Mr. Walt Whitman</salute>
                <salute>My Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I am sure you will pardon the liberty I am taking in addressing a stranger. No, not
                a stranger, for a man or a woman who writes for the people, cannot if he would, be a
                stranger to even the most ordinary citizen of the world.</p>
            <p> I am not accustomed thus to present my claim to acquaintanceship with writers. You
                are the first of our poets whom I have I have ever troubled with the correspondence,
                that I am told is their inevitable fate. </p>
            <p> Now, this let<unclear reason="cut away" resp="#kmp" cert="low">ter</unclear> I send you <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01083.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> has only come
                out of the reading of your late article in the North American Review which lies at my
                hand just finished. </p>
            <p> May I be permitted to say, that I believe you to approach the nearest to the "Poet of the future"
                as you <unclear reason="cut away" resp="#nhg" cert="high">prophesy</unclear> him to be, than any other
                    existing. You are
                indeed the suggestor. You have in this article given me at least, "much to desire, to
                study," but alas I shall never be able "to complete in turn" greatly as I desire so
                to do. I believe in the potency of science to reconstruct society, but not being a
                poet I had not credited it with "clearing a field for verse". I will believe this
                also, adding it to my "creed" the "I believes", of my religion which years ago I
                began to put in the place of the apostolic creed of the church. I shall watch for
                this poetry of the future with the eagerness of <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars"
                    quantity="15"/> <unclear reason="damage" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">born</unclear> of my faith <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01083.003_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> in science and humanity.</p>
            <p> May I tell you how I have come to Walt Whitman worship? </p>
            <p> Twelve years ago, when just awaking from the aimless woman life into which I was
                educated, I was persuaded to read "Leaves of Grass," by my brother who believed in
                you its author. I had heard of it of course, heard very bad things of it too. I was
                certain <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ak" cert="medium">my</unclear> dear
                brother would not ask me to read a bad book. I was too uninformed in poetry then, to
                appreciate the "Leaves" as I now do. But it did not impress me as a bad book, crude
                as I was. I am and always have been very glad it did not. Other women and men whom I
                talked with at that time and I am sorry to say ever since called it coarse. I
                comforted myself with Thoreau's word of you in his "letters", which you doubtless
                know by heart as I do. Later I read Joseph B. Marvin's review in <unclear
                    reason="cut away" resp="#ak" cert="high">the</unclear> "Radical Review" <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01083.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> and felt supreme
                self satisfaction in these words, "Only the voices of the manliest and the womanliest
                can rightly accentuate the words of "Leaves of Grass" etc. I had been <hi
                    rend="underline">brave</hi> enough to read aloud at a "Decoration Day" service
                in a church one of your pieces "Come up from the Fields Father". I am not a public reader and was <unclear reason="cut away" resp="#ak"
                    cert="low">trembling with</unclear> fright, but I must have
                "accentuated" the poetry for it brought tears to the eyes of many, and at its close, Wm. C. Gannett came forward to me
                with a beautiful earnestness in his truly thoughtful face saying "who wrote that"
                "will you let me take it home". (the copy of Drum Taps). That was my hour of triumph for my poet.
                For I had heard Mr. Gannett say, a friend of his a lady who knew you, said you were
                "coarse." </p>
            <p> I have waited for your vindication, with the assurance of perfect satisfaction that
                it would come. I read with delight Edmund C. Stedman's article in the late Scribner,
                not as wholly satisfactory to me as <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ak"
                    cert="low">Mergars's</unclear> in the Radical, but just and sweet and will be
                more widely seen and read than <gap reason="cut away" unit="chars" quantity="8"/>. </p>
            <p> I would be very glad to see you, but <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc.01083.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> that may never be. Remember me as
                one however who has always believed in you, always admired your words. If I were
                younger I would strive with all my <gap reason="cut away" unit="chars" quantity="8"
                /> to do something worthy of my worship of your genius, worthy to be remembered by you.
                But at fifty years of age crippled by a poverty <unclear reason="illegible"
                    resp="#ak" cert="high">that</unclear> makes me use the greatest portion of my
                energy to be economical and pursue a
                domestic vocation I cannot do much. </p>
            <p> I must not expect to draw upon a writers time to reply to this letter. If you will
                but acknowledge its receipt, and will tell me where and when the article mentioned
                by Stedman, the "recantation of Emerson" appeared I shall esteem it a great favor. I
                never knew this had been written and I could never quite forgive Emerson for his
                retraction from the commendation once bestowed upon you. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
                <signed>Amelia W. Bates</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01083.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01083.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01083.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
