<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05695">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 30 July 1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05695</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">217&#8211;219</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 30 July 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-07-30" xml:id="dat1">July 30, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-25" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-24" who="#no">checked, added comment about italicization, corrected spelling of "all" in last p</change>
            <change when="2014-11-10" who="#ak">corrected transcription and encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-07-18" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded and annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Keats Corner</name>
                    <name type="place">Hampstead,</name>
                    <date when="1883-07-30">Jul. 30, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Lazy me, that have been thinking letters to you instead of writing them!<!--<ptr
                    target="n0259"/>--> We have Dr. Bucke's<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>--> book<!--<ptr
                    target="med.00638_n5"/>--> at last; could not succeed in buying one at
                    Tr&#252;bner's<!--<ptr target="n0652"/>-->&#8212;I believe they all sold
                directly&#8212;but he has sent us one. There are some things in it I prize very
                highly&#8212;namely, Helen Price's<!--<ptr target="hyb.00002_n11"/>--> "Memoranda" and
                Thomas A. Gere's.<!--<ptr target="n3081"/>--> These I like far better than any personal
                reminiscences of you I have ever read &#38; I feel much drawn to the writers of
                them. Also your letter to Mrs. Price from the Hospitals, dear Friend. That makes one
                hand-in-hand with you&#8212;then &#38; there&#8212;&#38; gives one a glimpse of a
                very beautiful friendship. But why &#38; why did Dr. Bucke set himself to counteract
                that beneficient law of nature's by which the dust tends to lay itself? And
                carefully gathering together again all the rubbish stupid or malevolent that has
                been written of you, toss it up in the air again to choke and blind or disgust as
                many as it may? What a curious piece of perversity to mistake this for candour &#38;
                a judicial spirit. Then again, how do I hate all that unmeaning, irrelevant
                clatter about what Rabelais<!--<ptr target="n3082"/>--> or Shakespeare or the ancients
                &#38; their times tolerated in the way of coarseness or
                plainness of speech. As if you wanted apologizing for or could be apologized for on
                that ground! If these poems are to be <hi rend="italic">tolerated</hi>, I, for one, could not tolerate
                them. If they are not the highest lesson that has yet been taught in refinement
                &#38; purity, if they do not banish all possibility of coarseness of thought &#38;
                feeling, there would be nothing to be said for them. But they do: I am as sure of
                that as of my own existence. When will men begin to understand them?</p>

            <p>We have had pleasant glimpses of several American friends this summer&#8212;of Kate
                    Hillard<!--<ptr target="n0302"/>--> for instance, who, by the bye narrowly escaped a
                bad accident just at our door&#8212;the harness broke &#38; the cab came down on the
                horse &#38; frightened him so that he bolted&#8212;struck the cab against a
                lamp-post (happily, else it would have been worse)&#8212;overturned them &#38;
                it&#8212;but when they crawled out no worse harm was done than a few cuts from the
                glass&#8212;&#38; Kate &#38; her friend behaved very pluckily, &#38; we had a
                pleasant evening together after all. Then there was Arthur Peterson, looking much as
                in the old Philadelphia days: and Emma &#38; Annie Lazarus&#8212;who, owing to some
                letters of introduction from James the novelist,<!--<ptr target="n2001"/>--> have had a
                very gay time indeed&#8212;been quite lionized&#8212;and last, not least, Mr. Dalton
                Dorr, the curator of the Pennsylvania Museum in Fairmount Park&#8212;whom we all
                liked much. He is enjoying his visit here with all his heart&#8212;is a great
                enthusiast for our old Gothic Cathedrals, and for everything beautiful&#8212;but
                says there is nothing such a source of unceasing wonder &#38; delight as riding
                about London &#38; over the bridges &#38;c on the top of an omnibus watching the
                endless flow of people&#8212;it is indeed a kind of human Mississippi or Niagara.</p>

            <p>The young folks are busy packing up to start for the seaside. Herby<!--<ptr
                    target="n0262"/>--> wants a background for a picture in which green turf &#38;
                trees and all the richness of vegetation come down to the very edge of the sea and I
                seem to remember such a place near Lynn Regis, where I was thirty years ago, when my
                eldest child was born, so they are going to look it up. We hear the heat is very
                tremendous in America this year. I hope you are as well as ever able to stand it
                &#38; enjoy it? I wonder where you are. Friendly greetings to Mr. &#38; Mrs.
                    Whitman<!--<ptr target="n1046"/>--> &#38; Hattie<!--<ptr target="n0911"/>--> &#38; Jessie<!--<ptr
                    target="n1055"/>--> &#38; the Staffords.<!--<ptr target="n0262"/>--> Love to you, dear
                Friend, from us all.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>My little book on Mary Lamb just out&#8212;will send you a copy in a day or
                    two.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
