<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00778">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to James Redpath (?), 6 August 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00778</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">121-123</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to James Redpath (?), 6 August 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-08-06">August 6, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Redpath, James">James Redpath</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-03-10">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">fixed parsing error</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-25">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear friend,<ptr target="loc.00778_n2"/>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am going to write you to ask any friends you may be in communication with for aid for my soldiers. I remain here in Washington still occupied among the hospitals&#8212;I have now been engaged in this over seven months. As time passes on it seems as if sad cases of old &amp; lingering wounded accumulate, regularly recruited with new ones every week&#8212;I have been most of this day in Armory Square Hospital, Seventh st. I seldom miss a day or evening. Out of the six or seven hundred in this Hosp[ital] I try to give a word or a trifle to every one without exception, making regular rounds among them all. I give all kinds of sustenance, blackberries, peaches, lemons &amp; sugar, wines, all kinds of preserves, pickles, brandy, milk, shirts &amp; all articles of underclothing, tobacco, tea, handkerchiefs, &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c. I always give paper, envelopes, stamps, &amp;c. I want a supply for this purpose. To many I give (when I have it) small sums of money&#8212;half of the soldiers in hospital have not a cent. There are many returned prisoners, sick, lost all&#8212;&amp; every day squads of men from [the] front, cavalry or infantry&#8212;brought in wounded or sick, generally without a cent of money. Then I select the most needy cases &amp; devote my time &amp; services much to them. I find it tells best&#8212;some are mere lads, 17, 18, 19 or 20. Some are silent, sick, heavy hearted, (things, attentions, &amp;c. are very rude in the army &amp; hospitals, nothing but the mere hard routine, no time for tenderness or extras)&#8212;So I go round&#8212;Some of my boys die, some get well&#8212;</p>
            <p>O what a sweet unwonted love (those good American boys, of good stock, decent, clean, well raised boys, so near to me)&#8212;what an attachment grows up between us, started from hospital cots, where pale young faces lie &amp; wounded or sick bodies. My brave young American soldiers&#8212;now for so many months I have gone around among them, where they lie. I have long discarded all stiff conventions (they &amp; I are too near to each other, there is no time to lose, &amp; death &amp; anguish dissipate ceremony here between my lads &amp; me)&#8212;I pet them, some of them it does so much good, they are so faint &amp; lonesome&#8212;at parting at night sometimes I kiss them right &amp; left&#8212;The doctors tell me I supply the patients with a medicine which all their drugs &amp; bottles &amp; powders are helpless to yield.</p>
            <p>I wish you would ask any body you know who is likely to contribute&#8212;It is a good holy cause, surely nothing nobler&#8212;I desire you if possible could raise for me, forthwith, for application to these wounded &amp; sick here, (they are from Massachusetts &amp; all the New England states, there is not a day but I am with some Yankee boys, &amp; doing some trifle for them)&#8212;a sum&#8212;if possible $50&#8212;if not, then less&#8212;$30&#8212;or indeed any am't&#8212;</p>
         <p>I am at present curiously almost alone here, as visitor &amp; consolator to Hospitals&#8212;the work of the different Reliefs &amp; Commissions is nearly all off in the field&#8212;&amp; as to private visitors, <hi rend="italic">there are few or none</hi>&#8212;I wish you or some of your friends could just make a round with me, for an hour or so, at some of my hospitals or camps&#8212;I go among all our own dear soldiers, hospital camps &amp; army, our teamsters' hospitals, among sick &amp; dying, the rebels, the contrabands, &amp;c &amp;c. What I reach is necessarily but a drop in the bucket but it is done in good faith, &amp; with now some experience &amp; I  hope with good heart.<ptr target="loc.00778_n100"/>
         </p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
