<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02405">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Newton Johnson to Walt Whitman, 14 December 1878</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Newton Johnson</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="vm">Vince Moran</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02405</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John Newton Johnson</author>
                    <title>John Newton Johnson to Walt Whitman, 14 December 1878</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1878-12-14" xml:id="dat1">December 14, 1878</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Johnson, John Newton" ref="n0914">John Newton Johnson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-04-24" who="#nhg">corrected, added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-23" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-21" who="#ab">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-06" who="#ej">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-12-05" who="#vm">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02405.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">To Walt Whitman from J.N.J. of Meltonsville</name>
                    <date when="1878-12-14">Dec 14 '78</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute></salute>
            </opener>
            
            <p>Because the time is short this must be abrupt, disconnected, fragmentary (perhaps)</p>
            
            <p>Your card and paper brought from P.O. yesterday.</p>
            
            <p>I have recovered from <hi rend="underline">that laziness</hi> I complained of in spring or early summer. Do you know ones home or dwelling may be so situated with reference to open road, path to the spring, fields, pasture land, <unclear reason="damage" cert="medium" resp="#ab">garden</unclear> ground &amp;c that the position of out buildings, fences &amp;c are not well indicated? such has been mine. But my doubts being settled a little I can find occupation, and that will cure my sickening laziness&#8212;indeed several new steps are clearly indicated in my farm operations.</p>
           
            <p>My crop is fair&#8212;my renters did so well by high, warm land early planted&#8212;my own cotton started off in early summer <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr></choice> slow and a July <choice><sic>drouth</sic><corr>drought</corr></choice> coming on, the plant or "weed" was amazingly small, but it is mighty well filled with fruit.</p>
            
            <p>Little Walt<ptr target="n3015"/> is a robust, healthy fellow&#8212;much so.</p>
            
            <!--<p>Turn over &amp; over</p>-->
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02405.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>Perhaps I dont owe it to you, but to myself to explain&#8212;being so enthusiastic, why have I not before this <hi rend="underline">visited you</hi>. Well I thought you were so sick it would be little satisfaction to you&#8212;then since the price of cotton went down so much 3 years ago and followed by two small crops of it then most all of a few hundred dollars owing to me is by a man who bought property largely in the flush times&#8212;I dont know when he can <hi rend="underline">conveniently</hi> pay me (other creditors may be pressing)&#8212;I desire to see you sometime&#8212;</p>
            
            <p>Of course I am only a farmer with no understanding of fine peoples' etiquette&#8212;I might be a sort of <hi rend="underline">elephant</hi> in your hands (but I believe you and I laying our heads together could do almost anything&#8212;I dont know much of anything&#8212;I guess I possess about <hi rend="underline">the</hi> <hi rend="underline">best</hi> <hi rend="underline">rested</hi> brain in the world&#8212;I thought early that I would not endanger my sanity or health by any hard study (I dont <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nhg">win</unclear> I have ever <hi rend="underline">needed to know much</hi>&#8212;yet I know you think I am solid and sound&#8212;I'd like to loafe with you in a country place or library or through a city's streets.</p>
            
            <p>My <hi rend="underline">instinct</hi> has always been against immortality; this a state of probation &amp;c</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02405.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>My idea has always been that this life is <hi rend="underline">for itself</hi>, <hi rend="double underline">for itself</hi>.</p>
            
            <p>"Dignified appearance"&#8212;I swear I have on most all occasions of my life striven to be <hi rend="underline">un</hi>-dignified. Somehow dignity (<hi rend="underline">apparent</hi>) has been associated in my mind with selfish, resentful, misanthropic, un Democratic, un&#8211;brotherly feeling. I swear I have always most wished to be thought just and kind&#8212;been willing to be thought (if possible) a good natured fool. for simple ways, for restoring belief in what man sometimes is.</p>
            
            <p>I've thought lately these pieces would make a good, orderly arranged little book by itself. 1&#8212;Carol of Words (<hi rend="underline">things</hi> are the best teachers. 2. Open Road (<choice><sic>exhortaition</sic><corr>exhortation</corr></choice> to free and abundant thinking and aspiration) 3. Brooklyn Ferry. 4. With Antecedents 5 Carol of Occupations. 6 Broad Axe Poem.</p>
            
            <p>A <hi rend="underline">small percentage</hi> of the meaning of the Axe Poem escaped me till lately (it is grand)</p>
            
            <p>I have a young, poor farmer (of 26) new acquaintance, 1&#188; miles from me studying Edition 1871 after Burroughs' Notes<ptr target="n0834"/> and Eagle's flight<ptr target="prc.00050_n2"/>&#8212;he seems to get along well (with my clear explanations)&#8212;how long will he be <hi rend="underline">a Baptist</hi>?
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02405.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            He questioned me. These lines puzzled me always and I answered so&#8212;but instantly then this doubt or suspicion (<hi rend="underline">in talking with two men</hi>) (<hi rend="underline">he</hi> said what means "A young man comes to me bearing a message from his brother &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c 3 lines"</p>
            
            <p>&#9758; A young man takes up W.W.'s book thinking he (the youth) <hi rend="underline">understands human nature</hi> &#9758; how can he? for "only after many years" &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c Am I right? the young must wait and become old (to be wise).</p>
           
            <p>I've got my old renter the Methodist (local) preacher on Two Rivulets. I told him I never expected to convert him so great the <hi rend="underline">power of habit</hi> in thinking but wanted to show him some of us are great and good. He doesn't wish to grant that a man possessing all virtues possible to the best Christian <hi rend="underline">could</hi> be <hi rend="underline">good</hi> if he lacked Christian belief and worship. Walt: the man is not at all a fool, but I think he makes not one person love him (except relationship)&#8212;what a curious cold-hearted unloving "reformer" he <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#vm">is</unclear>. He goes through life (they say and he admits) dropping unpaid debts behind him&#8212;says he must withhold something to live on and <hi rend="underline">not starve</hi>. Some say he's dishonest&#8212;but I hope he'll do nearly right with me&#8212;certainly he treated me respectfully and kindly years ago when he seemed to expect nothing. He never has family worship but grace at <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nhg">table</unclear></p>
            
            <closer>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
