<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03316">
    <teiHeader>   
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 19 January 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03316</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 19 January 1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-01-19" xml:id="dat1">January 19, 1887</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-25" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2015-07-10" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-24" who="#ss">annotated</change>
            <change when="2014-10-14" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-02" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03316.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Gosforth<lb/>Newcastle-on-Tyne</name>
                    <date when="1887-01-19">19th Jany. 1887</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
          <p>I have been staying here, at home again, for the last three or four weeks, &#38;
                before returning to London tomorrow I should like to tell you something of my
                doings, which you will be interested in perhaps although quite ordinary. </p>
            <p>Before beginning about myself, though,&#8212; many thanks for the Lippincott's
                    article.&#8212;<hi rend="underline">My Book &#38; I</hi>, which is full of
                highest import. The <choice>
                    <abbr>par.</abbr>
                    <expan>paragraph</expan>
                </choice> at foot of <choice>
                    <abbr>p.</abbr>
                    <expan>page</expan>
                </choice> 122, stating the metier of <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> is
                specially significant. The whole shows unanswerably the tremendous significance,
                indeed, of your poetic standpoint, and I wish I could prevail upon you to embody the
                essential parts of the manifesto, with a touch of redirection for our English
                readers, in a preface in <hi rend="underline">Specimen Days</hi>? I may say here  
                that Walter Scott (which means David Gordon really)<ptr target="loc.03316_n1"/> will
                send you ten guineas for the right of including the book in the Camelot series, as soon as the book arrives. </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03316.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>  
            <p>This brings us to Kennedy's book, about whose adventures over here he has no doubt
                kept you informed. At present it is in the hand of Fred. W. Wilson of Glasgow,<ptr
                    target="loc.03316_n2"/> who has had it for some time. It is needless to say much
                therefore until Wilson makes some farther move. I must send him another reminder. </p>
            <p>If I had not had special news about you from different of your friends, I should have
                been alarmed at the bad reports circulated here of late. It was as well to let them
                go, seems that they were leading to certain friendly tributes, although they seemed
                to cast a certain imputation on your friends. I was sorry to hear from W.S.K.<ptr
                    target="n3039"/> afterwards that your having been out-of-sorts &#38; without
                appetite had probably been the cause of the rumour in the first instance. May sun
                &#38; seawind move to bring you respite from all further ills of body &#38; soul! </p>
            <p>Sun &#38; sea-wind occur peculiarly to me just at present, for in spite of
                winter &#38; storm, these have meant more in the story of my days lately, since
                coming up north here, than perhaps ever before. This is what I wanted to especially
                tell you about. For some time before, I had been working at a sea subject,&#8212;"A
                North Sea Interlude," and <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03316.003_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> so it was natural that I should go down to the sea-shore a good
                deal during my stay in this part. Sometimes in these recent rambles, the sense of
                sun &#38; wind, sea &#38; land, has lifted me into a state of physical &#38;
                spiritual exaltation, that some of the L. of Grass alone in all poetry could at all
                come near expressing. One morning in particular, ten days back, everything seemed
                to move in subtlest harmony with my own pulses. When I set off a wild rain-storm was
                driving in from the south-east, but lo! as I reached the sea sands the sun shone out
                as if consciously, &#38; the movement then of the waves, &#38; the hurrying, superb
                clouds above, formed a symphony, as it were, grandest ever known; a symphony not for
                ears alone, but for all the senses. The fresh salt sea smell, the lances of sunlight
                through the cloud-rack, the steady presence of the sands &#38; rocks &#38; the
                outreaching bastions of a pier; then far away again, the ships passing:&#8212; how
                little of it one makes actual in writing!&#8212; As a last touch of this music,
                below a densely black mass of cloud that came up threateningly appeared, right on
                the sea, the end of a rainbow, which seemed so preordained, so organic, so much at once
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03316.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> with
                imagination &#38; will, that it was almost as if I had willed it there. So, bathing
                hands &#38; face in one of the waves, I came away, with a sense of something new
                having come into life &#38; thought. In attempting to tell this, all the intimate
                spirit of that hour has eluded my words, but you will read into them what they lack,
                I know! Many other like excursion have made these days memorable for ever. How I
                wish I could <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> you some of these North sea scenes, 
                so stormy &#38; turbulent, but so touched with the great peace &#38; harmonising advent of the divine
                sun!&#8212;then, two or three days ago, I went over to Browney Valley, to see my old
                friends the coal-miners &#38; farmers there. The dominant feeling of the years spent
                in that quiet countryside came back to me then very strangely. One evening (last
                Saturday) I talked over <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> with a few of the
                younger fellows, &#38; this gave a keynote to all my doings more or less. </p>
            <p>I'm afraid it is not made very clear after all about all these things, &#38; why I
                should trouble you with them. But I want you to feel that as I go on I am getting
                more into harmony with the universe &#38; with men moving in its environment, &#38;
                so may help more &#38; more to carry out the great idea of Leaves of Grass. Believe
                this, of yours most affectionately </p>
            <closer>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Ernest Rhys</hi></signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>After to-day my address is again Sq. Cheyne Walk,
                    Chelsea, S.W.</p>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <p> I wish you would send me a postcard or a pencil scribble, anything to say how
                    your are, &#38;c. now &#38; again. </p>
            </postscript>
            <!--The following postscript is found in the left margin of the first page.--> 
            <postscript>
                <p> 
                Could you<ptr target="loc.03316_n3"/>  spare me a couple of portraits similar to that prefixed to Kennedy's book?&#8212;</p>
            </postscript>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww">a wonderful letter</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
