<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04049">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 22 August 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04049</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">193&#8211;194</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 22 August 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-08-22" xml:id="dat1">August 22, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-12" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-26" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-01-31" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Marley, Haslemere</name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">England</name>
                    <date when="1880-08-22" rend="right">Aug. 22, '80.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have had all the welcome papers with accounts of your doings,<ptr target="n0259"/> and to-day a nice long letter from Mrs. Whitman,<ptr target="n0368b"/> which I much enjoyed, giving me better account of your health again, &#38; of your great enjoyment of the water travel through Canada. So I hope, spite of drawbacks, you will return to Camden for the winter quite set up in body, as well as full of delightful memories. If only we were at 22nd St. to welcome you back &#38; talk it all over at tea! Ah, those evenings! My friends told me I looked ten years younger when I came back from America than when I went. And I am not yet quite re-acclimatized; &#38; what with missing the sunshine &#38; working a little too hard, was feeling quite knocked up: so Bee<ptr target="n0260"/> insisted on my coming down, or rather up, here to stay with some very kind &#38; dear friends. The house stands all alone on a great heath-covered hill, and below &#38; around are endless coppices, so that you step from the lawn into [a] winding wood-path, along which I wander by the hour: and from my window I look over much such a view as we had at Round Hill Hotel, Northampton, this time two years, only that with the soft haze that is so often spread over our landscape, the distant hill looks more ghostly in the moonlight. My friend is a noble, large-hearted, capable woman, who devotes all her life and energies to keeping alive an invalid husband; and he well deserves her care, for he has a beautiful nature, too, &#38; their mutual affection is unbounded. He is just ordered by the doctors to leave the home they have made for themselves up here&#8212;which is as lovely as it can be&#8212;&#38; to spend two years at least in Italy. So it is a sorrowful time with them&#8212;they have no children, but have adopted a little niece. Our new house is just ready &#38; we are daily expecting our furniture from America. Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> has been working as usual, making good progress &#38; has just done a beautiful little drawing for the new edition of his father's book. Bee, you will be glad to hear, has decided to continue her medical studies &#38; is going to be assistant to a lady doctor at Edinburgh, who is to pay her sufficient salary to cover all remaining expenses. Meanwhile we have got her at home for a few weeks to help us through with the move in, and a sad pinch it will be to part with her again. Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> has been paying a delightful visit to some friends of Carpenter's<ptr target="n0141b"/> near Leeds&#8212;a Quaker family&#8212;the daughter very lovable &#38; admirable. We do not forget the Staffords<ptr target="n1009"/> nor they us. Mont. often sends Herby a magazine or a token. Love to them when you see them, &#38; to Mr. &#38; Mrs. Whitman &#38; Hattie<ptr target="n0911"/> &#38; Jessie<ptr target="n1055"/> &#38; kindest remembrance to Dr. Bucke.<ptr target="n0119"/> Send me a line soon, dear Friend&#8212;I think of you continually &#38; know that somewhere &#38; somehow we are to meet again, &#38; that there is a tie of love between us that time &#38; change &#38; death itself cannot touch.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>With love,</salute>
                <signed rend="right">A. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
