<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00455">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 2 August 1867</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00445</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">124-125</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 2 August 1867</title>
               <date when="1867-08-02">August 2, 1867</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
                  <date when="1867-08-02">Aug 2nd 1867</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours duly received<ptr target="loc.00445_n1"/>  I have had so many things to attend to lately that I have not been able to get time to answer and can only do so now so that you may know that I hav'nt forgotten you</p>
            <p>We are still at work getting out specifications for the settling Reservoirs<ptr target="loc.00445_n2"/>&#8212;a job of about $700 000&#8212;and of course we feel mighty anxious to cover all points so that we wont be upset by any sharp practice</p>
            <p>On the street to-day I saw a very interesting yet somewhat painful sight&#8212;twas that of a family moving in from the plains&#8212;An old woman&#8212;I shoud judge all of eighty&#8212;another woman of about 35&#8212;a young man and his wife abt 25 a boy of 12 two children 8 and 6 and a little babe&#8212;all but the young man and his wife were in the wagon drawn by 4 oxen&#8212;the wagon covered with dirty white canvass&#8212;The boy had leading with a rope a fine old cow&#8212;a young cow and calf were alongside&#8212;under the wagon was a large white dog and inside by the old woman was a small black terrier&#8212;They had met with an accident in the way of b[r]eaking one of the hind wheels and were therefore hard up&#8212;The faces of all were a study&#8212;but particularly of the young man and his wife&#8212;neither of them was at all handsome but yet I shall remember their faces for a long time&#8212;The old woman had that peculiar look of crazy stupidity that you can hardly tell whether they are really stupid or thinking of by-gone life  The talk of the crowd was that they had been driven in by the Indians&#8212;but I doubt that part of the story&#8212;</p>
            <p>There is a report in town to-day that some of the "bloody injuns" were stealing cows &amp;c just outside town&#8212;about where we propose to set our pumping engines&#8212;Of course I suppose its all humbug&#8212;but yet cannot see what such a detailed statement as is in the paper this morning is printed for&#8212;<ptr target="loc.00445_n3"/>
            </p>
            <p>I had a letter from Mother a few days ago&#8212;she appears to be getting along middling well yet I wish she could get a better place to live&#8212;<ptr target="loc.00445_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>From a letter received from Mat to-day she is having a first rate time yet&#8212;I wish you would write her&#8212;address care of G. F. Mason,<ptr target="loc.00445_n5"/> Towanda, Give my regards to Mr &amp; Mrs O'Conner<ptr target="loc.00445_n6"/> and friends that I met in Washington&#8212;</p>
            <p>I hope you may be able to carry out your idea and come out to see us&#8212;</p>
            <p>good by for the present  write me as often as you can</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
