<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01583">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 9 October
                    [1868]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01583</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">56–58</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 9 October [1868]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1868-10-09" xml:id="dat1">October 9, 1868</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-03-07" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-21" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1868-10-09" rend="right">Oct 9</date><ptr target="loc.01583_n1"/>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Pete,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>It is splendid here this forenoon—bright and cool. I was out early taking a
                short walk by the river—only two squares from where I live. I received your
                letter of last Monday<ptr target="loc.01583_n2"/>—also the <hi rend="italic">Star</hi> same
                date—&amp; glad enough to hear from you—the oftener the better. Every
                word is good—I sent you a letter, on the 6th, which I suppose you rec'd next
                day. Tell Henry Hurt I received his letter of Oct. 5 all right, &amp; that it was
                welcome. Political meetings here every night. The coming Pennsylvania &amp; Ohio
                elections cause much talk &amp; excitement. The fall is upon us. Overcoats are in
                demand. I already begin to think about my return to Washington. A month has nearly
                passed away. I have received an invitation from a gentleman &amp; his wife, friends
                of mine, at Providence, R. I.<ptr target="loc.01583_n3"/> &amp; shall
                probably go there &amp; spend a few days, latter part of October.</p>

            <p>I am grateful to these young men on the RR. for their love &amp; remembrance to
                me—Dave,<ptr target="loc.01583_n4"/> &amp; Jim &amp; Charley Sorrell, Tom Hassett,
                Harry on No. 11.</p>

            <p>Every day I find I have plenty to do—every hour is occupied with something.
                Shall I tell you about it, or part of it, just to fill up? I generally spend the
                forenoon in my room, writing &amp;c., then take a bath, fix up &amp; go out about
                12, &amp; loafe somewhere, or call on some one down town, or on business, or perhaps
                if it is very pleasant &amp; I feel like it, ride a trip with some driver-friend on
                Broadway from 23d street to Bowling Green, three miles each way. You know it is a
                never-ending amusement &amp; study &amp; recreation for me to ride a couple of
                hours, of a pleasant afternoon, on a Broadway stage in this way. You see everything
                as you pass, a sort of living, endless panorama—shops, &amp; splendid
                buildings, &amp; great windows, &amp; on the broad sidewalks crowds of women,
                richly-dressed, continually passing, altogether different, superior in style &amp;
                looks from any to be seen any where else—in fact a perfect stream of people,
                men too dressed in high style, &amp; plenty of foreigners—&amp; then in the
                streets the thick crowd of carriages, stages, carts, hotel &amp; private coaches,
                &amp; in fact all sorts of vehicles &amp; many first-class teams, mile after mile,
                &amp; the splendor of such a great street &amp; so many tall, ornamental, noble
                buildings, many of them of white marble, &amp; the gayety &amp; motion on every
                side—You will not wonder how much attraction all this is, on a fine day, to a
                great loafer like me, who enjoys so much seeing the busy world move by him, &amp;
                exhibiting itself for his amusement, while he takes it easy &amp; just looks on
                &amp; observes.<ptr target="loc.01583_n5"/> Then about the Broadway
                drivers, nearly all of them are my personal friends. Some have been much attached to
                me, for years, &amp; I to them. But I believe I have already mentioned them in a
                former letter. Yesterday I rode the trip I describe with a friend, on a 5th Avenue
                stage, No. 26—a sort [of] namesake of yours, Pete Calhoun.<ptr target="loc.01583_n6"/> I have known him 9 or 10 years. The day was fine, &amp; I enjoyed the trip
                muchly. So I try to put in something in my letters to give you an idea of how I pass
                part of my time, &amp; what I see here in N. Y. Of course I have quite a
                variety—some four or five hours every day I most always spend in study,
                writing, &amp;c. The other serves for a good change. I am writing two or three
                pieces. </p>

            <p>I am having finished about 225 copies of Leaves of Grass bound up, to supply orders.
                Those copies form all that is left of the old editions. Then there will be no more
                in the market till I have my new &amp; improved edition set up &amp; stereotyped,
                which it is my present plan to do the ensuing winter at my leisure in
                    Washington.<ptr target="loc.01583_n7"/>
            </p>

            <p>Mother is well, I take either dinner or supper with her every day. Remember me to
                David Stevens &amp; John Towers.<ptr target="loc.01583_n8"/> Tell Harry on No 11 I will go
                [to] the Hall again &amp; see if I can find that man in the Sheriff's office.<ptr target="loc.01583_n9"/> I send you my love,
                &amp; <hi rend="italic">so long</hi> for the present. Yours for life, dear Pete,
                (&amp; death the same).</p>

            <closer>
                <salute/>
                <signed/>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>