<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00832">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 3 June 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="lh">Luke Hollis</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00832</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume"/>
                     <biblScope type="page">229&#8211;230</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 3 June 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-06-03">June 3, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#lh" when="2009-08-28">proofed and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-07">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1864-06-03">June 3 1864</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter came yesterday&#8212;I have not heard the least thing from the 51st since&#8212;no doubt they are down there with the Army near Richmond&#8212;I have not written to George lately&#8212;I think the news from the Army is very good&#8212;Mother, you know of course that it is now very near Richmond indeed, from five to ten miles<ptr target="loc.00832_n1"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, if this campaign was not in progress I should not stop here, as it is now beginning to tell a little upon me,<ptr target="loc.00832_n2"/> so many bad wounds, many putrified, &amp; all kinds of dreadful ones, I have been rather too much with&#8212;but as it is I shall certainly remain here while the thing remains undecided&#8212;it is impossible for me to abstain from going to see &amp; minister to certain cases, &amp; that draws me into others, &amp; so on&#8212;I have just left Oscar Cunningham,<ptr target="loc.00832_n3"/> the Ohio boy&#8212;he is in a dying condition&#8212;there is no hope for him&#8212;it would draw tears from the hardest heart to look at him&#8212;he is all wasted away to a skeleton, &amp; looks like some one fifty years old&#8212;you remember I told you a year ago, when he was first brought in, I thought him the noblest specimen of a young western man I had seen, a real giant in size, &amp; always with a smile on his face&#8212;O what a change, he has long been very irritable, to every one but me, &amp; his frame is all wasted away&#8212;the young Massachusetts 1st artillery boy, Cutter, I wrote about is dead&#8212;he is the one that was brought in a week ago last Sunday, badly wounded in breast&#8212;the deaths in the principal hospital I visit, Armory Square, average one an hour&#8212;I saw Capt Baldwin<ptr target="loc.00832_n4"/> of the 14th this morning, he has lost his left arm&#8212;is going home soon&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mr Kalbfleisch<ptr target="loc.00832_n5"/> &amp; Anson Herrick,<ptr target="loc.00832_n6"/> (M C from New York) came in one of the wards where I was sitting writing a letter this morning, in the midst of the wounded&#8212;Kalbfleisch was so much affected by the sight that he burst into tears&#8212;O I must tell you I gave the boys in Carver hospital a great treat of ice cream a couple of days ago, went round myself through about 15 large wards, (I bought some ten gallons, very nice)&#8212;you would have cried &amp; been amused too, many of the men had to be fed, several of them I saw cannot probably live, yet they quite enjoyed it, I gave everybody some&#8212;quite a number western country boys had never tasted ice cream before&#8212;they relish such things, oranges, lemons, &amp;c&#8212;Mother, I feel a little blue this morning, as two young men I knew very well have just died, one died last night, &amp; the other about half an hour before I went to the hospital, I did not anticipate the death of either of them, each was a very, very sad case, so young&#8212;well, mother, I see I have written you another gloomy sort of letter&#8212;I do not feel as first rate as usual&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt&#8212;</signed>
            </closer>

         <postscript>
            <p>You don't know how I want to come home &amp; see you all, you, dear Mother, &amp; Jeff &amp; Mat &amp; all&#8212;I believe I am homesick, something new for me&#8212;then I have seen all the horrors of soldier's life &amp; not been kept up by its excitement&#8212;it is awful to see so much, &amp; not be able to relieve it&#8212;</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
