<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00943">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 5 July 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Ellen M. O'Connor</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>

               <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00943</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Ellen M. O'Connor</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 5 July 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-07-06">July 5, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-12">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-03">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-20">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">added encoding for page breaks</change>
         <change who="#bbb" when="2009-08-06">updated annotations</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
            <pb facs="loc.00943.001.jpg" xml:id="leaf001r" type="recto"/>
            
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date when="1864-07-05">July 5th 1864</date>
                        <name type="place">Washington. D.C.</name>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
                </opener>
          <p>It will be two weeks to-morrow since you left us,<ptr target="loc.00943_n100"/> and I have missed you terribly every minute of the time. I think I never in my life felt so wholly blue and unhappy about any one's going away as I did and have since, about your going. I began to be really superstitious I felt so badly. I did not think that you were going to die, but I could not possibly overcome the feeling that our dear <pb facs="loc.00943.002.jpg" xml:id="leaf001v" type="verso"/>and pleasant circle was broken, and it seemed to me that we four should not be together any more as we have been. But now since you are so much better, I hope you will come back to Washington in the autumn to stay all winter, and I hope we shall spend a part of every day together, as we have so many days. Ah! Walt, I don't believe other people need you as much as we do. I am
                    <hi rend="italic">sure</hi>
                    they don't need you as much as
                    <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                    do. William says it seems <pb facs="loc.00943.003.jpg" xml:id="leaf002r" type="recto"/>so desolate since you left,&#8212;and even yet in the evening when I hear a car coming, I find myself watching for you, and listening for you.</p>
            <p>One reason that I have not written to you before is that I have been so unhappy I thought my letter would only make you so. I can't possibly tell you what a gap you have left, and how all seems gone since you left.</p>
            <p>William got your note, and answered it but he directed it to Brooklyn only, so it may not be carried to your house, &amp; <pb facs="loc.00943.004.jpg" xml:id="leaf002v" type="verso"/>you may have to look after it. Charlie got your letter to him, &amp; answered it the same day.<ptr target="loc.00943_n2"/> He went off last Friday to pay the Staff Officers down at the front in the 5th Corps, Warren's &amp; he said he wished you were here to go with them, as it would give you a fine chance to see your brother George. He expected to get back yesterday, but we have not seen him yet.</p>
            <p>Poor Ashton is sick in bed with rheumatism, a fearful attack of it, &amp; he is hourly expecting his brother to be sent-up, who has been badly <pb facs="loc.00943.005.jpg" xml:id="leaf003r" type="recto"/>wounded in the arm &amp; neck, but I have promised him that if his brother arrives before I leave, I will go &amp; see him.<ptr target="loc.00943_n3"/>
            </p>
            <p>The Johnsons are all well, &amp; still have good accounts of John.<ptr target="loc.00943_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>Our affairs remain as they did when you left, &amp; that is one cause of my delay. I know that William prefers &amp; I do, too, that this trouble concerning the house &amp; hall be settled before I leave, but I think I must go this week at any rate.</p>
            <p>Mr. Fessenden will probably be our Sec. of the Treasury, he has <pb facs="loc.00943.006.jpg" xml:id="leaf003v" type="verso"/>not yet accepted we hear.</p>
            <p>Mr. Irvinton made us a visit on Sunday. He is now located here, as you may know. He looked sick, &amp; says he is. He has had chills &amp; fever, caught in the James River.</p>
            <p>I can't bear to
                        <hi rend="italic">write</hi>
                        you, dear Walt, when I have so much to say to you, &amp; so much to ask. You must tell me when you write, about the baby &amp; the folk at home. Did the little California come up to the early promise of her babyhood? &amp; how is <pb facs="loc.00943.007.jpg" xml:id="leaf004r" type="recto"/>your mother? Tell me when you write.</p>
            <p>In the hurry &amp; suddenness of your leaving I forgot to give you Mrs. Beach's notes, shall I trust them to the mail or keep them for you till you come back?<ptr target="loc.00943_n5"/>
            </p>
            <p>I asked Miss. Howard about Jesse Mullory, &amp; she says he was sent to New York before you left Washington, but she says he was
                            <hi rend="italic">very</hi>
                            deaf before he left &amp; she thought him in a very bad way.<ptr target="loc.00943_n6"/> She has been obliged to give up going for a week past but will begin again next week. &amp; if you <pb facs="loc.00943.008.jpg" xml:id="leaf004v" type="verso"/>want to know about any of your boys, or about Armory hospital generally, she would be very glad to tell you. Send her a note any time, &amp; direct it to William &amp; he will take it to her office.</p>
            <p>The fourth was rather a dull day to me, the only satisfaction I had was in helping Mr. Wood pack his trunk, Jeannie &amp; I spent two hours with him in the morning, helping him, as he was to leave to-day.<ptr target="loc.00943_n7"/> He is still very poorly I think, but he has a <pb facs="loc.00943.009.jpg" xml:id="leaf005r" type="recto"/>vacation of two months, so I hope he will come back
                                <hi rend="italic">well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I got my pictures last week, &amp; they are rather bad, the front face, or rather three quarter face, is hideous, William forbids my giving any of them away. The side face is&#8212;well what do you say of it? I think it is
                                    <hi rend="italic">very</hi>
                                    sharp, &amp; I know I should not like any body that looked like it, do
                                    <hi rend="italic">you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What news from your brother George? I think our army affairs are looking rather dismal, don't you? And when <pb facs="loc.00943.010.jpg" xml:id="leaf005v" type="verso"/>gold went up so last week, I thought we were going to have a crash in the finance at once, &amp; now what a terrible rise there is in prices, sugar 38 cents a pound here. Is it so bad with you?</p>
            <p>What about your book? Have you been able yet to give a thought even?	</p>
            <p>And just how are you? Tell me won't you? I hope you are very, very much better.</p>
            <p>That Wednesday evening after you left I felt so badly at your leaving so suddenly. For it was sudden at <pb facs="loc.00943.011.jpg" xml:id="leaf006r" type="recto"/>last,&#8212;&amp; I wished I had persuaded you to stay just one day longer, but the very next day was
                                        <hi rend="italic">intensely hot,</hi>
                                        &amp; so for four days, &amp; then I was glad for your sake that you were safe home. Now it is cool, and
                                        <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                                        am one of the few who feel best the hottest days.</p>
            <p>See what a long letter I have written you. Jeannie says tell Mr. Walt that I hope he will come home soon, &amp; see papa, &amp; tell him I send my love to him &amp; a kiss. Louisa asks for you <pb facs="loc.00943.012.jpg" xml:id="leaf006v" type="verso"/>so does Mrs. Howells, &amp; many more, Dr. &amp; Mrs. Wood.<ptr target="loc.00943_n8"/>
            </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Good bye Walt, with much love -</salute>
                    <signed>Nelly.</signed>
                </closer>
            
            <postscript>
                <p>P.S. Send to me here till I write you again, &amp; if I know what day I am to leave I shall let you know, in the hope of seeing you as I pass through New York.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Nelly.</signed>
                </closer>
            </postscript>
        </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
