<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00949">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 1 November 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00949</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 1 November 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-11-01">November 1, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-14">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-17">revised annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-17">added encoding for page breaks</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00949.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date when="1865-11-01">Friday. Nov. 1st 1865.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Your letter was very welcome, and I<ptr target="loc.00949_n100"/> have not forgotten you one day, though I have not written you. But I have been very much occupied in thought, as well as much of my time in going daily, &amp; some days twice to see Miss Howard.<ptr target="loc.00949_n2"/> Her sister Sallie has the worst form of typhoid fever. She has been very ill for three weeks, &amp; alarmingly so for over ten days. Her mother <pb facs="loc.00949.002.jpg" type="verso"/>was sent for more than a week ago, and two doctors have come twice a day to see her for many days. I don't suppose there is any hope at all. She is wild with delirium all the time. Poor Garrie is worn, but she bears up like a hero under it, does not leave her sister night or day. I got a good nurse for them, as their nurse had to leave.</p>
            <p>It is very sad, &amp; I have not given up hoping till to-day, but she has no encouraging symptoms.<pb facs="loc.00949.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            </p>
            <p>I was so glad to hear that your little pet was better, and that your mother had got home! Has the little girl continued to improve? I hope so.</p>
            <p>It was good too, to hear that your mother was so well, &amp; George, &amp; all of you.</p>
            <p>I hope you are all well now. I trust the little girl is picking up fast.</p>
            <p>You ask about William.<ptr target="loc.00949_n3"/> His letters have been "few and far between", four in five weeks,&#8212; but now I look a little for him to-morrow, <pb facs="loc.00949.004.jpg" type="recto"/>Saturday, and shall surely expect him on Sunday.  I guess he has had a good time, &amp; he sent the <hi rend="italic">MSS.</hi> to Curtis.  You may see him in New York to-morrow.  He will see Curtis, I suppose.</p>
            <p>When you come back what <hi rend="italic">lots</hi> of things we shall have to talk about.</p>
            <p>I saw in the Tribune of <hi rend="italic">Wednesday</hi> the advertisement of <hi rend="italic">Drum Taps</hi>.  Glad we were to see it, Charley &amp; I.</p>
            <p>Have you sent one to Emerson?  <hi rend="italic">Do</hi>, in haste, won't you?  I <pb facs="loc.00949.005.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00949.006.jpg" type="verso"/>want him to have one right away.</p>
            <p>Dear Walt, will you see in New York Mr. Howells?<ptr target="loc.00949_n4"/> I don't even know his address, &amp; it is necessary that I should write him a business letter. I wonder how they are. Give him my love if you see him.</p>
            <p>Jeannie is well, &amp; sends love. I am well, so is Charley, &amp; he too, sends love.<!-- <ptr target="n5" xml:id="r5"/> --> We all want to see you back.</p>
            <p>Mr. Ashton is well, but
<hi rend="italic">very busy,</hi>
&amp; looks worn.<ptr target="loc.00949_n6"/> His wife is well, &amp; I guess they will come soon.</p>
            <p>Give my love to your mother, &amp; with much love to you - hoping soon to see you.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours&#8212;</salute>
               <signed>Nelly.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
