<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04218">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Joseph W. Thompson to Walt Whitman, 20 January 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>James W. Thompson</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="am">Alicia Meyer</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04218</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Joseph W. Thompson</author>
                    <title>Joseph W. Thompson to Walt Whitman, 20 January 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-01-20" xml:id="dat1">January 20, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Thompson, Joseph W.">Joseph W. Thompson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-11-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-20" who="#am">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-12" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-10-25" who="#ej">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00357_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Goldsmith Building, Temple.</name>
                    <date when="1880-01-20">January the 20<hi rend="superscript"><hi
                                rend="underline">th</hi></hi></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>

            <p>In December I received from you a post-card, under date St Louis <choice>
                    <sic>Misouri</sic>
                    <corr>Missouri</corr>
                </choice>
                <choice>
                    <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                    <expan>November</expan>
                </choice> 20, saying that you had been detained from home by illness but would soon
                return, when you would send to me the two books (<hi rend="underline">Vistas</hi>
                &amp; <hi rend="underline">Memoranda</hi>) which I wrote to you
                for back in the fall.<ptr target="n3025"/> Since that I have not heard from you&#8212;this makes me rather
                anxious to know that you are still getting on towards recovering your health&#8212;I am very glad indeed that you have had such a "good time" in the west of the
                States, but it would be <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">sad</unclear> if you were to be ill for long as a consequence of your
                travel.</p>

            <p>I have now sent you a post office order for 21 shillings&#8212;This is for your
                second volume of the complete Edition of 1875 ("<hi rend="underline">Two
                    Rivulets</hi>") <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_vm.00358_large.jpg" type="verso"/>I have a very dear cousin Ethel
                Thompson&#8212;who lately became 21 years old. That is an
                occasion for rejoicing and congratulating people over here. I don't know why. I
                think people ought to be condoled with, rather. Anyhow, it is also the practice to
                cheer them up with presents&#8212;and, as I believed that your "Leaves of Grass"
                would give my cousin more pleasure than anything else I could give her, I gave her
                that book.</p>

            <p>But her sister&#8212;another woman who is dear to me&#8212;Honora Thompson&#8212;had
                thought just the same and gave her the same book! So I have taken back "Leaves of
                Grass" and am going to keep it as a <hi rend="underline">loan copy</hi>. That is a
                copy to lend to those who know little about your poems and want to know more.</p>
            <p>And I am going to give to Ethel Thompson "Two Rivulets" so that she will be the
                gainer by <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nnk">two</unclear>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00359_large.jpg" type="recto"/>of her friends' having determined
                to give her Whitman as a birthday present.</p>
            <p>I want you, if you will, to write in the book "Ethel Thompson from Joseph William
                Thompson, December the 15<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi>
                1879" and, having written this, to sign it with your own name and the actual date of
                your so signing. Do you mind doing this for me and then sending it off by post
                to&#8212;
                <address><addrLine>Ethel Thompson</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Charles Thompson&#8212;esquire&#8212;</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Preswylfa</addrLine>
            <addrLine>near Cardiff</addrLine><lb/>
            <addrLine>England</addrLine></address>.</p>
            <p> I shall be very grateful to you, but not so grateful as I am for your having written
                what you have written
                (in your book, I mean).</p>
            <p>Honora Thompson tells me that she was not able satisfactorily to answer two questions
                which you put to her about the selection of your poems made by M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> W. M. Rossetti,<ptr target="n0522"/> I can tell you. The book is out of
                print and the publishers&#8212;<unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="low">Messrs</unclear> Chatto and Windus (of Piccadilly&#8212;
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00360_large.jpg" type="verso"/>London) have
                definitely answer'd the question as to whether they were going to republish it in
                the <hi rend="underline">negative</hi>.</p>
            <p>You say that you never received any thing from the publishers on account of that
                selection. But do you think that a profit was made? From the manner in which M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Rossetti writes in the preface, I should think it very
                possible that it was a <choice><orig>'labour</orig>
                    <reg>labor</reg>
                </choice> of love' on his part to bring the book out, and that he neither hoped for
                nor got any gain excepting the knowledge that he had done his best to make your works
                better known in England.</p>
            <p>That is how it <hi rend="underline">seems</hi> to me&#8212;I <hi rend="underline"
                    >know</hi> nothing.</p>
            <p>But many in England are anxious that there should be a <hi rend="underline">good</hi>
                selection of your poems in a popular form, so that all may gradually get knowledge
                of them. I who write to you am young (26) and inexperienced. I have lately abandoned
                my intention&#8212;half-formed&#8212;of trying to earn my living at the
                bar&#8212;and I am <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.00359_large.jpg" type="recto"
                    />uncertain what work I shall do. But
                    <hi rend="underline">some</hi> work, some good to the world, I will try to do.
                Amongst other things, if it is not done before I can put my hand to it, I will, if
                you will give me leave, make and bring out a selection of your poems and sell it at
                a cheap price. People will not give 10 dollars&#8212;or 5&#8212;for that of which
                they know nothing. And thus you <hi rend="underline">remain</hi> an unknown writer
                to the great mass of Englishmen and Englishwomen. I hope that, come time, I shall
                write to you for your permission&#8212;At present, I cannot undertake this
                work&#8212;I want to have a more thorough knowledge&#8212;such knowledge as the
                digesting by time can alone give&#8212;of your poems, and I need not add that if it
                came in my path to come to America to see you, it is a chance which I should very eagerly grasp at. That <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.00362_large.jpg" type="verso"/>may possibly
                happen in the summer of next year. I do not know.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, a M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lewin<ptr target="loc.04218_n1"/> of Birkenhead, who edits a small
                quarterly magazine called "Papers for the Times" seems to wish to reprint here the
                "Preface to Leaves of Grass" which you have omitted from all your later
                editions&#8212;May I ask you why you have omitted it? I know that you have
                practically embodied some of it in your other poems&#8212;but not all of it. I
                myself do not know whether your <hi rend="underline">preface</hi> is in reality a
                preface&#8212;something good to prefix&#8212;or itself a poem just as much as the
                other poems are. I have thought that that might be the reason for your no longer
                printing it as a preface. I have told M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                Lewin that I would ask you as to your wishes with
                regard to it being reprinted. I must tell <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="loc_vm.00363_large.jpg" type="recto"/>you that M<hi rend="superscript"
                    >r</hi> Lewin or whoever should undertake it would <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">probability</hi> have no margin of profit, but (probably) a
                margin the other way&#8212;But if I, personally, had anything to do with the
                publishing, I should make it a condition that any profit that there might be should
                be handed over to you.</p>
            <p>I am afraid that my letter is growing to a much-too-great size, but there is one more
                topic. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Edward Carpenter<ptr target="n0141b"/> has been so kind as to lend
                me M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Burroughs's<ptr target="n0129"/> "Walt Whitman as Poet and Person"<ptr target="n0834"/>
                which I have read with very great interest. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Child<ptr target="n1054"/> (I
                think his name is) at <choice>
                    <orig>Trubner's</orig><reg>Tr&#252;bner's</reg></choice> (the publisher's) says that he believes you have the
                remaining stock of these books. Is this so? If so, will you kindly send me a copy, to
                this <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_vm.00364_large.jpg" type="verso"/>address
                (Goldsmith Building, Temple, London) and let me know what I owe you for it. M<hi
                    rend="superscript">r</hi> Carpenter's copy of the book (1867) was <choice>
                    <abbr>pub<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>published</expan>
                    </choice> by the American News Company,<ptr target="n0037"/> but I have seen it spoken
                of as being published by J.S. Redfield<ptr target="n0499b"/>&#8212;in 1871. Perhaps that is
                a later edition.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I am, dear sir,</salute>
                <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
                <signed>J.W. Thompson</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p><address><addrLine>Walt Whitman&#8212;</addrLine>
<addrLine>Camden, New Jersey.</addrLine></address></p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
