<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="man.00018">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, [April or May 1880?]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                    <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>man.00018</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, [April or May 1880?]</title>              
                    <date cert="medium" notBefore="1880-04-01" notAfter="1880-05-31" xml:id="dat1">April or May 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="man">Charles Sixsmith Collection at the John Rylands Library, University of Manchester</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-08-28">corrected based on Ken's corrections</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>            
            <change when="2014-08-05" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-20" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2014-01-16" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-14" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="man_ej.00231_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note resp="#ww" type="editorial" place="top right">paper from Canada</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Lange Strasse 29, II. Dresden. Saxony.</name>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            
            <p>I sent you yesterday, as greeting for your birthday, a small gift which I hope may reach you sometime about May 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. The date below your photograph in the Two Rivulets had caught my eye that morning&#8212;and after some pondering I decided to make a selection from a set of etchings by Turner, which I had for labels from England, &amp; accordingly I sent you three of them which I thought might interest you most. Two of English landscape, extremely characteristic, and one of Greenwich Hospital, with vast London, half lost in its smoke, in the background. The fame of our greatest English artist must surely have reached you, even if you have not already some specimens of his work. He has done nothing better than these etchings for the 'Liber Studiorum' I think, for though one misses his splendour of color, yet one sees the very soul of the man at work, as it were, in an impromptu way: there are a hundred things to be read in these delicate lines, which no doubt you will see more clearly than I do so I'll say no more about them. Only you must not
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="man_ej.00233_large.jpg" type="verso"/> <unclear reason="damage" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">suppose</unclear> the present to be a more valuable one than it really is. they are not plates of the original etchings (these are now unattainable except by millionaires) but absolutely faithful facsimiles lately published at a moderate cost by a London company, from original plates in the possession of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stopford Brooke. Having seen the originals I can testify to the perfect accuracy of these copies. They are done I believe by some process like photography.</p>
            
            <p>I have left Ireland and pitched my tent temporarily (that is for a few years) in Germany, a sojourn which I find pleasant enough, except for the consciousness of living under the r&#233;gime of Bismarck. You can have no idea, no one can who has not lived in this country, how the weight of a government practically despotic, like this, presses like lead on the shoulders of each individual citizen, what shameful wrigglings it induces, to escape the load at one side or another. Police officers, dressed in plain clothes, are everywhere, no German will speak truly about politics even in his own house &amp; on the most trivial questions, for success in public life is barred to a man who will not be a mere tool in the hands of Bismarck. The people
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="man_ej.00234_large.jpg" type="recto"/><unclear reason="damage" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">do not know</unclear> their strength <unclear reason="damage" cert="medium" resp="#nhg">and</unclear> the Parliamen<supplied reason="damage" cert="high" resp="#kc">t</supplied> <gap reason="damage" quantity="2" unit="words"/> set of poltroons, full of petty spite one day and of abject terror the next, when the Zeus of the political Olympus thunders.</p><p>It is a curious evidence of the transforming power of American institutions and soil, that the one German I have met who seems to have the tone of manliness in his character is a returned American. His name is Plan. he went out pretty young, tried all the lives that men usually do who go out to seek their fortunes there&#8212;farming, trading, gold-digging, &amp;c. Succeeded well enough in the moneymaking line, came home to be married, is now a country innkeeper not far from this, &amp; says he is waiting for a good time to go back to the U.S. with his wife and children, as Germany is no place for a free man to live in. I could not describe to you how clearly his figure stands out among the rest of the Germans I know here, with what distinct individuality. We made friends at once. he took a fancy to me because I am Irish, and he had an Irish friend in California. (a good reason surely!) I think you would call him an ideal American, full of friendliness and good humour, and earnest loyalty to things and persons that attract him, full, too, of sound practical sense and resolution, with a curious leaven of recklessness and daring totally foreign to the German nature. He has too a real pleasure in literature, his favourite poem is Longfellow's Hiawatha</p>       
                
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="man_ej.00232_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
<p>
            <gap reason="torn away" extent="2 words" quantity="7" unit="chars"/> several <gap reason="torn away" extent="1 word" quantity="8" unit="chars"/> of your <gap reason="torn away" extent="3 words" quantity="14" unit="chars"/> women, a great many come to Dresden. Of course generally from the "upper classes" &amp; I must say, if I knew nothing of America except through them, I should form rather a curious opinion of you. Your 'ladies and gentlemen' appear to be much more cut off from the lower class, the People, than they are in England, where there is recognized inequality, but unbroken links of connection. Certainly not one of these people reminded me in the least of any traits in your 'Democratic Vistas' or 'Memoranda.' And another fact struck me&#8212;that while the upperclasses in England are generally <hi rend="underline">really</hi> superior, in true and worthy qualities, rightful leaders and worthy of their trust, the corresponding class in America are frivolous nobodies, an excrescence, not part of the living flesh and bone of the nation. But of course my impression may be, probably is, utterly wrong: how could it be more than a random guess, after nothing more than a profound study of an American neighbour at a foreign table d'h&#244;t&#233; or picture-gallery? I have for a couple of years cherished the intention of sometime seeing you, and something of America, but I have not yet been able to afford to leave Europe. Perhaps next year I may.</p>
            
            <p>I suppose by this time you have received from M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Alexander the price of the book. I forwarded the results of your inquiries to her from the continent, but have heard nothing since</p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">T.W.H. Rolleston</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
            
            <postscript><p>Turner's <hi rend="underline"><choice><abbr>may'nt</abbr><expan>may not</expan></choice></hi> come <choice><abbr>till</abbr><expan>until</expan></choice> some days after this. Have franked them through.</p></postscript>
        </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
