<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="man.00047">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Louisa Orr Whitman to Walt Whitman, 4 July 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Louisa Orr Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="am">Alicia Meyer</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>man.00047</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Louisa Orr Whitman</author>
                    <title>Louisa Orr Whitman to Walt Whitman, 4 July 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-07-04" xml:id="dat1">July 4, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="man">Charles Sixsmith Collection at the John Rylands Library, University of Manchester</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Orr">Louisa Orr Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-12-03" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-19" who="#am">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-09-26" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-08-30" who="#ej">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="man_ej.00126_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1880-07-04">July 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute/>Dear Brother Walt,</opener>

            <p>Your paper received and your postal,<ptr target="n0368b"/> and I have been wanting to write all the week,
                but busy as usual, Today is perfectly lovely we had a refreshing rain on Friday and
                the streets look clean, and every thing bright <choice>
                    <abbr>Geo</abbr><expan>George</expan></choice><ptr target="n0700"/> is busy as ever, but we generally have an hours or so drive in the evening, and I
                come home with a good appetite so it must do me good. Last week while I was at
                market Ida Johnson<ptr target="n1058"/> must have been here, Ed<ptr target="n1047"/> went to the door and he said it was Miss
                Johnson, have you heard from any of them? Did you see the account of the large fire
                in the southern part of <choice><abbr>Phila</abbr><expan>Philadelphia</expan></choice>, a Planing mill and lumber yard and 50 <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">houses</unclear>. The Planing mill was Will
                Nices the cousin that comes here a good deal, Walt I think you
                have heard me speak of the child that sister <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high"
                    resp="#ej">Kate</unclear> left at her death, she has always been with her <choice>
                    <sic>fathers</sic>
                    <corr>father's</corr>
                </choice> mother, but about a month ago, her grandmother died and we have taken
                Alice, she is nine years old, and a very good disposition, I took her feeling the
                care very much, for I really knew so little about her, only seeing her about twice a
                year but we do not find her any trouble to manage, indeed have been quite surprised
                to see how she fits right into our household ways, she is quiet, and seems perfectly
                contented with Tip for a
                companion, he appears to love her dearly, and they are always together, Alice has
                only been here since last Wednesday, so of course this is only a short experience. The
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#ej">Perks</unclear> and the
                Elversons are away, Mrs Berry and family think of going soon. Mrs Berry
                says she misses seeing you very much getting on and off the cars, and wishes to be
                remembered to you. You will miss the fire crackers and noise of the fourth in Canada a lucky miss

            I always dread the noise. I suppose you are having a good time, and keeping well, we all send love.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed>Lou</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="man_ej.00127_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <!--Note in WW's hand: "from Lou July 4 '80 | sent: July 7" -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
