<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="man.00027">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 28 March 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="am">Alicia Meyer</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>man.00027</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
                    <title>Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 28 March 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-03-28" xml:id="dat1">March 28, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="man">Charles Sixsmith Collection at the John Rylands Library, University of Manchester</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-11-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-14" who="#am">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-09-17" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-08-09" who="#ej">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="man_ej.00040_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">17. Holland Place</name>
                    <name type="place">Highfields</name>
                    <name type="place">Sheffield.</name>
                    <date when="1880-03-28">Easter Sunday 1880</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute/>Dear Walt,</opener>

            <p>It is a long time since I wrote to you<ptr target="n0141b"/>&#8212;but I have heard a good deal about you
                from the Gilchrists<ptr target="n3001"/>&#8212;about your journey West and back again. I <hi
                    rend="underline">am</hi> glad you have seen it all, and are satisfied&#8212;and
                the great mountains of Colorado&#8212;did they not make your <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="man_ej.00181_large.jpg" type="verso"/>soul shout? I would like to see you
                and be with you for a little time&#8212;it would seem so restful. I wonder now
                whether you have good friends about you at Camden, and feel at peace, spite of
                illness. Do you sometimes feel really satisfied, and as if you didn't care what
                happened, knowing it is done and can never be undone&#8212;dear Walt I wish you
                could live and renew your strength again in all those whom <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="man_ej.00182_large.jpg" type="recto"/>you have delivered. But perhaps you
                do so. I have long had it on my mind to write and ask you about the possibility of
                publishing a cheaper edition of <choice>
                    <abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>your</expan>
                </choice> Leaves of Grass in England;&#8212;there are so many now who cannot afford
                the long price of present editions. I have thought that the sale might be so
                increased by a cheaper edition (say a 7/6 one) as even to pay you. But then
                there is the <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="man_ej.00042_large.jpg" type="verso"
                />difficulty of publishers (Tr&#252;bner <choice>
                    <abbr>w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>would</expan>
                </choice> I think do you justice); and of course you could not issue your present
                stereotyped <choice>
                    <abbr>ed<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>edition</expan>
                </choice> in England at a lower price than in America. Still, what if a few friends
                in England combined to undertake the expense of a comparatively cheap edition, sell
                it through Tr&#252;bner or some other publisher, and the profits to go to you. Would
                you approve? I have thought a good deal about it, and that is the only feasible plan <choice>
                    <abbr>wh</abbr>
                    <expan>which</expan>
                </choice> occurs to me&#8212;that will make the book accessible <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003r" facs="man_ej.00043_large.jpg" type="recto"/>to the people, and
                also pay you. But then again, would such a cheaper <choice>
                    <abbr>ed<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>edition</expan>
                </choice> be pirated across the Atlantic &amp; sold in the U.S.A in competition with
                yours? Of course you have thought all this over: but you may not realise, what I am
                only beginning to realise, the great demand <choice>
                    <abbr>wh</abbr>
                    <expan>which</expan>
                </choice> is likely to arise here for your works, <hi rend="underline">not</hi> among the literary
                world but among the ordinary working day world. I have often been asked lately about
                cheaper editions&#8212;</p><pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="man_ej.00183_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/><p>A friend of mine, a carpenter, writes "I need not tell you not to
                forget 'Leaves of Grass' <choice>
                    <abbr>wh</abbr>
                    <expan>which</expan>
                </choice> I have no doubt will please me as much as did <choice>
                    <abbr>'Dem</abbr>
                    <expan>Democratic</expan>
                </choice> Vistas'. If I had sent you the references I made (and I made them to send
                to you) you would have been amused for I had marked almost every page and almost
                every paragraph. I considered it would be better to praise the whole book, for it is
                all excellent. It is to be hoped Whitman will publish a cheaper edition of his
                splendid works. He is one of those whom <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="man_ej.00184_large.jpg" type="recto"/>mankind in the future will surely
                know better than now how to <choice>
                    <orig>honour</orig><reg>honor</reg></choice>." I believe I once mentioned to you a M<hi
                        rend="superscript">rs</hi> Hardy who is now out in <choice>
                    <abbr>Penn<hi rend="superscript">a</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                        </choice> (Lawrence C<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>). If she ever comes to find you
                out&#8212;you will receive her. But I will not quote what she says of you&#8212;and
                yet I think I will&#8212;she says "I have not felt it a 'new birth of the soul'
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nhg">merely</unclear>, I felt
                that his poems were the food for which my poor weak soul <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="man_ej.00045_large.jpg" type="verso"/>was longing. Oh I do love him, the
                dear earnest old man,
                I want so much to see him to take him by the <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">left</unclear> hand and standing palm to palm
                look away up into his
                blue eyes and say 'Walt Whitman I love you'. There are only a very few men I know to
                whom I could say it, but he I know would be able to understand <hi rend="underline"
                    >all</hi> I mean by it; and it <choice>
                    <abbr>w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>would</expan>
                </choice> do us both good&#8212;in no other way could I tell him how much <pb
                    xml:id="leaf005r" facs="man_ej.00046_large.jpg" type="recto"/>I admire his
                poems".</p>

            <p>About myself, I feel that I cannot go on with this lecturing&#8212;and in a month I hope
                to be at work out in the country near here&#8212;at first on some land of
                Ruskins<ptr target="n3013"/>&#8212;but perhaps not for very long so. When you see Harry Stafford<ptr target="n0590"/> give him
                my love and say I am going to send him a photo: and hope he will send me one.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="man_ej.00047_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>Goodbye, dear friend whom I do not ever forget. I wish I could be near you,
                    in body, as I am in soul</p>
            <closer> 
                <signed>Edward Carpenter</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
