<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="man.00029">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 28 March 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="am">Alicia Meyer</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>man.00029</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 28 March 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-03-28" xml:id="dat1">March 28, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="man">Charles Sixsmith Collection at the John Rylands Library, University of Manchester</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-12-02" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-19" who="#am">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-09-17" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-08-12" who="#ej">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="man_ej.00051_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">5 Mount Vernon</name>
                    <name type="place">Hampstead.</name>
                    <date when="1880-03-28">March 28/ 80</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dearest Friend</salute></opener>

            <p>Has it seemed to you a long while since I wrote?<ptr target="n0259"/> It has to me, a very long while,
                &amp; many's the day that I have said to myself, to-morrow I shall write a long
                letter &amp; then the quiet leisure needed has never come. I sometimes think the
                best way would be to keep a letter always going&#8212;to jot down once a week, say,
                anything that I fancy will interest you &amp; then send you the sum total at a
                months end.</p>

            <p>I have news about dear Bee<ptr target="n0260"/> that will surprise and, perhaps, disappoint you. After she
                had studied four or five months at Bern the field of medical study began to broaden
                out before her: she realized <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="man_ej.00187_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> more than even before what science was being brought to bear on
                the investigation of disease, &amp; slowly, reluctantly, painfully she came to the
                conclusion that she had not sufficient grasp of intellect to master all that she saw
                a physician ought to master. She could get through her examinations well enough as
                she has done before&#8212;but could not she said "pass" her own inward examination
                or conscientiously enter upon practice&#8212;she would not add to the already too
                great number of "fumbling physicians". <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="man_ej.00188_large.jpg" type="recto"/>I thought perhaps she was suffering
                from such work &amp; took a morbid view of things, &amp; wrote to her to come home at
                once for a rest at any rate. So she is now with us, &amp; I said we would not speak
                of it to any one till she was rested, &amp; we had talked it well over. For I fully
                believe myself, that though not brilliantly gifted, her intellect is fully up to the
                average &amp; a
                character a good deal beyond&#8212;that her devotedness &amp; sympathy would in the
                end after long years of careful study make her an admirable physician. But I find
                her conviction is so strong &amp; so conscientious, so against <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="man_ej.00053_large.jpg" type="verso"/>her own wishes&#8212;for she loves
                both the studies &amp; the practice better than ever &amp; is bitterly disappointed,&#8212;
                that no more was to be said. And as regards my own feelings (though I am sorry for
                her sorrow, &amp; sorry too that the excellent work I think she would do should go
                undone) yet the profession was like a great man that swallowed her up from me. I had
                seen nothing of her for two years &amp; should not for three or four more, &amp; I
                    shrank from the
                arduousness of the life for her. And I have no doubt but that she will find scope <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003r" facs="man_ej.00054_large.jpg" type="recto"/>in other ways for
                her fine
                qualities. So I am well content&#8212;&amp; it is such a comfort &amp; delight to
                have her at home with us once more. And the training she has is a splendid
                preparation for life generally.&#8212;Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> has been working double tides to finish
                a picture he is going to send into the Academy on Tuesday; but whether it will get
                hung or no is always a toss up for young artists. One of our Philadelphia friends
                M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Murry Gibson has been over here &amp; gives Herby
                a small commission too. William Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/> spent good Friday afternoon with us; was
                very pleased with Herby's work. And then we had a long jolly talk about you dear
                Friend&#8212;you have no truer <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="man_ej.00189_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>appreciator &amp; friend than he I find he stands fast. Indeed
                your friends &amp; lovers in England are none of them half hearted,&#8212;but then
                perhaps it is not possible to be so toward you. We find Hampstead so pleasant &amp;
                healthful that we are looking out for a house to settle down in&#8212;and then dear
                friend if only you will come! it is not so formidable a journey as to Colorado. I
                wonder if you have been lecturing or writing about that.</p>

            <p>I have made the acquaintance of Mr. Buxton Forman<ptr target="n0240"/> whom you know by letter <pb
                    xml:id="leaf004r" facs="man_ej.00190_large.jpg" type="recto"/>&amp; who is a
                very old &amp; dear friend of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> concerning whom
                he has told me some very interesting particulars. Did you ever hear his history? if
                not I will tell it you in my next &amp; you will like him all the more. Rossetti
                thinks that little paragraph about <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium"
                    resp="#nhg">Ruskin's</unclear> admiration
                of your poems which appeared in last weeks Atheneum &amp; has no doubt been sent to
                you, will give a greater impetus to the circulation of your poems here than
                anything that has yet <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="man_ej.00056_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>happened. Indeed every year the soil gets more &amp; more ready
                for the crop.&#8212;In political matters we are faring very <unclear reason="illegible"
                    cert="low" resp="#nnk">badly</unclear> just now. England is fairly besotted by <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nhg">Beaconsfield's</unclear>
                <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">specious</unclear> but <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nhg">rascally</unclear>
                    foreign policy &amp;
                I believe he will have another lease of power. I hope M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Whitman<ptr target="n1046"/> are well&#8212;&amp; Jessie<ptr target="duk.00343_n2"/> &amp;
                Walter? My love to all My thoughts travel daily to America&#8212;it has become a
                part of my life in a very real sense. Love from us all;</p>


            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye Dearest Friend.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="man_ej.00057_large.jpg"
                type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="man_ej.00058_large.jpg"
                type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
