<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00411">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Alfred, Lord Tennyson, 27 April 1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00411</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">174–175</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Alfred, Lord Tennyson, 27 April 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-04-27" xml:id="dat1">April 27, 1872</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Tennyson, Alfred, Lord">Alfred, Lord Tennyson</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-08-01" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-12-10" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1872-04-27" rend="right">April 27, 1872</date>.<ptr target="med.00411_n1"/></dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Mr. Tennyson:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>This morning's paper has a vague sort of an item about your coming to America, or wanting to come, to view the working of our institutions, etc. Is there anything in it? I hope so, for I want more and more to meet you and be with you. Then I should like to give my explanations and comments of America and her shows, affairs, persons, doings, off-hand, as you witness them, and become puzzled, perhaps, dismayed by them. America is at present a vast seething mass of varied material human and other, of the richest, best, worst, and plentiest kind. Wealthy inventive, no limit to food, land, money, work, opportunity, smart and industrious citizens, but (though real and permanently politically organized by birth and acceptance) without fusion or definite heroic identity in form and purpose or organization, which can only come by native schools of great ideas—religion, poets, literature<ptr target="med.00411_n2"/>—and will surely come, even through the measureless crudity of the States in those fields so far, and to-day.</p>
            
            <p>The lesson of Buckle's books<ptr target="med.00411_n3"/> on civilization always seemed to me to be that the preceding main basis and continual <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> of civilization is the eligibility to, and certainty of boundless products for feeding, clothing, and sheltering everybody, infinite comfort, personal and inter-communication and plenty, with mental and ecclesiastical freedom, and that then all the rest, moral and esthetic, will take care of itself. Well, the United States have secured the requisite bases, and must now proceed to build upon them.<ptr target="med.00411_n4"/></p>
            
            <p>I send you by same mail with this, a more neatly printed copy of my "Leaves"; also "Dem. Vistas."</p>
            
            <p>Your letter of last fall<ptr target="med.00411_n5"/> reached me at the time. Have you forgotten that you put a promise in it, to send me your picture when "you could lay hands on a good one?"<ptr target="med.00411_n6"/>
            </p>
                
            <p>I have been in Brooklyn and New York most of the past winter and current spring, visiting my aged dear mother, near eighty. Am now back here at work. Am well and hearty. I have received two letters from you, July 12 and September 22, of last year. This is the second letter I have written to you.<ptr target="med.00411_n7"/> My address is: Solicitor's Office, Treasury, Washington, D. C., United States. Write soon, my friend. Don't forget the picture.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>