<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00660">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Tertio-millenial Anniversary
                    Association at Santa Fe, New Mexico, 20 July 1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00660</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                        <title xml:id="tg">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Iowa City</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Iowa Press</publisher>
                            <date when="2004">2004</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">7</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">69&#8211;71</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt WHitman to the Tertio-millenial Anniversary Association at
                        Santa Fe, New Mexico, 20 July 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-07-20" xml:id="dat1">July 20, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is
                        unknown. Genoways's transcription is derived from a typeset sheet with Whitman's holograph corrections, emendations, and signature, printed in facsimile
                    in the American Art Galleries auction catalog of December 5 and 6, 1934.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName
                        key="Tertio-millenial Anniversary Association at Santa Fe, New Mexico"
                        >Tertio-millenial Anniversary Association at Santa Fe, New Mexico</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-16" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-27" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-12-06" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Camden New Jersey<ptr
                            target="med.00660_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1883-07-20" rend="right">July 20 1883</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>To Messrs: Griffin Martinez Prince, and other gentlemen at Santa
                Fe&#8212;</salute>
                <salute>Dear Sirs:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your kind invitation to visit you and deliver a poem for the 333d Anniversary of Founding Santa Fe has reached me so late, that I have to
                decline, with sincere regret.<ptr target="med.00660_n2"/> But I will say a few words
                off-hand.</p>

            <p>We Americans have yet to really learn our own antecedents, and sort them, to unify
                them. They will be found ampler than has been supposed and in widely different
                sources. Thus far, impressed by New England writers and schoolmasters, we
                tacitly abandon ourselves to the notion that our United States have been fashioned
                from the British Islands only, and essentially form a second England
                only&#8212;which is a great mistake. Many leading traits for our future national
                personality, and some of the best ones, will certainly prove to have
                originated from other than British stock. As it is, the British and German, valuable
                as they are in the concrete, already threaten excess. Or rather, I should say, they
                have certainly <choice>
                    <abbr>reach'd</abbr>
                    <expan>reached</expan>
                </choice> that excess. To-day, something outside of them, and to
                counterbalance them, is seriously needed.</p>

            <p>Thus seething materialistic and business vortices of the United States, in their
                present devouring relations, controlling and belittling everything else, are, in my
                opinion, but a vast and indispensable stage in the new world's development, and are
                certainly to be <choice>
                    <abbr>follow'd</abbr>
                    <expan>followed</expan>
                </choice> by something entirely different&#8212;at least by immense modifications.
                Character, literature, a society worthy the name, are yet to be <choice>
                    <abbr>establish'd</abbr><expan>established</expan></choice>, through a nationality of noblest spiritual, heroic and democratic
                attributes&#8212;not one of which at present definitely exists&#8212;entirely
                different from the past, though unerringly founded on it, and to justify it.</p>

            <p>To that composite American identity of the future, Spanish character will supply some
                of the most needed parts. No stock shows a grander historic
                retrospect&#8212;grander in religiousness and loyalty, or for patriotism,
                courage, decorum, gravity and honor. (It is time to dismiss utterly the
                illusion-compound, half raw-head-and-bloody-bones and
                half Mysteries-of-Udolpho, inherited from the English writers of the
                past 200 years. It is time to realize&#8212;for it is certainly true&#8212;that
                there will not be found any more cruelty, tryanny, superstition, &amp;c., in the
                r&#233;sum&#233; of past Spanish history than in the corresponding r&#233;sum&#233;
                of Anglo-Norman history. Nay, I think there will not be found so
                much.)</p>

            <p>Then another point, relating to American ethnology, past and to come, I will here
                touch upon at a venture. As to our aboriginal or Indian population&#8212;the Aztec
                in the South, and many a tribe in the North and West&#8212;I know it seems to be
                agreed that they must gradually dwindle as time rolls on, and in a few
                generations more leave only a reminiscence, a blank. But I am not at all
                clear about that. As America, from its many far-back sources and current
                supplies, develops, adapts, entwines, faithfully identifies its own&#8212;are
                we to see it cheerfully accepting and using all the contributions of foreign lands
                from the whole outside globe&#8212;and then rejecting the only ones
                distinctively its own&#8212;the autochthonic ones?</p>

            <p>As to the Spanish stock of our Southwest, it is certain to me that we do not begin to
                appreciate the splendor and sterling value of its race element. Who knows but that
                element, like the course of some subterranean river, dipping invisibly for a hundred
                or two years, is now to emerge in broadest flow and permanent action?</p>

            <p>If I might assume to do so, I would like to send you the most cordial,
                heart-felt congratulations of your American fellow-countrymen here. You
                have more friends in the Northern and Atlantic regions than you suppose, and they
                are deeply interested in development of the great Southwestern interior, and in what
                your festival would arouse to public attention.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute rend="right">Very respectfully &amp;c.,</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
