<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00326">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Henry Clapp, Jr. to Walt Whitman, 12 May 1860</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Henry Clapp, Jr.</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>med.00326</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                  <editor>Sculley Bradley</editor>
                  <title xml:id="wwwc">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                     <date when="1953">1953</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">195-96</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Henry Clapp, Jr.</author>
               <title>Henry Clapp, Jr. to Walt Whitman, 12 May 1860</title>
               <date when="1860-05-12">May 12, 1860</date>
               <orgName xml:id="med">Location of original letter manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Clapp Jr., Henry">Henry Clapp, Jr.</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-31">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-16">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener rend="right">
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">New York,</name>
                  <date when="1860-05-12">May 12, 1860.<ptr target="med.00326_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Walt,</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p>The books are duly delivered. The publishers and printers deserve high praise for the superb manner in which they have done their work. For the poet, he shall hear from me next week. Meanwhile I am up to my eyes&#8212;and over my eyes even to blindness&#8212;in the slough of a fearful road to that great castle "success" which looms up in the dim religious distance, and from which white-winged angels, peopling every turret, beckon me with many colored banners. In plainer English I am fighting like a thousand Humans to establish the Saturday Press, and have for my almost only encouragement the cheering words of warm and appreciating friends who alas (as in such cases made and provided) have nothing but words to give, and also the printer will not be paid in words though they are "like apples of gold in pictures of silver." As for you, success is certain. It is written all over the book. There is an aroma about it that goes right to the soul.</p>  
            <p>What I can do for it, in the way of bringing it before the public, over and over again, I shall do, and do thoroughly&#8212;if the S.P. is kept alive another month. We have more literary influence than any other paper in the land, and as your poems are not new to me, I can say it will all be used for the book&#8212;in the interest of poetry.</p>
            <p>My brother George will deliver this. He is of the right stamp.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>In haste</salute>
               <signed>Henry Clapp.<ptr target="med.00326_n2"/>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
