<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mhs.00004">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Thomas Jefferson Whitman, 15 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>mhs.00004</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">93-95</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Thomas Jefferson Whitman, 15 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-15">May 15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="mhs">Missouri Historical Society</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-21">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Near Lancaster Ky<ptr target="mhs.00004_n2"/>
                  </name>
                  <lb/>
                  <date when="1863-05-15">May 15th 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother Jeff,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I believe I last wrote home from Lowell, but a fellow has to change about so often in this country, its hard work to remember where he was two days ago.</p>
            <p>After staying at Lowell a couple of days we were ordered to pack up and move again, so we started back on the same road we went out on, and encamped about a mile from this place. After stopping there two days, our Regt was ordered down to this Villiage to do Provost duty in the Town. Lancaster is a small one horse specimen of a southren Villiage, about 32 miles from Lexington, in the central part of the state and 16 or 18 miles from any railroad communication. The country about here is splendid. the fruit trees are just now in full bloom  the weather is fine,  we are liveing first rate  the men are all in good health, and we are haveing a good time generaly. Our Regt is now encamped on the outskirts of the Town in a nice shady spot all alone by ourselvs, the rest of our Brigade and the First Brigade of our Division being encamped about a mile out of Town. We have everything comfortable here, but I think I already see signs of moveing, and it wont be many days before we will have to pull up stakes and be off. We have been very much disapointed in the result of the fighting on the Rappahannock,<ptr target="mhs.00004_n3"/>  we had such favorable news from there at first, and Hooker managed things so nicely in crossing the river, and getting a good position, that I about made up my mind, that notwithstanding the bad luck, that has always attended the movements of the Potomac Army, it was about to do a big thing and I was almost sorry I wasent there to have a hand in. The account of the takeing of Richmond too was firmly believed here, as Gen Sturgis<ptr target="mhs.00004_n4"/>recd. a Tel Dix<ptr target="mhs.00004_n5"/> (said to be from Gen Burnside<ptr target="mhs.00004_n6"/>) saying that Gen Dix had advanced by way of Petersburg and that Richmond was certainly in our posession,  A few hours after the dispatch was recd, there came another from the same source confirming the first, and although I had not believed the news at first, I finaly began to think there must be some truth in it. And then to find out that we had not only not, taken Richmond, but that Hooker had been obliged to recross the river, was a terrible let down I can tell you. Still I have faith in Hooker and believe he will yet do something big, and takeing into account the many disadvantges he had to contend with, (the storm and the devilish cowardice of the Dutchman of the 11th Corps<ptr target="mhs.00004_n7"/>) I dont know as any other man could have done better than he. One thing I think is plain, in crossing the river and getting in the rear of Lee's army in the manner he did, Hooker showed fine generalship and altogather, I think more of him than I did before the fight.</p>
            <p>Well Jeff how are you all getting along at home. I dont hear from you very often, not as often as I should like to. I hope Mother and Mattie and Sis and all the rest of you are well. Walt says that Mother is still troubled sometimes, with the Rheumatism,  does she take sulphor baths  Walt said he was going to make arrangements for her to do so. Why not have a bath rigged up in her room,  it would not cost much, and would save the journey down to Perceys. Andrew, Walt says is working in the Navy Yard, so I suppose he must be better.<ptr target="mhs.00004_n8"/>
            </p>
            <p>I hear from Walt quite often,  he seems to be getting along very well. Have you heard from Hannah lately. when you get a letter from her, send it on so that I can see it. There has been nothing done in regard to consolidating our Regt. yet. I think likely they will wait untill the draft goes into opperation and then fill us up with conscripts.</p>
            <p>Direct your letters Department of Ohio and no matter where the Regt may be the letters will come all right. Good bye Jeff  Much love to Mother, Mattie, Hattie, and all</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>G. W. Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
