<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00193">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 11 September 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00193</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">241-242</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 11 September 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-09-11">September 11, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-13">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-10">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1864-09-11">September 11 1864<ptr target="nyp.00193_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have nothing of consequence to write, but I thought I would send you a few lines anyhow. I have just written Nelly a letter, &amp; send to Little Compton&#8212;We are full of politics here, the dispute runs high &amp; hot everywhere&#8212;I think the Republicans are going to make a stout fight after all, as there is confusion in the opposition camp&#8212;the result of course I do not pretend to foretell&#8212;</p>
            <p>My health is quite re-established, yet not exactly the same unconscious state of health as formerly&#8212;The book is still unprinted&#8212;Our family are all well as usual&#8212;I go two or three times a week among the soldiers in hospital here&#8212;</p>
            <p>I go out quite regularly, sometimes out on the bay, or to Coney Island&#8212;&amp; occasionally a tour through New York life, as of old&#8212;last night I was with some of my friends of Fred Gray association,<ptr target="nyp.00193_n2"/> till late wandering the east side of the City&#8212;first in the lager bier saloons &amp; then elsewhere&#8212;one crowded, low, most degraded place we went, a poor blear-eyed girl bringing beer. I saw her with a McClellan medal on her breast&#8212;I called her &amp; asked her if the other girls there were for McClellan<ptr target="nyp.00193_n3"/> too&#8212;she said yes every one of them, &amp; that they wouldn't tolerate a girl in the place who was not, &amp; the fellows were too&#8212;(there must have been twenty girls, sad sad ruins)&#8212;it was one of those places where the air is full of the scent of low thievery, druggies, foul play, &amp; prostitution gangrened&#8212;</p>
            <p>I don't know what move I shall make, but something soon, as it is not satisfactory any more in New York &amp; Brooklyn&#8212;I should think nine tenths, of all classes, are copperheads here, I never heard before such things as I hear now whenever I go out&#8212;then it seems tame &amp; indeed unreal here, life as carried on &amp; as I come in contact with it &amp; receive its influences&#8212;</p>
            <p>How is Ashton? &amp; is he there again?<ptr target="nyp.00193_n4"/> I got a letter from Charley Eldridge yesterday&#8212;I suppose he is now in Boston&#8212;My dear friend, I often often think of you, &amp; count on our being together again, may be quite soon&#8212;meantime good bye &amp; God bless you &amp; I send you my best best love&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>We are having a sloppy rainy dark Sunday here to-day&#8212;Lewis Brown (that was in ward K Armory Square) is a clerk in the Provost Marshall's office, cor 18th &amp; I sts<ptr target="nyp.00193_n5"/>&#8212;I got a letter from him the other day&#8212;perhaps you may see him some time&#8212;I am going off for a couple of weeks soon, to Burlington, Vt.<ptr target="nyp.00193_n6"/>&#8212;O how the rain is pouring down as I write&#8212;at the other window sits my mother reading the Sunday Herald&#8212;quiet &amp; pleasant &amp; soothing&#8212;only us two home to-day&#8212;not a word spoken in a long time&#8212;</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
