<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00137">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Charles S. Kingsley to Walt Whitman, 21 March 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Charles S. Kingsley</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00137</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">153</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles S. Kingsley</author>
               <title>Charles S. Kingsley to Walt Whitman, 21 March 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-03-21">March 21, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Kingsley, Charles S.">Charles S. Kingsley</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-09-04">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="nyp.00137_n100"/> scribble a few words to you that you may know I received your letter and that I delivered the enclosed one to Gray<ptr target="nyp.00137_n2"/> (not knowing where to find Bloom)<ptr target="nyp.00137_n3"/> on Saturday night. Rather, I left it for him, at his house. I read your letter yesterday (Sunday) at Freds. A Doctor Phillips of the army, a great friend of Charlie Russells,<ptr target="nyp.00137_n4"/> arrived last night and called upon me. We meet at Freds to day at two O.C[lock] and I suppose we will have a big time. I saw Ben Knower<ptr target="nyp.00137_n5"/> walking on Fifth Avenue yesterday escorting his pretty sister. Freitsh<ptr target="nyp.00137_n6"/> sends you his compliments, respects Etc. Etc. Fred and Bloom are both in excellent condition. Fred is now on Wool's<ptr target="nyp.00137_n7"/> staff and is just back from a tour of inspection among the forts down east, including Portland, Portsmouth, Boston, Newport, New London Etc. Etc., firing off all the guns to test their effectiveness Etc. But to appreciate the history of this tour of inspection you should hear it from Fred your self. It is very funny&#8212;  When last I saw Bloom, ten days or so ago he was just getting over a catarrah of the <gap reason="illegible"/>. Poor Bloom, he didn't smoke, nor drink, and I presume he was very miserable. As I write a pugilistic duo, in the alley beyond me, have just ended an "affaire d'honneur." The smaller of two wicked, naughty boys, is weeping and wiping a bloody nose on the ragged sleeve of his jacket. The victorious youth is about to throw a small quantity of mud at the conquered one, and that he may not soil his fingers therewith he has picked up a piece of barrell hoop upon the end of which he has scraped up the quantum suf. He does not throw with great precision for the conquered person after dodging the first shower from the victors improvised catapult, runs rapidly into his mothers room in the tenement house opposite and finds therein a shelter from the foe. I shall write a long letter one of these fine days Walt and will give you all the news of interest that I can glean.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Until then, may all be secure with you, Walt and believe me,</salute>
               <salute>Truly Yours</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
