<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00148">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Caleb H. Babbitt to Walt Whitman, 18 October 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Caleb H. Babbitt</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00148</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">105-106</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Caleb H. Babbitt</author>
               <title>Caleb H. Babbitt to Walt Whitman, 18 October 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-18">October 18, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Babbitt, Caleb H.">Caleb H. Babbitt</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-06">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-13">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Your welcom letter of the 27th I<ptr target="nyp.00148_n100"/> recd Tuesday but did not feel in a writing moode, so I have delayed it until now. I do not know but you think me rather neglectful in my writing to you but if you knew the pain that I have in my head, the whole of the time you would not think hard of me.</p>
            <p>Walt&#8212;I am sorry that I am as feeble, and that my friends and likewise my Doctor think that I never shall be able to join my Regt, it is hard for me to gaze or to think of the future, dark clouds seem to be lying in my pathway and I can not seem to remove them nor hide them from my mind, I have tried to look on the bright side of the picture, but Walt&#8212;how can I look on the bright side when they are both <hi rend="italic">dark</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Walt&#8212;I have been verry low since I have been at home, and all that has saved me is good nursing and some one to cheer me (which two things I have had) and now and then a letter from you. I must tell you who I have had to cheer and nurse me, besides my parents and sisters: is a young Lady whom I think the world of, yes : might as well tell you, that it is one I love. I feel she has saved me, in the worst of my sickness she hardly left my room how often have I thought what would become of me if it were not for her.</p>
            <p>Tuesday, she whent to V[ermon]t on a visit and will not be at home for several weeks, so I want you to write to her for Walt&#8212;she is one of the best Ladies in the world. I wish you could see her for I know you would like her and I know you will think a great deal of her for her taking such care of me promise me you will write to her, for it used to make her happy to read one of your letters to me  her address is Nellie F. Clark West Hartford Vt.</p>
            <p>I will now close hoping to hear from you soon I am yours with love and respect</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
