<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00178">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Jesse Mullery to Walt Whitman, 3 May 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Jesse Mullery</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00178</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">165</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Jesse Mullery</author>
               <title>Jesse Mullery to Walt Whitman, 3 May 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-05-03">May 3, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Mullery, Jesse">Jesse Mullery</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="20010-04-06">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-14">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-18">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Your welcome epistle of the 24th of April came to hand this morning and found me in good health and as usual very glad to hear from you.<ptr target="nyp.00178_n100"/> My Brothers James &amp; Joseph are both well and in the Regt and wish me to return thanks for your kind remembrance of them</p>
            <p>I received a letter from you written at Brooklyn bearing date of the 13th of April we marched from Burksville the following day. I have not had a chance to answer it. We finished our march to this place last Thursday afternoon and as soon as we halted my Regiment were ordered on Picket where we remained three days, consequently I could not write; and since we came in from picket we have been under marching orders. By the way we are waiting transportation towards Petersburgh. Our train started yesterday morning and about tomorrow we will start. We wait now for the Cars to return which took the 2nd Brigade of the Division in that direction on Monday. The soldiers have not emerged from the gloom which was cast over their minds on hearing of the death of our Beloved President. My heart is to full to write anything about him, for I cannot tell how well he was liked by the Soldiers who fought for the Flag under him. I am pained to say that many of my company secretly rejoiced when we received the news of the assasination. But none dared to cheer although if some Rebel had proposed it there were plenty ready to join in. All I want is to see the assassin dealt with if caught in a proper manner.</p>
            <p>I hope I shall soon have the pleasure of seeing you in Washington when I will tell you a great many things that I cannot write. Look out for me when you hear the 1st Div. of the 6th corps coming to Washington.</p>
            <p>We are kept very close now on account of the Orders for going back. Otherwise I would try to visit the Prison Camp and also the burying ground. There are a large number of my comrades buried there and I should like to have the satisfaction of seeing their graves.</p>
            <p>Should you see Miss Howard please remember me to her.<ptr target="nyp.00178_n2"/> Hoping to see you soon I will close for the present. Please write me before unless you hear of the Corps coming home. Yours truly.</p>
            <closer rend="right"/>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
