<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00132">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walter Whitman, Sr., Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, Andrew Jackson Whitman, George Washington Whitman, Hannah Louisa Whitman, and Edward Whitman, 27 March 1848</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00132</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">8-10</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walter Whitman, Sr., Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, Andrew Jackson Whitman, George Washington Whitman, Hannah Louisa Whitman, and Edward Whitman, 27 March 1848</title>
               <date when="1848-03-27">March 27, 1848</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walter Sr.">Walter Whitman, Sr.</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Andrew Jackson">Andrew Jackson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Hannah Louisa">Hannah Louisa Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Edward">Edward Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
               <opener>
                  <dateline rend="right">
                     <name type="place">New Orleans</name>
                     <date when="1848-03-27">March 27, 1848</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>To day we received the first letter from you, and glad enough we were to get it too. The passage that gave me, and Walter too, the most pleasure was the one that said you were well, and that all the rest were well also. You say the weather is very cold there, here it is just the other way, that is it is pretty warm. I have now begun to wear the summer clothes sister Hannah made me which I find very comfortble.</p>
               <p>It would have made you laugh to see me come home from the post office this morning with your letter. Eddy never was so glad when New Year's came, as I was to get your letter</p>
               <p>You must write to us oftener than you have at least twice a month, which we are going to do</p>
               <p>You need not be alarmed about the yellow fever<ptr target="nyp.00132_n1"/> as that gentleman will (the folks think) not visit this place this summer. The reason they give for that is this. It does not come but once in three or four years, and last season it was very hard and killed a great many persons (I mean it does not come but once in three or four years in such a shape). Besides it is a great humbug, most every one in our office has had (some of them have had it twice) and got well. It is caused mostly (I think all of it) by the habits of the people, they never meet a freind but you have to go drink and such loose habits.</p>
               <p>You know that Walter is averse to such habits, so you need not be afraid of our taking it<ptr target="nyp.00132_n2"/>
               </p>
               <p>Yesterday we were to have a balloon ascension, but just as it was ready to go up the balloon bursted so it did not go up, this is the third time she (it was a lady that was to go up in it) has tried it and each time failed</p>
               <p>We are very nicely situated in our new place;&#8212;just "around the corner" is a very fine public park, which we take a walk in every night<ptr target="nyp.00132_n3"/>
               </p>
               <p>I believe I told you in my last letter that I was also at work at the "Crescent" office at five dollars a week, and I have the exchange papers for which I get twenty five cents per hundred, in a few weeks I expect to get two dollars a week for them</p>
               <p>If you do not get the paper (the "Crescent") regular you must send Andrew or George down to the Eagle office for it, I always see that two copys go every morning. My work is good and light. I have such a part of the mail (and I can do it most over night) and then I have nothing to do for the rest of the day (I generally get through with it about two o'clock) but stay in the office.</p>
               <p>We have (I think) got along very well for such a long journey, not a single accident occurred on the way</p>
               <p>Dear Father, I hope you are getting along good with your work &amp;c. Mother says it is cold so you can't work  here it is warm enough. In building houses here they do not do as they do in New York. Here they dig a hole in the ground some two feet deep and about the same width, and in length as far as the wall is to go, (they can not dig cellars here like in the north, you don't dig in the ground more than two feet before it is filled with water.) This trench they cover the bottom with boards (the ground is mostly made of quick-sand) and then build the wall on it. They cannot mak[e] good brick here, so they have to come from a distance. Carpenters wages are very high here, some forty to fifty dollars a month and found</p>
               <p>I will write a letter to you pretty soon, but in this one I must not forget George and Andrews</p>
               <p>Dear brothers, I should like to see you very much indeed but I suppose I cannot, you must make Mother or Hannah write to us as often as they can. Theres is nothing, I beleive, there is not any thing here you would like to hear from or of</p>
               <p>Dear Sister,<ptr target="nyp.00132_n4"/> I should like to see you very much indeed but I suppose you would like to hear about the ladies in N. O. They are something like the "critters" in N. Y. except they were one or two more "flonces" and live more in the open air &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</p>
               <p>to Eddy  you must got to school and learn to read and write and then you must send letters to me, besides you must be a good boy &amp;c</p>
               <p>And now Dear Mother I must bid you good bye for a little while but will write to you again shortly</p>
               <p>We are both very well and the warm air argrees with Walter very much</p>
               <p>I have had a little attack of the disentery but I am very very well now, in fact I have not been sick much at all</p>
               <p>Dear Mother good bye</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>your son Jefferson Whitman</signed>
               </closer>
            
            <postscript>
               <p>My best respects to the rest of the family<ptr target="nyp.00132_n5"/>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
