<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00230">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Lizzie H. Smith to Walt Whitman, 17 September 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Lizzie H. Smith</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00230</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Lizzie H. Smith</author>
               <title>Lizzie H. Smith to Walt Whitman, 17 September 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-09-17">September 17, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Berg Collection at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Smith, Lizzie H.">Lizzie H. Smith</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="nyp.00224.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Watersboro</name>
                  <date when="1864-09-17">Sept 17th</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Mr Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I take the liberty of addressing you at the request of my cousin Milton S. Roberts, at whose home I am making a brief visit. He would not have delayed writing until this late hour, but he has not been well &amp; did not feel in the mood of writing, &amp; and under such circumstances did not think his letters would be very interesting. He has spoken a great many times to his friends how very very kind you were to him, &amp; I assure you Mr. Whitman those kind attentions will never be forgotten. I hope that you may long be spared to do good among our sick &amp; wounded soldiers, who indeed must feel very grateful to meet <pb facs="nyp.00224.002.jpg" type="verso"/>with such a friend as my cousin represents yourself to be. Kind words which cost nothing will often cheer their drooping spirits &amp; as it sure give them new life and courage. My cousin seems to be gaining slowly, &amp; his friends does not think him strong enough to return for two or three weeks. He would be likely to gain strength much faster at home thou he could in Washington</p>
            <p>He wished me to write you, if you would not be kind eough to see Dr Bliss in regards to his furlough being extended a several weeks longer, by doing this you will confer a great favor, he would have been in Washington at the time his furlough expired if he had been able, &amp; as it was he was very anxious to go, but his friends did not deem it prudent. Please write him as soon as you can make it conveneient what Dr Bliss says. Milton thinks that by the time he receives a letter from you that he will be able to answer it. Mr. Whitman we all thank you more <pb facs="nyp.00224.003.jpg" type="recto"/>than words can express for your kindness to Milton.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>Lizzie H. Smith</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Please direct Milton S. Roberts to Waterboro home.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
