<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00196">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 6 January 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00196</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">246-248</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 6 January 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-01-06">January 6, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-01">proofread</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-10">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn </name>
                  <date when="1865-01-06">January 6 1865<ptr target="nyp.00196_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your welcome letter of December 30 came safe. I have written &amp; sent my application to Mr Otto,<ptr target="nyp.00196_n2"/> &amp; also a few lines to Mr Ashton, with a copy of it.<ptr target="nyp.00196_n3"/> I am most desirous to get the appointment, as enclosing, with the rest of the points, my attentions to the soldiers &amp; to my poems, as you intimate.</p>
            <p>It may be Drum-Taps may come out this winter, yet, (in the way I have mentioned in times past.) It is in a state to put right through, a perfect copy being ready for the printers&#8212;I feel at last, &amp; for the first time without any demur, that I am satisfied with it&#8212;content to have it go to the world verbatim &amp; punctuation. It is in my opinion superior to Leaves of Grass&#8212;certainly more perfect as a work of art, being adjusted in all its proportions, &amp; its passion having the indispensable merit that though to the ordinary reader let loose with wildest abandon, the true artist can see it is yet under control. But I am perhaps mainly satisfied with Drum-Taps because it delivers my ambition of the task that has haunted me, namely, to express in a poem (&amp; in the way I like, which is not at all by directly stating it) the pending action of this <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Land we swim in</hi>, with all their large conflicting fluctuations of despair &amp; hope, the shiftings, masses, &amp; the whirl &amp; deafening din, (yet over all, as by invisible hand, a definite purport &amp; idea)&#8212;with the unprecedented anguish of wounded &amp; suffering, the beautiful young men, in wholesale death &amp; agony, everything sometimes as if in blood color, &amp; dripping blood. The book is therefore unprecedently sad, (as these days are, are they not?)&#8212;but it also has the blast of the trumpet, &amp; the drum pounds &amp; whirrs in it, &amp; then an undertone of sweetest comradeship &amp; human love, threading its steady thread inside the chaos, &amp; heard at every lull &amp; interstice thereof&#8212;truly also it has clear notes of faith &amp; triumph.</p>
            <p>Drum Taps has none of the perturbations of Leaves of Grass. I am satisfied with Leaves of Grass (by far the most of it) as expressing what was intended, namely, to express by sharp-cut self assertion, <hi rend="italic">One's-Self</hi> &amp; also, or may be still more, to map out, to throw together for American use, a gigantic embryo or skeleton of Personality, fit for the West, for native models&#8212;but there are a few things I shall carefully eliminate in the next issue, &amp; a few more I shall considerably change.<ptr target="nyp.00196_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>I see I have said I consider Drum-Taps superior to Leaves of Grass. I probably mean as a piece of wit, &amp; from the more simple &amp; winning nature of the subject, &amp; also because I have in it only succeeded to my satisfaction in removing all superfluity from it, verbal superfluity I mean. I delight to make a poem where I feel clear that not a word but is indispensable part thereof &amp; of my meaning.</p>
            <p>Still Leaves of Grass is dear to me, always dearest to me, as my first born, as daughter of my life's first hopes, doubts, &amp; the putting in form of those days' efforts &amp; aspirations&#8212;true, I see now, with some things in it I should not put in if I were to write now, but yet I shall certainly let them stand, even if but for proofs of phases passed away&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother &amp; all home are well as usual. Not a word for over three months from my brother George<ptr target="nyp.00196_n5"/>&#8212;the probabilities are most gloomy. I see the Howells<ptr target="nyp.00196_n6"/> now &amp; then. I am well, but need to leave here&#8212;need a change. If you see Miss Howard tell her Jesse Mullery<ptr target="nyp.00196_n7"/> has been to see me&#8212;came yesterday &amp; has just left this forenoon. He talked of nothing but her. His life is saved, &amp; he will have tolerably good strength &amp; health, at least for present. His address is Ward <ptr target="nyp.00196_n8"/>, Centre st Hospital, Newark New Jersey. I was up at Mrs Price's the other night. She is better this winter. Mrs Paulina Wright Davis7 is stopping with her this winter. I have sent a paper with sketch of Hospital Visits, to Dr Wm F Channing.<ptr target="nyp.00196_n9"/> I cannot forgive myself for not acknowledging his assistance for the Hospitals, by letter at the time. I send you another paper also, as you might like it. I take it by a line in your letter that Charles Eldridge has not gone to Boston.<ptr target="nyp.00196_n10"/> I have been reading the strange articles from the Richmond press.<ptr target="nyp.00196_n11"/> A thousand Satans baffled, with terror, hatred, malignant squirming, appear in every paragraph. Little California is playing around me as I finish, &amp; has been for half an hour. Love to dear Nelly &amp; Jeannie &amp; all.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
