<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00444">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 30 May
                    [1882]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nyp.00444</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                        <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">286&#8211;288</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor, 30 May [1882]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1882-05-30" xml:id="dat1">May 30, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Series III</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="nyp">The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and
                        American Literature, New York Public Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-04-25" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-14" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-10-24" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-10-03" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Camden<ptr target="nyp.00444_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1882-05-30">Tuesday Evening</date>
                    <date when="1882-05-30">May 30&#8212;</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>The whole hinge of the Chadwick letter<ptr target="nyp.00444_n2"/>&#8212;involving
                you and yours, with me, &#38; including the question of veracity&#8212;seems to me
                to be essentially <hi rend="italic">What are the relations of Emerson to W W</hi>?
                As permanently left by <hi rend="italic">the sum</hi> of the transactions and
                judgments of twenty-five years&#8212;(yours of 29th <choice><orig>recd</orig><reg>received</reg></choice>)&#8212;(just the same as
                the Bible means its whole &#38; final spirit, not one or two picked out verses or
                texts)&#8212;confirmed by a most deliberate and emphatic act of the last year of his
                <choice>
                    <orig>E's</orig>
                    <reg>Emerson's</reg>
                </choice> life&#8212;seems to me the mood of your reply to the Chadwick letter may well be
                    <hi rend="italic">different</hi> from the other (which the more I read it, the
                more it unfolds&#8212;it is such a piece of <hi rend="italic">literary
                    work</hi>)<ptr target="nyp.00444_n3"/>&#8212;I see clearly that the question
                above is more involved than that of veracity you speak of&#8212;see the other page I
                send&#8212;</p>
            <p>Personal information&#8212;perhaps nothing but what you knew already&#8212;</p>
            <p>&#9758; I suppose you know that the <hi rend="italic">Life of
                Emerson</hi>&#8212;(&#38; a very good one I guess)&#8212;published nearly a year ago
                by Osgood&#8212;<hi rend="italic">all with the sanction &#38; revision of the family
                    &#38; of <choice>
                        <orig>E.</orig>
                        <reg>Emerson</reg>
                    </choice> himself</hi><ptr target="nyp.00444_n4"/>&#8212;gives <hi rend="italic">in full the letter
                    of 1856 you quote</hi>&#8212;thus confirming &#38; sanctioning it&#8212;See said
                    <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>.<ptr target="nyp.00444_n5"/></p>
            <p>Seems to me would be good to bring in quite verbatim&#8212;it is certainly
                <hi rend="italic">true</hi>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Emerson had much more of a personal friendship for W W than has been generally known;
                making a determined visit to Brooklyn soon after the appearance of Leaves of Grass,
                twenty five years ago, walking out to the little cottage in the suburbs, several
                miles from the ferry where Mr W then lived. From that time regularly for years
                afterwards whenever he came to New York he appointed a meeting, and they two
                generally dined together and spent some hours.<ptr target="nyp.00444_n6"/> When Mr
                Whitman was in Boston in 1860 Emerson was his frequent &#38; cordial visitor. As
                time elapsed, though officious persons intervened, and there was a lull of some
                years, I doubt if it could be said that Ralph Waldo Emerson's affections (and few
                know how deeply he could love!) ever went out more warmly to any one, and remained
                more fixed, under the circumstances, than toward Walt Whitman.</p>
            <p>Mr Chadwick evidently thinks that if the author of Leaves of Grass had any case to
                state, that walk on the common in 1860 was his time. But it is well known to his
                intimate friends that Walt Whitman, who has the most simplicity and good nature of
                any man alive, is also the haughtiest, the most disdainful at those periods when
                expected to talk loudest and best, and when he probably could do so, is apt to
                remain perfectly silent. The main reason certainly was, curious as it may seem, that
                Emerson's objections, on that famous walk, did not at all touch Whitman's principle
                of treatment which was a moral one, or rather it involved the verteber of all
                morals. I have heard the author of Leaves of Grass say that what he sought to do in
                "Children of Adam" seemed all the more necessary after that [conversation?]. Though
                Emerson's points were of the highest and keenest order, they sprang exclusively from
                conventional and what may be called the usual technical literary considerations. I
                know from what he has told me that Whitman himself had long dwelt on these very
                points in his own mind&#8212;that he was anxious to hear the utmost that could be
                brought forward in their behalf. And now when he heard what the best critic of the
                age so brought forward, and his inmost soul and brain remained altogether untouched,
                his final resolution was taken, and he has never changed from that hour.</p>
            <p>Then to clench the whole matter of the relations between these two men, I doubt
                whether there is any thing more affecting or emphatic in <choice>
                    <sic>Emersons</sic>
                    <corr>Emerson's</corr>
                </choice> whole
                career&#8212;a sort of last coruscation in the evening twilight of it&#8212;than his
                driving over to Frank Sanborn's in Concord, Sept 1881, to deliberately pay
                "respects" for which he had obligated himself twenty five years before.<ptr
                    target="nyp.00444_n7"/> Nor was the unusual compliment of the hospitable but
                formal dinner made the next day for Walt Whitman, by Mr and Mrs Emerson, without
                marked significance. It was a beautiful autumn Sunday. And if that afternoon, with
                its occurrences there in his own mansion, surrounded by all his family, wife, son,
                daughters, son-in-law, nearest relatives, and two or three very near
                friends&#8212;some fourteen or fifteen in all&#8212;if that does not mean how
                Emerson, by this simple yet almost solemn rite, wished, before he departed, to
                reiterate and finally seal his verdict of 1856, then there is no significance in
                human life or its emotions or<ptr target="nyp.00444_n8"/>&#8212;</p>
           
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
