<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00156">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William E. Vandemark to Walt Whitman, 29 December 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>William E. Vandemark</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00156</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">207-208</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>William E. Vandemark</author>
               <title>William E. Vandemark to Walt Whitman, 29 December 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-12-29">December 29, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Vandemark, William E.">William E. Vandemark</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-03">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-06">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-14">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear father</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>to day i<ptr target="nyp.00156_n100"/> received a letter from yo and i was glad to here from yo i am not very well and have not ben for some time i have pain in my head and breast i think the clorform that i have taken is the caus of it my hip is very painful to day i was exasamend i think that i will go before the board in a day or two i may get my discharge i have hurd that my ridgement is going home for the winter to recruit thair is only 17 men left inny more for duty father i long to see yo and have a talk with yo i will try and get a pas to go to Washington to see yo after i have ben before the board for another exsamanation</p>
            <p>father i hope yo had a good time a Crismis &amp; i hope yo en Joyed yiour Self wat a blessed privelge it is to be so that we can en Joy the privelage wile some are on beds of sickness and have ben cut off in their youth&#8212;</p>
            <p>dear father i wish yo a happy new yrs and a good time i will try and get a pas to come and see yo next friday i hante sure of getting one yet but i will try to get one&#8212;i like this place very well here i will never go to new york agin on a trans bus for they use men thair worse than dogs i would have done better if i had staid in washington  they know how to use men thair and how to tak cair of them wen i see yo i will tel yo all</p>
            <p>I think the war is nearly ended now I hope it is at all events, for thair has been men enuf lost on both sides in one war how many widows and orphans it has caused all ready&#8212;i wish that i could get detailed in washington at some thing that i coud do i woud be very glad and would try to do my duty&#8212;father let me Know how things gets a long in army squair tel crain that hante had answer from the letter that i sent him and i would like to here from him i have seen hathford wen i was home and had a talk with him he is all rite now</p>
            <p>father i will close good by dear father and friend from a friend William E Vandermark to a dear friend Walt Whitman good by</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
