<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00272">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor (for
                    Moncure D. Conway), [10 November 1867]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nyp.00272</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">347–349</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to William D. O'Connor (for Moncure D. Conway), [10 November
                        1867]</title>
                    <date cert="low" when="1867-11-10" xml:id="dat1">November 10, 1867</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="nyp">The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and
                        American Literature, New York Public Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Conway, Moncure D.">Moncure D. Conway</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2010-12-17" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-04" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <salute>My dear Conway:</salute><ptr target="nyp.00272_n1"/>
            </opener>

            <p>Mr. Whitman has shown me your letter of October 12, with news of Mr. Hotten's
                proposed London print of Leaves of Grass or selection therfrom, edited by Mr.
                Rosetti, with an Introductory Essay or preface, by Mr. R.</p>

            <p>Now, in view of the latter, if I may take the liberty, I wish to speak of two or
                three points, or rather, enforce them—for no doubt they will, to a certain
                extent, have occurred to Mr. Rosetti. But as I have made Leaves of Grass &amp; their
                author my study for the last seven years, &amp; have had some fortuitous advantages,
                perhaps Mr. Rosetti would not consider it intrusive in me, that I send this letter,
                which I wish you to hand him.</p>

            <p>Considering the attitude of the public, and their average calibre, and also
                considering the general bearing of most of the criticisms on Mr. Whitman's poetry, I
                would suggest the expediency, in any forthcoming, friendly examination of his genius
                &amp; writings, of dwelling pretty strongly on the following points, &amp; making
                them unmistakably appear: <list>
                    <item>1st—That personally the author of Leaves of Grass is in no sense or
                        sort whatever the "rough," the "eccentric," "vagabond" or queer person, that
                        the commentators, (always bound for the intensest possible sensational
                        statement,) persist in making him. He has moved, &amp; moves still, along
                        the path of his life's happenings &amp; fortunes, as they befall or have
                        befallen him, with entire serenity &amp; decorum, never defiant even to the
                        conventions, always bodily sweet &amp; fresh, dressed plainly &amp; cleanly,
                        a gait &amp; demeanor of antique simplicity, cheerful &amp; smiling,
                        performing carefully all his domestic, social, &amp; municipal obligations,
                        his demonstrative nature toned very low, but eloquent enough of eye,
                        posture, &amp; expression, though using only moderate words; and offering to
                        the world, in himself, an American Personality, &amp; real Democratic
                        Presence, that not only the best old Hindu, Greek, and Roman worthies would
                        at once have responded to, but which the most cultured European, from court
                        or academy, would likewise, on meeting to-day, see &amp; own without demur.
                        All really refined persons, and the women more than the men, take to Walt
                        Whitman. The most delicate &amp; even conventional lady only needs to know
                        him to love him.<ptr target="nyp.00272_n4"/>
                    </item>

                    <item>2.<ptr target="nyp.00272_n5"/> Critically, a significant, if not the most
                        significant, fact about Leaves of Grass, is, that the genesis &amp;
                        fashioning of them have evidently not been for literary purposes, merely or
                        mainly. Neither in mass nor detail have their pages been tried by the <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> of current literary or esthetic
                        standards. Instead of that, the Book is the product of the largest universal
                        law &amp; play of things, &amp; of that sense of kosmical beauty, of which
                        even literature is but a fraction. This is probably the clue to the
                        explanation of the puzzle of the widely-vexatious formal &amp; esthetic
                        argument involved in Leaves of Grass.</item>

                    <item>3. The idea, however, which is this man's highest contribution, and which,
                        compared even with the vastness of Biblical &amp; Homeric poetry, still
                        looms &amp; towers—as, athwart his fellow-giants of the Himalayas, the
                        dim head of Kunchainjunga rises over the rest—is the idea of Totality,
                        of the All-successful, final certainties of each individual man, as well as
                        of the world he inhabits. Joyousness, out of such sure ultimate happiness
                        &amp; triumph, rings throughout his verse. He holds the solution of each
                        &amp; every problem—the spell, giving full satisfaction; and his
                        talisman is <hi rend="italic">Ensemble</hi>. This is the word that
                        epitomises the philosophy of Walt Whitman. Add the word <hi rend="italic">modernness</hi>, &amp; you begin to unlock Leaves of Grass.<ptr target="nyp.00272_n6"/></item>
                </list></p>
            <p>These are the points, my dear Conway, that I wish, through you, to submit to Mr.
                Rosetti. I have mentioned to Mr. Whitman my intention of writing him, &amp; he, W.,
                has made no objection. I would add, for myself, for Mr. Rosetti, that I hope he will
                not be deterred from giving fullest swing to what I am sure I have discovered in
                him, namely, an intuitional admiration &amp; appreciation of our Poet, by the
                ostensibly timid attitude held at present by the critical &amp; reading world toward
                Leaves of Grass—but hope he will strike at that loftier, honestly enthusiastic
                range of minds &amp; readers, which, perhaps by the time Mr. Hotten's volume gets
                well in the hands of the public, will prove the genuine audience Mr. Whitman is
                certain of.</p>

            <p>Again asking pardon of Mr. Rosetti for perhaps intruding these suggestions—yet
                placing them in any &amp; every respect at his service should they be so fortunate
                as to strike him favorably—I remain &amp;c &amp;c</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>