<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00173">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William Mullery to Walt Whitman, 21 October 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>William Mullery</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00173</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">161-162</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>William Mullery</author>
               <title>William Mullery to Walt Whitman, 21 October 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-10-21">October 21, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Mullery, William">William Mullery</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-13">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-10">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="nyp.00173_n100"/> have just returned home last eve[ning] from Washington, being there to see about getting the body of my son Capt. <hi rend="italic">Michael Mullery</hi> of Co. I, 7th Regt N.J. Vols. who was killed while leading his men in a desperate charge before Petersburgh, Va., June 16th. I took a friend with me from Jersey City (T.C. Brown Esq.) but could only get a pass for one, so Mr. Brown has gone to City point to get the Body. he took the boat for city point last Wednesday at 3 oclock and is now I hope on his way back with the body.</p>
            <p>Your friend Jesse came home from Washington June 23rd on a 30 days furlough, and the same eve[ning] recd the sad intelligence of the death of our son Michael, when Jesse came home he was so reduced and weak that I thought he could not live a week, but he gained fast after a week or two, and returned back the 25th of July to Davids Island, (where he was transferred to from Washington) and from there he got transferred to Newark, and got another furlough on the 3rd of August, for 30 days and came home, and improved very fast, he returned Sept 5th, and is there yet at Ward U S. Genl. Hospital Center St. I took Breakfast with him yesterday morning. he look well and is fleshy, but not fit for the front. I will write to him to day and send him your letter, and he will call and see you at his earlyest conveniance, he spoke very highly of you when he came home and had your "carte de viste"&#8212;and took it back with [him] to Newark, he is now assistant cook in the Hospital. he belongs in the 7th Ward.</p>
            <p>His Brother James is still at the front with Sheridan he is well and so far unhurt. Thank God, he has never been home since he went in the service, if he lives, we look for him next August when I must write to him, and let him know about the invitation you have given him to call &amp; see you. I have another son Joseph who enlisted Sept 9th last year, for one year. he is with his brother James in Co K 15th NJ V.</p>
            <p>Mr. Thos. C. Brown keeps store at 21 Newark Av. Jersey City.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>I remain Truly &amp; Respectfully Yours Much Obliged</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
