<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00141">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Alvah H. Small to Walt Whitman, 24 July 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Alvah H. Small</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00141</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">179-180</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Alvah H. Small</author>
               <title>Alvah H. Small to Walt Whitman, 24 July 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-07-24">July 24, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Small, Alvah H.">Alvah H. Small</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-06">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Mr. Whitman Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="nyp.00141_n100"/> will now improve a few moments to pen you a few lines in accordance to your request.</p>
            <p>I left Washington last Monday at 3 oclock in the afternoon and arrived in Baltimore at 5 Oclock and I then reached this Citty and took the cars again at 9 Oclock and arrived here in Williamsport the next morning at 10 oclock.</p>
            <p>I had a very pleasant passage and enjoyed the ride very much but yet I found that my wounds were somewhat situated and they have been more sore than usual and so I have not gone about the place a great deal yet, but what I have seen so far I think I like the place very much.</p>
            <p>The Business is chiefly lumbering and it is carried on in a more extensive manner than I have ever before seen it and the place is fast building up and will very soon be incorporated into a citty.</p>
            <p>I like the place very much what I have seen of it yet I have not been about but a little and I cannot write you so much as I would like to and so I will write you again. I want to hear from Washington and how things are moving and will be much pleased to hear from you and I will try to write you more in my next letter.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>I remain yours truly,</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
