<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00146">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Caleb H. Babbitt to Walt Whitman, 18 September 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Caleb H. Babbitt</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00146</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">104-105</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Caleb H. Babbitt</author>
               <title>Caleb H. Babbitt to Walt Whitman, 18 September 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-09-18">September 18, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Babbitt, Caleb H.">Caleb H. Babbitt</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-04">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-31">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-12">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am going to <hi rend="italic">try</hi> and write you a few lines this morning, but you must overlook my poor composition also my writing, for I am very weak and my mind is not as it was before I was <hi rend="italic">sun stroke</hi>. Walt, this is the first letter I have writen since I came home, but it is by no means the first one I would like to have writen you. Walt (you must excuse one for so adressing you) your letters have been of more value to me than you can imagine, it was not only the words that was writen that don me the good but to know that they come from the bottom of the heart of a true and sympathizing friend.&#8212;It does not seem as though I could ever repay you for your kindness toward me both while I was in the Hospital, and since I came home. I often think to myself, what can I do to repay you for your kindness I can think of nothing at present, but sometime I may have an opportunity. your letters are not only a blessing to me but a comfort to my friend to know that I have the sympathy, and good will, of a true friend, like yourself. My Sister and also my friends are very anxious to see and to read your <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> and I hope they soon may soon have an oportunity of so doing. I do not wish you to think that I want to beg one of you, but that I wish to buy one of them.</p>
            <p>Walt, In your letters you wish me to imagine you talking with me when I read them, well I do, and it does very well to think about, but it is nothing compared with the original.</p>
            <p>I presume you would like to know how I have been since I came home and how I am at the present time. I have been <hi rend="italic">pretty sick</hi>. My furlough of forty days is out to day (for to day is Sunday so you will see that it has taken me some time to write this simple epistle). and in days of which time I knew nothing and no friends and also the Doctor gave me up! Dear Walt, it has been Gods blessed will for me to regain my health in a small degree and to day I am able to be proped up in bed and able to write to my true friend and comrade. I am just about the same as I was when <hi rend="italic">you</hi> saw me at Armory Hospital. I have to be sure begun with kind friend who have been friends sure but then Walt I would have amused them all for a few days if you could have been with me. how often think I of the many fine chats we have had all alone by ourselves in a loving and peaceful manner and those days will never be forgoten by me, and I am certain they will not by you, In your last you spoke about my furlough, in regard to that my Doctor has got through the proses you spoke of, and I am as anxious to be honorable in regard to that matter, as you are to have me and I hope there may be no trouble. My Sister Mary says when I go back to war she shall write to you.</p>
            <p>This is what I call a short and simple letter but it is writen by me. I will bid you good by hoping to hear from you soon. I am yours with love and respect</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
