<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00161">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Isaac Livensparger to Walt Whitman, 7 May 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Isaac Livensparger</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00161</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">155</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Isaac Livensparger</author>
               <title>Isaac Livensparger to Walt Whitman, 7 May 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-05-07">May 7, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Linensparger, Isaac">Isaac Linensparger</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-02">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-14">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Father,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>As I<ptr target="nyp.00161_n100"/> always wish to fulfill my promises I will enjoy this afternoon in writing a letter in order to let you know how I got home and how my health is    So I left Washington that evening at 5 Oc and got to Baltimore at 7 and left at 6 and got to Harisburg at two in the night. I changed cars and was off in a few minutes in the morning of the 4th Wednesday a train just a head of us run off track and was hurt which throwed us back six hours we ought to have got to Pittsburg at one that day But did not get in until after six then I had to wait until two in the night   But I was glad of it. I went to the Soldiers Home and got my supper and took a good sleep   I left Pittsburg a little after 2 after that we run right through   I got to Bucyrus just in time for dinner. I had good luck there was one of my Fathers old acquaintances there in a bugy [took me] straight on home to the door whar I had a grand interunion with my friends   I found all of them in good health   they were a little supprised to see me but they had been looking for me every day for a long time everything is a month behind things in Washington    It snowed all day this Monday the roads are very bad people are just getting their roads [open] the trees are just beginning to put forth their leafs. If my friend is in the Hospital yet tell him I got home all right   I guess I will close by biding you good by for this time and request from you to send a letter in return at some later time.</p>
            <p>I am very respectfully your soldier boy Isaac Livensparger, Address Lykens, Crawford Co[unty] Ohio</p>
            
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
