<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00177">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Jesse Mullery to Walt Whitman, 23 January 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Jesse Mullery</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00177</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">164</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Jesse Mullery</author>
               <title>Jesse Mullery to Walt Whitman, 23 January 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-01-23">January 23, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Mullery, Jesse">Jesse Mullery</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-03">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-17">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-18">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>My Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="nyp.00177_n100"/> have been thinking about writing you at Brooklyn but as I did not know for certain that you were there I have waited until now so that I might be shure this would find you in Washington I presume you are there by this time and I hope soon to receive a communication from you. I have thought of you very often since I saw you and would have gone to Brooklyn to see you again had my health been good enough. I have not been out much since I saw you as the weather would not admit and when the weather is stormy my wound pains me so much that I am obliged to remain quiet: I received a letter from James a few days ago acknowledgeing the receipt of your card. I also sent him your letter which he says he was very much pleased with: and he says he will always keep the card in remembrance of one who was so kind to me when I was so much in kneed of a little care When I wrote him before I did not tell him the picture was for him but merely enclosed your letter with the card in it telling him to return the letter after he had read it. And in answering he says The accompanying picture I understand
is for me for which you will please give Mr Whitman my warmest thanks also for his kind rememberance of me  I hope he may live to see you for I believe he has a great desire to as he speaks of you in every letter&#8212;</p>
            <p>I presume you have seen some of my Washington friends ere this, and I hope to hear from them when I hear from you. If you see Miss Howard please remember me to her as you know I have good reason to thank her for many a kind turn which she wrought for me during my stay in that city<ptr target="nyp.00177_n2"/>. I cannot forget Armory Square hospital and I have a strong desire to visit that place again. Please tell Mr Woods (if you see him) I am enjoying good health and I send my kind regards to him and all others that I am acquainted with who may be in Ward A.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Hoping to hear from you soon I will subscribe myself yours affectionately</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
