<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="owu.00003">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Martha Whitman to Walt Whitman, 11 August
    1867</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Martha Whitman</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
<persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>owu.00003</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>Martha Whitman</author>
    <title>Martha Whitman to Walt Whitman, 11 August 1867</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1867-08-11" xml:id="dat1">August 11, 1867</date>
    <orgName xml:id="owu">The Bayley-Whitman Collection, Ohio Wesleyan University, Delaware, OH</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Whitman, Martha">Martha Whitman</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-11-24">added annotations from Waldron, corrected</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-10-03">checked, corrected</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2010-12-14" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-04" who="#vs">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="owu.00003.001.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <date when="1867-08-11">Sunday, August 11th/67</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I received your letter and was right glad to get it<ptr target="owu.00003_n1"/> I am in rather a writing mood
                today and have written a long letter to Han<ptr target="owu.00003_n2"/> I also enclosed one from Jeff it was a
                very long and lively one and I thought it would please her. I am having very
                pleasant times here, sometimes, it is very gay, it it the style here when any one
                has company every one calls on them. tomorrow I have to return quite a number it is
                quite a bore to me to make fashionable calls but of course I must submit to it. but
                what I enjoy most of any thing else is sitting in my window looking down the <choice>
                    <orig>Susquanhanna</orig>
                    <reg>Susquehanna</reg>
                </choice> for miles and on the opposite side long ranges of the <choice>
                    <orig>Alleganny</orig>
                    <reg>Allegheny</reg>
                </choice> Mountains they are mostly cultivated and their is something delightful
                about the scenery I would never tire looking at it we have not had what I call a
                real hot day <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="owu.00003.002.jpg" type="verso"/> this
                summer the children are very happy and contented seldom talk about home they are
                very fat and burnt Hattie talks a good deal about seeing you, and says she is going
                out with Uncle Walt. I write to Mother quite often it seems to cheer her up to get
                letters, I tell her every little particular I have been to a number of picnics they are very pleasant. this week we expect to go to the
                Barclay coal mines<ptr target="owu.00003_n3"/> every one around here seems related some way to Mr or Mrs Mason
                we also go riding a good deal the time passes quickly and I am much pleased that I
                decided to come here I expect to leave for Washington with Mary &amp; Jule the 29th
                ins't Wont you come and
                <!-- appears to be missing a word here, perhaps "see" LL, 12/15/2010 --> me Walt
                before you leave for Brooklyn<ptr target="owu.00003_n4"/> I want to see you very much about those "Notes"<ptr target="owu.00003_n5"/> I would
                like much to have a copy but think it hardly worth while to send them here but you
                will save me a copy when I come to Washington I dont think of any more to write at
                present and it is getting late and I want yet to write one to Mother bidding you
                good night I remain your Affectionate sister</p>

            <closer>
                <signed>Mattie<!-- <ptr target="n0707"/> --></signed>
            </closer>


            <!-- The postscript appears on the recto of the first leaf. -->

            <postscript>
                <p>I forgot to tell you the children said before they went to sleep to give their
                    love to Uncle Walt</p>
            </postscript>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="owu.00003.003.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="owu.00003.004.jpg" type="verso"/>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>