<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="owu.00007">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Martha Whitman to Walt Whitman, 28 October 1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Martha Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>owu.00007</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Martha Whitman</author>
                    <title>Martha Whitman to Walt Whitman, 28 October 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-10-28" xml:id="dat1">October 28, 1872</date>
                    
                    <orgName xml:id="owu">The Bayley-Whitman Collection, Ohio Wesleyan University, Delaware OH</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Martha">Martha Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2010-12-16" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-04" who="#vs">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="owu.00007.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                         
                <opener>
                    <dateline rend="right">
                        <name type="place">St. Louis</name>
                        <date when="1872-10-28">Oct 28th/72</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear brother Walt</salute>
                </opener>
                
                <p>I have received a good many letters and books etc. from you and have been very neglectful to thank you for remembering me but you must know dear brother that I think just as much of you as if I did write we talk about you and dear Mammy every day and wish it could be that you would visit us. we have such a nice home and the children are so large that you would enjoy them</p>
                
                <p>I often think of what you used to say about Hattie when she was a wild noisy little creature that was 'be patient Mattie she will make a fine girl' she is every thing that we would desire Jeff takes her out a great deal and it improves her much Jessie is not
                    
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="owu.00007.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            behind her they both study hard and it is my greatest ambition to have them educated as Mammy says there will be one rich Whitman I would prefer to spend our money on the children.</p>
                
            <p>Now dear brother I want to talk a little <choice><orig>business</orig> <reg>business</reg></choice> with you Jeff and I have you know wanted Mammy to make us a visit but when she lived in Brooklyn she thought she couldn't come on account of Eddy but now George has Ed—and we think that Mammy can and ought to make us a visit we would make her so comfortable and Jeff would take her out riding <hi rend="underline">I know she wants to come</hi> I wish you would write as soon as you receive this and tell me what you think about it. I intend starting for Camden next week and dont you think you could come on and see me then I can talk to you so much better than

                    <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="owu.00007.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    
                    write and it seems so long since I have seen you that you must come if you can. I had a letter from Lou a few days ago and she wanted me to bring the children but I will not bring them it would not do. Jeff will be home and everything will go on just the same as if I was here Now Walt dont say that we cant have Mammy for we have set our hearts on it and the children are wild with delight at the prospect</p>
                
            <p>I hav'nt much to write about Jeff is quite busy but he is well and has good times he sometimes says if I was only strong and well that his cup of <choice><orig>happiness</orig> <reg>happiness</reg></choice> would be complete but there is always an <hi rend="underline">if</hi> still I cannot complain some days I feel real strong and then the weather is bad and that affects me more than anything else but when I see you I
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="owu.00007.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                will have a good talk</p>
                
                <p>the children have just returned from dancing school and are practicing some new steps they send lots of love to you and told me they would write soon Jeff has gone to the Opera and now with much love</p>
                             
                <closer>
                    <salute>I subscribe myself your devoted</salute>
                    <signed>Sister Mattie</signed>
                </closer>
                                  
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>