<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="pml.00011">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Abby H. Price, 29 March 1860</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>pml.00011</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">49-50</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Abby H. Price, 29 March 1860</title>
               <date when="1860-03-29">March 29, 1860</date>
               <orgName xml:id="pml">Pierpont Morgan Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Price, Abby H.">Abby H. Price</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-14">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#bbb" when="2009-08-20">proofread</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-09">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Boston,</name>
                  <date when="1860-03-29">Thursday night, | March 29.<ptr target="pml.00011_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>As I know you would like to hear from me, my dear friend,<ptr target="pml.00011_n2"/> I will not yet go to bed&#8212;but sit down to write to you, that I have been here in Boston, to-day is a fortnight, and that my book is well under way. About a hundred and twenty pages are set up&#8212;it will probably make from six to seven hundred pages, and of a larger size than the last edition. It is to be very finely printed, good paper, and new, rather large-sized type. Thayer &amp; Eldridge,<ptr target="pml.00011_n3"/> the publishers, are a couple of young Yankees&#8212;so far very good specimens, to me, of this Eastern race of yours. They have treated me first rate&#8212;have not asked me at all what I was going to put into the book&#8212;just took me to the stereotype foundry, and given orders to follow my directions. It will be out in a month&#8212;a great relief to me to have the thing off my mind.</p>
            <p>I am more pleased with Boston than I anticipated. It is full of life, and criss-cross streets. I am very glad I [have] come, if only to rub out of me the deficient notions I had of New England character. I am getting to like it, every way&#8212;even the Yankee twang.</p>
            <p>Emerson called upon me immediately, treated me with the greatest courtesy&#8212;kept possession of me all day&#8212;gave me a bully dinner, &amp;c.<ptr target="pml.00011_n4"/>
I go on the Common&#8212;walk considerable in Washington street&#8212;and occupy about three hours a day at work in the printing office. All I have to do, is to read proofs. I wish you lived here&#8212;I should visit you regularly every day&#8212;probably twice a day. I create an immense sensation in Washington street. Every body here is so like everybody else&#8212;and I am Walt Whitman!&#8212;Yankee curiosity and cuteness, for once, is thoroughly stumped, confounded, petrified, made desperate.</p>
            <p>Let me see&#8212;have I any thing else to say to you? Indeed, what does it all amount to&#8212;this saying business? Of course I had better tear up this note&#8212;only I want to let you see how I cannot have forgotten you&#8212;sitting up here after half past 12, to write this precious document. I send my love to Helen and Emmy.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
