<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="pml.00012">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Abby H. Price,<ptr target="pml.00012_n1"/> 11&#8211;15 October, 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>pml.00012</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">161-164</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Abby H. Price, 11&#8211;15 October, 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-11">October 11&#8211;15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="pml">Pierpont Morgan Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Price, Abby H.">Abby H. Price</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-31">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-26">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington </name>
                  <date when="1863-10-11">October 11 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear friend,<ptr target="pml.00012_n1"/>
            </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letters were both received, &amp; were indeed welcome. Don't mind my not answering them promptly, for you know what a wretch I am about such things. But you must write just as often as you conveniently can. Tell me all about your folks, especially the girls, &amp; about Mr Arnold<ptr target="pml.00012_n2"/>&#8212;of course you won't forget Arthur,<ptr target="pml.00012_n3"/> &amp; always when you write to him send him my love. Tell me about Mrs Urner<ptr target="pml.00012_n4"/> &amp; the dear little rogues. Tell Mrs Black<ptr target="pml.00012_n5"/> she ought to be here hospital matron&#8212;only it is a harder pull than folks anticipate. You wrote about Emma, her thinking she might &amp; ought to come as nurse for the soldiers&#8212;dear girl, I know it would be a blessed thing for the men to have her loving spirit &amp; hand, &amp; whoever of the poor fellows had them would indeed feel it so. But, my darling, it is a dreadful thing&#8212;you dont know these wounds, sicknesses &amp;c&#8212;the sad condition in which many of the men are brought here, &amp; remain for days, sometimes the wounds full of crawling corruption &amp;c&#8212;Down in the field hospitals in front they have no proper care &amp; attention, &amp; after a battle go for many days unattended to&#8212;</p>
            <p>Abby, I think often about you, &amp; the pleasant days, the visits I used to pay you &amp; how good it was always to be made so welcome. O I wish I could come in this afternoon, &amp; have a good tea with you, &amp; have three or four hours of mutual comfort &amp; talk, &amp; be all of us together again. Is Helen home, &amp; well? And what is she doing now? And you, my dear friend, how sorry I am to hear that your health is not rugged&#8212;but, dear Abby, you must not dwell on anticipations of the worst. (But I know that is not your nature, or did not use to be.) O I hope this will find you feeling quite well, &amp; in good spirits&#8212;I feel so well myself&#8212;I will have to come &amp; see you I think&#8212;I am so fat, out considerable in the open air, &amp; all red &amp; tanned worse than ever. You see therefore that my life amid these sad &amp; unhealthy hospitals has not yet told upon me, for I am this fall running over with health, so I feel [as] if I ought to go on that account [working] among all the sick &amp; deficient [who are deprived of] it&#8212;&amp; O how gladly I would [bestow upon you a] liberal share, dear Abby, [if such a]<ptr target="pml.00012_n6"/> thing were possible.</p>
            <p>I am continually moving around among the hospitals. One I go to oftenest the last three months is Armory Square, as it is large, generally full of the worst wounds &amp; sicknesses, &amp; is one of the least visited&#8212;to this, or some one, I never miss a day or evening. I am enabled to give the men something&#8212;add perhaps some trifle to their supper all round. Then there are always special cases, needing something special. Above all the poor boys welcome magnetic friendship, personality (some are so fervent, so hungering for this)&#8212;poor fellows, how young they are, lying there with their pale faces, &amp; that mute look in the eyes. O how one gets to love them, often, particular cases, so suffering, so good, so manly &amp; affectionate&#8212;Abby, you would all smile to see me among them&#8212;many of them like children, ceremony is mostly discarded&#8212;they suffer &amp; get exhausted &amp; so weary&#8212;lots of them have grown to expect as I leave at night that we should kiss each other, sometimes quite a number, I have to go round&#8212;poor boys, there is little petting in a soldier's life in the field, but, Abby, I know what is in their hearts, always waiting, though they may be unconscious of it themselves&#8212;</p>
            <p>I have a place where I buy very nice home-made biscuits, sweet crackers &amp;c&#8212;Among others, one of my ways is to get a good lot of these &amp; for supper go through a couple of wards &amp; give a portion to each man&#8212;next evening two wards more, &amp; so on&#8212;then each marked case needs something to itself&#8212;I spend my evenings altogether at the hospitals&#8212;my day, often. I give little gifts of money in small sums, which I am enabled to do. All sorts of things indeed, food, clothing, letter-stamps (I write lots of letters), now &amp; then a good pair of crutches &amp;c &amp;c. Then I read to the boys&#8212;the whole ward that can walk gathers around me &amp; listens&#8212;</p>
            <p>All this I tell you, my dear, because I know it will interest you. I like Washington very well (did you see my last letter in N Y Times of Oct 4, Sunday?)<ptr target="pml.00012_n7"/> I have three or four hours work every day copying &amp; in writing letters for the press, &amp;c., make enough to pay my way&#8212;live in an unexpensive manner any how&#8212;I like the mission I am on here, &amp; as it is deeply holding me I shall continue&#8212;</p>
            <p>October 5
Well, Abby, I guess I will send you letter enough&#8212;I ought to have finished &amp; sent off the letter last Sunday, when it was written&#8212;I have been pretty busy&#8212;we are having new arrivals of wounded &amp; sick now all the time&#8212;some very bad cases&#8212;Abby, should you come across any one who feels to help, contribute to the men through me, write me. (I may then send word some purchases I should find acceptable for the men)&#8212;but this only if it happens to come in that you know or meet any one, perfectly convenient&#8212;</p>
            <p>Abby, I have found some good friends here, a few, but true as steel&#8212;W D O'Connor &amp; wife, above all. He is a clerk in Treasury&#8212;she is a Yankee girl&#8212;then C W Eldridge<ptr target="pml.00012_n8"/> in paymaster's department. He is a Boston boy too&#8212;their friendship has been unswerving.</p>
            <p>In the hospitals among these American young men, I could not describe to you what mutual attachments &amp; how passing deep &amp; tender these boys&#8212;some have died, but the love for them lives as long as I draw breath&#8212;those soldiers know how to love too when once they have the right person &amp; the right love offered them. It is wonderful. You see I am running off into the clouds&#8212;but this is my element&#8212;</p>
            <p>Abby, I am writing this note this afternoon in Major Hapgood's office&#8212;he is away sick&#8212;I am here a good deal of the time alone&#8212;it is a dark rainy afternoon&#8212;we don't know what is going on down in front, whether Meade is getting the worst of it, or not<ptr target="pml.00012_n9"/>&#8212;(but the result of the big elections cheers us)<ptr target="pml.00012_n10"/>&#8212;I believe fully in Lincoln&#8212;few know the rocks &amp; quicksands he has to steer through. I enclose you a note Mrs O'Connor handed me to send to you, written I suppose upon impulse&#8212;she is a noble Massachusetts woman, is not very rugged in health&#8212;I am there very much&#8212;her husband &amp; I are great friends too&#8212;Well I will close&#8212;the rain is pouring, the sky leaden&#8212;it is between 2 &amp; 3&#8212;I am going to get some dinner &amp; then to hospital&#8212;good by, dear friends, &amp; I send my love to all&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
