<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rlc.00001">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Rudolf Schmidt, 16 January 1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rlc.00001</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">150–153</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Rudolf Schmidt, 16 January 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-01-16" xml:id="dat1">January 16, 1872</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="rlc">The Royal Library of Copenhagen</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Schmidt, Rudolf">Rudolf Schmidt</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-10-17" who="#el">corrected encoding of notes</change>
            <change when="2011-05-09" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-12-01" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D. C. United States</name>.
                    <date when="1872-01-16" rend="right">January 16, 1872</date>.
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear sir:</salute><ptr target="rlc.00001_n1"/>
            </opener>

            <p>Supposing that the books &amp; papers I sent you in response to your letter have safely arrived, I thought I would now write you a few lines. What I have to submit &amp; say, I will just say without ceremony—confident you will receive it in the same spirit in which it is written.</p>
            
            <p>I sent you (by Mr. Clausen<ptr target="rlc.00001_n2"/>) my poems "Leaves of Grass"—and little prose work "Democratic Vistas"—also a piece I recited at opening of an Exhibition of Industry in New York;<ptr target="rlc.00001_n3"/> adding several criticisms, sketches, &amp;c. about the books &amp; about myself, written by different persons from different points of view. These will furnish you with sufficient material for your examination, digest, &amp;c.</p>
            
            <p>The main object of my poetry is simply to present—sometimes by directions, but oftener by indirections—the Portraiture or model of a sound, large, complete, physiological, emotional, moral, intellectual &amp; spiritual <hi rend="italic">Man</hi>, a good son, brother, husband, father, friend &amp; practical citizen—&amp; <hi rend="italic">Woman</hi> also, a good wife, mother, practical citizen too—adjusted to the modern, to the New World, to Democracy, &amp; to science. My verse strains its every nerve to arouse, brace, dilate, excite to the love &amp; realization of health, friendship, perfection, freedom, amplitude. There are other objects, but these are the main ones.</p>
            
            <p>The central purpose of "Democratic Vistas" is to project &amp; outline a fresh &amp; brawny race of original American Imaginative authors, with <hi rend="italic">moral purpose</hi>, Hegelianism, underlying their works, poems—and with Science &amp; Democracy—also thoroughly <hi rend="italic">religious</hi>—(not ecclesiastical or sectarian merely.)</p>
            
            <p>And now an item for your proposed review:</p>
            
            <p>When you are composing your review, I would like to have you bring in, in a proper place, the following mentioned facts<ptr target="rlc.00001_n4"/>—that neither my poetic "Leaves" or "Democratic Vistas" is cordially accepted in the United States—nor do the chief literary persons or organs of the country admit the poems as having any merit, or recognize the author as a poet at all—that he has once indeed been ignominiously ejected from a moderate government employment at Washington by special order of a Cabinet officer there, for the sole &amp; avowed reason that he was the writer of the book; that up to this time no American publisher will publish it (the author printing the various editions himself)<ptr target="rlc.00001_n5"/>—that many of the booksellers refuse to keep it for sale—that the swarms of versifiers and writers of book notices in America are quite generally banded against this new man (myself) and that his position, in his own country, both as to literary recognition &amp; worldly prosperity, has been, and remains to-day, under a heavy &amp; depressing cloud.</p>
            
            <p>Of course you will at the same time hardly need to be told that I take all this very coolly—that my book is written in the sun &amp; with a gay heart—for these surely, fully belong to me. But I think a good foreign review of my works would be more complete by giving those facts—would be hardly complete without them—for they are <hi rend="italic">the substantial facts</hi>, notwithstanding a few exceptions.</p>
            
            <p>Meanwhile, abroad, my book &amp; myself have had a welcome quite dazzling. Tennyson writes me friendly letters, inviting me to become his guest.<ptr target="rlc.00001_n6"/> <choice><orig>Freilegrath</orig> <reg>Freiligrath</reg></choice> translates &amp; commends my poems. Robert Buchanan,<ptr target="rlc.00001_n8"/> Swinburne, and all the great English &amp; Dublin colleges, affectionately receive me &amp; doughtily champion me. And while I, the author, am without any recompense at all in America, the English pirate-publisher, Hotten,<ptr target="rlc.00001_n9"/> derives a handsome annual income from a bad &amp; defective London reprint of my Poems.</p>
            
            <p>I wish you to speak of the purpose of "Democratic Vistas." (It is at present in danger of falling still-born here.)</p>
            
            <p>I should be glad to hear more from you, your magazine—Denmark too. For all, accept my friendliest good wishes.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Direct</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman</signed>
                <signed rend="right">Washington, D. C.</signed>
                <signed rend="right">Solicitor's Office Treasury,</signed>
                <signed rend="right">United States America</signed>
            </closer>
            
            <postscript>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Later</hi>—Upon reading over my letter within, previous to mailing it, I had almost decided not to send it—as a part of it may be open to the imputation of a complaining spirit, &amp; querulousness—Yet as nothing can be further from my real state of mind, (which is <hi rend="italic">more</hi> than satisfied, &amp; delightedly grateful for my literary fortunes &amp; reception by the world,) I will let it go.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>