<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00031">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 17 April
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00031</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                        <editor>Sculley Bradley</editor>
                        <title xml:id="wwwc">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">90&#8211;92</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 17 April 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-04-17" xml:id="dat1">April 17, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-17" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-14" who="#no">checked, corrected transcription: added "the" in p7</change>
            <change when="2014-11-10" who="#ak">corrected transcription, checked encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-07-19" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded and annotated.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.,</name>
                    <date when="1883-04-17" rend="right">April 17, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:<!--<ptr target="n2002"/>--></salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I got your letter of the 14th yesterday.<!--<ptr target="syr.00031_n1"/>--></p>

            <p>I had the misfortune to catch a heavy cold on the chilly Sound boat in returning from
                Providence, which increased seriously after my return, and developed into a bad
                attack of erysipelas, with which my head and face were well covered.<!--<ptr target="syr.00031_n2"/>-->
                Being very ill, and a sorry object to behold with the
                eruption, I have been forced to absent myself from the office for several days, and
                keep in bed as much as possible. I am better now, and hope to get out tomorrow, when
                I will at once attend to the copyright business.<!--<ptr target="nyp.00489_n2"/>--></p>

            <p>I need not say how grieved I am at Dr. Bucke's withdrawal of the lines of Lucretius
                from the title page.<!--<ptr target="nyp.00489_n4"/>--> He was so pleased with the epigraph,
                and so particularly pleased, as it seemed, with my enthusiastic enjoyment of it,
                that his change of mind is unaccountable to me. The withdrawal is an error, which I
                believe he will yet be sorry for. There are words, Luther says, which are half
                battles, and these of Lucretius are among them. They appealed directly to educated
                men, and gave the title page dignity, winning the reader thus from the start, and
                reinforced by all the following contents of the book, they gave it a powerful hold
                upon the respect of thinking and enquiring people. Their omission loses us an
                advantage&#8212;one more considerable than may at first sight appear.</p>

            <p>Ill as I was when I got your letter, and with but a sort of dying interest in
                anything, this bit of news startled me, and I felt dashed, I assure you.</p>

            <p>However, it can't be helped now, and I will at once proceed to get copyright for the
                despoiled title page.</p>

            <p>I am obliged to Mr. McKay<!--<ptr target="syr.00031_n2"/>--> for his offer, and will let him
                know in due time how many copies I desire. There are several persons with whom I
                wish to place copies, with a view to doing the book good.</p>

            <p>The news of Comstock's<!--<ptr target="nyp.00457_n2"/>--> disaster came to me in a letter
                from Dr. Channing<!--<ptr target="loc.00945_n5"/>--> at a time when I was illest, and I
                wanted to write to you at once, but was not able. It gave me the greatest relief and
                exultation, and did me positive good. When I get out, I will search the papers for the
                details. It is manifestly a crushing defeat for Comstock, and shows that he is on
                the descending plane, down which I hope, and indeed heard, that my Tribune letter
                materially contributed to send him. He took my dare beautifully meek, I must say.
                The only newspaper item I have seen on the Heywood matter,<!--<ptr target="n3086"/>--> was
                a little editorial in last Friday's Star, from which it appears that the Judge's
                ruling&#8212;I mean, charge&#8212;to the jury was terribly against Comstock on the
                ground of his treacherous methods in working up his cases. His "decoy" business is
                what damns him, and this has thoroughly got into the public mind. He never again can
                make head against it. When you bear in mind that Heywood had really in the syringe
                matter, flatly broken a statute, his acquittal by the jury in the very face of the
                evidence against him, shows the prejudice against Comstock, and makes the victory
                remarkable.</p>

            <p>Something ought to be written now to fix the triumph, and as a keynote for press
                comment. If I were well, I would certainly attempt it, but so far as I am concerned,
                the opportunity must be lost, for I am <hi rend="italic">hors de combat</hi> for the
                present. Nothing is more dangerous than the operations of an official wretch like
                Comstock, backed as he is by eminent clergymen like Chancellor Crosby, Dr. Hall,
                Newman, &#38;c., of whose displeasure great journals even, like the Tribune, are
                afraid, and whose tool they either support or will not censure. The instance is, the
                peril&#8212;the terrible peril&#8212;in which he placed your book, when he got
                Oliver Stevens to move against it, for I have found that he, through his man Friday,
                Brittain, was at the bottom of that matter. He ought to be crushed, signally,
                publicly, in the interest of free letters and the rights of thought; he ought to be
                nailed up, like a skunk to a barn-door, as an example to deter. Above all things, he
                ought to be snaked out of his position as a special agent of the United States Post
                Office Department, which would be irretrievable disgrace for him, and irremediable
                overthrow. This the press ought to demand. It is nothing less than a
                public&#8212;national&#8212;infamy, that an infamous dog like this, convicted of such
                practices&#8212;a decoy duck, a dirty stool pigeon&#8212;should be in the employ of
                the United States, and derive his power for mischief from the status his official
                rank gives him.</p>

            <p>I hear that the North American is getting up an article about you. Do you know
                anything about it?</p>

            <p>I am glad you are off for the spring woods.</p>

            <p>Wish I could go too!</p>

            <q><l>"For only those who in sad cities dwell,</l>

            <l>Are of the green fields fully sensible."</l></q> <!-- quote from William Ellery Channing -->

            <closer>
                <salute rend="center">Goodbye for this time. Faithfully</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'Connor</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
