<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00028">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 10 December
                    1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00028</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 10 December 1886</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1886-12-10" xml:id="dat1">December 10, 1886</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-04" who="#smb">Stephanie Blalock</change>
            <change when="2015-07-01" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-06-20" who="#nhg">corrected image names</change>
            <change when="2014-10-14" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-06" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00113.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ht">see notes Feb 11 1889</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1886-12-10">December 10, 1886.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It has been a great trouble to me not to be able to write to you. The difficulty of
                managing pen and ink is indescribable, and only equalled by the difficulty of
                putting even the simplest expressions together. I begin to fear that paralysis is
                not far off. I move about with slowness and difficulty. But worst of all is the
                horrible deadness of the mind. I put <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00114.jpg" type="verso"/> in an appearance every day at the
                office, but it is a long time since I have been able to do anything.</p>
            <p>I got two postal cards from you in August, and recently yours of the 19th ultimo. It
                saddens me to know of your condition, and I wish it could be otherwise.</p>
            <p>You mention having got a German paper (in August) with a long notice of L. of G. Did
                you see a pamphlet by Dr. Karl Knortz<ptr target="uva.00476_n1"/>&#8212;a lecture about
                you delivered in <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_kc.00115.jpg" type="recto"
                />New York to a large audience, I heard with great applause? He sent me a copy, and
                I undertook to get it translated, but the young lady I trusted hung fire when just
                near the close, and I have not got the translation quite yet! I hope to have it
                before long. A German friend who glanced over the article, told me the language was
                very powerful.</p>
            <p>You remember the article from the <hi rend="underline">Nation</hi> in review of the
                New Zealand professor's book about you.<ptr target="syr.00028_n1"/> Since then <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="syr_kc.00116.jpg" type="verso"/> Charley
                    Eldridge<ptr target="loc.01007_n4"/> has sent me the book, which I will forward
                to you, if you would like to see it. It is remarkable and good, though I don't
                always see as he does, and wish he were more comprehensive. But it is most
                significant, and he is flat-footed for you, and from a background of theory which
                compels respect, and must make the Apaches of criticism pause to think.</p>
            <p> What is most significant, however, is the article called "American Poets" in the <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003r" facs="syr_kc.00117.jpg" type="recto"/> October number
                of the British Quarterly Review. C.W.E. has just sent it to me, and I want to run it
                over once more, when I will send it to you. It is disfigured by a few lines, but as
                a whole it is a glorious tribute, and full of splendid and whole-hearted ardor. He
                reviews all our poets&#8212;Lowell, Whittier, Bryant, Longfellow, etc.,&#8212;and
                then puts you far above them all, giving you <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00118.jpg" type="verso"/>the larger part of the reviewing
                space besides. Now when you reflect that the London Quarterly is the great High Tory
                and aristocratic organ in Great Britain&#8212;the very essence of patrician
                respectability&#8212;you will realize where we are, and the advance we have made!
                The article is a bad blow for the enemy! This is evident by the silence of the <hi
                    rend="underline">Tribune</hi>, the <hi rend="underline">Nation</hi>, etc., in
                regard to <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="syr_kc.00119.jpg" type="recto"/>it.
                They are mum!</p> 
            <p>I have your article on Burns<ptr target="syr.00028_n2"/> and am going to read it
                carefully, when I am a little better. The <hi rend="underline">scan</hi> I have given
                it, made me feel that it was admirable. I look with interest for all the others.</p>
            <p>If you are writing again to Dr. Bucke,<ptr target="n0119"/> tell him how badly off I
                am, and that I will answer his letters as soon as I can. At present my brain is just
                mud&#8212;I have a heap of letters unanswered.</p>
            <p>No matter what the venal press may say, there is <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00120.jpg" type="verso"/>no doubt that Julian Hawthorne told
                the truth about his interview with Lowell, and that Lowell lied. Julian got him into
                an awful scrape, no doubt, by the publication. 'Tis joy to see a bird like Lowell
                come to grief with his foreign friends, to whom he toadied so basely.<ptr
                    target="syr.00028_n3"/></p>
            <p>I hope to write you a better letter next time, and that your locomotion and general
                health may improve. I am always deeply glad to hear from you.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Affectionately</salute>
                <signed>W.D.O'C</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>Walt Whitman.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
