<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00021">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 14 March
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00021</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 14 March 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-03-14" xml:id="dat1">March 14, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-14" who="#nhg">updated image names</change>
            <change when="2014-06-06" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-20" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-26" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00064.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes March 23 1889</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Providence, R.I. <lb/>98 Congdon Street,</name>
                    <date when="1883-03-14" rend="right">March 14, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>After I telegraphed you today, I got the proofs, mailed from Washington, and immediately sat down
                and have spent most of the day proof reading. I return the sheets with this
                evening's mail, and as I shall not probably see another proof, I hope you will see
                that <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr_kc.00065.jpg" type="verso"/> the
                corrections are carefully made, since I loathe typographical errors.</p>

            <p>I wish you would see that the printer puts all names of books into <hi
                    rend="underline">italics</hi>, as my copy indicated. I don't like to see a page
                so dotted with guillemets or quotation marks. Besides, this was the plan followed in
                the pamphlet&#8212;"The Good Gray Poet."</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_kc.00066.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p>One thing I must beg, that you will restore to its place in the text so much of
                Emerson's letter as my <hi rend="underline">MS</hi> gave. I had a tussle with Dr. Bucke about this, and he gave in,
                and allowed that there was no reason why the letter should not appear twice, or even
                three times in different parts of the book, for different reasons. It is absolutely
                necessary to my point on Cook that the letter should <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00067.jpg" type="verso"/> stand right up there and face him
                in the context, and I beg you to have this done.</p>

            <p>Be sure and let me have (sent here, until further notice) the proofs of the <hi
                    rend="underline">Good Gray Poet</hi>. There is a bit of it appended to these slips,
                and I notice that my first footnote has been changed, not entirely to my taste. What
                I wrote explained the <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="syr_kc.00068.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>
                somewhat too enigmatic "sad pleasure" of the text, and the
                revised version ignores the point. I thought what I wrote perfectly deserved,
                besides, for Lowell
                is a perfect cad, and deserves the kick I gave him in my footnote. His interference
                with that letter was an extraordinary piece of <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00069.jpg" type="verso"/> meanness and impudence, for which
                he deserved a sharper thrust than I gave him.</p>

            <p>I am not sure, thinking it over, but that I may, when I see the proofs, take out three
                or four lines on the last page of the <hi rend="underline"><choice>
                        <abbr>G.G.P</abbr><expan>Good Grey Poet</expan></choice></hi>.</p>

            <p>I write in a hurry, so as to catch <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="syr_kc.00070.jpg" type="recto"/> the mail, and not
                disappoint you. Jeannie is very ill, confined to her bed, perhaps never to be
                well again. I don't know, the prospect is distracting and gloomy.</p>

            <p>I have been quite ill ever since I came here, and have read these proofs in a state
                of feebleness and confusion. It is <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00071.jpg" type="verso"/> probable that my state is reaction
                from the severe work of the winter at Washington.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>More anon</salute>
                <salute>Goodbye</salute>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W.D. O'Connor</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman</salute>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>P.S. If I <hi rend="underline">can</hi> see a revise, I should like it.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
