<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00132">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Lewis K. Brown to Walt Whitman, 5 November 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Lewis K. Brown</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>tex.00132</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">120-121</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Lewis K. Brown</author>
               <title>Lewis K. Brown to Walt Whitman, 5 November 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-11-05">November 5, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="tex">Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Brown, Lewis K.">Lewis K. Brown</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-07">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-13">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Walter</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>As I<ptr target="tex.00132_n100"/> am not a going out to day I thought that my time could not be better imployed than by writing to you. So hear goes,&#8212;First I must tell you about the patients hear. I was up to Ward A, this morning to see No. 40, he is better than he was when you went away, and Harry, the Wardmaster, thinks that he will get well&#8212;Concerning the patients in Ward C, they are all getting better. &#8212; I was asking Miss Platt<ptr target="tex.00132_n2"/> how your patients wer in the ward and she told me that they wer better&#8212;that man with the bad leg is mending his wound is quite painful yet but is getting along as well as you could expect. the man in the other wards are mending&#8212;thear has bin no wounded brought in since you left&#8212;things in this ward have chainged some since you left.  Miss Lowell<ptr target="tex.00132_n3"/> has got back &amp; is <hi rend="italic">getting things put to rites</hi>, as she thinks, you know that she has bin on a visit to N.York. J. A. Tabor has gon to his Regt.    he went on Monday&#8212;I guess it was rather unexpected to him. Cuningham is about the saim as he was when you left him. I cannot see any change. since Tabor has gon <hi rend="italic">Billy Clements</hi> (that little fellow that was in this ward) has been dresser. he does verry well&#8212;all of the rest of the patients in theis Ward are mending&#8212;all things are a going on in the same old stile hear&#8212;  I received a letter from T. P. Sawyer to day  he is well. he sayes that they have bin on the move so that he could not answer my letter before.   his Regt is now  near Bealtons Station, a building railroad. he did not mention any thing about your letter&#8212;he is a going to try to get a pass to come up hear this winter&#8212;</p>
            <p>Conserning my self I am about old fassion. my leg mends slowly (about as it was when you wer hear) I have bin out in the city on Monday &amp; Tuesday, both days I was at the relief associations, to try to get a shirt or two&#8212;yesterday I got a order from the Chaplain yesterday to get two shirts from the Christian Commission, when I went up and showed them the order they told me that they had non&#8212;than I went into their store room and thear was some nice shirts thear. 1 told them that they wer just the kind that I wanted&#8212;but they told me that they were layed out for distributation amongst the diferant camps through the city. so I got non of them, &amp; I was mad enough to, after walking up thear three times and than get nothing, (the Relief association may be a verry nice thing, <hi rend="italic">but I cant see it</hi>, for I never get any thing from them yet&#8212;you have give me more than all of the rest put together. . so you are the relief association that I (as well as all the rest of the boys) like best.</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
