<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00121">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Justus F. Boyd to Walt Whitman, 10 March 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Justus F. Boyd</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>tex.00121</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">111</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Justus F. Boyd</author>
               <title>Justus F. Boyd to Walt Whitman, 10 March 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-03-10">March 10, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="tex">Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Boyd, Justus F.">Justus F. Boyd</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-12">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-03">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-18">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> 
                  <name type="place">Cohoctah, Michigan,</name> 
                  <date when="1863-03-10">March 10, 1863</date>
                  <name type="person">Mr. Whitman</name>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="tex.00121_n100"/> am seated in an easy chair pen in hand trying to scribble a few lines to you. I expect it will take me all day to write this for I cant sit up but a few moments at a time. I was taken down with chills &amp; fever when I got to Pittsburg. I stayed there from Saturday night until Monday morning before any train left I dont think I ever was so sick in my life as I was in Pittsburg I about gave up there that I never should get home alive, but there was a Dr there he gave me some medison he said that would take me home &amp; it did.</p>
            <p>We was behind time at most every place we changed cars so we had to wait I expected to have got home in three days at the outside but instead of three I was six.</p>
            <p>It dont look much like winter here there is not a parrticle of snow on the ground &amp; its about such weather as it was in Washington although its not quite so muddy There hasnt been any sleighing here this winter &amp; there wont be now its to late in the season</p>
            <p>They are making maple sugar in this part of the world now when I get well I will eat some for you but I suppose you think that wont do you much good.</p>
            <p>I tell you I am glad I am out of that Hospital &amp; when I get into another to stay I will let you know it.</p>
            <p>Oh how are you getting along with your office I am in hopes you have recd it before this time I begun to think that your office &amp; my discharge had gone to the same place now I have got my papers I think you had ought to receive yours</p>
            <p>I cant write any more this time my hand trembles so I can hardly write but I will try &amp; do better next time give my best respects to Mr &amp; Mrs O Connor.<ptr target="tex.00121_n2"/> Yours &amp;c.</p>
            <closer/>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>PS Write soon</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
