<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00140">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Alonzo S. Bush to Walt Whitman, 11 February 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Alonzo S. Bush</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="br">Bev Rilett</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>tex.00140</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">128-129</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Alonzo S. Bush</author>
               <title>Alonzo S. Bush to Walt Whitman, 11 February 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-02-11">February 11, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="tex">Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Bush, Alonzo S.">Alonzo S. Bush</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-09">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#br" when="2009-08-31">proofed and edited</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-06">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-14">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline rend="right"> </dateline>
               <salute>Friend Walter,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Sir accordain to promis I<ptr target="tex.00140_n100"/> now embrace this opportunity of informing you of my Safe arrival at Hed Quarters of 1st Ind Cav. My Friends gave me a warm reception Such as how are you Bush got robed did you &amp;c I told them how it came to pass and how much I lost and finely that Washington was a hard place  I tell you that Hoosiers are a fraid of thieves and murders and it made them open their eyes when they found out that I had been bit. Well I feel at home here and dont think I will come to the city untill I am muster out for good</p>
            <p>Everything is lovely down here and the goose hangs high the weather has been pretty cold cince I came back and therefor we have had no hunt as yet. I was just in time for the boat. I had the pleasure of meeting my Capt G. Lutt so I was not alone had quite a nice time told them how long I had been in city and what kept me you ought to here them laugh at me for not being sharper   I told them it would be all right in cours of time live &amp; learn is my moto.</p>
            <p>Walter I told that friend of mine about you and he thinks he will like you very much   I showed him your Photograph. he liked it very much. Walter tell Benedict &amp; Brown not to forget me and not send there to me.<ptr target="tex.00140_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing going on here at presant and I have nothing to write every thing is same day after day no changes. We have plety to eate &amp; wear and nothing to do.</p>
            <p>We are all waiting for the 8th June so that we can go home and see our Sweet hearts. I supose you know what they are. If you dont I do and I long for to see mine very much and I think she will want to see me&#8212;</p>
            <p>give my letter the least notice possible and oblidge yours remember me to all the Boys at armory Squre. Hoping to receive that Fatherly letter from you soon I will close good by</p>
            <closer rend="right"/>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
