<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="uva.00393">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 13 May 1878</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>uva.00393</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
                    <title>Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 13 May 1878</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1878-05-13" xml:id="dat1">May 13, 1878</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="uva">Papers of Walt Whitman (MSS 3829), Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Carpenter, Edward">Edward Carpenter</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-06" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-10-08" who="#nhg">Removed biblStruct, adjusted transcription based on images</change>
            <change when="2013-10-08" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-08" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-02" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="uva_ej.00111.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Edinburgh,</name>
                    <date when="1878-05-13" rend="right">13. May 78.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I am sorry to hear of your being kept in with rheumatism.<ptr target="n0141b"/> I am afraid you have been suffering a good deal. And just at this spring time it is such a pleasure to be out and about. I hope by the time this reaches you you may be well again. You will 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="uva_ej.00112.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                miss the Gilchrists a good deal. I had a letter from Grace<ptr target="n0890"/> about a fortnight ago telling me of their move. She seems to be wanting to get back to England. Herbert<ptr target="n0262"/> I suppose is travelling about a bit. I feel sorry that the household in North 22 street is broken up&#8212;I so often look back to those few days I spent there. I wonder whether we shall all meet again in England. Is there still a chance of 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="uva_ej.00113.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                your coming?</p>
            
            <p> My winter's work of lecturing is over now; I have had a very pleasant time of it&#8212;though living a rather solitary life. I was lecturing in 3 towns&#8212;York, Sheffield and Chesterfield. I made the last my headquarters, and then went once a week to York, twice to Sheffield and gave a lecture every week in Chesterfield. The people write answers to the questions in the lecture and then send up papers which I look over &amp; return to them. It is interesting work because one 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="uva_ej.00114.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                has all sorts of people&#8212;men &amp; women young and old of all conditions of life&#8212;except the poorest. And one gets to know a good many of them. We had a jolly excursion the other day into the country near Sheffield&#8212;a sort of geological open air science ramble. About 70 people came old &amp; young, respectables &amp; non respectables, and it was very friendly &amp; pleasant.</p>

            <p>I am staying here now with my friend Cotterill<ptr target="n0891"/> who has just returned from African explorations. And in a few days I am going home to Brighton. I met a brother of Edward Dowden's<ptr target="n0199"/> here 
                
                <!-- The conclusion of the letter is written sideways on the recto of the first page (nhg). -->
                
                a day or two ago&#8212;a parson&#8212;a pleasant sort of fellow&#8212;Irish. Thank Harry Stafford<ptr target="n0590"/> for me please for his letter. If he gets a photograph of himself done any time, I should like one.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>With love dear friend</salute>
                <salute>Yours</salute>
                <signed>Edward Carpenter</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
