<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="uva.00460">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 6&#8211;12 October
                    1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>uva.00460</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Clara Barrus</editor>
                        <title xml:id="cb">Whitman and Burroughs&#8212;Comrades</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Houghton Mifflin Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1931">1931</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">147&#8211;148</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 6&#8211;12 October 1879</title>
                    <date notBefore="1879-10-06" notAfter="1879-10-12">October 6&#8211;12, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="uva">Papers of Walt Whitman (MSS 3829), Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-09-19">corrected date information</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-05" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-20" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-02-20" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-12-13" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">SHOTTERMILL, HASLEMERE,</name>
                    <date when="1879-10-06">Surrey, October 6, <choice>
                            <abbr>'79</abbr>
                            <expan>1879</expan>
                        </choice></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dearest friend,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your letter came to me here just when Edward Carpenter and a group of his friends,
                one of them a native of Ceylon of the Tamil race, and all admirers and lovers of
                your Poems, were with us; and greatly they enjoyed hearing it.</p>

            <p>We look forward to the new book I need not say. We all agreed in hoping you
                would reconsider the title so far, that is, as to leave out the clause 'by a half
                paralytic.' If you ask me why, I should be puzzled to say, unless it is that one
                resents that mere accident of slight bodily infirmity being thrust forward as if it
                were a part of you for health and vigour, dear friend, are and ever must remain
                synonymous with our Walt's name.</p>

            <p>We have been spending the last six or seven weeks in this village I am so fond of
                where my children grew up; we came to live here after my husband's death
                and remained seven or eight years <choice>
                    <abbr>till</abbr>
                    <expan>until</expan>
                </choice> the boys needed London for their studies, a wild, breezy little place
                lying up high amongst heath-covered hills, the walks over which, with wide
                views over rich green valleys below, springy turf to tread on, sweet smells around
                and elastic invigorating air, are delicious! And old friends have given
                us a very warm reception. Tennyson has been to see us, and we have been to luncheon
                with him, and seen his fine little grandson just the same age as mine. He made many
                enquiries after you, looks fairly well and is little if at all aged since we went
                away; is a good deal bothered just now about his new play Irving is so
                shilly-shally about bringing it out on the stage, and <choice>
                    <abbr>till</abbr>
                    <expan>until</expan>
                </choice> that is decided it cannot be published in any other way. He has lately
                inherited quite a large addition to his fortune from an elder brother.</p>

            <p>Herby is busily and hopefully painting away, a small landscape on the fair days, and
                a piece of still life some roses and a fragment of beautiful antique sculpture
                before a mirror on the wet ones.</p>

            <p>Bee I hope by this time is at Berne. She has been successfully working
                away at German, boarding in a school at Wiesbaden since I last wrote, and can now
                speak and write it enough to enter on medical studies at Berne. Percy is, I think,
                in Westphalia, superintending the starting of the 'process' at some large works
                there.</p>

            <p>I am going to spend a week with an invalid cousin in Essex and then we shall settle
                down in London or close to it for the winter.</p>

            <p>I am trying to write a brief memoir of my Husband to prefix to the new edition of the
                Blake Macmillan is going to bring out.</p>

            <p>Giddy sends her kindest remembrances and says she would not wonder if she
                were to drift back again to America in a few years.</p>

            <p>I cannot tell you, dear friend, how often and how affectionately my thoughts turn to
                America the great beautiful land with its growth and its vigour and impetus and its
                friendly sunny welcomes.</p>

            <p>Edward Carpenter is gone back to Sheffield to lecture there through the winter. He
                enjoys his work.</p>

            <p>A friend told me an anecdote of Tennyson's two sons which will please you. One of
                them was going abroad and the other went to see him off at the station. They kissed
                one another heartily at parting. Hallam, the eldest, who is still unmarried, is such
                a comfort to his father and mother. He seems like son and daughter in one to
                them.</p>

            <p>Write soon again, dear friend, and let us know if the book is ready that we may have
                some copies for ourselves and friends speedily.</p>

            <p>Love to your brother and sister and to Hattie and Jessie,</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye, dearest Friend</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
