<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="wcu.00002">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Hannah Heyde Whitman, 15 May 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>wcu.00002</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Hannah Heyde Whitman, 15 May 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-05-15">May 15, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="wcu">Hunter Library at Western Carolina University</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Hannah Heyde">Hannah Heyde Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">copied plain from Walt WhitmanQR; encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn,</name> 
                  <date when="1864-05-15">May 15, 1864</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear sister Han,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mother duly received your last letter and glad were we to hear from you again. Of
course the great topic of thought and talk with us all just now is about George. We
yesterday received a letter<ptr target="wcu.00002_n2"/> from Walt saying that he had heard from George up to last
Tuesday at noon and that up to that time he was all right. He had lost quite a number
of his company&#8212;his first Lieutenant&#8212;but was himself unhurt. Oh I do so hope that
George may get through safe. What a blessing twill be if he does escape&#8212;and yet I
hardly dare hope&#8212;it does not seem possible that one can go through so much and
come out entirely unharmed, but oh for mother's sake I do so hope he may escape.
Mother is getting very old and I fear the worst results if anything should happen to
George. If we hear anything more be assured I will not fail to write you at once.</p>
            <p>So Han you have got a mansion of your own&#8212;I hope you won't get proud and not
shirk to your poor relations. Well Han, since we have seen each other I have also been
doing pretty well. I have a wife and two babies to see to. Think of that with butter at
40°&#8212;However we manage to move along&#8212;I am still in the water office&#8212;engineering&#8212;
have a pleasant place and a pretty good time. I am much worried dear sister to see
that you don't get much better&#8212;that you are so unwell. I was in hopes that when the
spring came that you get all right again. You must keep up your courage and take good
care of yourself and you will come around all right in a short time. I see you feel pretty bad about George's not coming down to see [you]. Poor fellow, he wanted to come bad enough but when he was on he had a long time to get his company mustered in
or out. I believe the next day after he got through with that he was ordered to recruit
in Brooklyn. Did you know that the officers did not have any furlough? They did not
and had to report for duty regularly&#8212;yet George did not expect to leave so soon and
thought he would be about to get leave to visit you.</p>
            <p>Han, write to mother (and me too) as often as you can. Mother is pretty well, much
better I think than we have reason to expect at her age. We often talk about you and
wish that you would come on and see us. Mother often speaks of coming on to see you
and if George comes out all right, you need not be thrown into a flurry if you see an
old lady and young man (perhaps good looking) coming along your way&#8212;that would
be mother and George, or mother and I (if I then the part in bracket comes in).
Good bye dear sister&#8212;write us soon&#8212;all send their love&#8212;affectionately your
brother Jeff.</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
