<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transmiss.news.dc.189805">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Trans-Mississippi Convention</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename></forename> <surname></surname></author>
                <principal>Timothy Schaffert</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>transmiss.news.dc.189805</idno>
                <authority>Trans-Mississippi and International Exposition of 1898</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2013 by University of any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">Text transcribed from Wakefield Scrapbook page: TMI04536</note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>

                 <msDesc>
                      <msIdentifier>
                           <settlement></settlement>
                           <repository></repository>
                           <idno></idno>
                      </msIdentifier>
                      <history>
                           <provenance>Omaha Public Library</provenance>
                      </history>
                 </msDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">The Trans-Mississippi Convention.</title>
                    <title level="j">Dodge Criterion</title>
                    <author><forename></forename> <surname></surname></author>
                    <publisher></publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Dodge, NE</pubPlace>
                    <extent>1</extent>
                    <date when="1898-05">May 1898</date>
                    <biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
                    <note type="source">"The Trans-Mississippi Convention." <hi rend="italic">Dodge Criterion</hi> May 1898.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>newspapers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-03-27"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2012"><name>Laura Weakly</name>Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>

<pb n="unknown" xml:id="transmiss.news.dc.189805.001"/>
    
<p>The Trans-Mississippi Convention.</p>

<p>The West is in the midst of a period of extraordinary prosperity, and its characteristic energy is reflected in the splendid preparations making for the Trans-Mississippi Exposition. Efforts were naturally made to secure for Omaha the half-million or so of dollars which the National Educational Association ordinarily leaves behind in a convention town. Outgeneraled in this attempt, Omaha, under the lead of Professor C. G. Pearse, Superintendent of Schools, and Dr. Victor Rosewater, the brilliant young managing editor of the Omaha Bee, has organized an educational convention, which meets from June 28 to 30, and which promises to be a noteworthy event of its kind. A feature of the convention will be a special day at the exposition, which comprises an educational exhibit illustrating the methods in use in Western schools. I have no doubt that teachers from the East will find invigoration in the educational atmosphere which is sure to prevail at Omaha. The program of the convention has evidently been planned with great care, and is far superior in attractiveness to that of the N. E. A. The only deterrent feature about the Omaha convention, in so far as teachers in the East are concerned, is the cost of the journey, although the railways west of Chicago offer the usual reductions in fare.</p>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>