<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Trans-Mississippi International Exposition, Omaha, June to November, 1898</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">Art, Manufacturing, Mechanics, Commerce, Science, Music: Illustrating the Progress of the West.</title>
                <author><forename></forename> <surname></surname></author>
                <principal>Timothy Schaffert</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>transmiss.book.tmie.1898</idno>
                <authority>Trans-Mississippi and International Exposition of 1898</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2013 by University of any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">Scanned by The University of California Libraries.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <repository></repository>
                        <idno></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <history>
                        <provenance>Omaha Public Library</provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">Trans-Mississippi International Exposition, Omaha, June to November, 1898</title>
                    <title level="m" type="sub">Art, Manufacturing, Mechanics, Commerce, Science, Music: Illustrating the Progress of the West.</title>
                    <author><forename></forename> <surname></surname></author>
                    <publisher>s.n.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>S.l.</pubPlace>
                    <extent>32</extent>
                    <date when="1898">1898</date>
                    <note type="source"><hi rend="italic">Trans-Mississippi International Exposition, Omaha, June to November, 1898: Art, Manufacturing, Mechanics, Commerce, Science, Music, Illustrating the Pprogress of the West</hi>. S.l.: s.n., 1898.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                 <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>books</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-03-05"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2012"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
<text>

<front>
<div type="cover">
<pb n="unnumbered" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.001"/>

<p>TRANS-MISSISSIPPI INTERNATIONAL EXPOSITION</p>

<p>OMAHA JUNE TO NOVEMBER 1898</p>

<p>ILLUSTRATING THE PROGRESS OF THE WEST.</p>

<p>ART</p> 
<p>MANUFACTURING</p>
<p>MECHANICS</p>
<p>COMMERCE</p>
<p>SCIENCE</p>
<p>MUSIC</p>

</div>
</front>

<body>

<pb n="2" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.002"/>

<p>Trans-Mississippi and International Exposition.</p> 

<p>JUNE TO NOVEMBER, 1898.</p> 

<p>OFFICERS.</p> 
<p>GURDON W. WATTLES...President</p> 
<p>ALVIN SAUNDERS Resident...Vice-Pres't</p> 
<p>HERMAN KOUNTZE...Treasurer</p> 
<p>JOHN A. WAKEFIELD...Secretary</p> 
<p>CARROLL S. MONTGOMERY...General Counsel</p> 

<p>EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE.</p> 
<p>ZACHARY T. LINDSEY...Chairman and Manager Department Ways and Means</p> 
<p>EDWARD ROSEWATER...Manager Department Publicity and Promotion</p> 
<p>FREEMAN P. KIRKENDALL...Manager Department Buildings and Grounds</p> 
<p>EDWARD E. BRUCE...Manager Department Exhibits</p> 
<p>ABRAM L. REED...Manager Department Concessions and Privileges</p> 
<p>WILLIAM N. BABCOCK...Manager Department Transportation</p> 

<p>T. S. CLARKSON, General Manager.</p> 
<p>WALKER &amp; KIMBALL, Architects-in-Chief.</p> 

<p>UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT COMMISSION.</p> 
<p>Department of Agriculture...J. H. Brigham, President of Commission</p> 
<p>Treasury Department...C. E. Kemper</p> 
<p>Department of the Interior...F. W. Clarke</p> 
<p>State Department...W. H. Michael</p> 
<p>Smithsonian Institution and National Museum...F. W. True</p> 
<p>Department of Justice...Frank Strong</p> 
<p>Post Office Department...J. B. Brownlow</p> 
<p>War Department...Capt. Henry C. Ward</p> 
<p>Navy Department...Lieut. Commander E. M. Stedman</p> 
<p>Fish Commission...Wm. de C. Ravenel</p> 
<p>Life Saving Station...Capt. H. M. Knowles</p> 

<p>W. V. Cox, Secretary, Omaha.</p> 

<p>PRESIDENTS OF STATE COMMISSIONS.</p> 
<p>Arizona...T. J. Barkeley...Phoenix</p> 
<p>Arkansas...W. G. Vincenheller...Little Rock</p> 
<p>California...M. H. DeYourig...San Francisco</p> 
<p>Colorado...Gov. Alva H. Adams...Denver</p> 
<p>Florida...Geo. W. Wilson...Jacksonville</p> 
<p>Georgia...W. J. Northen...Atlanta</p> 
<p>Idaho...W. P. Shawhan...Payette</p> 
<p>Illinois...Clark E. Carr...Galesburg</p> 
<p>Indiana...Frank B. Von Behren...Evansville</p> 
<p>Iowa...S. H. Mallory...Chariton</p> 
<p>Kansas...Geo. W. Glick...Atchison</p> 
<p>Kentucky...C. N. McElroy...Bowling Green</p> 
<p>Louisiana...C. Harrison Parker...New Orleans</p> 
<p>Maryland...Thomas J. Shryock...Baltimore</p> 
<p>Minnesota...J. L. Gibbs...Geneva</p> 
<p>Missouri...John A. Knott...Hannibal</p> 
<p>Montana...W. H. Sutherlin...Helena</p> 
<p>Nebraska...William Neville...North Platte</p> 
<p>Nevada...H. B. Maxson...Reno</p> 
<p>New Jersey...Robert Mitchell Floyd...Jersey City</p>
<p>New Mexico...L. B. Prince...Santa Fe</p> 
<p>New York...Chauncey M. Depew...New York City</p>
<p>North Carolina...Hon. J. L. C. Harris...Raleigh</p>
<p>North Dakota...C.A. Lounsberry...Fargo</p> 
<p>Ohio...H. E.Valentine...Bucyrus</p> 
<p>Oklahoma...J. C. Post...Kingfisher</p>
<p>Oregon...W. S. Mason...Portland</p> 
<p>South Dakota...A. McKinney...Lead City</p> 
<p>Tennessee...Theodore Cooley...Nashville</p>
<p>Texas...S. J. T. Johnson...Dallas</p>
<p>Utah...L. W. Shurtliff...Ogden</p>
<p>Washington...Geo. W. Thompson...Tacoma</p>
<p>West Virginia...B.W.Peterson...Wheeling</p>
<p>Wisconsin...John C. Koch...Milwaukee</p>
<p>Wyoming...Joseph M. Carey...Evanston</p>

<pb n="3" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.003"/>

<p>The Trans-Mississippi Exposition.</p> 

<p>[From Harper's Weekly, Copyright 1898 by Harper &amp; Brothers.]</p> 

<p>STAND here this rare first day of June, 
beneath this cloudless sky of the 
West, and look far down this noble 
court, with its great buildings, massive 
and magnificent, classic in their architecture and rich in ornament, their 
snowy facades mirrored in the long 
lagoon that stretches away two 
thousand and more feet to the fountain playing before the splendid public 
building erected by the general government in 
recognition of the progress and the power of 
the great West. It is indeed a fair sight.</p> 

<p>Just a moment ago the President of 
the United States touched a tiny electric 
button in the capital city of the nation, 
and now the machinery of a great exposition is in play, responsive to his finger. Turning from the toil of 
war to the noble pursuits of peace, he has set in motion the energies 
of one of the most important expositions of any day.</p> 

<p>The red-suited members of the Marine Band from Washington 
have played sonorously, the chorus of singers have sung, and the 
speakers have spoken, and the vast audience has rendered its 
response of applause the Trans-Mississippi Exposition, has begun. 
Just as one expects to find in a new Western town tokens at 
every turn of the spirit of Western enterprise, so one quite naturally 
expects to find evidences, of sectional indeed, of national thrift 
and enterprise in this exposition now under way in this hustling, 
rushing, bustling Western city of Omaha. Enterprise and sincerity 
seem to me to dominate in this really quite remarkable fair. If the 
people of this region had done nothing more than afford this fine 
token of sincerity in fulfilling promises, it would have been worth 
the pains and the millions that have gone into it. In carrying out 
the plans of this exposition, those in charge have had two important 
advantages immense area for grounds and cordial assistance. 
Nearly or quite two million five hundred thousand dollars have been 
expended in preparing this exposition.</p> 

<p>Nearly as many acres of ground as Paris will have for her 
exposition in 1900 200 acres, to be precise bordering the edge of 
a bluff, with the lazy, mud-stained Missouri in the distance, have 
given fine opportunity for the development of the exterior scheme 
of the exposition. The grounds where the more important buildings 
stand are in the form of a great quadrangle over two thousand feet 
in length, and perhaps five hundred and fifty in width. In the 
central portion of this lies a lagoon. Bordering it are fme stretches 

<pb n="4" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.004"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.004.figure.001">
<p>PHOTOGRAPH BY RINEHART. UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="5" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.005"/>

of turf, with much promise of bloom when the natter summer comes, 
and at their edge rise beautiful buildings, snowy white, large, 
artistic, architecturally exquisite. Strong men in architecture from 
various American cities have united to produce about the sides of 
this long lagoon the most imposing and attractive series of buildings 
ever erected for similar purposes in America, save for the buildings 
which distinguished the Columbian Fair above all other expositions 
of the century.</p> 

<p>The quadrangle lies east and west, and at the eastern end, 
lying at right angles, are the State buildings, structures highly 
creditable to the dozen or more Western commonwealths which are 
represented. Beyond the State buildings that inevitable feature of 
the modern exposition, the Midway, displays its manifold attractions.</p> 

<p>Perhaps the candid Nebraskan would tell you in a moment of 
frank contriteness that the prime object of this exposition was to 
boom Omaha. And yet this is not an exposition of the common 
commercial type. It is something much higher, and keenly sympathetic with higher elements of life.</p> 

<p>Had there been no White City at the lower end of Lake 
Michigan, this must easily have been the most striking and important public enterprise of the kind in the history of American fairs.</p> 

<p>Beginning at the viaduct over one of the city streets crossing 
through the grounds, the buildings stretch away in white beauty 
along the lagoon. The buildings are large, imposing indeed, and so 
cleverly treated in their adornment of staff that they quite completely carry out the illusion of permanency. They are fitted out 
for the best possible display of the exhibits of home and foreign 
tokens of the world's progress. Over three hundred thousand 
square feet of space had been contracted for before the exposition 
opened. To your right as you look down the great quadrangle the 
snowy buildings extend until they fall into a fine perspective at the 
extreme western end cut by the Government Building, a vast 
structure five hundred feet in length. First the Electrical and 
Machinery Hall, then the Manufactures Building, the Administration 
Building, Building of Agriculture ; then the immense Government 
Building stretching across the whole western end of the court. At 
its right, continuing on around the court, comes the Fine Arts 
Building, of a noble type of architecture and admirably suited to its 
purpose, the tall arched entranceway, the arch of States, rising 
opposite the Administration Building, then the Building of the Liberal 
Arts, the Mines and Mining Building, and at the eastern end, at the 
viaduct, the Auditorium for holding public meetings.</p> 

<p>Utility and art have been capitally combined in these buildings. 
They have the general appearance of permanency in cornice and 
wall and massive pillar to give them an air of noble strength, while 
at the same time they are so admirably arranged interiorly that the 
best opportunity is afforded of display, whether it be the newest 
wrinkle in electricity, or the widest scope of modern mining, or the 
best in art, or the richest in husbandry.</p> 

<p>Connecting important buildings of the quadrangle are long 
shady colonnades pillared and canopied in the all-pervasive staff, and 

<pb n="6" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.006"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.006.figure.001">
<p>PHOTOGRAPH BY RINEHART. EAST END TOWERS AND COLONNADES.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="7" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.007"/>

yet massive and lasting to the eye. The great extent of the grounds 
would make walking from building to building decidedly unpleasant 
in shine of sun or time of rain, were it not for these colonnades. 
At either end of the great lagoon they spring into arched form, 
adding a striking note of beauty to the general view.</p> 

<p>Here and there about the grounds, so disposed as to interfere in no degree with the general architectural effect, 
are smaller buildings, some of them devoted to the interests of trade, 
and all of them delightfully novel and interesting.</p> 

<p>But at no point has the prevailing good taste been allowed to 
lapse. Novelty has not been allowed to displace elegance, nor has 
any freakishness been given play. Dignity and harmony characterize the buildings and the arrangements of the grounds of the 
exposition. Over on the Midway ample scope has been afforded for 
such display as suggests the incongruous or the unreal, and even 
here there is apparently a steadfast purpose toward fidelity of 
representation.</p> 

<p>Taken all in all, the general impression of this exposition 
must be decidedly satisfactory.</p> 

<p>In a deeper sense, it would seem to be an exposition of much 
significance, illustrating, as it does, the commercial, the manufacturing, the agricultural, and the mining progress of a section of the 
country a vast resourceful empire in itself.</p> 

<p>The opening-day of the exposition, June 1, brought many 
thousands of people from the regions roundabout, as well as a liberal 
proportion of Omaha's one hundred and fifty thousands of inhabitants. 
One would hardly believe it possible a musket was in the hands of 
the nation, to look out over the great court on the opening-day, and 
see the assembled thousands. Reduced rail rates have, and will 
have, no doubt, their influence in attracting people, aside from the 
genuine beauty of the exposition, while nearly one hundred national 
conventions medical, humanitarian, religious, ethical, commercial, 
and the like will add their thousands to the throngs. So, take it 
all in all, Omaha promises to have her hands full this summer. 
The exposition closes on the ist of November.</p> 

<p>The exposition grounds are easily accessible by electric railway from the downtown part of the city.</p> 

<p>Taking advantage of experiences in electrical effects produced 
at other expositions, the managers of this department have provided 
an admirable display, both in the ornamentation of the buildings 
with innumerable lights, and in producing novel and striking effects 
in the fountain immediately in front of the Government Building at 
the western end of the ground.</p> 

<p>It would not be easy to estimate the value of such an 
exposition as this in illustrating to the nation at large the immense 
resources of the region which lies in the great Mississippi basin, and 
contiguous to it. The railroad trains, which these weeks past have 
been entering the grounds, and stopping now atone, now at another, 
great building, to unload immense boxes of exhibits, have brought 
their freightage from many States, and from a vast region of country. 
These exhibits o f the mining, the manufacturmg p the agriculture 

<pb n="8" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.008"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.008.figure.001">
<p>PHOTOGRAPH BY RINEHART. GRAND COURT (LOOKING WEST).</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="9" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.009"/>

the forestry, the horticulture, the commerce, the business of this 
vast region, from the Canadian line to the Gulf of Mexico, are not 
mere advertising dodges. The States themselves, through appropriations, have provided the funds to show to the world the best of 
the material resources of their commonwealths; and while art and 
music and all phases of the aesthetic have not been neglected, it is 
perhaps this fine panorama of the material West which is here 
afforded, that most will interest. Cast in a different figure, this 
Trans-Mississippi Exposition is an epitome of the wealth and not 
only of the wealth, but of the progress of the great central region 
of the nation.</p> 

<p>One of the speakers at the opening of the exposition put the 
progress of the region in a nutshell when he made note of the fact 
that in the land where, only fifty years ago, the Indians wandered at 
will, there are now 22,000,000 people, with an aggregated wealth of 
twenty-two billions of dollars.</p> 

<p>In the telegram which President McKinley sent to the 
exposition, after setting in motion its machinery, he paid a tribute, 
for which the success of this exposition will give warrant, when he 
said that nowhere have the unconquerable determination, the selfreliant strength, and "the sturdy manhood of American citizenship 
been more forcibly illustrated than in the achievements of the people 
of the region this exposition exploits.</p> 

<p>The corner-stone of the exposition was laid on Arbor Day, 
1897, so that the vast enterprise has been accomplished in a year's 
time. Many of the States of the region have contributed liberally 
to the exposition in the way of suitable buildings, while the general 
government appropriates $200,000 for its building, and in it has 
placed exhibits of great interest. The government has also taken 
official notice of the exposition in the issuance of a series of postage 
stamps, from one cent to $2, inclusive, commemorative of the event. 
Over three hundred million of these stamps were ordered for the 
first installment. The designs on the stamps are appropriate to the 
great West and its progress, illustrating phases of pioneer life.</p> 

<p>W. S. HARWOOD.</p> 

<p>ELECTRIC FOUNTAIN "NAUTILUS."</p> 

<p>AN electric fountain in the west end of the lagoon stands directly 
before the noble building of the United States Government. 
The fountain is designated "Nautilus." Neptune is seated on high, 
viewing his realm with regal dignity. Before him riot his captive 
waters in holiday attire, assisted by the rainbow subjects of a rival 
sovereign. Innumerable sprays of vari-colored crystal fluid dart 
forth in rapid sequence, now bursting into flaming red, then quieting to subdued mother-of-pearl, and again offering a bouquet of. 
myriad shades to the water-god.</p> 

<p>The lighting of the exposition grounds and buildings was 
consigned to the charge of Mr. Luther Stieringer, a well-known 
electrical expeft, who has been connected with the illuminations 

<pb n="10" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.010"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.010.figure.001">
<p>PHOTOGRAPH BY RINEHART. LOOKING NORTHEAST FROM LIBERAL ARTS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="11" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.011"/>

feature of all the large expositions, and particular the World's Fair 
where Mr. Stieringer was consulting electrical engineer. His 
original conceptions at Chicago were the chief delight of the thousands of visitors.</p> 

<p>The electrical illuminations in the Grand Court excel any 
former achievement, without a single exception. They form the 
crowning feature of the exposition.</p> 

<p>UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT BUILDING.</p> 

<p>THE United States Government Building partakes 
of the classic style, the Ionic order being used. 
It is arranged in three sections, that at the center 
having a frontage on the lake of 208 feet, and a 
height to top of balustrade over cornice of 58 feet, 
having a depth of 150 feet. The main entrance 
facing the center of the basin is reached by a broad 
flight of steps and through a colonnade. The 
entrance is flanked on either side by pavilions 
capped by richly decorated domes. The main 
building is surmounted by a colossal dome, which 
towers far above all other buildings. This dome 
is capped by an heroic figure representing "Liberty 
Enlightening the World," and at night this figure 
is lighted by electricity, the torch being 178 feet above the ground, 
Total length of the building 504 feet.</p> 

<p>THE GOVERNMENT EXHIBIT.</p> 

<p>The Government exhibit is most comprehensive, giving ocular 
demonstration of all the functions of government through the various 
Cabinet Departments, State, Treasury, War, Navy, Postoffice, 
Interior, Justice and "Agriculture; through the Fish Commission, the 
Smithsonian Institution and its kindred the National Museum and 
the Zoological Park. The exhibits of the various departments are 
most complete, interesting and instructive. The thoughtful student 
of our form of government and its executive departments finds 
here an epitome in picture, autograph, wax figure, and relic of the 
growth, development and history of our nation. Portraits of the 
Presidents, of the Secretaries of State, originals of presidential 
proclamations from the days of Washington, the original rough draft 
of the Declaration of Independence, letters from the rulers of the 
globe to the United States Government, and rare documents from 
the archives of the Department of State are gathered here in compact 
form, for the instruction and entertainment of Americans. Indian 
curios, illustrating the habits and customs of aborigines, from Alaska 
to San Diego, and from ocean to ocean, together with evidences of 
the industry of the Geological Survey; the progress of education^ as 

<pb n="12" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.012"/>

noted by the Bureau of Education; and models from the Patent 
Office, interest every visitor of the Interior Department exhibit. 
Samples of currency, past and present, lighthouse models, and illustrations of the life-saving service are contributed by the Treasury 
Department. The War Department has not neglected the exposition, and shows projectiles, weapons of warfare, ammunition, 
signal corps utensils, and wax figures of uniformed soldiers from the 
days of the Puritan, in 1620, to the present natty regular. The 
models of the Maine and other great war vessels, supplemented by 
samples of the ordnance of the Navy Department are the conspicuous 
feature of the Navy exhibit. The Postoffice Department delights 
philatelists, particularly, with its complete series of United States 
stamps, and models showing the growth and development of the 
postal service, from the pony express to the modern postoffice car. 
Portraits of the Judges of the Supreme Court, past and present, and 
rare documents from the Department of Justice, keep the lawyers 
eagerly looking over the display of this branch of the government. 
The Agricultural Department devotes its attention particularly to an 
illustration of the practical workings of its bureaus and divisions. 
Probably the rarest collection to the average visitor is that presented 
by the Smithsonian Institution devoted to ethnology and anthropology, 
though the specimens from the National Museum in the divisions of 
biology and geology interest students of natural history. The Fish 
Commission has arranged the most attractive showing, and here 
crowds gather continually to watch the gambols of live fish from 
both salt and fresh waters.</p> 

<p>SOUVENIR COINS.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.012.figure.001">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.012.figure.002">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>A highly interesting feature of 
the Treasury Department exhibit is a 
coin stamp in operation. Here visitors 
witness the stamping 
of the Exposition 
Souvenir Coins. 
The medallion was 
made after a composite head, the creation of an eminent artist, from the photographs of 
forty-four beautiful young women, native of the twenty-four 
Western States and Territories. It idealizes the highest type of 
Western young womanhood. On the obverse side appears an Indian 
in the act of spearing a buffalo. The two illustrations not only form 
a very attractive pocket-piece or watch ornament, but indicate 
forcibly the strides of Western civilization in the past fifty years. 
In addition to these, the government will also have a number of 
gold, bronze and silver medals struck off as awards to exhibitors, 
which will bear appropriate emblems and descriptions. A series 
will also be issued for each of the departments into which the 
exhibits are divided.</p>

<pb n="13" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.013"/>

<p>FOREIGN EXHIBITS.</p>

<p>By direction of President McKinley, the State Department 
extended special official invitations to the rulers of foreign nations, 
requesting them to participate in the exposition. The invitation was 
very generally accepted, and, while the foreign exhibits are by no 
means equal to those at the World's Fair, they exceed, in extent 
and character, those at the other expositions held in America, and 
the visitor will find the following foreign nations represented with 
special exhibits: Canada, France, Hawaii, the Central American 
Republics, the South American Republics, Austria, England, Belgium 
and Switzerland. On the Midway, Japan, China, and several other 
Oriental countries are strikingly in evidence.</p> 

<p>ARCHITECTURE.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.013.figure.001">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>THE accompanying illustrations convey 
but a vague idea of the attractiveness 
of the splendid structures which the 
genius of architect and builder has 
devised and realized. The general 
effect is superb, and the visitor will 
regret but one thing as his vision 
sweeps through the Grand Court and 
he comprehends the magnitude and 
beauty of the buildings, their artistic 
grouping, and the exquisite harmony 

of color, column and cupola, and that regret is that the buildings, 
the statues, the grounds, the pavilions, the colonnades, the landscape 
effects, the electric combinations, the exposition itself, is to endure 
but five months.</p> 

<p>The Grand Court, with lagoon, is the center, around which 
are arrayed the great buildings of the exposition. Entering from 
the south through the Arch of States, and standing upon one of 
the island bridges, the visitor sees at the west end of the Court the 
Government Building, surmounted by the noble American dome, 
topped by a massive statue of " Liberty Enlightening the World." 
To the right is the Agriculture Building, and to the left the Hall of 
Fine Arts, the two connected with the Government Building by 
handsome Pompeian promenades of columns. To the left of the 
Government Building, near the exposition fence, is the building 
erected to display the work of the Life Saving Service.</p> 

<p>Turning to the north, the Administration Arch is directly in 
front. It is the counterbalancing feature to the Arch of States. 
Here are the executive offices of the exposition, the Service Building, Press Building and Fire and Police Building, being immediately 
north on the west side of Twentieth street.</p> 

<p>Next east of the Administration Building is the Manufactures 
Building, and immediately opposite is the Liberal Arts "Building. 
Next eastward, on the north side of the Court, Is the great <choice><orig>struc-

<pb n="14" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.014"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.014.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. THE FOUNTAIN NAUTILUS.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

ture</orig><reg>structure</reg></choice> devoted to machinery and electricity, and immediately across 
the lagoon is the Mines and Mining Building. 

Facing directly east, the eye is pleased by the pavilions and 
kiosks, whose fanciful beauty completes the triumph of the archi
<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.014.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. N. W. SECTION GRAND COURT.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="15" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.015"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.015.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. FINE ARTS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

tects in the construction of this Court. On the south of the 
restaurant viaduct is the Auditorium, with a seating capacity of 
2,500, and on the north is the Boys' and Girls' Building. Booths, 
colonnades, vine-clad columns, stairways, terraces, shrubbery, 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.015.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. MINES AND MINING BUILDING</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="16" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.016"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.016.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. AGRICULTURE BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

shade, lawn, statuary, boats, gondolas, fountains and flags combine 
to connect, enliven and embellish the scene. It is unlike any and 
all other courts of all other expositions, and equals if it does not 
exceed the achievements of the greatest.</p> 

<p>On the bluff tract, overlooking the Missouri valley, <choice><orig>sur-

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.016.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO BY RHINEHART LIBERAL ARTS</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<pb n="17" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.017"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.017.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. THE MANUFACTURES BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

rounded</orig><reg>surrounded</reg></choice> by a beautiful shaded park, adorned with rare shrubbery 
and beautiful lawns, is the Horticultural Building, with its distinctive 
style of architecture and its magnificent showing of fruits, flowers 
and plants, and on this tract are the State buildings, the <choice><orig>Pottawat-

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.017.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. ELECTRICITY AND MACHINERY BUILDING</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<pb n="18" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.018"/>

tamie</orig><reg>Pottawattamie</reg></choice> wigwam, a 
considerable section 
of the Midway, 
special buildings 
and the mammoth 
power plant of the 
exposition.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.018.figure.001">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>Crossing back 
from the east Midway over the north 
viaduct, the visitor 
passes through another division of the Midway, and on the north 
tract, will find the Transportation and Agricultural Implement 
Building, covering five acres of ground and containing a complete 
exposition in itself of transportation appliances and implements 
of husbandry. Near by are the Apiary Building and the Dairy 
Building. On this tract, also, there are various outdoor exhibits illustrating irrigation, sugar beet growing, alfalfa farming and other processes. Here, too, covering the greater part of ten acres, is the 
greatest Indian exhibit ever attempted or likely ever to be attempted. 
This deserves a special description, and it will be found elsewhere 
in this pamphlet.</p> 

<p>It should be remarked, also, that there are several other 
exhibits of unusual interest, such as a tobacco plantation, a cotton 
field and a tea garden. In the main buildings visitors will see the 
practical utility of many appliances which will convert raw material 
into finished product before their eyes. Every building has its 
novelties, and in all parts of the exposition exhibits more interesting to students than Midway amusements are open day after day 
for inspection without expense.</p> 

<p>List of Exposition Buildings.</p>

<p>Government, Life Saving Supervising Architect, Washington.</p> 

<p>Liberal Arts, Auditorium, Press Fisher &amp; Lawrie, Omaha.</p> 

<p>Fine Arts Eames &amp; Young, St. Louis.</p> 

<p>Mines and Mining S. S. Beman, Chicago.</p> 

<p>Manufactures, International Hall J. J. Humphreys, Denver.</p> 

<p>Agriculture Cass Gilbert, St. Paul, Minn.</p> 

<p>Apiary John McDonald, Omaha.</p> 

<p>Dairy F. A. Henninger, Omaha.</p> 

<p>Horticulture Chas. F. Beindorff, Omaha.</p> 

<p>Arch of States, Administration, Service, Hospital, Fire and 
Police, Transportation, Girls' and Boys', South Viaduct, Restaurants and Towers, North Viaduct, Kiosks, Band Stand, Colonnades, 
Electric Fountain, Arch of States Fountains, Lagoon Finish, Ticket 
Booths, etc. Walker &amp; Kimball, Architects-in-Chief, BostonOmaha.</p> 

<pb n="19" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.019"/>

<p>STATE BUILDINGS.</p> 

<p>Nebraska .... Craddock &amp; McDonald, Lincoln and Omaha.</p> 
<p>Illinois and Annex .... Wilson &amp; Marshall, Chicago.</p> 
<p>Georgia .... Dunnavant &amp; Thompson, Nashville and Omaha.</p> 
<p>Iowa .... Josselyn &amp; Taylor, Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p> 
<p>Wisconsin .... Ferry &amp; Clas, Milwaukee, Wis.</p> 
<p>Minnesota .... McLeod &amp; Lamoreaux, Minneapolis, Minn.</p> 
<p>New York .... Dunham Wheeler, New York.</p> 
<p>Kansas .... John F. Stanton, Topeka, Kan.</p> 
<p>Montana .... Leo Bonet, Omaha.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.019.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. COURT, FINE ARTS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<p>HOW TO REACH THE GROUNDS.</p> 

<p>OMAHA has an elaborate and efficient street car system. All its 
lines are operated by electricity. South Omaha and Council 
Bluffs are connected with Omaha directly by motor lines. Three 
distinct motor lines reach the exposition grounds : cars via Sherman 
avenue pass the Sherman avenue entrances; cars on the Twentyfourth street line pass the Twenty-fourth street entrances, and cars 
on the Twentieth street line running via Twenty-fourth street reach 
the grounds. In addition to these regular lines, on big days, and 
whenever the travel demands it, cars make special direct trips from 
Howard and Harney streets to the grounds. Cars leading toward 
the exposition, but not running to it, transfer to the lines running 

<pb n="20" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.020"/>

directly there. The Belt Line Railway, the Northwestern system 
in Nebraska, and the Missouri Pacific Railway pass the grounds 
going in and out of the city, and offer facilities for reaching and 
leaving the exposition, independent of the street car system. Hacks, 
carriages, carry-alls, and all sorts of vehicles carry passengers to 
and from the grounds. Cars returning to the city will await visitors 
at every exit from the exposition grounds. The street railway has 
largely increased its facilities for the occasion, and cars run between 
the city and the grounds on a one-minute schedule. The largest 
crowds can therefore be accommodated without material delays.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.020.figure.001">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>THE INDIAN EXHIBIT.</p> 

<p>CONGRESS has just set apart a special fund of 
$40,000, to be expended in creating at Omaha 
the rarest ethnological exhibition ever attempted in 
this or any other land. Situated in the heart of the 
American Union, within easy reach of all the remaining 
great Indian reservations, it has bet-n possible here, at 
comparatively slight expense, to gather upon the north 
tract a show which would be possible nowhere else in 
America. Sioux from the Dakotas, Omahas and Winnebagos from Nebraska, Sacs and Foxes from Iowa, 
Chippewas from Minnesota, Kickapoos from Kansas, 
Mandans from North Dakota, Crows, Blackfeet, Cheyennes and 
Flatheads from Montana, Sheepeaters, Bannocks and Nez Perces 
from Idaho, Yakimas from Washington, Utes from Colorado, Arrapahoes and Shoshones from Wyoming, Piutes from Nevada, Zunis, 
Moquis, Navajos and Apaches from Arizona and New Mexico, 
Diggers and Mojaves from California, Umatillas from Oregon, and 
representatives from Indian Territory and Oklahoma of Creeks, 
Chickasaws, Choctaws, Seminoles, Cherokees, Osages, Otoes, 
Tonkawas, Kiowas, Comanches, Poncas, lowas, Quapaws, Delawares, Kaws, and other tribes and remnants of tribes congregated 
in their wickiups, tents, tepees, wigwams and cabins, pursuing their 
usual avocations and illustrating their dances, religious rites and 
savage customs, make up a show unlike anything ever before 
adopted as a drawing card for an exposition. Delegations from 
every tribe in the Union will be on the grounds at one time or 
another during the exposition. Each type will be exhibited in appropriate costume with weapons, utensils, industrial appliances, 
ceremonial objects, burial structures and handiwork. Their 
games, their solemn festivals, their peculiar customs and 
their natural surroundings will be reproduced. In connection with 
these illustrations of savage life, of aboriginal habits and customs, and 
the paraphernalia of the plains, mountains, lakes and forests, their 
homes, exhibits of their industrial advancement, their school work 
and other incidents of their slow but sure movement toward civilization and enlightenment, will be prominent. The Indian Department 
at Washington has placed at the disposal of the exposition its 
facilities, office force and field employes for making up this notable 

<pb n="21" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.021"/>

exhibit. The Indian Congress is undoubtedly the strongest, most 
original and most interesting feature of the exposition. It is the 
last opportunity of seeing the American Indian as a savage, for the 
government work now in progress will lift the savage Indian 
into American citizenship before this generation passes into history, 
and the onward march of American civilization and American industry 
will wipe off the maps of the United States the Indian reservation 
and wipe off the face of the earth the reservation Indian.</p> 

<p>The Indian Congress is a permanent feature of the Exposition.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.021.figure.001">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>THE AMUSEMENT SECTION.</p> 

<p>AT no exposition has there been a greater variety 
or greater number of genuinely interesting 
attractions on the Midway. This feature 
of the great show occupies a portion of the 
bluff tract and a portion of the north tract. 
The two sections are connected by the north 
viaduct and each has its unique features, 
picturesque foreigners and novelties. A 
Chinese village, a Moorish village, a German village, a Flemish village and an English 
County Fair, are among the larger of this 
form of entertainment. On the west Midway 
are the streets of all nations, with a Greek 
theatre, Turkish bazaars, Assyrian swordsmen and wrestlers, camels, donkeys and the incidental attractions 
which make all these so attractive to American visitors. On the 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.021.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. NORTH MIDWAY.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<pb n="22" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.022"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.022.figure.003">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. CHINESE VILLAGE.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

east Midway the Streets of Cairo, large as the same show at the 
World's Fair and every way as interesting, keep crowds in good 
humor. On west Midway are a giant seesaw, shooting the chutes, 
the Cyclorama of the Battle of the Monitor and the Merrimac, the 
Old Plantation, Hagenbach's wild animal show, an ostrich farm, 
a Wild West entertainment, rolling the roll, a miniature train, 
Chiquita and a score of novelty entertainments, all specially interesting and making up in variety, instruction and amusement an 
aggregation of shows well worth visiting.</p> 

<p>On the east Midway are the Devil's Dance, Temple of 
Palmistry, the Moorish Maze, Illusion Palace, and a dozen other 
large and small entertainments well counterbalancing the attractions 
on the other side of the viaduct, the two combined Midways offering 
inducements to fun-seekers which can consume days and evenings 
most agreeably.</p> 

<p>On both Midways and, in fact, in all parts of the grounds, are 
restaurants, lunch stands, refreshment halls and places .where the 
weary may rest, the fun-loving may laugh, and even the serious 
may be engaged at all hours from 8 A. M. till 11 P. M. The rules 
strictly prohibit the sale of intoxicants stronger than beer and wine, 
and all the places of resort are under the constant surveillance 
of guards, police and detectives. The Midway is instructive, 
amusing, refreshing and wholesome. The coarse features complained of at other expositions have been rigidly eliminated.</p> 

<pb n="23" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.023"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.023.figure.001">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>THE GREAT EXHIBITS.</p> 

<p>WHILE every building contains 
much of interest, and no single great building can be systematically inspected in less than a day, 
some of the exhibits deserve more 
than passing mention. These are 
the Government, already described 
at length, the Agricultural, the 
Mineral, the Manufactures, the Liberal Arts, the Fine Arts, the Electricity, and the Transportation and 
Agricultural Implements.</p> 

<p>The Fine Arts exhibit contains 600 pictures, every one a 
gem, and the whole a gallery of art which must gratify the taste 
and engage the attention of every lover of art. Some of the best 
works of the old masters grace the walls of this building, and among 
modern painters a most judicious selection has been made. With 
an art catalogue and an eye for the beautiful, any man or woman 
can employ a week profitably in this building. No person should 
allot less than a day to this exhibit.</p> 

<p>The Mines Building, located near the eastern end of the Grand 
Court, is an imposing structure, and in it there are displayed exhibits 
illustrating the mining industry in all its phases, giving a comprehensive idea of the wealth of the mineral resources of the West. 
Each large State, as represented by the State Commissioner, shows 
in its own exhibit the characteristic resources of that particular State 
in precious stones. For example, in Utah, the beautiful topaz, of 
shades peculiar to that State, are shown, and various other mineral 
gems, including the last discovered, "variscite," a peculiar opaque 
green mineral, which will probably become as valuable as the turquoise, but it has never been found outside of the border lines of 
Utah. New Mexico exhibits her unequalled resources in turquoise. 
The 214 cut stones shown from one company, in addition to forty 
pieces of the rough turquoise in its enclosing rock, contain among 
them some of the most remarkable specimens of turquoise that have 
ever been known, one of which has been polished for inspection 
here since the opening day of the exposition. Far more important, 
though scarcely more interesting, are the exhibits of gold and silver 
in the Mining Building. The collection has been restricted so as to 
make every specimen show some particular educational feature. 
The collection of gold nuggets from Alaska gives a peculiar study, 
not only to the characteristic shapes of Klondike nuggets, but of the 
peculiar color of the gold from that region, in comparison with nuggets from California, Colorado, and other parts of the country. 
Other gold displays, in the various States, are intended thoroughly 
to demonstrate what great gold producers several of the States in the 
West are, or are likely to become ; and, also, to enable students interested in such lines to become familiar with the various important 
gold-bearing rocks. Further, two States bring with them ton lots of 
low-grade gold-bearing placer dirt, to be panned out before the eves, 

<pb n="24" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.024"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.024.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. HORTICULTURE BUILDING, CENTER FACADE.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

of the visitor, to show the processes of panning in detail. The Black 
Hills also show all the various steps of obtaining gold from their most 
extensive, but low-grade deposits.</p> 

<p>The exterior decorations of the Agricultural Building are characteristic of the exhibits within. Classic statuary, representing the 
seasons, garlands of fruits and flowers, bas relief figures of bull's 
heads and barn-yard fowls, with inscriptions appropriate to agriculture, adorn the pediments, panels and spandrels of this magnificent structure. Corn being King in the prairie States, naturally it 
is used largely in the decorations, yet cereals of every kind are employed to good effect. Marked skill is shown in the friendly rivalry 
by the different States in the graceful arrangement of exhibits. 
Liberty bells, canopies, spinning tops, candelabra, flags, statues, 
cornucopias and hour glasses in parti-colored corn, wreaths, festoons, 
scrolls and arabesques of wheat, barley, oats and rye, make the 
interior rich in design. A table spread with Nebraska food products, 
surrounded by a family dressed in the latest style of corn-husk 
clothing and seeds, attracts a great deal of attention. A cannon, 

<pb n="25" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.025"/>

with ammunition of glass balls filled with grain, speaks "For Cuba," 
while near by a corn-blade American flag floats gracefully. Minnesota's flour and Nebraska's sugar beets, and the product therefrom, 
show what prairie sunshine will draw from earth's dark laboratory. 
Texan birds and butterflies of brilliant coloring lighten the sombre 
effect of dark-haired animals; fruits from Utah, New Mexico, and 
other States of the Southwest, give evidence of a growing industry 
in semi-arid regions. A miniature electric railway meanders around 
the exhibit, placed by one of the great trunk lines, showing 
agricultural resources. Arkansas, Texas and Louisiana show their 
magnificent products of forest and field. Iowa outdoes herself, and 
Nebraska's counties set the pace for all other exhibitors. Pictures 
of Western farm-life make a charming frieze, and the flag drapery 
is particularly effective. Oregon's forestry display is, perhaps, the 
most unique of all. Imagine a sawed log sixty-two feet long, sections 
of trees six feet in diameter, and others less in girth, but finer in 
grain, are there. Woods and grains show that Oregon is rich in 
resources. And so it goes throughout the great building. The 
agricultural and forestry exhibits are comprehensive and complete.</p>

<p>The Horticultural Building contains an exceptionally interesting exhibit. It stands in the south end of the Bluff tract, looking 
content and serene in its own matchless beauty. Park-like grounds 
flank the structure, which is by far the most ornate and highly decorated building in the grounds. The view from the front is delightful; a fountain plays softly into a basin surrounded by shrubbery, 
and beds of shaded, velvet pansies lying on the grass plots fascinate 
the eye. Inside the main rotunda is roofed by an enormous double 
dome, each surrounded by a circle of Corinthian pillars, forming the 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.025.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. ADMINISTRATION ARCH.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<pb n="26" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.026"/>

imposing and striking effect of an arch within an arch. From the 
middle of the space below the dome there rises an immense pyramid 
of shrubbery. Splendid palms, feathery ferns and the prickly cactus 
carry this miniature mountain well up into the dome, the whole surmounted by a stately century plant of extraordinary size. This 
rotunda is entirely filled with a lavish display of the horticulturists
art, forming a beautiful and representative exhibit.</p> 

<p>The great building devoted to manufactures is crowded with 
exhibits in infinite variety, measuring the rapid growth of the manufacturing industries throughout the West. There are many live 
exhibits of exceptional merit and interest, which engage the closest 
attention of visitors.</p> 

<p>In the Electricity Building, the marvelous development of 
electric science is illustrated in a most fascinating manner. It 
must be remembered that since the World's Fair electricians have 
marched forward with remarkable strides, and the Trans-Mississippi 
Exhibition is, therefore, the greatest ever attempted.</p> 

<p>In the Transportation Building, covering five acres, every 
style of vehicle and every appliance of modern rapid transit is illustrated. Not only so, but the development of the transportation idea, 
from the crude locomotives of the early inventors to the monsters of 
the Baldwin Work's, can be studied from actual examples. In the 
same building the agricultural implement manufacturers have arranged an exhibit of their machines and appliances superior to anything hitherto undertaken.</p> 

<p>The seemingly endless array of exhibits in the Liberal Arts 
Building speaks volumes for the progress made in handicraft of every 
description, while the educational exhibits, which have been installed in the galleries, afford striking evidence of the fact that 
Western people are not unmindful of the importance of a thorough 
system of training for the children of the Trans-Mississippi country.</p> 

<p>PARTICIPATION BY STATES.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.026.figure.001">
<p>PORTICO&amp;#8212;ILLINOIS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>THIRTY-SIX States and Territories have been allotted space 
for exhibits, either in their own 
structures or in the main Exposition 
Buildings. Many of these have 
special buildings upon the bluff tract, 
and several of the States are represented not only by special exhibits 
within their own domicile, but also 
occupy space in the Mines, Agriculture and Manufactures Buildings, 
not to speak of distinctive displays 
of their citizens in the Liberal Arts 
Building.</p> 

<p>Nebraska, the home of the 
exposition, naturally leads off with 
the largest appropriation of funds 

<pb n="27" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.027"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.027.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY REINHART [sic.]. NEBRASKA BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

and the most extensive exhibits. The building represents the 
largest expenditure and is the most pretentious of the States' group. 
In it the visitor will find Nebraska's resources attractively displayed.</p> 

<p>Iowa was the first of the Trans-Mississippi States to make an 
appropriation, and the building of that State stands alongside that 
of Nebraska. Iowa has a State exhibit in addition to representation in the principal buildings, and the western metropolis of Iowa, 
Council Bluffs, has erected a wigwam wherein to house exhibits from 
Pottawattamie County, and to receive and entertain visitors. Iowa 
appropriated $3 5,000 for exposition purposes.</p> 

<p>Illinois, next to Nebraska, appropriated the largest sum for 
the exposition, her contribution being $45,000. Of this $20,000 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.027.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. IOWA BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="28" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.028"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.028.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. ILLINOIS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

was set aside for a building, and as a consequence the Illinois Building attracts wide attention, and is one of the favorites of the group. 
Illinois is present also in several of the large buildings. The 
striking feature of the Illinois Building is a series of large paintings 
of the World's Fair by Keyes.</p>

<p>Minnesota, a lumbering State, houses her State exhibit in a 
Swiss cottage, constructed of Minnesota logs. But she does more, 
for her resources are represented in the Agriculture Buildings and 
in the Manufactures Building, and individual Minnesotans are 
among the foremost exhibitors in the Agricultural Implement 
Building.</p>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.028.figure.002">
<p>PHOTO OF RINEHART. MINNESOTA BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="29" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.029"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.029.figure.001">
<p>NEW YORK BUTLDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>New York, in 
her own building, 
makes a showing 
for her- manufacturers which is creditable to the imperial 
Eastern commonwealth.</p> 

<p>Wisconsin, outside the realm called 
the Trans-Mississippi region, emulating the example of 
Illinois, has a delightfully attractive 
home on the bluff 
tract.</p> 

<p>Georgia, with 
the Cotton Centennial fresh in her mind, expended $10,000 of State money in her 
building, composed of Georgia pine, and it attracts general attention.</p>

<p>Montana has a cosy little building, and occupies 2,000 square 
feet in the Mines Building and 1,000 square feet each in the Agriculture and Liberal Arts Build-ings. Her legislature appropriated 
$15,000; Marcus Daly gave a similar amount, and other enterprising citizens added considerable sums.</p> 

<p>The Kansas Building is ornate and suitable, and the 
exhibits from this State will command attention in nearly all the 
buildings.</p> 

<p>Oregon makes attractive displays in the Mines and Agriculture Buildings. Her State Building is also well worth visiting, and is among the most noteworthy and interesting in the 
States' group.</p> 

<p>The State exhibits, outside the State buildings, are as 
follows : Iowa, Nebraska, Kansas, 
Missouri, Minnesota, California, 
Colorado, South Dakota, North Dakota, 
Oregon, Utah, Montana, Nevada, New 
Mexico, North Carolina, Georgia , 
Washington, Texas, Illinois, Idaho, 
Wyoming, Oklahoma, Indian Territory and others. 
No portions of the 
great exposition are 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.029.figure.002">
<p>WISCONSIN BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<pb n="30" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.030"/>

worthy more 
thoughtful attention than the exhibits of the States and 
their State buildings. Only by visiting them can the 
observer form a 
proper conception 
of variety and extent of resources of 
the commonwealths 
which compose our 
greater West.</p> 

<p>Hotel Facilities.</p> 

<p>THE hotels of 
Omaha, Council Bluffs, and South 
Omaha can readily house and feed 50,000 visitors. The lodging houses 
and private dwellings open to guests, together with the numerous 
restaurants, lunch-stands and boarding houses, afford accommodations for another 100,000. Rates range from $5 per week for room 
and board to $4 per day. The houses offering entertainment near 
the grounds charge from 25 cents to $i per day for rooms, and meals 
can be had near by at from 15 to 75 cents each. A man and wife 
spending a week at the exposition will pay $i per day admission, 
$1.50 per day for room and meals; or say $25 for a week's sojourn. 
They can be even more economical if they choose. Many visitors 
are meeting all their expenses, including railroad fare, at a cost of 
$10 per person per week, and in some cases $7 per week. There 
need be no fear of a want of accommodations.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.030.figure.001">
<p>GEORGIA BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.030.figure.002">
<p>KANSAS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.030.figure.003">
<p>MONTANA BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<pb n="31" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.031"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.031.figure.001">
<p>PHOTO BY RINEHART. PRESS BUILDING.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<p>The Press Building, which stands about a block north of the Administration 
Arch, is headquarters for visiting newspaper men and women. It is provided with 
work rooms, desks, typewriters, and every facility for working newspaper correspondents. On either side of the reception hall are telegraph offices, open day 
and night.</p> 

<p>BOARD OF EDUCATION.</p> 

<p>THE management and control of the congresses of philosophic and scientific 
societies, the educational features of the exposition as well as all branches 
of woman's work, has been assigned to the Board of Education, composed 
exclusively of women. The officers of the Board are as follows: President, Mrs. 
Winona Sawyer, Lincoln; Vice- Presidents, Mrs. Thos. L. Kimball, Omaha; Mrs. 
Kittie L. Dutton, Hastings; Mrs. Frank Johnson, Crete; Secretary, Mrs. Frances 
M. Ford, Omaha. The members of the board were chosen from prominent cities 
in Nebraska and Iowa, and the plan of its organization provides for an advisory 
council to consist of two women from each State outside of Nebraska. The board 
has charge of the exhibits of public schools, kindergartens, manual training and 
industrial schools, art schools, reform schools, and all schools of special instruction. The Boys' and Girls' Building, costing nearly $10,000, of beautiful design, 
was erected by the Board from funds contributed by school children of the Trans-Mississippi States. The woman's clubs of the West have taken up headquarters 
in the building.</p> 

<p>OMAHA AS A RAILROAD CENTER.</p> 

<p>FOURTEEN lines of railway converge at Omaha from all directions. Over 
eighty passenger trains arrive and depart each day, of which sixty are 
through trains.</p> 

<p>The following is a list of the railroads entering Omaha:</p> 

<p>Union Pacific.</p> 
<p>Burlington &amp; Missouri River Railroad.</p> 
<p>Chicago, Burlington &amp; Quincy.</p> 
<p>Chicago, Milwaukee &amp; St. Paul.</p> 
<p>Chicago &amp; Northwestern.</p> 
<p>Chicago, St. Paul, Minneapolis &amp; Omaha.</p> 
<p>Chicago, Rock Island &amp; Pacific.</p> 
<p>Fremont, Elkhorn &amp; Missouri Valley.</p> 
<p>Kansas City, Pittsburg &amp; Gulf.</p> 
<p>Kansas City, St. Joseph &amp; Council Bluffs.</p> 
<p>Missouri Pacific.</p> 
<p>Omaha Bridge &amp; Terminal.</p> 
<p>Sioux City &amp; Pacific.</p> 
<p>Wabash.</p> 

<pb n="32" xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.032"/>

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.032.figure.001">
<p>CITY HALL.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure> 

<p>THE EXPOSITION CITY.</p> 

<p>Omaha was founded in 1854. It is to-day one 
of the most important commercial distributing centers 
in the Central West.</p> 

<p>U. S. census population 140,452.</p> 

<p>Within the limits of Omaha there are 24J square 
miles.</p> 

<p>There are 67 miles of well-lighted, well-paved 
streets; 600 miles of graded streets; 120 miles of 
sewers.</p> 

<p>Original cost of public improvements, $10,026435; expenditures for 1897, over $400,000.</p> 

<p>Omaha has 200 miles of water mains; pumping 
capacity 22,000,000 gallons daily.</p> 

<p>Omaha's public buildings represent an investment of over $2, 500, 000.</p> 

<p>Omaha is the third largest live stock market in America. Receipts for the 
year 1897 were: Cattle, 825,689; hogs, 1,594,038; sheep, 612,803; horses and 
mules, 6,632; total number of cars, 60,083.</p> 

<p>Value of annual product of South Omaha packing houses, $75,000,000.</p> 

<p>The smelting and refining works are the largest in the United States; annual 
output from $12,000,000 to $20,000,000.</p> 

<p>Annual product of Omaha manufactories exceeds $80,000,000 in value.</p> 

<p>There are 120 wholesale houses; aggregate capital, $10,000,000; total annual 
sales, $40,000,000.</p>

<p>Total clearings for 1897, as reported by the clearing house, $243,152,000.</p> 

<p>Fourteen railways converge at Omaha; 80 passenger trains arrive and depart 
daily; five railways maintain headquarters at Omaha; the Burlington union depot 
now under construction will cost $400,000. There are 215 miles of telegraph wire; 
1,000 of single telephone wire, 20,000 feet of cables, and 93 miles of pole lines; 
underground system of 48,000 feet of cables, 33,313 of trench, equal to 1,724 miles 
of single wire.</p> 

<p>There are 95 miles of electric car lines, reaching all points of interest, 
Elmwood, Riverview, and Hanscom Parks, and the city of Council Bluffs. Omaha's 
public parks embrace 560 acres.</p> 

<p>Total U. S. revenue collections for the six months ending December 31, 1897, 
$1,310,739.61.</p> 

<p>Tax on distilled spirits in bond, $622,440.50.</p> 

<p>Estimated custom duties collected at the port of Omaha during the last fiscal 
year, $736,117.15.</p> 

<p>Eighty-six railway postal clerks report to the Omaha office.</p>
 
<p>Omaha is military headquarters of the Department of the Missouri; Ft. Crook, 
recently completed at a cost of $800,000, is garrisoned by eight companies; a large 
army supply depot is maintained in Omaha.</p> 

<p>Omaha has fifty public and parochial schools, and eleven colleges; the 
public school buildings cost $1,500,000.</p> 

<p>There are 120 church edifices and mission houses; aggregate Sunday attendance 
30,000.</p> 

<p>The public library contains 52,304 volumes. The art and curio col'ection, bequeathed by the late Byron Reed, is valued at 
$1,000,000.</p> 

<p>Lininger art gallery is one of the most 
noted in the West.</p> 

<p>The Coliseum has a seating capacity of 
12,000. It is one of the largest convention 
halls in the United States.</p> 

<figure xml:id="transmiss.book.tmie.1898.032.figure.002">
<p>DOUGLAS COUNTY COURT HOUSE.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>