<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transmiss.news.owh.18980306">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Trans-Mississippi Exposition Stamps</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename> <surname></surname></author>
                <principal>Timothy Schaffert</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>transmiss.news.owh.18980306</idno>
                <authority>Trans-Mississippi and International Exposition of 1898</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2013 by University of any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">Text transcribed from Wakefield Scrapbook page: TMI04565.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>

                 <msDesc>
                      <msIdentifier>
                           <settlement></settlement>
                           <repository></repository>
                           <idno></idno>
                      </msIdentifier>
                      <history>
                           <provenance>Omaha Public Library</provenance>
                      </history>
                 </msDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Trans-Mississippi Exposition Stamps</title>
                    <title level="j">Omaha World-Herald</title>
                    <author><forename></forename> <forename type="middle"></forename> <surname></surname></author>
                    <publisher></publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Omaha, NE</pubPlace>
                    <extent>1</extent>
                    <date when="1898-03-06">6 March 1898</date>
                    <biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
                    <note type="source">"Trans-Mississippi Exposition Stamps." <hi rend="italic">Omaha World-Herald</hi> 6 Mar. 1898.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>newspapers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-04-04"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2012"><name>Laura Weakly</name>Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>

<pb n="unknown" xml:id="transmiss.news.owh.18980306.001"/>

<p>TRANS-MISSISSIPPI EXPOSITION STAMPS</p>

<p>The designs for the exposition stamps are such as will make them not only at-tractive in appearance, but deserving of preservation as souvenirs of the great west. The 1-cent stamp will be simple in design, yet it makes a very pretty picture. It will represent the early Jesuit missionary and pioneer, Father Marquette, standing on the banks of the Mississippi river. The drawing is from a painting by Lamprecht.</p>

<p>The 2-cent stamp will be a little more elaborate and will be a picture of the famous Eads bridge across the Mississippi, at St. Louis and will also show a portion of that city.</p>

<p>The 4-cent stamp has a simple yet a unique design which will commend it to curio hunters. It will be that of an Indian mounted upon a pony and is floor a drawing by Frederic Remington.</p>

<p>The 5-cent stamp will bear on its face a miniature copy of an illustration in Schoolcraft's "History of the Indians" and represents the red men hunting buffalos.</p>

<p>The design of the 8-cent stamp is another typical picture and represents Fremont, "the pathfinder," raising the American flag on the Rocky mountains.</p>

<p>The 10-cent variety will carry one back to early experiences with which many western people are familiar, and will show the hardships of emigrants on the western prairies. The design is from a painting by A. G. Heaton of Philadelphia, and shows an emigrant wagon drawn by a team of horses, one of which has fallen to the ground and is unable to rise. Standing around it are the emigrant, his wife and children, looking on in despair.
</p>
<p>The man who buys a 50-cent stamp will find a mining scene, typical of the mountain regions. There is an old miner and two mules, the latter laden with mining implements.</p>

<p>The $1 stamp shows a herd of cattle fleeing across the prairies in front of a storm.</p>

<p>The $2 stamp represents a harvest scene of the present day in the north-west. The whole set forms a good illustration of the history of the west, both the mountains and the prairies, before and after civilization had set in.</p>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>