<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transmiss.news.odb.1898a">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Exposition and Education</title>
                <title level="a" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>Ella</forename> <forename type="middle">B.</forename> <surname>Perrine</surname></author>
                <principal>Timothy Schaffert</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>transmiss.news.odb.1898a</idno>
                <authority>Trans-Mississippi and International Exposition of 1898</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2013 by University of any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">Text transcribed from Wakefield Scrapbook page: TMI04536</note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>

                 <msDesc>
                      <msIdentifier>
                           <settlement></settlement>
                           <repository></repository>
                           <idno></idno>
                      </msIdentifier>
                      <history>
                           <provenance>Omaha Public Library</provenance>
                      </history>
                 </msDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Exposition and Education</title>
                    <title level="j">Omaha Daily Bee</title>
                    <author><forename>Ella</forename> <forename type="middle">B.</forename> <surname>Perrine</surname></author>
                    <publisher></publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Omaha, NE</pubPlace>
                    <extent>1</extent>
                    <date when="1898">1898</date>
                    <biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
                    <note type="source">Ella B. Perrine. "Exposition and Education." <hi rend="italic">Omaha Daily Bee</hi> 1898.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>newspapers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-03-27"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2012"><name>Laura Weakly</name>Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>

<pb n="unknown" xml:id="transmiss.news.odb.1898a.001"/>

<p>EXPOSITION AND EDUCATION</p>

<p>The leading questions asked by a large number of out-of-town exposition visitors are, first, "Where are the exposition grounds?" and then, "Where is the old capitol site?" For the fame of this historic landmark, with the beautiful view to be obtained from it, seems to have gone abroad. And indeed a little time spent on "Capitol Hill," where our High school now stands, at the beginning of one's stay in I Omaha, is no small help in getting one's bearings. However much one may dislike climbing the steps leading to the High school grounds, the charming vista more than compensates for the effort. It is easy to understand why the founders of the school, whose names are graven on the cornerstone, selected this site. They have been amply repaid for their energy and foresight in planning the structure.</p>

<p>The High school exhibit in the north gallery of the Manufactures building compresshensively sets forth the work in all its various departments. One booth contains the drawing and written work. The other contains a more varied exhibit, including that of the High school cadets, the manual training department and a swinging case of mounted botanical specimens, while the
space reserved by the Board of Education shows views and plans of nearly all the school buildings throughout the city and also the system of blanks used in transacting business and keeping records.</p>

<p>The blanks may be classified under eight heads, as follows: Blanks used by the Board of Education in transacting business; in the business office by the secretary, showing the method of purchasing all supplies, books, stationery, etc., by the superintendent of instruction in directing the work of the schools; by principals, teachers and janitors in making reports, and by the superintendent of buildings in conducting repairs; miscellaneous blanks, including the ones designating "flag days" and others, also forms of diplomas conferred on the completion of High school, kindergarten Ind eighth grade 
courses of study, and certificates issued by the examining committee to successful candidates.</p>

<p>The secretary, Mr. J. M. Gillan, after a careful comparison of the systems used in other cities, considers it very thorough and complete.</p>

<p>In a glass case is seen the elegant silk flag bought by the High school girls, for which the cadet companies contest each year, the victorious battalion 
retaining it for a year. There are two gun racks of rifles, one containing Springfields, the other Remingtons.</p>

<p>By the way, it may be of interest to mention that the soldiers at Fort Crook are so pleased with these gun racks that an effort is being made to induce the 
government to purchase similar ones.</p>

<p>Photographs of the officers of the companies and of "Company Z" entire, composed of girls, in which I have been told membership depends on scholarship, 
complete the exhibit made by the cadets.</p>

<p>With these pictures are hung photographs of the banjo club and foot ball teams of the past few years.</p>

<p>The manual training department displays a well-filled case of finished work, much of which at first glance might be taken for in-laid work, but which the 
instructor, Mr. Wigman, says is jointed cabinet work, as the wood used in inlaid work never exceeds one-thirty-second of an inch in thickness. Dumbbells, 
Indian clubs, vases of all shapes and sizes, fruit stands, napkin rings and paper knives in many colored woods, beautifully polished, are noticed in the 
case. Upon a raised platfrom are foot rests, shoe )lacking cases and tables. One of the tapoles has in the center a chess board, with backgammon and cribbage 
boards at the sides and ends. This department has in prospect a "line exhibit" which will show the successive steps leading up to the finished work.</p>

<p>Drawing, because of the effective way in which it can be mounted, is always an at-tractive feature of school exhibits. Miss Evans, supervisor of mechanical 
and free-hand drawing in the High school, presents the latter under four heads: Nature work,</p>

<p>design, cast work and drawing from life. A little thought shows how each subject naturally follows the one preceding. Nature conventionalized produced design. After facility in cast work is acquired, drawing from life is readily taken up. In the last fellow pupils, particularly cadets in uniform and with rifles, the evidently favorite subjects. While the objects sought in this branch of the work are correctness of outline, a proportion and action rather than a likeness or portriat, a great degree of proficiency is shown in this as well.</p>

<p>A portrait, front view, by James Godfrey, is of especial merit; also one by Estella Brandeis.Elsie Day has  a full length figure. George Barker, Elsie Schwartz, Florence Ferrin and Dorothy Frederickson show good work.</p>

<p>In the drawings from casts may be mentioned a "Venus de Milo" and Michael Angelo's "Dying Slave," by Jeannette Miller and Nelli McMillan, respectively, both of whom have sevearl other pieces in this and other liens equally good. A "Laughing Head of Donatello" is the work of Francis McGavock. Among other having meritorious drawings from casts are Katherine Wiley, Doane Powell and Florence Jordan.</p>

<p>Many artistic designs for wall paper in colors are noticed. Ethel Partridge has a beautifully tinted one in renaissance style; Estella Brandeis a quaint Persian one; Clara Hervey a dainty one in conventionalized thistle leavees and blossoms; Edna F. John one in blue and white; bessie Anders and Ellen Anther, too, have effective designs. All of the designs shown are original. Josephine Biart and Nellie McMillan are represented in water color and Florence Lewis in pen and ink in the mounted pieces.</p>

<p>A volume of compositions or illustrations in pen and ink wash drawings is perhaps the most valuable part of the collection, so far as the pupils are concerned, and of most interest to the public. Subjecst or themes, as in written composition, are assigned some days in advacne of the time required for their completion. Thus they are really tests of skill and knowledge acquired during the year's work.</p>

<p>The "head piece" in the obok is the work of Doane Powell. Pearl Ryley, who designed the cover of the last High School Register; Preston Davison; in fact, all represented in the volume have excellent pieces. The Omaha exhibit as a whole is in charage of Miss Edith Burgess and Miss Laura Jordan, both recent graduate of teh High school.</p>

<p>ELLA B. PERRINE.</p>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>