<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11443">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Royal Visit to the Wild West</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11443</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">Royal Visit to the Wild West</title>
<title level="j">The Morning Post</title>
<pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
<date when="1887-05-12">May 12, 1887</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>


</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>American Indians</term>
<term>Aristocracy (Social class)</term>
<term>Cowboys</term>
<term>Heads of state</term>
<term>Horses</term>
<term>Hunting</term>
<term>Indian weapons</term>
<term>Mexicans</term>
<term>Scouts (Reconnaissance)</term>
<term>Shooting</term>
<term>Tomahawks</term>
<term>Visits of state</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Alexandra, Queen, consort of Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1844-1925</term>
<term>Argyll, John Douglas Sutherland Campbell, Duke of, 1845-1914</term>
<term>Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1841-1910</term>
<term>Franz, Prinz, Herzog von Teck, 1837-1900</term>
<term>George, Prince, Duke of Cambridge, 1819-1904</term>
<term>Louise, Princess, Duchess of Argyll, 1848-1939</term>
<term>Oakley, Annie, 1860-1926</term>
<term>Red Shirt, 1845?-1925</term>
<term>Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819-1901</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
<change when="2015"><name>Clark, Linda</name>, <name>Hanna, Sam</name> and <name>Adams, Deb</name> Proofreading</change>
<change when="2015"><name>McQuay, Colleen</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11443.001"/>

<head>ROYAL VISIT TO THE "WILD WEST."</head>

<p>The Prince<!--link to Prince of Wales personography--> and Princess of Wales,<ref target="n01">1</ref> accompanied by the Princess Louise of Wales,<ref target="n02">2</ref> the Duke of Cambridge,<ref target="n03">3</ref> the Crown Prince of Denmark,<ref target="n04">4</ref> Duke of Teck,<ref target="n05">5</ref>  and the Marquis of Lorne,<ref target="n06">6</ref> visited the <orgName xml:id="exhibition.am">American Exhibition</orgName> yesterday afternoon, and after having been conducted through the main building the Royal party took up a position on the grand stand to witness a special performance of the Wild West Show. The first part of the programme was a grand processional review, in which the whole of the Indians, cowboys, scouts, and Mexicans connected with the show took part. After riding round at full gallop, the whole of the band formed a long line and advanced, with Colonel Cody at their head, towards the grand stand. A race between a cowboy, a Mexican, and an Indian, on ponies, followed; after which an illustration was given of an attack by Indians on an emigrant waggon with equal vigour, the frontiersmen eventually driving off their assailants. Then came shooting feats by <persName xml:id="oakley.a">Miss Oakley</persName> and <persName xml:id="smith.l">Miss Smith</persName>, a race between frontier girls, and the riding of bucking horses by cowboys. The exciting incident of the attack on the Dradwood<ref target="n07">7</ref> stage coach by Indians, and the rescue by Buffalo Bill and his band of scouts, followed, and after this a realistic representation of Indian camp life was witnessed. The closing scene was the most exciting of the show. In the centre of the arena stood a settler's cabin, the head of the family having, it was to be presumed, just returned from a hunting expedition, when suddenly a hostile Indian appeared, and was promptly shot by the settler. A band of savages immediately rushed from all directions, and, after a desperate combat, the cabin seemed to be on the eve of capture when, with a ringing cheer, Buffalo Bill and his scouts dashed up and dispersed the Indian braves. At the conclusion the principal performers were presented to the Prince and Princess of Wales. The Indians seemed greatly to appreciate the Royal visit, and <persName xml:id="red.shirt">Red Shirt</persName>, to whom the Prince was introduced as the coming chief of the Pale Face Nation, said, through <persName xml:id="irving.w">Broncho Bill</persName>, it made his heart glad that one so high above other men should visit him. Though his skin was red and the pale-faced chief's was white, their hearts were one. The Prince then handed Red Shirt a number of cigarettes, which the latter passed round to his companions. A number of relics of Indian fights were shown to the Royal party, including tomahawks, bows and arrows, and scalps. All the Royal visitors expressed themselves highly pleased with the exhibition, and on leaving the Prince warmly complimented Colonel Cody and the directors, and expressed the wish that the venture would prove a grand success.</p>


</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: The Princess of Wales was Alexandra of Denmark (Alexandra Caroline Marie Charlotte Louise Julia, 1844-1925) who became Queen Alexandra when her husband, the Prince of Wales, became Edward VII, King of Great Britain in 1901.</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: Princess Louise Caroline Alberta (1848-1939), Duchess of Argyll, the fourth daughter and sixth child of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert, was a gifted sculptor and a dedicated advocate of many issues including education of women.</note>   

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: The Duke of Cambridge was Prince George (George William Frederick Charles, 1819-1904), first-cousin of Queen Victoria, who became the Duke of Cambridge in 1850.</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: Frederick VIII (1843-1912), Crown Prince of Denmark for 43 years, became King of Denmark in 1906 until his death in 1912.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: Prince Francis Paul Louis Alexander (1837-1900), a Major-General in the British Army and married to Princess Mary Adelaide of Great Britain, held the title of Duke of Teck from 1871 until his death. </note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: Marquis of Lorne was John George Edward Henry Douglas Sutherland Campbell, 9th Duke of Argyll; he held the title Marquis of Lorne from 1847 to 1900.</note>

<note xml:id="n07">Note 7: The Deadwood stagecoach.</note>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
