<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp09195">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Buffalo Bill On Screen in Indian Fights</title>
                <author></author>
                <principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
                <principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
                <principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
                </distributor>
                <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
                <address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
                <idno type="module"></idno>
                <idno type="project"></idno>
                <availability>
                    <p></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author></author>
                    <title level="a" type="main">Buffalo Bill On Screen in Indian Fights</title>
                    <title level="j" type="main">Rochester Democrat and Chronicle</title>
                    <date when="1917-01-28">January 28, 1917</date>
                    <extent> pages</extent>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository></repository>
                        <idno></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <p> type-written pages</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support></support>
                                <extent> pages
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
                                </extent>
                                <condition>
                                    <p></p></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="type" script="type" medium="type"><p>Media: type</p></handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history><origin></origin>
                        <provenance></provenance>
                        <acquisition></acquisition>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p></p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p></p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>Texts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Newspapers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-10-11"><name xml:id="ed">Dwiggins, Erin</name>Initial Encoding</change>
            
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div1>
                <pb facs="wfc.nsp09195"/>
                <head><hi rend="bold">BUFFALO BILL ON SCREEN IN INDIAN FIGHTS</hi></head>
                <head type="sub">Great Scout in Picture on Avon Theater Bill.</head>
                <head type="sub"><hi rend="bold">MADE AS HISTORY RECORD</hi></head>
                <head type="sub">United States Troopers and Scouts Re-enact, with Indians Scenes of Old Plains Warfare &#8212; American Historical Society Helps</head>
                <p>When patrons of the Avon Theater view the five-reel film picturing the old-time warfare of the Western plains between United State cavalrymen and frontiersmen, chief among is Buffalo Bill, during the first three days of the week, they will, of course, not realize that the head of the producing company that made it, in co-operation with the government and the American Historical Society, has particular pride and sentimental interest in this screen offering.</p>
                <p>He is George K. Spoor, president of the Essanay company.  He was long one of the closest friends of the late Colonel Cody.  After the West became comparatively tame, both Mr. Spoor and Buffalo Bill became showmen, and, although in different fields of entertainment, they became fast friends through the admiration each had for the other's qualities.  When the scheme was conceived to have United States troopers and Indians re-enact some of the scenes of desperate fighting that made the great West a very dangerous and adventurous region a generation or so ago, the government was pleased to co-operate, and the American Historical Society encouraged the undertaking, in order that they might have the film as valuable records for future generations.</p>
                <p>Of course, it was necessary to have men to play the all-important roles of the great scouts of those days.  Clever troopers could have been "made up" for the parts, but it was hoped that a fe wof the surviving scouts, especially Buffalo Bill, could be persuaded to participate.  Colonel Cody, although still vigorous, was getting pretty old, and he had his own big affairs to look after, so he was rather averse to entering the picture.  Finally, however, the influence of the friendship between him and Mr. Spoor prevailed, and he consented.  As a result, not only audiences to-day, but those for many years to come, will be able to see his picturesque figure and thrill with his skilful and daring exploits, it is said, in these exciting scenes.  He and General Nelson A. Miles, a famous old Indian fighter, who commands the troops, stand out as heroes on the film.</p>
                <p>This picture will be shown here for the first time in the Avon, and is the only one having official approval in which the renowned scout ever appeared.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
