<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11518">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Chief No Neck's Story</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11518</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">Chief No Neck's Story</title>
<title level="j">World</title>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<date when="1890-07-30">July 30, 1890</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>
McCracken Research Library, Buffalo Bill Center of the West
</repository>
<idno>MS6.3772.009.04 (Crager scrapbook)</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>American Indians</term>
<term>Atlantic crossings</term>
<term>Passenger ships</term>
<term>Sioux Nation</term>
<term>Translators</term>
<term>United States. Office of Indian Affairs</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Craft, Francis M.</term>
<term>O'Beirne, James R.</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015-09-22"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> and <name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="sh">Hanna, Sam</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11518.001"/>

<head>CHIEF NO-NECK'S STORY.</head>

<milestone unit="line"/>

<head>He Declares Buffalo Bill Treats the Indians Well.</head>

<p>One of Buffalo Bill's Indians sailed up the Bay yesterday with a present of $100 in his pocket and a handsome suit of clothes on his back, and said Buffalo Bill had given them to him with admonition to tell the newspapers a good story when he reached New York. He came on the Kaiser Wilhelm. Springing lightly over the taffrail, he picked up the fresh trail of <persName xml:id="obeirne.j">Gen. J. R. O'Beirne</persName>, Emigration Commissioner, and silently tracked him to his tepee in the Barge Office. 

<figure n="drawing">
  <ab type="credit">H. T. SMITH</ab>
  <p>CHIEF NO NECK.</p>
</figure>

"How! How!" he grunted in fine Sioux linguals. "Me Tahu-Wanicxta: me No-Neck. Minnecour chenumpa mi a cour?"</p>

<p>The General complied and handed him his cigarette case. Then No-Neck, who was billed among the second-cabin passengers as Low-Neck, and laughingly spoken of as Chief Decollet&#233;, proceeded to make himself at home. His handsome silk umbrella&#8212;imported duty free&#8212;was deposited in a corner, his heavy winter overcoat was pulled off and his raven locks were arranged with the aid of a nice pocket-brush and sweetly scented with Parisian musk and he was ready for the council, arranged by cablegram from the other side. Interpreters <persName xml:id="crager.g">Crager</persName> and Father <persName xml:id="craft.f">F. M. Crafts</persName> seated themselves near the chief. No-Neck's appearance was that of an extra good liver, and to prove that he had not been starved by Buffalo Bill he was weighed on the baggage scales of Barney Biglin. Two hundred and six and one-half pounds was his weight. If he did not smoke about one hundred cigarettes a day he might weigh more.</p>

<p> Speaking of the treatment he and his fellows received, he said they were given bread, meat, coffee, tea, milk in cans, butter, rice, barley, prunes and bacon. They also received $25 a month. He got $30 because he was Chief of Police of the Wild West Show. Sick Indians, he said, are sent back to this country. Five have died and are buried in graveyards, with their names painted on slabs. The doctors gave them medicine, but they were afraid of it. They were also afraid to go to hospitals.</p>

<p>"Of all the countries I have been in," said No-Neck, "to me the United States is best. Too little ground for the number of people over there. If Buffalo Bill gets any more Sioux from the reservation he must give them $50 a month."</p>

<p>"What did he tell you when he gave you the $100?" he was asked.</p>

<p>"He said, 'When you go over say that you were treated well.'" was the reply.</p>

<p>"Would you tell a different story for $100?"</p>

<p>"Yes. But they did not teach me to tell this story. What No-Neck has spoken is true. No-Neck loves his own country best and would not go back to the Wild West Show."</p>

</div1>
</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
