<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11308">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Orpheum</title>
                <author></author>
                <principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
                <principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
                <principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
                </distributor>
                <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
                <address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
                <idno type="module"></idno>
                <idno type="project"></idno>
                <availability>
                    <p></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author></author>
                    <title level="a" type="main">Orpheum</title>
                    <title level="j" type="main">The Duluth News Tribune</title>
                    <date when="1914-05-15">May 15, 1914</date>
                    <extent> pages</extent>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository></repository>
                        <idno></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <p> type-written pages</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support></support>
                                <extent> pages
                                    <dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
                                </extent>
                                <condition>
                                    <p></p></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc hands="1">
                            <handNote xml:id="type" script="type" medium="type"><p>Media: type</p></handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                        <typeDesc>
                            <typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
                        </typeDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history><origin></origin>
                        <provenance></provenance>
                        <acquisition></acquisition>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p></p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p></p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>Texts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Newspapers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
                    <term>Essanay Film Manufacturing Company</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
                    <term>Garrison, Lindley M. (Lindley Miller), 1864-1932</term>
                    <term>Lane, Franklin Knight, 1864-1921</term>
                    <term>Tammen, Harry Heye, 1856-1924</term>
                    <term>Bonfils, Frederick Gilmer, 1860-1933</term>
                    <term>Miles, Nelson Appleton, 1839-1925</term>
                    <term>Baldwin, Frank Dwight, 1842-1923</term>
                    <term>Lee, Jesse M.</term>
                    <term>King, Charles, 1844-1933</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
                    <term>Denver (Colo.)</term>
                    <term>Colorado Springs (Colo.)</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-03-04"><name>Dwiggins, Erin</name>Keywords</change>
            <change when="2013-12-12"><name>Dwiggins, Erin</name>Proofreading</change>
            <change when="2013-12-06"><name xml:id="ed">Dwiggins, Erin</name>Initial Encoding</change>
            
            
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>

            <div1 type="type">
                <pb facs="wfc.nsp11308"/>
                <head>ORPHEUM</head>
                    
                    <p>How Colonel Cody ("Buffalo Bill") came to represent the famous Indian wars for the moton picture camera is told in an interesting article in the Denver Post of recent date. The pictures are now being shown at the Orpheum theater, and are creating much interest. They were given their first presentation recently at Denver, and "Buffalo Bill" himself made the introductory speech. Here is the way the post tells of it:</p>
                    
                    <p>"Before the great crowd Colonel Cody ("Buffalo Bill") appeared at the outset and delivered a preliminary address, which was pathetic, humorous, eloquent and illuminative. He gave the history of the pictures with a simplicity and ease that won for him the hearts and the admiration of the hearers.</p>
                    
                    <p>"He had an idea. He thought of his long career on the plains, of the wars he had been in; of the Indian battles which he had fought; of the advance of white civilization through many stirring years, and he thought this page of thrilling American history should be perpetuated for the benefit of this and future generations.</p>
                    
                    <p>"The new art of motion pictures made it possible to reproduce some wonderful fights. But to accomplish all this it was necessary to have the approval and help of the government, a strong financial backing and the sanction of the famous generals who had helped to make history. He heard, while in the wilderness, that the secretary of war was in Colorado. 'So,' said Cody, 'I chased myself down to Denver, met Mr. Garrison, laid down my ideas before him and he gave them cordial approval, promising the hearty support of the war department.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'Later I saw Secretary of the Interior Lane at Colorado Springs and asked his co-operation. He had the Indians under his supervision. He was a necessary factor. He took to the proposition warmly.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'Next I had to have money. It would take $100,000. I didn't have a dollar. I went to Tammen and Bonfils in your city and asked them if they would back me. There was no hesitation.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'Then Tammen and I went east to find the best picture makers the country could produce. We found them in the Essanay people, and Mr. Spoor, the president, gladly agreed to join in the work.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'Then we secured the personal aid, co-operation and support of General Miles, General Baldwin, General Lee, General King and all those Indian fighters with whom I had been associated years ago.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'Backed by the national government, they were as keen as I was for a true historical reproduction of the scenes that resulted in the final surrender of the Indians to the white race. So the work began. The American troops and the American Indians were at our disposal. We had to pay the latter as well. We gave them from $2 to $5 a day each for their services. We left with the Indians some $10,000, so you can see what a costly proposition it is.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'We all, General Miles directing, went to the old fighting ground, and there, with wonderful accuracy, we reproduced, after weeks of work, the most wonderful series of Indian war scenes the world has known.</p>
                    
                    <p>"'When completed, they had first to be shown to the president and his cabinet at Washington, to receive their approval or disapproval, for, if found satisfactory they were to be placed in the archives of the war department and the interior department. Last week, before the cabinet, the leading senators and diplomats, they were shown in the government building and formally indorsed.'"</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>