<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp06439">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Fighting and Trapping</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp06439</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">Fighting and Trapping</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">Buffalo Bill Tells All About Them Out West</title>
<title level="j">Omaha Daily Bee</title>
<pubPlace>Omaha, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<date when="1887-06-25">June 25, 1887</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>


</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Abolitionists</term>
<term>American bison</term>
<term>American bison hunting</term>
<term>American frontier</term>
<term>American Indians</term>
<term>Bowie knife</term>
<term>Cheyenne Indians</term>
<term>Elk hunting</term>
<term>Grizzly bear hunting</term>
<term>Kansas Pacific Railway Company</term>
<term>Military reconnaissance</term>
<term>Oxen</term>
<term>Scouting (Reconnaissance)</term>
<term>Tomahawks</term>
<term>United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Alekse&#301; Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke of Russia, 1850-1908</term>
<term>Carr, E. A. (Eugene Asa), 1830-1910</term>
<term>Rain in the Face, approximately 1835-1905</term>
<term>Yellow Hand, 1850?-1876</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Kansas</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2014-05-19"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="fc">Christianson, Frank</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="sh">Hanna, S.</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp06439.001"/>

<head type="main">FIGHTING AND TRAPPING.</head>

<milestone unit="line"/>

<head type="sub">Buffalo Bill Tells All About Them Out West.</head>

<milestone unit="line"/>

<head type="sub">Some Information Graciously Vouchsafed to <persName xml:id="victoria.q">Her Majesty's</persName> British Subjects by the Hon. W. F. Cody&#8212;Early Blood-Lettings in <orgName xml:id="bleeding.kansas">Bleeding Kansas</orgName>&#8212;Bill as a Trapper&#8212;Hair-Breadth 'Scapes&#8212;Interesting Facts About the Indians Not Generally Known.</head>

<milestone unit="line"/>

<p>W. F. Cody ("Buffalo Bill") in Murray's Magazine<ref target="n01">1</ref> for June: I am frequently asked whether the Indians who accompanied me to this country are old friends of mine, accustomed by a long course of training to the parts they play in my exhibition of the "Wild West." It would be more correct to call them old enemies. Their rehearsals have taken place on the war-path, and possibly they may some day return to it. Their experience of civilization is small; their services are at my disposal for a limited period, never exceeding a year, after which they return to their reserves, richer and possibly wiser men. It is indeed only by obtaining a constant succession of untutored braves that I can insure that freshness of incident and spontaneous action which are so peculiarly characteristic of the red men. Civilization has very mixed effects upon an Indian; if he once learns to speak English he will soon forget his native cunning and pride of race. I find no difficulty in persuading a sufficient number to join me. I explain to them what I want done, and they have perfect confidence in my word that whatever agreement is made will be carried out to the letter. They know that they will be well paid and well fed; in other matters, clothing, for instance, their requirements are small. It is of course, only possible to arrange with them during a period of peace; if they ever go on the warpath again our relations will perhaps be of a different character. But in peace their most relentless enemies can safely traverse their country. They abide honorably by pledges once given, and among them, when the hatchet is buried, treachery is unknown.</p>

<p>This is more than could always be said for the white men in my young days. My father<ref target="n02">2</ref> was killed before my eyes by a coward's hand striking treacherously from behind. I was but a boy of ten at the time; we were living in Kansas, and there was a struggle between the free-state party and the slave owners as to whether slavery should be permitted or not. In some states it was allowed, in others prohibited. As new territories were bought from the Indians or opened up to settlement, pending their subsequent creation into fresh states, the two parties disputed the question so hotly that a kind of guerrilla war commenced between those who were trying to extend slavery into those northwestern territories and free state men, who opposed it. My father was a strong free state man, and in the political agitation which preceded the outbreak of actual hostilities he took a leading part. One day, in 1855, he was speaking at an open-air meeting, I believe the first political meeting held in Kansas; the pro-slavery party mustered strong, but my father made no secret of his views; the temper of the crowd grew violent and threatening; they began to press around the dry goods boxes on which he was standing before a frontier store; while he was trying to pacify the angry mob one of the scoundrels, Charles Dunn<ref target="n03">3</ref> by name, jumped onto the box behind him and stabbed him in the back with a bowie-knife. He died from the wound, and for the moment the murderer escaped, for the sympathy of the mob was with the crime. But a few years afterward, when the civil war broke out, I had my revenge. The pro-slavery party of Kansas joined the southern cause; Charles Dunn was killed, and out of all those who had participated in my father's murder there was only one who escaped death at the hands of 

<pb facs="wfc.nsp06439.002"/>

the free state men.</p>

<p>Thus I had to shift for myself at an early age, and those were days when it was almost impossible to avoid coming into contact with Indians at every turn. I drove a stage, rode the pony-express, took freight across the plains, did whatever I could for a living, and gained a knowledge of every mile of country which none could beat; I got to know the ways of the Indians, too, and they soon knew me. I went trapping and hunting all over their country; they hated the  trappers and were always on the lookout for them, so that it was a dangerous game, and a man always carried his life in his hand on such expeditions. One or two of us would penetrate up the stream in the wildest part of the country, far from any settlements and only inhabited by roving bands of Indians. Choosing the ground, we would build a tog hut, or dugout, as it is called, and set about trapping beaver or hunting buffalo and wapiti. Hundreds of trappers have been killed while setting their traps along a stream or skinning the game they have caught. I have had many a tussle myself, but been as lucky as a man who goes unhurt through a battle in which thousands are killed. When the Indians "jump" you, if you have been on the lookout, there is generally time to get behind a tree, and then make the best fight of it you can.</p>

<p>I remember one occasion, however, when the red men treated me quite genereusly. It was an experience I shall never forget. I was fourteen years old--still only a boy trapper, as one might say--and started on an exhibition with a man named Dave Harrington.<ref target="n04">4</ref> We went right away, 125 miles from any settlement, with a yoke of oxen and a light wagon to carry supplies and haul our furs back. We found a creek where there were lots of game, and there we made our winter camp. On a side of a hill we built a dug-out, and turned the oxen out to graze upon a small island, where we left them; then we began trapping, and did splendidly for a few weeks, everything going well. But one day, while we were out after elk, as we were going round a sharp bend of the creek, I fell so heavily upon a slippery hill slope that I broke the shin-bone of my leg.</p>

<p>Dave Harrington managed to carry me back to the dug-out; but, unluckily, not long before this one of our oxen had slipped upon the ice in trying to cross from the island and received injuries which obliged us to kill it. We had thus only one left, and he was not strong enough to haul me back in the wagon to the settlement. So Dave had to leave me lying in the dug-out, and started upon his journey of 125 miles to get help, promising to be back in twenty days. I had plenty of food and snow water, so there was no fear of my starving. On the eighteenth day, hearing a noise outside, I supposed it was Dave returned before his time, and sang out to let him know I was all right. For answer there sprang into the little dug-out a party of Indians. I was soon susrounded by as many as the hut would hold, and I saw at a glance that they were on the war-path. They began threatening me with knives and tomahawks, and things did not look very bright; then the chief looked in, and I recognized him as "Rain in the Face," an old man whose camp I had once visited. I called out to him that I knew him, and that a year ago I had lived in the same place as he did, and had played with his children. He remembered me, and, jumping into the midst of his warriors, stopped them just as they were about to kill me. "This is only a papoose--a boy!" he exclaimed; "we do not fight with boys, but with men."

<pb facs="wfc.nsp06439.003"/>

So they spared my life; but everything I had in the hut, except some meat, they took away. After this the days came and went, but no Dave Harrington appeared. I feared he must have perished in a storm or been caught by the Indians, for the twentieth day was long past. But he came at last on the twenty-ninth day, bringing a yoke of oxen. He had suffered terribly in the snow drifts; but he persevered through everything, and, putting me in the wagon, conveyed me back safely to the settlement, where I finally recovered. Dave was a brave fellow. He imperiled his life to rescue me, and showed what what one man, whose nerve does not fail him, will sometimes dare for another in that wild country.</p>

<p>During the rebellion the Indians took advantage of the defenseless state of the frontier, and became much bolder in their raids upon our territories. They made no distinction of parties; but saw their opportunity while the whites were fighting, and let themselves loose upon us, as there was no one to stop them. As soon, therefore, as the north had whipped the south our troops were sent straight to the borders to quell the Indians. I knew that part of the country better than most men, and was employed on scouting duty. The difficulty was to find the enemy, who had no fixed quarters; and men well acquainted with their habits and customs were reqvired to guide the troops in their haunts. Even when the whereabouts of a tribe was known it was not easy to come up with them. To follow the trail over dry grass needed much care and patience. A single hoof mark sometimes gave the only indication; this must be followed until it led to others, where the main body had passed. No tricks such as turning back along the track ought to deceive a clever trailer; and he must be able to move along quickly, or he would never overtake the Indians. The troops often got near them in the evening too late for an attack; all night the men would lie in wait, holding their horses by the bridles, while the scout steals forward on foot to discover the best side to approach. Disguised as an Indian, he can often get close up to the encampment, unperceived, and thus enable the commanding officer to form his plans with certainty. Cunning as the Indians are, the white man can beat them at their own game. Indeed, whether it be in shooting, or riding, or trailing, or anything else, it is my experience that a white man who is up to his business can always outdo men of any other race in the world, even on their own ground.</p>

<p>Not that I mean to underrate the fighting powers of the Indians; our troops have often enough had to retire, as everyone knows. Capture is the worst thing to be feared. For this reason the Indians made but few prisoners. Men knew that it was better to die fighting than to be taken, with the fate in store for captives of being tortured and burned at the stake. Yet it was not always possible to avoid capture, and there have been friends of my own who have suffered that awful death. I have been caught myself more than once, but my good fortune has stood by me each time. On one occasion, while scouting in 1868, a tribe with whom we were at peace suddenly took to the warpath. I had been in their company in the morning and found them perfectly friendly, but happening to visit the camp again in the evening I discovered that their attitude had changed during the day, and without anything to warn me I rode straight into the midst of the enemy, as they had then become. Instantly the warriors closed in upon me, circling round and beating me with whips and clubs. The surprise was so unexpected and I had no time to use my rifle or make any attempt at escape, so I had recourse to a stratagem. Putting a bold face on, I told them that I was bringing a number of cattle as a present from the commanding officer, who believed them to be still friendly. They knew that if I were killed all chance of obtaining the cattle would be gone, and I was allowed to retire for the purpose of collecting the herd and driving it into the camp. Once out of sight, I made a bolt for it hnd succeeded in reaching the fort, seventeen miles off, leaving the Indians to wait for the cattle as long as they pleased.</p>

<p>Although their usual method of warfare is by means of ambuscades and surprises, the Indians are not afraid to meet their enemies in a stand-up fight in the open. In the war of 1876, when I was chief scout under General Carr, we came one day face to face with the Cheyennes, and the two forces were drawn up opposite each other in regular line of battle, about half a mile apart. I had been employed in so many expeditions by this time that I had acquired a high reputation among the Indians as a "warrior," and while our troops were halted preliminary to an attack the Cheyenne chief, Yellow-Hand, rode out in front of his line and challenged me to single combat. He shouted out that he was the greatest warrior in his own tribe, and honored me by saying that I was reputed the greatest warrior among the whites. If I dared he wanted me to come forward and fight it out with him, to see which of us proved the better man. I accepted his challenge, of course, and rode to meet him without delay. We both had rifles and both our horses were soon shot under us. Then we continued the battle on foot, he with a tomahawk, I with a bowie-knife. But I was too quick for him, and at last as he was raising his arm to strike I seized hold of it and held him until I could deal a decisive blow. I have his scalp now; had it ended the other way he would have had mine, for one of us must have been killed.</p>

<p>That affairs was thought a great deal of by the Indians, for Yellow-Hand was a famous chief, and after it I was looked upon as a mighty warrior indeed, although, as I have said, a white man does not really deserve any special credit for beating an Indian when they meet on equal terms. Still, it is a good thing for a man who has to deal much with Indians to gain their respect as a fighter. When peace is made they will always come in first to the man that has fought them hardest. They are great admirers of bravery and skill on the war-path, and although they will devise every possible means of killing an enemy and taking his scalp, yet the oftener he defeats them in battle, the further he outwits them in trailing, and the more of their braves he slays, so much the more do they look up to him as a great warrior, and when the war is over pay him all honor if he visits their country.</p>

<p>I have frequently proved this to be the case during the hunting expeditions I have organized when we have been right through the indian territory without any mishap. When the Grand Duke Alexis, of Russia came over to the United States I took him out into the buffalo country, and we had one of the largest hunts I can remember. Of course we were escorted by troops, although the Indians were pretty quiet all the time, so there was no danger on that occasion. But it was an instance of the confidence which the tribes place in a man they know and respect that I was able to fetch 150 warriors from a district 200 miles away, who were willing to accompany me all that distance in order to give the grand duke a war dance on the plains.</p>

<p>Only a few years before I had been hunting buffalo under very different circumstances. It was when the Kansas Pacific railroad was being graded, and I had undertaken to supply the workmen with meat. Troops were stationed all along the line to protect the works which were being carried through a dangerous Indian country. It was not safe to go even a few miles from the soldiers; but meat had to be procured, and I used to take my ceance, often traveling six, ten, or even fifteen miles after game without an escort. A wagon accompanied me, with one man to drive and another to cut up the meat; all the shooting I did myself. We were often jumped by the Indians, but I arranged with the <choice><sic>o&amp;cer</sic><corr>officer</corr></choice> commanding the troops that whenever this happened I would, if possible, set the grass alight, and as soon as he saw smoke rising he sent a company of soldiers to my rescue. Until they came we managed to keep the Indians off as best we could. Directly we found that they were upon us we used to throw the buffalo hams and hind-quarters, the only parts we kept for meat, out of the wagon, and make a sort of breastwork of them, from behind which, lying underneath the wagon, we kept shooting away at the Indians as they rode round us. I also set the grass on fire, and we never failed to keep them at bay until help arrived, for they did not find it easy to come to close quarters over the open prairie with men who could shoot as well as we did.</p>

<p>The actual hunting was easy enough to a man who knew his business. There were hundreds os thousands of buffalo, and the only difficulty lay in the rough ground over which it was necessary to gallop with full speed in order to come up with them. Sometimes a wounded bull would turn upon you, but in all kinds of hunting, whether of grizzlies or buffalo or anything else, it is generally only the greenhorn who gets mauled through his ignorance.</p>

</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Published from January 1887 through December 1891, <hi rend="italic">Murray's Magazine,</hi> was a monthly magazine published by the John Murray Publishing House which included mostly fiction writing. The full title of the William F. Cody article is "Fighting and Trapping Out West."</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: <persName xml:id="cody.i">Isaac Cody</persName> (1811-1857).</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: Charles Dunn (d.1860).</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: Dave Harrington (d.1859).</note>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
