<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp00040">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Rough Riders Recall Many Hilarious Tales of Yore</title>
                <author>Carberry, Jim</author>
                <principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
                <principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
                <principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <idno type="module">Rough Riders</idno>
                <idno type="project">wfc.nsp00040</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a" type="main">THE ROUGH RIDERS RECALL MANY HILARIOUS TALES OF YORE</title>
                    <title level="j">Albuquerque Tribune</title>
                    <date>undated</date>
                    <extent>1 page</extent>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="subject">
                    <term>Rough Riders</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>Texts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
                    <term>Newspapers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
                    <term>Rough Riders</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
                    <term>Rough Riders Association</term>
                    <term>Spanish American War</term>
                    <term>Cavalry</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
                    <term>Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919</term>
                    <term>McGinty, William M., 1871-1961</term>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
                    <term>San Juan Hill</term>
                    <term>Cuba</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-06-20"><name>Heppler, Jason</name> Adding source metadata</change>
            <change when="2011-09-13"><name xml:id="jah">Heppler, Jason</name> Initial transcription and markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="article">

                <head type="main">THE ROUGH RIDERS RECALL MANY HILARIOUS TALES OF YORE</head>

<div2>  
              <p>"The funniest thing I ever saw," pint-sized Billy McGinty, the president of the
                    Rough Riders Assn., was saying, "was when they turned those eastern boys loose
                    to break their horses."</p>
                
                <p>McGinty, an impish 82-year-old, grinning under a large black ten-gallon hat in
                    the lobby of El Fidel Hotel. Other spry veterans of that famous brigade gathered
                    for their 54th annual reunion over the week end.</p>
                
                <p>"These fellas were pretty good riders," he went on, "sure, they had to be to get
                    in. But, they hadn't ridden anything but polo ponies in college. These horses
                    hadn't been broke but once if that.</p>
                
                <p>"Well sir, they got 'em out thee with the rest of 'em at the Fair Grounds at San
                    Antonio. There must have been a thousand horses out in that field. Then they
                    told 'em all to scramble for a horse and break one.</p>
                
                <p>"By the time the dust cleared, them eastern boys were scattered all over
                Texas."</p>
                </div2>
<div2>
                <head type="sub">Eastern Boys</head>
                
                <p>About 30 of the surviving 80 or so veterans of the celebrated charge up San Juan
                    Hill in 1898 were in town for the reunion. Al-most all of the volunteers (ex-
                    cept 110 of the "eastern boys") enlisted from New Mexico, Arizona and Oklahoma
                    in reply to Teddy Roosevelt's challenge to men who wanted "rough living, rough
                    coun- try and rough riding."</p>
                
                <p>They voted last year to hold their reunions here until the "last man of the
                select 1200 originally picked for the 1st U. S. volunteer cavalry in 1898.</p>
                
                <p>Tonight, everyone had a story to tell, and they naturally concerned the
                Spanish-American War, horses or Col. Roosevelt.</p>
                
                <p>Arthur Anderson, 83, of Stockton, Cal., broke in with his tale of the most
                    stubborn horse ever born. In Tampa, Fla., where the Rough Riders shipped out to
                    Cuba, his company had a horse that "kicked, bit and just generally tried to kill
                    anyone who climbed on him."</p>
                
                <p>Anderson said he thought if he took the horse into the shallow waters of the gulf
                    where it couldn't keep its head down to buck, he could break him. It didn't
                    work: "That dumb thing just put his head down and start- ed bucking. Never
                    raised it up until he floated on his side. Dead from pure stubbornness."</p>
                
                <p>Anderson took some kidding about being "an old-timer" when he said he couldn't
                    ride in the parade which opened the gathering. The kidding, stopped when he said
                    the reason was that he had been riding the day before and still ached.</p>
         </div2>
<div2>       
                <head type="sub">Story of General</head>
                
                <p>Trooper Robert. "Buck" Denny of Whittier, Cal., added the inevitable general
                    story. "Remember the time old (Gen.) "Shafty" Shafter tried to get on one bf
                    those Cuban ponies? He weighed 300 pounds. Took three orderlies just to get him
                    in the saddle, and then the poor horse caved in and they had to get another
                    one."</p>
                
                <p>The men who followed Col. Roosevelt in the 20-minute charge up San Juan Hill
                    speak of him with respect approaching awe. "He grandstanded a lot," Hunter
                    commented, "but he had the nerve to back it up." "He never asked any of his men
                    to do what he wouldn't do himself I can tell you that," McGinty added.</p>
                
                <p>To illustrate, 80-year-old H. H. Wynkoop of Santa Fe told the story of a group of
                    the Rough Riders under their first shelling at El Paso: "We got caught up on the
                    hill side and the Spaniards really had us zoned in. It was the 'first time we
                    had ever been Un- der fire, and all of us just ducked behind some rocks and
                    buried our heads.</p>
                
                <p>"And who comes riding up but the colonel himself. He yelled 'You men! Are you
                sheep? Get up and stand at attention!'"</p>
                
                <p>They did, Wynkoop said, and while the shells screamed and blasted around them T.
                R. marched them ramrod-straight off the hillside to cover.</p>
                
                <p>A leathery veteran named Jess Langdon who lives in East Rockaway, N.Y., explained
                    how he enlisted in the Riders when he was 16. (At 72, the six-foot, 200-pound.
                    Langdon is the "kid" of the troop.)</p>
                
                <p>Langdon said he met Roosevelt at the door to the recruiting office and told him
                    what he wanted. "Can you ride?" Roosevelt snapped. "Anything with hair," Langdon
                    snapped back. The colonel laughed: "Then go ahead and tell them I sent you."</p>
                
                <p>The veterans, some of whom hadn't seen each other in 20 years, drifted in and out
                of the conversation, but the stories went on:</p>
         </div2>
<div2>       
                <head type="sub">Tales Rescued</head>
                
                <p>Langdon, who broke two ribs the previous day breaking a horse, went on to tell of
                    the luckiest mistake he ever made. The Riders were entrenched above the Spanish
                    lines, taking turns sniping. When Langdon's turn came up, he drew a bead, pulled
                    the trigger, and nothing happened. He ducked back into the trench and found he
                    hadn't unlocked his rifle, a bullet whizzed through his campaign hat.</p>
                
                <p>"If I hadn't been so dumb I wouldn't be here to tell about it."</p>
                
                <p>Hunter told the one about the time the officers (who had practically the only
                    horses on the island) offered to pay him $5 apiece for same. Hunter and another
                    private raided the officer's corral one night and sold the lieutenant 25 horses
                    the next morning. "Their own horses and they paid us for 'em!"</p>
                
                <p>One recalled the time they captured 'the distillery at Siboney and some of the
                    troopers filled up their canteens with rum. Only to be stranded without water
                    for the next three days. McGinty told how he was running across an open field
                    with an imponded case of canned tomatoes when the Spaniards spotted him. "Didn't
                    hurt me," he said, "but they must have hit those tomatoes 10 times. I was red
                    from head to foot when I got back."</p>
                
                <p>When the Rough Riders embarked from Tampa on the troopship Yucatan, only 484 made
                the trip. The rest of the contingent of 1200 had to be left behind.</p>
                
                <p>"They never come to the reunions," McGinty said sadly. "They felt so (damn) bad
                    about it we never See 'em out here. It ís too bad. There just wasn't enough
                    room."</p>
</div2>
            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
