<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11480">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Sunday Amusements of the Upper Classes</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11480</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">The Sunday Amusements of the Upper Classes</title>
<title level="j">The Ipswich Journal</title>
<pubPlace>Ipswich, England</pubPlace>
<date when="1888-03-02">March 2, 1888</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Amusements</term>
<term>Aristocracy (Social class)</term>
<term>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Convocation. Upper House</term>
<term>Clergy</term>
<term>England. Parliament</term>
<term>Exhibitions</term>
<term>Sabbath</term>
<term>Sunday</term>
<term>Wild west shows</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Canterbury (England)</term>
<term>Hampton Court (Richmond upon Thames, London, England)</term>
<term>Hyde Park (London, England)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name>, <name xml:id="sh">Hanna, Sam</name> and <name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="cm">McQuay, Colleen</name> Transcription</change>



</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<!-- <pb facs="wfc.nsp11480.001"/> -->


<head>THE SUNDAY AMUSEMENTS OF THE UPPER CLASSES.</head>
<p>In the Upper House of Convocation for the province of Canterbury, one of the principal subjects for discussion was "The Sunday Amusements of the Upper Classes." It was initiated by the Bishop of Exeter laying on the table a petition which set forth "That there has been of late very marked increase in the employment of the afternoon and evening of the Lord's Day by amusements of various kinds in the upper and fashionable classes of society. That the society papers (so-called) in particular, and occasionly the daily papers on Monday give more or less full accounts of entertainments which have taken place. Those of recent date include formal dinner parties, smoking concerts, theatrical and semi-theatrical performances, comic recitations, and amusing programmes of fun and frolic, exhibitions of jugglery, Sunday parade in Hyde Park, coach drives of clubs, the drags assembling at Hampton Court, Richmond, and other places of resort; the 'Sunday up the river;' boxing at the Pelican Club, lawn tennis, dances at clubs and private houses, exhibitions (once at least) of the Wild West Show, Show Sunday in the Studio of Artists. Some of these are novelties in the way of Lord's day profanation. That the long lists of those present at these Sunday amusements which are given in the society papers embrace men of eminence in art, science, politics, and commerce, as well as mere <hi rend="italic">dilettanti</hi> men and women whose prominence in only that of devotion to pleasure. That many of these amusements are public. That their presence testifies to very loose Sunday habits on the part of the rich, and great, and noble of the land. Such abuses of the Lord's Day evidence an insatiable desire for distraction and dissipation, a very low regard for the claims of the Word of God, and a determination to put away the restraints of religion." The petitioners, who numbered 104, asked counsel on the subject, and suggested a protest against Sunday excursion trains, and a remonstrance against the Sunday amusements and entertainments. The signatories included members of both Houses of Parliament, clergymen, and others. The discussion which arose on the question was adjourned, as it was held that the Bishop of London (who was absent) should be present, as in his diocese the alleged Sunday desecration had been committed.</p>
</div1>
</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
