<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11529">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Wild West Show</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11529</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">The Wild West Show</title>
<title level="j">Liverpool Courier</title>
<pubPlace>Liverpool, England</pubPlace>
<date when="1891-07-13">July 13, 1891</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>
McCracken Research Library, Buffalo Bill Center of the West
</repository>
<idno>MS6.3772.034.4 (Crager Scrapbook)</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>American Indians</term>
<term>American newspapers</term>
<term>Audiences</term>
<term>Bovril Limited</term>
<term>Cowboys</term>
<term>Firearms</term>
<term>Frontier and pioneer life</term>
<term>Historical reenactments</term>
<term>Horsemanship</term>
<term>Horsemen and horsewomen</term>
<term>Horses</term>
<term>Mexicans</term>
<term>Sharpshooters</term>
<term>Shooters of firearms</term>
<term>Shooting</term>
<term>Targets (Shooting)</term>
<term>Translators</term>
<term>United States--Politics and government</term>
<term>Shooting</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Baker, Johnny, 1869-1931</term>
<term>Oakley, Annie, 1860-1926</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Liverpool (England)</term>
<term>Manchester (England)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015-09-11"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> and <name xml:id="sh">Hanna, Sam</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11529.001"/>


<head>THE WILD WEST SHOW.</head>
<p>To imagine that the present exhibition illustrative of life in the far West is like anything tha[t] has had the advantage of a similar description in the past is to be guided by a wrong assumption altogether. So complete a realisation of prairie scenes was never attempted until Colonel W. F. Cody, or to give him his better known title, Buffalo Bill, originated the show which is now attracting thousands of people to the ground adjoining Newsham-park.<ref target="n01">1</ref> He has around him a large body of Indians of various tribes, and although there has been an impression in the minds of some of the spectators that many of the grotesquely painted individuals were white men, closer observation has convinced them of their mistake. As a matter of fact, a number of the Indians who take part in the performance were associated with the last Indian rebellion and assisted the American Government on that occasion.  They are in charge of a gentleman&#8212;<persName xml:id="crager.g">Mr. George C. Crager</persName>&#8212;who was the special correspondent of one of the most popular daily newspapers in America and who converses in thirteen dialects. His services as interpreter are necessary because there is a wide distinction between the different tribes represented. The show will finish in Liverpool on Saturday next, as it is due in Manchester a week to-day. Therefore those who desire to visit it must take advantage of the next few days. Nor should intending visitors forget one important fact&#8212;that it is essential, if they wish to see the most interesting feature of the proceedings, to be present at the commencement, when the Indians, cowboys, vaqueros, and other performers are introduced separately. It is an exceedingly pretty ceremony and at once fixes attention and excites the interest of the audience.  Apart from the descriptive scenes there are marvellous feats of horsemanship by cowboys and vaqueros, and a display of extraordinary skill in shooting by <persName xml:id="oakley.a">Miss Oakley</persName> and <persName xml:id="baker.l">Johnny Baker</persName>, but their performance is equalled if not surpassed by Col. Cody who, whilst riding around the arena fires at glass balls which are thrown into the air by an Indian attendant. There is no item in the programme which is at all uninteresting, and the very favourable opinion which has already been expressed by the audiences is the surest indication of the good merits of the exhibition. This afternoon a horse belonging to Mr. Wm. E. Nelson, of Oakhill-park, Liverpool, which has given its owner considerable trouble and cannot be ridden, is to be experimented with by some of Col. Cody's clever horsemen, who declare their ability to ride it, notwithstanding the bad character it has received. The gilt Maltese Cross medal worn by the cowboys is the gift of the Bovril Company,<ref target="n02">2</ref> who have a booth on the ground.</p>


</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Newsham Park, a 121 acres Victorian-era public park in Liverpool, England, opened in 1868.</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: The Bovril Company was the maker of a thick, salty meat extract developed in 1870 by John Lawson Johnston (1839-1900). The English called it beef tea.</note>  
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
