<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.papers.00016">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Buffalo Bill's Legacy: Finding the West and Westerners in Contemporary
          Italy</title>
        <author>Christianson, Frank</author>
        <principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
        <principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
        <principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
        <address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
        <idno type="module"/>
        <idno type="project">wfc.papers.00016</idno>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>

      <notesStmt>
        <note/>
      </notesStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Laegreid, Renee</author>
          <title level="a" type="main">Buffalo Bill's Legacy: Finding the West and Westerners in
            Contemporary Italy</title>
          <note>The Frontier Goes Global: The Wild West in Europe</note>
          <note>Boundary Markers and Border Crossers, Fifty-Second Annual Conference of the Western
            History Association</note>
          <note>Western History Association</note>
          <date when="2012-10-07">2012-10-07</date>
          <extent>1 page</extent>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p/>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p/>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Scholarship</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Papers</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
          <term>Colorado</term>
          <term>Denver (Colo.)</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-10-09"><name xml:id="jah">Heppler, Jason A.</name> Initial
        encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>

      <div1 type="type">


        <head type="main">Buffalo Bill's Legacy: Finding the West and Westerners in Contemporary
          Italy</head>

        <head type="sub">Boundary Markers and Border Crossers, Fifty-Second Annual Conference of the
          Western History Association, October 7, 2012.</head>

        <byline>By Renee Laegreid, Hastings College</byline>

        <p>Beginning in 1889, Buffalo Bill crossed the boundaries of the Atlantic, taking his Wild
          West Show overseas to perform for crowds of spectators throughout Europe. He carefully
          advertised his shows, constructing months-long advertising campaigns to create enormous
          anticipation in the towns and cities on his tour. After his shows, the memories of the
          cowboys, cowgirls and Native Americans remained topics of community conversation for
          years; stories of the show often treated like a prized possession, handed down from one
          generation to another. As one witness to a show in Trieste, Italy recalled, "Buffalo Bill
          took us to the world of the cowboy, the Indian tribes—the red skins— . . . It was a whole new
          world for us." Buffalo Bill's last tour ended in 1906, but Italian interest in the new
          world of the American West continues to the present day. Buffalo Bill crossed the
          boundaries of the Atlantic to bring the American West to Europe, and over one hundred
          years later, pieces of his West not only remain, but have become increasingly apparent.
          This paper addresses the persistence of Buffalo Bill and his Wild West shows in the
          collective memory of Italians, and how the memory of Buffalo Bill and his show, although
          evolving over time, continues to shape the Italian perspective on the American West. The
          influence is seen in the growing interest in American Western culture and literature,
          American-style rodeo, "Western Riding" (reining and cutting competitions), and the growth
          of American Quarter Horse industry in Italy. This is fertile ground for exploring the
          evolving idea of the West that takes place outside of American borders, focusing, as
          Buffalo Bill did, on the exceptionalist vision of that West.</p>

      </div1>
    </body>

    <back> </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
