<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00145">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to Julia Cody Goodman, April 12, 1903</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2012</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00145</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>Letter and envelope. Julia Cody Goodman (1843-1928) was WFC's elder sister (and eldest). BBWW performed in Manchester, England, April 13-May 2, 1903. McCullough Peaks are located about fifteen miles northeast of Cody, Wyoming, and south of the pioneer community of Corbett, Wyoming [see Bonner, p135]. DeMaris Hot Springs is located on the Shoshone River just west of Cody; Garland is a small community northeast of Cody and Ralston. Located between Corbett and Ralston was Eagles Nest stage stop. South Fork, Ishawooa, and Dry Fork are located near Cody. DeForest Richards was Governor of Wyoming until his death on April 28, 1903. Additional notes needed on Carey Act, Homestead Act, Shoshone Irrigation Co., State Land Board, and Burlington Quincy Railroad. "Mr. Ridgely" likely refers to H. S. Ridgely who was one of WFC's divorce lawyers in Cody.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to Julia Cody Goodman</title>
<date when="1903-04-12">April 12, 1903</date>
<extent>9 pages, plus envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>McCracken Research Library (MRL)</repository>
<idno>MS6.0153</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>9 hand-written pages, plus envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support>The Queens Hotel Manchester Limited letterhead</support>
<extent>9 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

 <profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>


<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2012-02-20"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura</name> Initial Encoding</change>
  <change when="2011"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2011"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2011"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.001" />

<opener>
<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"><figDesc>Drawing</figDesc></figure>The Queens Hotel Manchester Limited.</note>

<dateline><date>Sunday. Apr. 12th / 03.</date></dateline>


<salute>Dear Julia.</salute>
</opener>

<p>Yours written on your 60th birth day received. I am pleased that you feel so well. I wish I could say I did. But I am going to get out of this business&#8212; that is just wearing the life out of me&#8212; there is such a nervous strain <choice><sic>continualy</sic><corr>continually</corr></choice>&#8212; And the thing has got onto my nerves&#8212; And this must be my last summer. to day <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> snowing here. And we open out doors tomorrow

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.002" />

<fw>2/</fw>

The way it looks now by the time. I finish my season. here. Oct 16th We will have our Mill built and in running order at our mine. then I will have a good steady income from that. I am going to fix dear old TE. up And go there and rest this winter&#8212;I have just got to go someplace where <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> quiet and rest. And get my nerves quiet&#8212; I think when Lou and Arta sees I am determined&#8212; they will agree to a mutual <choice><sic>seporation</sic><corr>separation</corr></choice>. Lou. likes to be boss. She loves to be the whole thing&#8212; And if I give her all the North

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.003" />

<fw>3/</fw>

<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"><figDesc>Drawing</figDesc></figure>The Queens Hotel Manchester Limited.</note>

Platte property&#8212; And <choice><sic>mony</sic><corr>money</corr></choice> besides. She will take it. She will be a rich woman- And her own boss- Now. Dear about the land below Corbett&#8212; under McCollough Peake&#8212; I am glad you liked it. I am sure its the best soil in that country. And it has a good stock range in the McCollough Peake country. that will never be taken up. have the Boys look the range over and build your main home <choice><sic>oposite</sic><corr>opposite</corr></choice> one of the big draws

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.004" />

<fw>4/</fw>
 
that come into the river from the South&#8212; this will give you an outlet for your stock to get up in to the hills&#8212; Look the place over carefully before building in the bend about a mile below the Corbett ranch is a nice sheltered place to build&#8212; there are trees there out of the wind close to the river. the first house you put up can after while be use as your stables Now about <choice><sic>fileing</sic><corr>filing</corr></choice> on it. The .Govenor who is President of the State Land Board. And the Burlington. Rail Road.&#8212; told me if I would give up my waterright

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.005" />

<fw><del>4</del> 5/</fw> 

<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"><figDesc>Drawing</figDesc></figure>The Queens Hotel Manchester Limited.</note>

And segregation. The the U. S. government would take up my proposition And build a canal to irrigate all the land on North side of river from Demarris Springs to Garland&#8212; When I released my segregations under the Carey Act. the land would be thrown open for settlement under the homestead Act. of course the home steaders would have to pay for water for

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.006" />

<fw>6/ </fw>

irrigation&#8212; whatever the Government charged Mind you the Government does not furnish water free. Mr Ridgely can explain this to you. Should the government not build a canal to water this tract others will. The Shoshone Irrigation Co. could water the land from Corbett to Eagles Nest- by flumeing the river near Corbett&#8212; And you could <choice><sic>by</sic><corr>buy</corr></choice> water from them&#8212; But as I understand it. the U. S. Government is going to do it. However you need not go to much expense until you know what is going to be done

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.007" />
<fw>7/</fw>

<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"><figDesc>Drawing</figDesc></figure>The Queens Hotel Manchester Limited.</note>

this you can find out by asking those who are informed on the different laws governing lands&#8212; I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know how well Ridgley is posted on the government and Carrie Act. and Laws&#8212; But he should get posted I will write Roy. to fix you up Some Kind of a team when you want it. But Sister. Enquire think this over use your own Judgement before

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.008" />

<fw>8/</fw>
 
You decide to take up this land&#8212;For I might see things different if I was there&#8212;A big $5.000.000 Co is going to take a canal out of South fork up near Ishawooa&#8212; And irrigate all the land from there to Dry Fork. You might do better under their ditch. Say things are going to Boom in Cody Town And I guess I must build the big addition. with the exception of your married help. get the rest in a tent&#8212;double every one up close&#8212; take Josie in with you. You will soon need all your

<pb facs="wfc.css00145.009" />
<fw>9/</fw>

<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"></figure>The Queens Hotel Manchester Limited.</note>

rooms&#8212; that house must be got on to a paying basis.</p>

<closer>
<salute>With love</salute>

<signed>Brother</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>The room in the big addition that the Club was to rent can be made in to bed rooms&#8212; Must have double windows on all westside. And contractors must be made to do good work. No green lumber used. Yes have your fly screens put on and the house fixed up&#8212;</p>

<closer><signed>Brother</signed></closer>
</postscript>


</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">
<pb facs="wfc.css00145.010" />

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mrs. Julia. Goodman</addrLine>
<addrLine>Cody.</addrLine>
<addrLine>Wyo.</addrLine>
<addrLine>U. S. A.</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>


</div1>

</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
