<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00443">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck, July 24, 1895</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>Supported in part by a grant from the Wyoming Cultural Trust Fund, a program of the Department of State Parks and Cultural Resources.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2013</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00443</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>BBWW performed in Montpelier, Vermont, July 24, 1895. Horace C. Alger (1857-1906) was a banker from Sheridan, Wyoming, who was mayor of Sheridan in 1889 and a candidate for Governor of Wyoming in 1898. Cody, Beck, and Alger were responsible for developing the Shoshone Irrigation Company. Theo Heckert was a railroad contractor who had a "grading outfit" used in construction of the Cody canal [See Patrick's The Best Little Town by a Dam Site, p19]. Russell refers to M. R. "Mike" Russell, a/k/a/ "Deadwood Mike," a long-time friend of WFC, who was owner of the Buffalo Saloon in Deadwood, S.D.; when WFC bought cattle and horses from Mike Russell, the brand TE came, too; thus, the name TE Ranch, Ishawooa, Wyoming. Anson Higby (~1862-unknown) was a banker in Deadwood, S.D., who in 1893 partnered with Mr. C. H. Grinnell (later Mayor of Sheridan), J. R. Phelan, George T. Beck to form the Sheridan Fuel Company on lands approximately four miles north of Sheridan. This area soon became a thriving company-owned mining camp known as Higby. Higby became president of the Basin State Bank in Basin, Wyoming, as well as mayor and baseball coach of the town. He was the secretary for the Wyoming State Fair board for about five years beginning in 1913. Higby was elected to the board of directors for several emerging oil-gas companies including the Flat Top Oil &amp; Gas Company, the Emery Oil Company, the Glenhurst Company, and worked for the Midwest Refining Company out of Casper, Wyoming. "Leighter" might have been misspelled by WFC. He may have been referring to one of these two men who had major investments in the Sheridan area: Levi Z. Leiter (1834-1904) was a businessman from Chicago with extensive business interests in Wyoming, including ranching, mining, and the development of water resources. Joseph Leiter (1868-1932), only son of Levi Leiter, was a self-described capitalist [See 1920 and 1930 United States Federal Census Record for Joseph Leiter]. He managed the business affairs of his father and then of his father's estate starting in 1904 which included four ranches in Wyoming [See http://www.ucrossfoundation.org/about-us/ucross-ranch/]. Leiter was a major force with the Lake DeSmet Water Project in Johnson County, the second Kearney Lake Company and other irrigation projects that serve crop lands to this day. William E. Hymer (~1853-1933) was one of the early members of the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck</title>
<date when="1895-07-24">July 24, 1895</date>
<extent>1 page</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Buffalo Bill Letters to George T. Beck (Acc. #9972)</repository>
<idno>ah031280</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 hand-written page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pencil"><p>Media: pencil</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Beck, George Washington Thornton, 1856-1943</term>
<term>Alger, Horace Chapin, 1857-1906</term>
<term>Heckert, Theodore</term>
<term>Russell, Michael R. "Mike", 1847-1930</term>
<term>Higby, Anson, ~1862-?</term>
<term>Grinnell, C. H.</term>
<term>Phelan, J. R.</term>
<term>Zeiter, Levi Z., 1834-1904</term>
<term>Leiter, Levi Z. (Levi Ziegler), 1834-1904</term>
<term>Hymer, William Ebert, 1853-1933</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Shoshone Irrigation District (Wyo.)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015-03-23"><name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Changed Leiter's name</change>
  <change when="2013-06-27"><name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Added annotations</change>
  <change when="2013-01-28"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00443.001"/>

<note type="letterhead">
<figure n="portrait"><p>The Buffalo Bill Wild West and Congress of Rough Riders of the World.</p></figure>
Col. W. F. Cody (Buffalo Bill), President.<lb/>Nate Salsbury, Vice-Pres't and Manager.<lb/>John M. Burke, . . . General Manager.<lb/>Albert E. Scheible, . . . Business Manager.<lb/>Jule Keen, . . . Treasurer.</note>


<opener>
<dateline>Montpelier July 24<ref target="n01">1</ref></dateline>

<salute>Dear <persName xml:id="beck.g">George</persName>&#8212;</salute></opener>

<p>I have wired &amp; wrote you&#8212; I wrote <persName xml:id="alger.h">Alger</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="heckart.t">Heckart</persName>&#8212; But no reply. I hope nothing will prevent the meeting at Sheridan Aug. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> And George have it settled then and there&#8212; would like to know if Higby<ref target="n02">2</ref> is in if he is <persName xml:id="russell.m">Russell</persName> will be in. Two good Men&#8212; What about <hi rend="underline">Leighter</hi><ref target="n03">3</ref>. Have you fixed contract with Wyo. State Land Board? We must have our contract before we go to far&#8212; Organize Town Site Co. also Aug 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> I wrote <persName xml:id="hymer.w">Hymer</persName> to put the Sulphur Springs<ref target="n04">4</ref> in to the Townsite Co&#8212; Then find out best way to get good title to Land for Town. Take it cool but get there&#8212; And have things Iron bound&#8212; &amp; <choice><sic>lets</sic><corr>let's</corr></choice> get to work&#8212;</p>

<closer><signed>Bill</signed></closer>


</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: The year is not inscribed by Cody but is 1895 as determined by the Routes List: Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in Montpelier, Vermont, on July 24, 1895. </note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: "Higby" was likely Anson Higby (b. 1862), a banker in Deadwood, S.D., who in 1893 partnered with Mr. C. H. Grinnell (later Mayor of Sheridan), J. R. Phelan, and George T. Beck to form the Sheridan Fuel Company on lands approximately four miles north of Sheridan. This area soon became a thriving company-owned mining camp known as Higby. Higby became president of the Basin State Bank in Basin, Wyoming, as well as mayor and baseball coach of the town. He was the secretary for the Wyoming State Fair board for about five years beginning in 1913. Higby was elected to the board of directors for several emerging oil-gas companies including the Flat Top Oil &amp; Gas Company, the Emery Oil Company, the Glenhurst Company, and worked for the Midwest Refining Company out of Casper, Wyoming.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: "Leighter" might have been misspelled by Cody, who may have been referring to one of these two men who had major investments in the Sheridan area: Levi Z. Leiter (1834-1904), a businessman from Chicago with extensive business interests in Wyoming, including ranching, mining, and the development of water resources; or Joseph Leiter (1868-1932), only son of Levi Leiter, who was a self-described capitalist. Joseph Leiter managed the business affairs of his father and then of his father's estate starting in 1904 which included four ranches in Wyoming. Joseph Leiter was a major force with the Lake DeSmet Water Project in Johnson County, the second Kearney Lake Company, and other irrigation projects that serve croplands to this day. </note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: "Sulphur Springs" is likely Cody's reference to "DeMaris Springs," a warm sulphur spring located in the middle of the original Cody City town site.</note>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
