<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00448">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck, September 15, 1895</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>Supported in part by a grant from the Wyoming Cultural Trust Fund, a program of the Department of State Parks and Cultural Resources.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2013</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00448</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>BBWW performed in Ithaca, New York, on September 14, 1895. September 15th was a Sunday so no performance. "Heck" could be Theo Heckert, a railroad contractor who had a "grading outfit" used in construction of the canal. [See Patrick, p19]. George Bleistein (1861-1918) of Buffalo, New York, owned the Courier Printing Company and provided printing for BBWW; Bleistein was also a partner and director in the Shoshone Irrigation Company. William E. Hymer (~1853-1933) was one of the early members of the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company. W. A. Paxton (1837-1907) was one of Omaha's leading entrepreneurs involved in cattle, stockyards, wholesale groceries, land, and politics. The Paxton-Gallagher business became renowned for its line of wholesale groceries, including Butternut coffee. The Paxton &amp; Gallagher Wholesale Grocery Company was founded in 1879 by William Paxton and Benjamin Gallagher. Paxton was being pursued as a potential investor in The Shoshone Irrigation Company but later decided against joining. [See Bonner, p31). Gallagher was a grocery man who operated a series of companies along the Union Pacific railroad route. M. E. Smith and Co. was a wholesale dry goods business located in Omaha, Nebraska; the company began in 1868 and bought out by the Bryne-Hammer Co. in 1925 for $1,830,000. "Note" mentioned in WFC letter (AHC) to George T. Beck 1895.09.15. Jerry Ryan was an engineer that George T. Beck sent with Labin Hillsberry to discover if the Shoshone River could be brought around south of the mountain to irrigate a large area of the Big Horn Basin; Ryan would also become a shareholder in the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company, formed in 1895 [See Patrick]. The W. F. Cody Transportation Co. was started in 1894 and worked in conjunction with the Sheridan Inn that Cody also owned in Sheridan, Wyoming; both enterprises were managed by Cody's friend George Canfield. </note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck</title>
<date when="1895-09-15">September 15, 1895</date>
<extent>4 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Buffalo Bill Letters to George T. Beck (Acc. #9972)</repository>
<idno>ah031288-91</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>4 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>4 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Courier Printing Company</term>
<term>M. E. Smith and Co.</term>
<term>Bryne-Hammer Co.</term>
<term>W. F. Cody Transportation Co.</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Beck, George Washington Thornton, 1856-1943</term>
<term>Heckert, Theodore</term>
<term>Bleistein, George, 1861-1918</term>
<term>Hymer, William Ebert, 1853-1933</term>
<term>Paxton, William A., 1837-1907</term>
<term>Gallagher, Benjamin</term>
<term>Hillberry, Labin</term>
<term>Ryan, Jerry and James</term>
<term>Canfield, George, 1836-1899</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Shoshone Irrigation District (Wyo.)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2013-06-28"><name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Added annotations</change>
  <change when="2013-02-01"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00448.001"/>

<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"><p>Childs &amp; Son, Utica, N.Y.</p></figure>Cortland House.<lb/>All Rooms Warmed By Steam.<lb/>Delos Bauder, Proprietor.<lb/></note>

<opener>
<dateline>Cortland, N. Y. Sep. 15 1895<ref target="n01">1</ref></dateline>

<salute>Dear <persName xml:id="beck.g">George</persName>.</salute>
</opener>
<p>I expected a letters here to day from You and Heck. Telling me what you had done. Did you get a secretary? If so let him write me I know too well what poor letter writers you and <persName xml:id="heckart.t">Heck</persName> are. I sent Curley<ref target="n02">2</ref> to <persName xml:id="bleistein.g">George Bleistein</persName> from Elmira Say George, I know you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> like <persName xml:id="hymer.w">Hymer</persName>&#8212; But he is a pusher. And thats the kind of men we want with this big job. And one can


<pb facs="wfc.css00448.002"/>

catch more flies with molasses than with vinegar So pat him on the back&#8212; Say did you send the <hi rend="underline">stock</hi> for Bleistein. <persName xml:id="salsbury.n">Salsbury</persName> &amp; Myself? Do you know what Heck done with the <orgName xml:id="company.t">Transportation Co</orgName><ref target="n03">3</ref> at Sheridan. I got a wire from Paxton &amp; Gallagher <ref target="n04">4</ref>&amp; from Smith &amp; Co&#8212;<ref target="n05">5</ref> of Omaha. Asking me to guarantee Heckarts orders for supplies and furnishing goods which I did. I wish some one would keep me posted on matters at that end. So I would know what is being done&#8212; And then there will be no mistake and I can understand and help to protect our credit


<pb facs="wfc.css00448.003"/>

<note type="letterhead"><figure n="drawing"><p>Childs &amp; Son, Utica, N.Y.</p></figure>Cortland House.<lb/>All Rooms Warmed By Steam.<lb/>Delos Bauder, Proprietor.<lb/>Cortland, N. Y.   ______ 189__ </note>


You did not write me as you promised and explain all about the co&#8212; That point that I wanted to know about being a Stock Co&#8212; And if any of the old co&#8212; can give us any trouble. And if the State Land Board is going to give us a contract for our land &amp; if you settled with Ryan and his partner about their water right. You know we broke our contract with


<pb facs="wfc.css00448.004"/>


them by not paying them when we agreed to&#8212; and they can make us dance to their music if they choose to. I know old man I am over nervous about these things. But we have got our friends into this. And we must protect them. Our everlasting reputation is at stake. All our energy &amp; what brains we posess must be brought into actions Nothing must be left undone&#8212; George&#8212; I look to you to attend to this until I can get there to help you&#8212;</p>

<p>Write me often. Do keep me posted&#8212; Tell Heck to write me&#8212;</p>

<closer>
<salute>Your friend &amp; pard</salute>

<signed>W. F. Cody</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in Ithaca, New York, on September 14, 1895. There was no Sunday performance on September 15th.</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: "Curley" is unidentified.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: The transportation company in Sheridan was owned by Cody and known as the W. F. Cody Transportation Company.</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: The Paxton-Gallagher business became renowned for its wholesale groceries, including Butternut coffee. The Paxton &amp; Gallagher Wholesale Grocery Company was founded in 1879 by William Paxton<!--link to William A. Paxton personography--> and Benjamin Gallagher. Gallagher was a grocery man, and operated a series of companies all along the Union Pacific railroad route.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: M. E. Smith &amp; Co. was a wholesale dry goods business located in Omaha, Nebraska. The company began in 1868 and was acquired by the Bryne-Hammer Co. in 1925 for $1,830,000.</note>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
