<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00438">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck, June 3 [1895]</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>Supported in part by a grant from the Wyoming Cultural Trust Fund, a program of the Department of State Parks and Cultural Resources.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2013</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00438</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>Year 1895 is derived by routes list: BBWW performed in Hartford, Conn., June 3, 1895. Prior to that, BBWW performed in New Haven May 31-June 1, 1895, where Cody mentions being prostrated by the heat. W. A. Paxton (1837-1907) was one of Omaha's leading entrepreneurs involved in cattle, stockyards, wholesale groceries, land, and politics. The Paxton-Gallagher business became renowned for its line of wholesale groceries, including Butternut coffee. The Paxton &amp; Gallagher Wholesale Grocery Company was founded in 1879 by William Paxton and Benjamin Gallagher. Paxton was being pursued as a potential investor in The Shoshone Irrigation Company but later decided against investing. [See Bonner, pp18, 31]. According to Bonner, Paxton and his group objected to Hymer. Dennis Cunningham and Jerry Ryan would not contribute much in the way of money to the project. Dennis Cunningham was one of the shareholders of the company organized on March 20, 1895, which later would be named the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company [See Bonner, pp 13, 31, 70, 72]. Jerry Ryan was an engineer that George T. Beck sent with Labin Hillsberry to discover if the Shoshone River could be diverted south around the mountain to irrigate a large area of the Basin. Ryan would also become a shareholder in the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company formed in 1895 [See Patrick's The Best Little Town by a Dam Site]. William E. Hymer (~1853-1933) was one of the early members of the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck</title>
<date when="1895-06-03">June 3 [1895]</date>
<extent>1 page</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Buffalo Bill Letters to George T. Beck (Acc. #9972)</repository>
<idno>ah031274</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 hand-written page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pen"><p>Media: blue ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Beck, George Washington Thornton, 1856-1943</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2013-04-24"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Added annotations</change>
  <change when="2013-01-28"><name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="lc">Clarke, Linda</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00438.001"/>

<note type="letterhead">
<figure n="portrait"><p>The Buffalo Bill Wild West and Congress of Rough Riders of the World.</p></figure>
Col. W. F. Cody (Buffalo Bill), President.<lb/>Nate Salsbury, Vice-Pres't and Manager.<lb/>John M. Burke, . . . General Manager.<lb/>Albert E. Scheible, . . . Business Manager.<lb/>Jule Keen, . . . Treasurer.</note>

<opener>

<dateline>Hartford <del>May</del> June 3<hi rend="sup">th</hi><ref target="n01">1</ref></dateline>

<salute>My Dear <persName xml:id="beck.g">George</persName></salute>
</opener>

<p>Your telegram just <choice><sic>rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi><corr>received</corr></sic></choice> found <add>me</add> quite ill but getting better. I got prostrated by the heat last friday in New Haven&#8212;<ref target="n02">2</ref> and I tell you its been a tough go to pull through. And perform twice a day But I done it. Am glad Paxton and party are going in.<ref target="n03">3</ref> As I am so anxious to have Paxton of all men&#8212; Let Paxton &amp; party say what they want to do. And how much money all are to put up. And Salsbury and I will be on deck with ours&#8212;<ref target="n04">4</ref> and by the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of June I can help you out&#8212; As every body is so down on Hymer&#8212; Let Paxton select a General Superintendent.<ref target="n05">5</ref> I am Satisfied. What about Cunningham &amp; Ryan &amp; Hymer putting up?<ref target="n06">6</ref></p>
<closer>
<salute><choice><sic>Hastly</sic><corr>Hastily</corr></choice> yours&#8212; </salute>

<signed>W. F. Cody</signed>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>

<back>

<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Although Cody did not include the year in the dateline of this letter, it was almost certainly written in 1895.  Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in Hartford, Connecticut, on June 3, 1895.</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in New Haven, Connecticut, on Friday, May 31, 1895.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: Cody and Beck were hoping to persuade <persName xml:id="paxton.w">William A. Paxton</persName>, a successful businessman in Omaha, Nebraska, to invest in their Big Horn Basin irrigation venture, which would become the <orgName xml:id="company.s">Shoshone Irrigation Company</orgName>.  Paxton decided against joining the venture.</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: <persName xml:id="salsbury.n">Nate Salsbury</persName>, Cody's business partner and manager of Buffalo Bill's Wild West, joined Cody as an investor in the Shoshone Irrigation Company</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: Cody refers to <persName xml:id="hymer.w">William E. Hymer</persName>, an early partner in his Big Horn Basin irrigation project who was later dropped from the venture by the other partners.  According to historian Robert Bonner, Hymer's participation was a key reason why William A. Paxton chose not to invest in the project.</note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: "Cunningham" is likely <persName xml:id="cunningham.d">Dennis Cunningham</persName> (b. 1843), who then owned considerable property in Omaha, Nebraska, and was a partner in an Omaha-based contracting firm.  "Ryan" is likely Jerry Ryan, who had been sent by George Beck to assess irrigation possibilities in the Big Horn Basin in 1893.  A man named Jerry Ryan was one of Cunningham's partners in his Omaha contracting business, but it is not clear whether Cunningham's associate was the same person who reconnoitered the Big Horn Basin for Beck.  Cunningham and Ryan were apparently stockholders in the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company, the predecessor of the Shoshone Irrigation Company, the concern that actually built the <orgName xml:id="canal.c">Cody Canal</orgName>.  Neither man appears to have contributed much capital to the project, and neither remained in the inner circle of investors when the Shoshone Irrigation Company replaced the previous company.</note>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
