<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11448">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Royal Visit to the American Exhibition</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11448</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">Royal Visit to the American Exhibition</title>
<title level="j">The Era</title>
<pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
<date when="1887-06-18">June 18, 1887</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>American bison</term>
<term>American bison hunting</term>
<term>American Indians</term>
<term>Bars (Drinking establishments)</term>
<term>Cowboys</term>
<term>Firearms</term>
<term>Railroads</term>
<term>Revolvers</term>
<term>Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain)</term>
<term>Stagecoaches</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Albert Victor, Prince, Duke of Clarence and Avondale, 1864-1892</term>
<term>Alexandra, Queen, consort of Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1844-1925</term>
<term>Bartholdi, Fr&#233;d&#233;ric Auguste, 1834-1904</term>
<term>Burke, John M., d. 1917</term>
<term>Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1841-1910</term>
<term>Louise, Princess Royal, Duchess of Fife, 1867-1931</term>
<term>Maud, Queen, consort of Haakon VII, King of Norway, 1869-1938</term>
<term>Mikhail Nikolaevich, Grand Duke of Russia, 1832-1909</term>
<term>Oakley, Annie, 1860-1926</term>
<term>Salsbury, Nathan, 1846-1902</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>London (England)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
<change when="2015"><name>Clark, Linda</name>, <name>Hanna, Sam</name> and <name>Adams, Deb</name> Proofreading</change>
<change when="2015"><name>McQuay, Colleen</name> and <name>Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="type">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11448.001"/>

<head>ROYAL VISIT to the AMERICAN EXHIBITION.</head>

<milestone unit="line"/>

<p>The Princess of Wales<ref target="n01">1</ref> and a large party paid an unexpected and informal visit to the <orgName xml:id="exhibition.am">American Exhibition</orgName> on Wednesday morning. The party included Prince Albert Victor, the Princesses Victoria, Maud, and Louise of Wales,<ref target="n02">2</ref> the Grand Duke Michael of Russia,<ref target="n03">3</ref> and gentlemen in attendance. On reaching the Exhibition at eleven o'clock, the Royal party at once proceeded to the Wild West Camp, where they were received by Colonel Cody (Buffalo Bill), <persName xml:id="salsbury.n">Mr Nate Salisbury</persName>, and <persName xml:id="burke.j">Major John M. Burke</persName>, and after visiting Colonel Cody's tent they proceeded to the Royal box. At the request of the Princess, <persName xml:id="smith.l">Miss Lilian Smith</persName> and <persName xml:id="oakley.a">Miss Annie Oakley</persName> gave their exhibition of shooting, and the Grand Duke Michael then shot at a number of balls thrown from the trap and with Miss Oakley's guns, making a capital score. The Old Deadwood Stage Coach was next brought out, and, Colonel Cody himself driving, the Royal party made the tour of the ring several times. Unusual precautions against accident were taken, the subsequent attack on the coach being made, not by the Indians, but by the more trustworthy cowboys, who gave the visitors an idea of an attack on the coach by road agents or highwaymen. At the conclusion of this episode the Grand Duke Michael and a number of other gentlemen were furnished with mounts by Col. Cody and given a few hints as to the method of riding on a Mexican saddle, and then the buffaloes were stampeded in the open, and the gentlemen joined with the cowboys in the mimic buffalo hunt, having been prepared with revolvers for the purpose. They expressed themselves as greatly pleased with the experience, while the Princess was evidently highly amused at the strange spectacle. The party also visited the stable and the buffalo corral, after which the Indians sang a number of characteristic songs, and the party then returned to the American Exhibition, where they were received by <persName xml:id="whitley.j">Mr John R. Whitley</persName>, Mr Vincent A. Applin,<ref target="n04">4</ref> Mr Burnet Landreth,<!--link to Burnet Landreth personography--> and Mr Townsend Percy,<ref target="n05">5</ref> and conducted to the Art Gallery and trophy-rooms. After inspecting these and the other exhibits, they proceeded through the building to the Western Gardens, where the switch-back railroad had been prepared for their reception. The Princess made two round trips on the switch-back, which required two cars to convey the party. Next they proceeded to the toboggan slide, where the Princess went down twice conducted by Colonel Montague,<ref target="n06">6</ref> while the Princesses and other members of the party made some half-dozen trips. The Royal party expressed themselves greatly delighted with the novel and exhilarating pastime. Having inspected Bartholdi's<ref target="n07">7</ref> diorama of New York Harbour, Bertram and Co.'s American bar<ref target="n08">8</ref> was visited for refreshments, and the Princess and party partook of some "cool American drinks." The Royal party left at two p.m.</p>




</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: The Princess of Wales was Princess Alexandra of Denmark (Alexandra Caroline Marie Charlotte Louise Julia, 1844-1925) and later Queen Alexander, consort to Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1844-1925.</note> 

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: Prince Albert Victor of Wales was Albert Victor Christian Edward (1864-1892), the Duke of Clarence and Avondale. Princess Victoria of Wales was Victoria Alexandra Olga Mary (1868-1935); Princess Maud of Wales was Maud Charlotte Mary Victoria (1869-1938). All three were grandchildren of Queen Victoria.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: Grand Duke Michael Nikolaevich (Nicolaievich) of Russia (1832-1909), son of Tsar Nicholas I of Russia (1796-1855) and brother to Alexander II of Russia (1818-1881).</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: Vincent Augustin Applin (1850-1895), Executive Secretary for the American Exhibition and a member of the Incorporated Law Society of London and Solicitor of the Supreme Court.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: Townsend Percy (b.~1847), the official Press Representative for the American Exhibition and a member of the Royal Geographical Society of London, was an author and lecturer.</note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: Colonel Montague is not identified.</note>

<note xml:id="n07">Note 7: Fr&#233;d&#233;ric Auguste Bartholdi (1834-1904), the French sculptor who is best known for designing the Statue of Liberty.</note>

<note xml:id="n08">Note 8: Bertram &amp; Co's American bar is not further identified.</note> 

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
