<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11417">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">In Buffalo Bill's Wild West</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
<name n="Stetler, Julia S.">Julia S. Stetler</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11417</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>This article had to be pieced together from 42d and 42c, as marked in the text. 42b is identical to a passage within 42d and has thus been integrated into this document. Eyewitness report of the show before opening and of the opening performance. Civilization vs. Prairie analogy, comparison of German "Sch&#252;tzenfest" with the Wild West performance, the appeal of these types of shows and the authenticity of the Wild West, descriptions of the participants, cowboys, Indians. Description of the first performance and the show acts.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main" xml:lang="en">In Buffalo Bill's Wild West</title>
<title level="j">Freisinnige Zeitung</title>
<date when="1890-07-24">July 24, 1890</date>
<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
<extent></extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>McCracken Research Library, Buffalo Bill Center of the West</repository>
<idno>MS6.3776.42.02-03 (German scrapbook)</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p></p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="type"><p></p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person></person>
</listPerson>
<listOrg>
<org></org>
</listOrg>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
<change when="2015"><name xml:id="fc">Christianson, Frank</name>; <name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name>; <name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article" xml:lang="de">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11417.001"/>

<head>In Buffalo Bill's Wild West.</head>

<p>Auf dem weiten, sonst so w&#252;sten Platz zwischen <hi rend="italic">Kurf&#252;rstendamm</hi> und <hi rend="italic">Augsburgerstrasse,</hi> wo die Ausl&#228;ufer Berliner Gebiets in's <hi rend="italic">Charlottenburger</hi> Territorium &#252;bergehen, ist seit gestern eine neue Welt entstanden. Eine seltsam eigenartige Mischung weltst&#228;dtischer Civilisation und amerikanischen Indianerlebens bietet sich hier pl&#246;ltzlich dem Blick des Zuschauers, da &#252;berrascht hier neben breitstirnigen B&#252;ffeln ein <hi rend="italic">Café Bauer,</hi> neben Sioux ein Zigarren-Kiosk, nebst den Indianerwigwams eine Sanit&#228;tswache, ein Telephon-Zimmer und neben vielen Anderem sogar eine in Berlin fast ganz unbekannte Einrichtung, ein Zimmer f&#252;r Journalisten. &#8222;Seht, die Wilden sind doch bessere Menschen!&#8221; m&#246;chte man dem Komitee unseres in Regenstr&#246;men verflossenen Sch&#252;tzenfestes zurufen, wenn bei den Schiessk&#252;nsten, die wir bei Buffalo Bill zu sehen bekommen, nicht die ganze Sch&#252;tzenbr&#252;derkunst ohnedies schon v&#246;llig in Vergessenheit gebracht w&#252;rd. Es ist ein wahres Gl&#252;ck, dass das zweifelhafte Vergn&#252;gen des <hi rend="italic">Budenschiessens</hi> bereits zu Ende gegangen ist und nun nicht zu konkurriren braucht mit den Leuten Buffalo Bill's, zu denen fr&#252;her auch der famose Kunstsch&#252;tze Carver geh&#246;rte. Wie sollten unsere Sch&#252;tzenk&#246;nige bestehen z.B. gegen die grazi&#246;se Miss Anny, die einen Pfennig hoch in die Luft schleudert und ihn krummgeschossen mit einem Pistolenschuss wieder herunterholt. </p>

<p>Doch wir d&#252;rfen nicht nur Miss Anny (sic) r&#252;hmen&#8212;das ganze so eigenartig interessante Unternehmen ist ein erfolgreicher Schuss ins Centrum. Die kleinen Vorf&#252;hrungen wilder V&#246;lkerschaften haben allm&#228;hlich an Interesse in Berlin verloren, sie werden nicht mehr so ernst genommen und auf K&#252;nstlerfesten&#8212;so n&#228;mlich in <hi rend="italic">Schlachtensee</hi> bereits ganz k&#246;stlich parodiert. Was Buffalo Bill aber den Berlinern bietet, das ist schon dem ganzen Arrangement nach etwas wiklich [missing part] und verdient die rege Teilnahme auch des verw&#246;hnten Berliner Publikums. </p>

<p>Buffalo Bill, oder in unser geliebtes deutsch &#252;bertragen &#8222;B&#252;ffel-Wilhelm&#8221;, nennt sich jener grosse, schlanke, elastische Oberst W.F. Cody, dessen Charakterkopf mit energischem Schnurr- und Knebelbart unter seinem m&#228;chtigen Kalabreser seit einigen Tagen bereits von den Litfasss&#228;ulen herabblickt. Buffalo Bill ist eine Gestalt, in der sich die Vornehmheit des Kavaliers mit der Energie des Pfadfinders und der Romantik des Abenteurers eigenartig, aber sehr sympathisch mischt. Der scharfe durchdringende Blick jenes sch&#246;nen Auges erzwingt Beachtung und Respekt. Buffalo Bill ist ganz der Mann dazu, seine zweihundertk&#246;pfige Gesellschaft in Disziplin zu halten, nachdem ihm damals das Kunstst&#252;ck gegl&#252;ckt ist, diese nicht nur ethnographisch interessante Truppe zusammen zu bringen. Das weite Lager, das da in der N&#228;he der Station Zoologischer Garten aufgeschlagen ist, zerf&#228;llt in die 39 Wigwams der Indianer aus Arapahoee, Brow- und Blackfeet, Cheyenne, Sioux und die Zelte der Cowsboys. </p>

<p>In kegelf&#246;rmigen, mit roh bemaltem Segeltuch umspannten R&#228;umen, die mit Holzdielen versehen sind, kauern hier die Indianer jener f&#252;nf, fr&#252;her vielfach verfeindeten St&#228;mme, die jetzt ihren Frieden mit der Regierung gemacht und in den Reservationen untergebracht sind. Nur unter der Verpflichtung, sie in die Reservationen wieder zur&#252;ckzuf&#252;hren, konnte Buffalo Bill sie nach Europa bringen. Jeder der f&#252;nf St&#228;mme ist hier durch seinen H&#228;uptling vertreten, an der Spitze dieser H&#228;uptlinge aber steht Rocky-Bear, der dem Stamme der Sioux angeh&#246;rige &#8222;Felsenb&#228;r&#8221;, ein F&#252;nfziger etwa, Gatte zweier Frauen und Vater von elf Kindern. Leider haben sich die Familien dem Europazuge der Indianer nicht angeschlossen; von Indianerrinnen sieht man hier nur die Frauen der beiden Dolmetsch-Blassgesichter. Dagegen finden sich bei den Cowboys mehrere Damen, vorz&#252;gliche Sch&#252;tzen und Reiterinnen. Nicht alle freilich sind so interessant und liebensw&#252;rdig wie Miss Anny Arkley, jene jugendliche schwarz&#228;ugige Amerikanerin mit energischem, gerbr&#228;unten Antlitz&#8212;am allerwenigsten ist dies die Medizinfrau der Truppe, eine 60 j&#228;hrige Frau Whittaker, die nicht nur den inneren und &#228;ussern Menschen, sondern auch die Garderobe der Indainer kurirt und ausflickt.  </p>

<p>Ueberhaupt ist f&#252;r das leibliche Wohl der Truppe ganz vortrefflich gesorgt. Zwei amerikanische K&#246;che sind emsig mit der Herstellung der Mahlzeiten bem&#252;ht, f&#252;r die seit lange schon mit hiesigen Lieferanten Vertr&#228;ge abgeschlossen sind. Auch die Indianer haben sich bereits&#8212;was das Essen betrifft&#8212;zur Civilisation bequemt, sogar zu Messer und Gabel. Amerika ist nun einmal das Land der Ueberraschungen, der Lebensl&#228;ufe in auf-und absteigender Linie. Da sendet es uns die auf dem Kriegspfad so gef&#252;rchteten Indianer, wir treten in die Zelte der H&#228;uptlinge ein, die in ihrer unterdr&#252;ckten, ges&#228;nftigten Wildheit uns anmuten wie die resignirt melancholischen [L&#246;wen?] und Tiger in den K&#228;figen des Zoologischen Gartens&#8212;und diese Indianer und Cowboys bedient nun ein junger Kaffeekoch, der bereits einmal ein Verm&#246;gen von 200 000 Franks besessen und in Monte Carlo verspielt hat. Welch' interessante bluterf&#252;llte Vergangenheit sie haben m&#252;ssen, diese Indianerh&#228;uptlinge, besonders der nicht jetzt den Eindruck ungez&#252;gelter bestialischer Wildheit machende Oberh&#228;uptling Rocky-Bear, dessen aus Hirschleder gefertigtes, mit Perlen und B&#252;ffelsehnen versehenes Kriegshemd geschm&#252;ckt ist mit einer ansehnlichen Sammlung von lockenartig aufgeh&#228;ngten Haaren, der Troph&#228;e vom Haupte all derer, denen er im Kampfe den Garaus gemacht hat! </p>

<p>Weniger zu sentimentalen Erw&#228;gungen geben die Cowboys Anlass, die in Berlin bereits bekannte Erscheiningen sind. Die diesmal erschienenen Cowboys sind sehr behaglich, sehr elegant eingerichtet, ihre Zelte zeigen mehr Komfort, asl sie f&#252;r gew&#246;hnlich dr&#252;ben, jenseits des grossen Wassers, wohl haben m&#246;gen. Am elegantesten freilich ist das durch einen B&#252;ffelkopf und sein rotges&#228;umtes Dach sofort auff&#228;lliges Zelt Buffalo Bill's, in dem sich unter dem Sternenbanner der Union und neben dem Bilde des grossen Washington indische und japanische Rarit&#228;ten, Reiseerinnerungen, Bilder etc. in buntem Durcheinander befinden. Manch drollig heiteres Genrebild bot sich uns in beiden Lagern schon bei unserem ersten Besuch, bei dem wir zum Schluss auch die etwa hundert Tiere umfgassende Viehherde besichtigten, der einige zwanzig glut&#228;ugige Prairie-B&#252;ffel angeh&#246;ren, die auf deutschem Boden, in M&#252;nchen, sich um zwei Babies vermehrt haben. </p>

<p>Vor einem sehr zahlreichen Publikum, das dichtgedr&#228;ngt die sehr komfortabel angelegten Logen und Trib&#252;nen f&#252;llte, hat nun Mittwoch Nachmittag die erste Vorstellung von Buffalo Bill's Wild-West stattgefunden. Diese Produktionen unterscheiden sich schon insofern vorteilhaft von denen vieler anderer wilden Truppen, als es sich hier nicht um die Schaustellung gelernter Szenen handelt, sondern um die ungeschminkte Wiedergabe des Lebens jener unserer Kultur so entlegenen Weltstriche. Aber freilich&#8212;Buffalo Bill's Truppe ist schon einige Jahre in Europa und so ist es nat&#252;rlich, dass in einigen Vorf&#252;hrungen sich doch bereits ein leichter Mangel and Urspr&#252;nglichkeit geltend macht. Aber dies ist doch nur sehr selten der Fall, so in der Darstellung, welche eine Wiedergabe des Zweikampfes zwischen Buffalo Bill und dem Siuox H&#228;uptling Yellow-Hand vom Jahre 1875 sein soll und in dem Angriff auf das Grenzdorf. Dieser Eindruck verschwindet aber sofort, sobald Indianer und Cowboys und Vaqueros auf ihren behenden, z&#228;hen, im Laufe kaum den Boden ber&#252;hrenden Pferden, welche von der spanischen, durch Cortez in Mexiko eingef&#252;hrten Rasse abstammen, dahinjagen und &#252;ber die weite Fl&#228;che hin sich das bunte, reichbewegte Bild der durcheinander st&#252;rmenden Reiter entwickelt. Mit einem Sprung sind sie vom Pferde und wieder im Sattel&#8212;dies zeigt besonders die interessante Darstellung des ehemaligen Ponypost, bei der der Reiter alle zehn Meilen das Pferd wechseln und f&#252;nfzig Meilen ohne Anhalten reiten musste. Die 16 Nummern umfassenden Produktionen enthalten mehrere Darstellungen fr&#252;herer Einrichtungen West-Amerikas. So wird u.A. auch die echte &#8222;Old Dead word Coach&#8221; (sic) vorgef&#252;hrt, ein historischer alter Postwagen, in dem nach der Versicherung des Programms bereits &#8222;Zwei Pr&#228;sidenten der Vereinigten Staaten, vier K&#246;nige und andere F&#252;rstlichkeiten&#8221; gefahren sind und in die auch heute eine amerikanische Familie piet&#228;tvoll hineinstieg, um sich von den heranst&#252;rmenden Indianern angreifen und den Cowboys unter Buffalo Bill's F&#252;hrung erretten zu lassen. Und all diese Indianer-Attacken, all diese K&#228;mpfe zwischen den westamerikanischen Kuhhirten und ihren indianischen Gegnern sind um so instruktiver und dramatischer, als in beiden Parteien noch M&#228;nner vorhanden sind, die wirklich einander fr&#252;her feindlich gegen&#252;ber gestanden haben. Wir sind zwar nicht der Meinung Brick Pomerons, der eine solche Vorstellung Buffalo Bill's f&#252;r wichtiger h&#228;lt als das ganze Drama von &#8222;Romeo und Julia&#8221;, aber fesselnd und lehrreich ist dieses Bild, das die Produktionen von den Gebr&#228;uchen und der Lebensweise im fernen Westen der Union entrollen, in hohem Masse. Dazu kommt, dass Menschen- und Tiermaterial der Truppe ein aussergew&#246;hnlich gutes ist. Welch verbl&#252;ffend sichere Sch&#252;tzin, welch' tollk&#252;hne gewandte Reiterin ist diese, aus Far-West stammende Anny Oakley. Ausser ihr und Buffalo Bill, der besonders zu Pferde ungemein stattlich repr&#228;sentirt, besitzt die Truppe in dem kleinen J. Broker und in C. Daly noch zwei Sch&#252;tzen von erstaunlicher Trefflichkeit&#8212;ersterer schiesst und trifft sogar auf dem Kopfe stehend. Von grosser Wirkung war die Vorf&#252;hrung der Bucking-Pferde, die sich keinem Reiter f&#252;gen wollen: das eine der Tiere erhob sich kerzengrad und liess sich dann auf den R&#252;cken fallen, um dem Reiter zu entgehen. Das Lassowerfen, die B&#252;ffeljagd, Wettreiten von Hinterw&#228;ldlerinnen und Indianerknaben bilden das weitere Programm dieser Vorstellungen, die ihren H&#246;hepunkt erreichen, wenn der Boden erdr&#246;hnt von den Hufschl&#228;gen der dahinwirbelnden Rosse. Nach der Vorstellung bietet eine Wanderung durch die Lagerzelte immer wieder Neues und Fesselndes und hier besonders gewinnt man den Eindruck, dass es nicht eine blosse Schaustellung ist, die Buffalo Bill, der ber&#252;hmte Kundschafter der amerikanischen Regierung hier bietet, sondern ein ebenso abwechslungsreiches wie getreues Bild wirklichen Lebens, erh&#246;ht durch die zahlreichen echten Ger&#228;tschaften, Waffen etc. die sich in reicher F&#252;lle besonders in dem reichen Zelte Buffalo Bill's finden.</p>


</div1>

<div1 type="article" xml:lang="en">
<head>In Buffalo Bill's Wild West</head>

<p>Yesterday, in the large, usually deserted space between <hi rend="italic">Kurf&#252;rstendamm</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Augsburgerstrasse,</hi> where the far reaches of the Berlin city area change over into the territory of <hi rend="italic">Charlottenburg,</hi> a new world emerged. A strange mix of urban civilization and American Indian life presents itself to the onlooker, and thus we are not surprised when we find a <hi rend="italic">Caf&#233; Bauer</hi> adjacent to a herd of buffalo, a cigar kiosk next to the Sioux and their wigwams, as well as a sick room, a telephone room, and in addition to many other amenities even a press room, which is a virtually unfamiliar facility in all of Berlin. "See, the wild men are the better men yet!" you would want to shout to the organizing committee of our Sch&#252;tzenfest, which nearly drowned in the torrential rains, but in view of the shooting skills of Buffalo Bill's troupe we have already forgotten the entire shooting artistry of our club members.<ref target="n01">1</ref> How lucky for them that the dubious entertainment of <hi rend="italic">Budenschiessen</hi><ref target="n02">2</ref> has already concluded and does not need to compete with Buffalo Bill's people, who used to call the famous trick shooter <persName xml:id="carver.w">Carver</persName> one of their members. How could our Sch&#252;tzenk&#246;nige<ref target="n03">3</ref> stand in comparison to, for example, the gracious <persName xml:id="oakley.a">Miss Anny</persName>, who is able to shoot a penny out of the air with a single shot of her revolver. </p> 

<p>But we should not only credit Miss Anny&#8212;the whole strange and interesting company is a successful center shot. The small companies of exotic peoples have slowly lost their appeal in Berlin and they are not taken very seriously anymore. At art fairs&#8212;as it just happened in <hi rend="italic">Schlachtensee</hi><ref target="n04">4</ref>&#8212;they have become the targets of exquisite parody.  Given the entire arrangement, what Buffalo Bill is offering to the Berliners is something [illegible] and deserves the active participation even of the spoiled Berlin audience. </p> 

<p>Buffalo Bill, or translated into our beloved German, "B&#252;ffel-Wilhelm," is the name by which this tall, lean and athletic Colonel W. F. Cody goes, whose characteristic face with strong beard and mighty cowboy hat has looked down on us from the large advertising columns for the last few days. Buffalo Bill is a person in whom the nobility of the gentleman and the energy of the scout and the romance of adventure blend in a strange yet very sympathetic way. The sharp, piercing look of his eyes commands respect. Buffalo Bill is perfectly suited to keep his company of 200 disciplined after having pulled off the amazing feat of assembling this troupe, which is not only interesting in an ethnological way. The large camp that has been erected near the station of the zoological garden consists of 39 Indian tents of the Arapahoe, Brown- and Blackfeet, Cheyenne, and Sioux tribes as well as those of the cowboys. </p>

<p>The cone-shaped, red-painted rooms that are equipped with wooden floors shelter the Indians of those five tribes, who in the past were often enemies. Now they sit together and have made their peace with the government, which relocated them onto the reservations. Buffalo Bill was only able to bring them to Europe after he had promised to return them to the reservations. Each of the five tribes is represented by its chief, but the head of the chiefs is Rocky Bear,<ref target="n05">5</ref> who belongs to the tribe of the Sioux. He is in his fifties, married to two women and father of eleven children. Unfortunately, their families have not joined the European adventure of these Indians; the only female Indians are the wives of the two white translators. In contrast, there are several women among the cowboys, superb riders and shots. Of course not all of them are as interesting and lovely as Miss Anny Arkley, this youthful, black-eyed American with strong, tanned features&#8212;and then there is the medicine woman of the troupe, a sixty-year old Mrs. Whittaker, who does not only cure the bodies of the humans inside and out, but also takes care of the wardrobe of the Indians.</p> 

<p>The culinary needs of the troupe are very well met. Two American cooks are very busy preparing the meals, and contracts with local suppliers have long been arranged. Even the Indians, in regards to food, have adjusted to civilization and the use of silverware. After all, America is the land of surprises, of ascending and descending career paths. Here we are sent to the Indians, feared tremendously when on the warpath, and we enter into the tents of their chiefs who seem to us in their subdued, tamed wildness more like the resigned and melancholic lions and tigers in the cages of the zoological garden&#8212;and these Indians and cowboys are now served by a young coffee server who once lost his entire fortune of 200,000 Francs in a casino in Monte Carlo. What an interesting, bloody past these Indian chiefs must have, especially this Rocky Bear, who does not make a very untamed and beast-like impression on us at the moment. His war shirt is made from elk leather, embroidered with pearls and buffalo sinew and decorated with a substantial collection of curly hair, strung up, a trophy from the heads of all those whose life he snuffed out in battle.</p> 

<p>The cowboys give a little less reason for sentimentalities, since they have made regular appearances in Berlin. These cowboys this time around are housed very comfortably and elegantly; their tents are equipped with more items of comfort here than they probably usually are on the other side of the great water. Of course the most elegant among them is the tent of Buffalo Bill, which sports a buffalo head and a red seam around the roof. Inside, the star spangled banner is hung next to a picture of the great Washington and Indian and Japanese rarities, travel mementoes, pictures etc. in a colorful clutter. Another cheerful image was presented to us already on our first visit to the camp, when we visited the herd of animals towards the end, which is about 100 strong. Among it are about 20 buffalo with glowing eyes, which were joined by two buffalo babies born here on German soil, in Munich. </p>

<p>The first performance of Buffalo Bill's Wild West took place Wednesday afternoon in front of a very numerous audience that filled the very comfortable seating at the arena. These productions are very different in the positive sense from many other troupes, because these are not just the presentation of rehearsed acts but the naked and truthful representation of the life in the far West that is so unfamiliar to us. Granted, since Buffalo Bill and his troupe have been traveling in Europe for a few years, some of the acts seem to be a little bit lacking in originality. But this is only an occasional occurrence, for example in the act that supposedly displays that duel between Buffalo Bill and the Sioux chief Yellow Hand<!--link to Yellow Hair personography--> from the year 1875, as well as in the act "attack on a settler's cabin." This impression, however, vanishes immediately when the Indians, cowboys and vaqueros chase across the arena on their quick, tenacious horses that barely touch the ground when running; they are descendants of the Spanish breed of horses that Cortez introduced to Mexico; they chase across the wide arena and create a colorful, dynamic image of riders. Suddenly they jump out of their saddles, and just as quickly they are back in, this is especially well demonstrated in the interesting display of the former Pony Express, for which the rider had to change his horse every 10 miles and had to ride for 50 miles without a break. The 16 acts include several that display original items of the Western United States, for example the authentic "Old Dead word Coach"<ref target="n06">6</ref>, a historic old mail coach that has held, according to the program, "two presidents of the United States, four kings and other nobles." And today was no exception, because an American family volunteered to climb in and be attacked by charging Indians and be saved by Buffalo Bill and his cowboys. All of these Indian attacks, all these battles between the western American cowboys and their Indian adversaries are the more instructive and the more dramatic because in both parties there are men that were actual enemies in the past. We wouldn't go so far as to share Brick Pomeroy's opinion, who believes that the performance of Buffalo Bill is more important than the whole tragedy of Romeo and Juliet;<ref target="n07">7</ref>;  however, it is a captivating and educational portrait that these productions of the customs and way of life of the far West and the United States provide, very much so. In addition to this, the human and animal cast of this troupe is especially extraordinary. What an amazingly sure shot, what a courageous and skilled rider she is, this Anny Oakley from the far West. In addition to her and Buffalo Bill, who is especially impressive on horseback, the troupe also includes little J. Broker<ref target="n08">8</ref> and C. Daly,<ref target="n09">9</ref> two other trick shooters of extraordinary talent&#8212;the first shoots and hits even in a headstand. Of tremendous effect was the presentation of the bucking horses, which did not subdue to any rider: one of the animals reared straight up into a vertical position and then threw itself on the ground in order to evade its rider. The lasso throwing, the buffalo hunt, the horse races of women and Indian boys are further acts in the program, which culminates in the deafening thunder of the galloping horses' hooves. After the performance, a stroll through the camp offers ever new and captivating images, and you gain the impression that this is not a simple show that Buffalo Bill, the famous scout of the American government, offers here but a dynamic and authentic representation of the real life, which is augmented by a plethora of authentic items, weapons, etc. that can be found in Buffalo Bill's tent.</p>




</div1>


</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Annual shooting competition of the local shooting club, followed by a large party, which is called the "Sch&#252;tzenfest."</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: Shooting gallery at a fair, here used with a derisive connotation, since it refers to the master shooting competition at the shooting club.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: "Shooting royalty," i.e. the winners of the annual competition.</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: Schlachtensee is a part of Berlin.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: <persName xml:id="rockybear">Rocky Bear</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Inyan Mato</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Eya Matao</hi> (1836-1909), an Oglala Sioux chief.</note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: Should read "Old Deadwood Coach."</note>

<note xml:id="n07">Note 7: Journalist and editor Brick Pomeroy, in a newspaper article that was included in the Wild West program, noted that ". . . All of this imaginary Romeo and Juliet business sinks to utter insignificance in comparison to the drama of existence, as is here so well enacted, and all the operas in the world appear like pretty playthings for emasculated children by the side of the setting of reality. . ."</note>  

<note xml:id="n08">Note 8: "little J. Broker" is probably <persName xml:id="baker.l">Johnny Baker</persName>.</note>
 
<note xml:id="n09">Note 9: Claude L. Daly (~1865-1892) was contracted to perform in the European tour of Buffalo Bill's Wild West as a sharpshooter; he died of cholera in Brussels, Belgium, in November, 1892.</note> 
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
