<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11420">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Buffalo Bill in Berlin</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
<name n="Stetler, Julia S.">Julia S. Stetler</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11420</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>Eyewitness report of the opening performance in Berlin. The author uses the civilization vs. Prairie metaphor, describes concessions, the cowboy band, and the Indians. When the show opens, he describes the participants and the overall impression, as well as the show acts: shooting, Deadwood Stage Coach in particular. Remarks that there is a mistake in the program. </note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main" xml:lang="en">Buffalo Bill in Berlin</title>
<title level="j">Das Kleine Journal</title>
<date when="1890-07-24">July 24, 1890</date>
<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
<extent></extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>McCracken Research Library, Buffalo Bill Center of the West</repository>
<idno>MS6.3776.43.02 (German scrapbook)</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p></p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="type"><p></p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person></person>
</listPerson>
<listOrg>
<org></org>
</listOrg>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
<change when="2015"><name xml:id="fc">Christianson, Frank</name>; <name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name>; <name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article" xml:lang="de">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11420.001"/>

<head type="main">&#8222;Buffalo Bill in Berlin.&#8221;</head>

<head type="sub">(Originalbericht des <hi rend="italic">&#8222;Kleinen Journal.&#8221;</hi>)</head>

<p>Der Zug nach dem Westen, diese moderne Kulturbewegung, ist pl&#246;tzlich ganz verwildert, ist ein wilder Zug nach dem &#8222;Wilden Westen&#8221; geworden, denn in den n&#228;chsten Tagen werden Tausende hinausstr&#246;men nach dem Kurf&#252;rstendamm wie gestern und durch ihre Menge wie gestern <hi rend="italic">ad oculos</hi> beweisen, da&#223; die Stadtbahn eine mangelhafte Einrichtung ist, nicht das geeignete Mittel, um den Verkehr von Berlin nach der Prairie und namentlich umgekehrt zu bew&#228;ltigen. Denn die Prairie hat sich jetzt dort drau&#223;en aufgethan oder vielmehr zugethan, denn wir stehen pl&#246;tzlich an einer Stelle, wo die Civilisation mit Brettern vernagelt ist und die Wildheit gegen 1 bis 4 Mark Eintrittsgeld anf&#228;ngt. Uebrigens ist auch ein bi&#223;chen Zahm-Amerika mit hergekommen, die Verk&#228;ufer von &#8222;Puogemms,&#8221; wof&#252;r wir das sch&#246;ne deutsche Wort &#8222;Programme&#8221; haben, von einem eigenth&#252;mlichen, aus Mais und Zucker hergestelleten, in Seidenpapier eingewickelten Geb&#228;ck, von moussirendem Hochheimer auf Eis und dergleichen Erfrischungsscherzen, die auf den Trib&#252;nen angeboten werden, d&#252;rfen als Vertreter desselben gelten. Doch da sind wir schon auf den Trib&#252;nen, die in weitem Viereck den Platz umz&#228;unen, die vornehmen von einem Zeltdach &#252;berdeckt, die anderen umso luftiger. Es ist f&#252;nf Uhr, die Vorstellung wird bald ihren Anfang nehmen, schon hat die Musik begonnen. Nicht etwa irgend eine preu&#223;ische Regimentsmusik, sondern auch eine solche transatlantischer Herkunft. Es ist eine echte Cowboy-Kapelle, die sich hier h&#246;ren l&#228;&#223;t, und was spielt sie als erste Nummer? &#8222;Drunten in der Elbe schwimmt ein Krokodil.&#8221; Also auch nach dem Wilden Westen schon ist die herrliche Melodie gedrungen, das ist die Macht der Musik! Nat&#252;rlich wird man unter den besonderen Umst&#228;nden auch zu einem besonderen Texte greifen m&#252;ssen. Wir machen einstweilen den Vorschlag:

<quote>
<lg><l>Hier ist nicht die Elbe</l>
<l>Und kein Krokodil.</l>
<l>Indianer, roth'  und gelbe,</l>
<l>Und Buffalo Bill!</l></lg>
</quote>

Und roth und gelb sind die Indianer wirklich; auch blau und gr&#252;n und andere grelle Farben werden von ihnen bevorzugt, theils am Leibe, theils am Kleide. Die Sparsamsten unter ihnen beziehen ihre Garderobe einzig und allein aus dem Malkasten und die Kost&#252;me sitzen wie angegossen, ohne Naht und ohne Wattirung. Geschminkt sind diese Herren Indianer so dick aufgetragen und geschmacklos wie die Cocotten und so abwechslungsreich wie das Programm Buffalo Bill's. Das mu&#223; man ihm lassen, dem Obersten Cody, er ist ein ganz vorz&#252;glicher Regisseur. Wie er seine ganze wilde westliche Welt zun&#228;chst dem Publikum vorstellte, das war flott, gro&#223;artig und in vortrefflicher Steigerung. Wie sie dahinsausen, die Indianertrupps und die Schaaren von Cowboys und mexikanischen Vaqueros auf ihren behenden, ausdauernden Pferden, zwischen den Gruppen die einzelnen Ber&#252;hmtheiten, &#8222;Black Heart&#8221; (Schwarzes Herz), der H&#228;uptling der Arraphoes-Indianer, Buck Taylor, der K&#246;nig der Cowboys, die Indianerh&#228;uptlinge &#8222;Little Chief&#8221;, &#8222;Brave Bear&#8221;, &#8222;Eagle Horn&#8221;, wie reizend sich die Gruppe der drei Damen machte, deren eine au&#223;er ihren Reiterbravourleistungen noch die imposantesten Spr&#252;nge mit dem Pferde zum Besten gab, wie nett der junge Bennie Irving, der kleinste Cowboy der Welt, die Reihen unterbrach, bis dann nach dem Auftritt der Boy Chiefs, dem kleinen H&#228;uptlinge der Sioux, zwei wehende Fahnen, darunter das Sternenbanner, in sausender Karriere &#252;ber den Platz gef&#252;hrt wurden. Nun kam die Gruppe der Ogallala-Sioux-Indianer, der H&#228;uptling Low Neck und Rocky Bear (Felsenb&#228;r), der &#8222;Medizinmann&#8221; der Sioux, bis dann, als effektvoller Abschlu&#223; des ganzen prachtvoll entwickelten Aufzuges, nach einer kleinen Kunstpause der Oberst Cody, &#8222;Buffalo Bill&#8221;, das Haupt der Kundschafter der Armee der Vereinigten Staaten und dieser interessanten, bunten Reise-Armee, heransprengte, von Beifallsrufen und H&#228;ndeklatschen empfangen. Auf sehnigem Schimmel eine kraftvolle, geschmeidige Gestalt, das Antlitz zugleich freundlich und k&#252;hn, von langen, schon in’s Graue spielenden Haaren umweht, in mexikanischer Kleidung, den breitrandigen grauen Kalabreser k&#252;hn auf's Haupt gedr&#252;ckt, im Ganzen f&#252;r unsere Begriffe wohl etwas theatralisch, aber eine durchaus sympathische Erscheinung. Er gr&#252;&#223;t h&#246;flich die Zuschauer und kommandirt dann die Seinen, die mit kurzem Anlauf nach vorn st&#252;rmen, ein furchtbares, quiekendes, kr&#228;hendes, kreischendes Geheul aussto&#223;end, bis sie in langer Reihe in die Zeltkulissen abgaloppiren. </p>

<p>Nun beginnt die eigentliche Vorstellung, die eine Menge von reiter- und J&#228;gerkunstst&#252;cken und  –k&#252;nsten umfa&#223;t und oft wirklich Erstaunliches bietet. Um nur Einiges zu nennen, heben wir die au&#223;erordentlichen Schie&#223;proben des Fr&#228;ulein Anna Oakley, des kleinen Johann Baker und des Herrn Daly (mit der Pistole) hervor. Zuletzt zeigte sich auch Buffalo Bill als Sch&#252;tze, indem er w&#228;hrend des Galopp-Rittes nach emporgeworfenen Glaskugeln knallte. Diese Produktion geh&#246;rte zu den Meisterleistungen Dr. Carver's, und oberst Cody, der vielleicht nicht nach Wunsch disponirt war, konnte nicht eine &#228;hnliche Fertigkeit aufweisen. Als Regisseur aber hatte er nicht mehrfach Gelegenheit, sich hervorzuthun; der &#8222;Ueberfall eines Emigrantenzuges durch Indianer und Vertheidigung desselben durch die Grenzbewohner&#8221;, mit daran sich schlie&#223;enden, quadrille-&#228;hnlichem Tanz &#8222;Virginia Reel&#8221; der Cowboys und Grenzbewohnerinnen zu Pferde, sowie der &#8222;Angriff der Indianer auf den Deadwood-Postwagen, der von Buffalo Bill und den unter seinem Befehl stehenden Cowboys zur&#252;ckgeschlagen wird&#8221;, waren mit nat&#252;rlichster Lebendigkeit gegeben, ganz vortrefflich inszenirte Schauspiele. Wie bei dem Emigrantenzuge die vor 35 Jahren im Gebrauch gewesenen Wagen als &#8222;echtes Material&#8221; mitspielten, so ist auch die &#8222;Old Deadwood Coach&#8221; eine historische Rarit&#228;t. Dieser alte viersitzige und mit vier Maulthieren bespannte Postwagen, der schon recht morsch und gebrechlich aussieht und keine Fensterscheibe mehr sein eigen nennt, ist schon vielen Leuten, die bis vor 18 Jahren darin die Reise zwischen Deadwood und Cheyenne antraten, zum Leichenwagen geworden, denn die Indianer lie&#223;en nicht mit sich spa&#223;en. Heut ist die Sache weniger gef&#228;hrlich, und so lie&#223;en sich denn sogar einige der anwesenden Damen des Publikums, &#252;brigens Engl&#228;nderinnen, bereit finden, mit ihren Herren gemeinsam die Reise zu unternehmen und das bald erforderliche Gewehrgeknatter aus n&#228;chster N&#228;he mitanzuh&#246;ren. Zu diesem &#8222;blinden Wagnis&#8221; d&#252;rfte sie haupts&#228;chlich wohl die Programm-Anmerkung bewogen haben, da&#223; &#8222;zwei Pr&#228;sidenten der Vereinigten Staaten, vier K&#246;nige und andere F&#252;rstlichkeiten, welche dem Jubil&#228;um der K&#246;nigin von England beiwohnten&#8221;, in dem Wagen gesessen haben, nat&#252;rlich auch zu einer Zeit, als das schon nicht mehr gef&#228;hrlich war. Ob man &#252;brigens alles glauben soll, was in dem umfangreichen Programm zu lesen ist, wissen wir nicht, wenigstens kann man ein bi&#223;chen verwirrt werden, wenn man am Schlu&#223; der Vorrede liest, da&#223; die Unternehmer &#8222;die Ehre haben, sich nunmehr dem Wiener Publikum vorzustellen.&#8221; Ist das etwa wildwestlich, uns Berliner so ganz zu &#252;bersehen? </p>

<p>Zwei der interessantesten Nummern waren das Einreiten der wilden Pferde und die B&#252;ffeljagd. Wie die Beschreibung sagt, bocken oder springen die meisten Texas-Ponnies, wenn sie die Gelegenheit g&#252;nstig finden, diese speziellen Eigenschaften zu zeigen. Manche thun dies Stunden lang und halten nur inne, um Athem zu sch&#246;pfen. &#8222;Ein bockender Mustang ist das beweglichste Schauspiel, das man sehen kann.&#8221; Das ist richtig, die Thiere kr&#252;mmen im Sprunge den Leib v&#246;llig nach oben, w&#228;hrend Vorder- und Hinterf&#252;&#223;e sich ber&#252;hren und der Kopf zwischen die Vorderbeine gesteckt wird.</p>


</div1>


<div1 type="article" xml:lang="en">

<head type="main">Buffalo Bill in Berlin.</head>
<head type="sub">(Original report of <hi rend="italic">Das Kleine Journal</hi>).</head>

<p>The westward migration, this modern cultural movement, has suddenly gone wild, has become a migration to the "Wild West," because in the next few days thousands will pour out to the <hi rend="italic">Kurf&#252;rstendamm</hi> just like yesterday, and the masses will again prove, as was obvious yesterday, that the streetcars are an inadequate system and not the appropriate means to deal with the traffic from Berlin to the Prairie and back. It is indeed the Prairie that has materialized out there, because we are suddenly standing in a place where civilization is hidden behind boards and the wilderness begins for an entrance fee between one and four Marks. Incidentally, a little bit of "tame" America has also arrived: the vendors of "puogemms", for which we have the nice German word of "Programs."<ref target="n01">1</ref> [They also sell] a strange pastry made of corn and sugar and wrapped in silk paper, and a frothy <hi rend="italic">Hochheimer</hi><ref target="n02">2</ref> on ice and similar amusing refreshments that are offered in the stands. These [vendors] can be considered representatives of "tame" America. And then we are in the stands that surround the arena in a wide rectangle; the upper class ones covered with a tent roof, the other ones the more airy. It is five o'clock, the performance is about to start, the music is already playing. Not some kind of Prussian military band, but one with transatlantic origins. It is a real cowboy-band we can hear here, and what is their first song? "Down in the Elbe a Crocodile Swims."<ref target="n03">3</ref> Even to the Wild West this wonderful melody has reached, this is the power of music! Of course, under these special circumstances we have to apply special lyrics. Our suggestion: 
<quote><lg><l>This is not the Elbe</l>
<l>And no crocodile</l>
<l>Indians, red and yellow</l>
<l>And Buffalo Bill! </l></lg></quote>

And red and yellow the Indians truly are, also blue and green and other bright colors are their preference, partly on their bodies, partly on their clothing. The most frugal among them literally draw their wardrobe onto their bodies, and therefore their costumes fit them perfectly, no seams and no padding. The Indians' make-up is as thick and tacky as that of the <hi rend="italic">Cocotten</hi><ref target="n04">4</ref> but as varied as the program of Buffalo Bill. This we must admit, this Colonel Cody is a very exquisite producer. The way he presented his whole wild western world to the audience was fast-paced, magnificent, and in perfect progression. How they raced around, the Indian groups and the masses of cowboys and Mexican vaqueros, on their quick, arduous horses, in between the groups of several celebrities; "Black Heart<ref target="n05">5</ref>," chief of the Arapahoe, <persName xml:id="taylor.w">Buck Taylor</persName>, the king of the cowboys, the Indian chiefs "Little Chief<ref target="n06">6</ref>,"  "Brave Bear<ref target="n07">7</ref>,"  "Eagle Horn<ref target="n08">8</ref>;"  how pretty the group of three ladies presented itself, of whom, besides their excellent trick riding; one of them also demonstrated the most imposing jumps on her horse; how endearingly the young Bennie Irving, the smallest cowboy on earth, broke up the formation, all the way to the appearance of the Boy Chiefs, the small chiefs of the Sioux, two raised flags, among them the Star Spangled Banner; they all paraded around the arena in rapid succession. Now comes the group of Ogallala-Sioux Indians, chief Low Neck<ref target="n09">9</ref>,"  and Rocky Bear<ref target="n10">10</ref>,", the medicine man of the Sioux, and then, as a very dramatic conclusion of the whole glorious parade and after a small artistic pause, Colonel Cody, Buffalo Bill, chief of scouts of the United States Army and of this interesting, colorful travel-army, bursts into the arena, welcomed by applause and shouts of bravo. On a wiry white horse, a powerful, limber appearance, his expression friendly and bold at the same time, with long blowing hair slightly going into the grays, in Mexican clothing, the broad gray hat boldly propped onto his head; all in all for our sensitivities maybe a little theatrical, but overall very sympathetic appearance. He greets the audience cordially and then commands his troupe, which races forward with a short spurt while emitting a terrible, squealing, crowing, and screeching noise while they ride down the stands in a long line. </p>

<p>Now the actual show begins, which includes a multitude of trick riding and trick shooting and often is truly amazing. To mention just a few we would like to highlight the shooting of <persName xml:id="oakley.a">Ms. Annie Oakley</persName>, little <persName xml:id="baker.l">Johann Baker</persName> and Mr. Daly<ref target="n11">11</ref> (with the revolver). Lastly, Buffalo Bill also presents his shooting skills, shooting glass balls while on horseback. This act was one of the main skills of <persName xml:id="carver.w">Doc Carver</persName>, and Colonel Cody could not surpass that man, perhaps because he did not perform at his best today. However, as a producer he repeatedly had the opportunity to shine; the "attack on the emigrant train by Indians and defense of the same by the settlers" with the subsequent quadrille-like dance "Virginia Reel" of the cowboys and lady settlers on horseback, as well as the "Attack of the Indians of the Deadwood Stagecoach, which was fought back by Buffalo Bill and his cowboys" were presented with utmost vibrancy and very excellently staged. Similar to the wagons of the emigrant train that were used 35 years ago and now deployed as "authentic material" in the show, the "Old Deadwood Coach" is a historic rarity also. This old stage coach, with four seats and drawn by four mules, already looks fairly rotten and dilapidated and does not have any window panes left; it became a hearse for many people that traveled in it between Deadwood and Cheyenne up until 18 years ago, because the Indians were not to be trifled with. Today this affair is less dangerous, and therefore some of the ladies in the audience volunteered to ride in it in the arena together with their husbands (they were English, by the way), and to hear the discharge of the guns at close range. They might have persuaded to undertake this adventure after reading a note in the program that claims that "two presidents of the United States, four kings and other nobles that attended the jubilee of the <persName xml:id="victoria.q">Queen of England</persName>" have been passengers in the coach, of course also at a time at which this was not dangerous anymore. If we should believe everything that we can read in the voluminous program we do not know, but it certainly is a little confused when you read, at the end of the foreword, that the company "has the honor to introduce itself to the audience in Vienna." Is this the Wild West way, to overlook us Berliner so? </p>

<p>Two of the most interesting acts were the taming of the wild horses and the buffalo hunt. According to the description, most of the Texas ponies will buck and jump when they find the opportunity to demonstrate such special skills. Some of them do that for hours on end, and only pause to take a breath. "A bucking bronc is the most animated spectacle possible." That is correct; the animals buck their bodies up during the jump, while their front and hind feet touch and their heads are lowered between their front legs.</p>



</div1>

</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: The word the author uses here, “puogemms,” most likely stems from a false understanding of the English word “program.” It seems he wrote it phonetically, not knowing much English.</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: A specialty white wine of Germany.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: A popular folk tune widely known to the German audience.</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: A nineteenth century term for prostitutes.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: Black Heart (William Black Heart), or Cante Sapa, (born 1855), an Oglala Lakota.</note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: Little Chief (Macaci-Kaola or Itancan Cikala), next in authority to Red Shirt, was a sub-chief of the Oglala Lakota at Pine Ridge Reservation, with family ties to the Sicangu at Rosebud Reservation. Little Chief appeared with Buffalo Bill's Wild West from 1887 through perhaps as late as 1909.</note>

<note xml:id="n07">Note 7: Brave Bear was an American Indian performer in Buffalo Bill's Wild West.</note>

<note xml:id="n08">Note 8: Eagle Horn was an American Indian performer in Buffalo Bill's Wild West.</note>

<note xml:id="n09">Note 9: Low Neck is likely a reference to No Neck (b.1850-), a Hunkpapa  Lakota Sioux, U. S. Army scout for the Ninth Cavalry, and a performer in Buffalo Bill's Wild West. He co-adopted John No Neck when the child was found after the massacre at Wounded Knee, South Dakota, 1890. Chief No Neck became a peacemaker during the Ghost Dance era (1891-1900).</note>

<note xml:id="n10">Note 10: Rocky Bear, Inyan Mato or Eya Matao (b. 1836), an Oglala Sioux chief.</note>
 
<note xml:id="n11">Note 11: Mr. Daly was likely Claude Lorraine Daily (or 'Daly') (1865-1892), a young sharpshooter from Altoona, Pennsylvania, who performed with Buffalo Bill's Wild West as a pistol and revolver expert during the 1889-92 seasons. In 1892 at age 27 Mr. Daily died of cholera in Brussels, Belgium.</note>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
