<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00489">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck, July 5, 1896</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>Supported in part by a grant from the Wyoming Cultural Trust Fund, a program of the Department of State Parks and Cultural Resources.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2013</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00489</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>BBWW performed in Dayton, Ohio, on July 6, 1896. "S. V. Nagle, an associate of the firm of F. A. Nagle, Commission Merchants, of Chicago" was the agent for German settlers coming to the Big Horn Basin for the promise of cheap land [Bonner, p69-75]. The "lady" Cody refers to in this letter is probably Daisy May Sorenson, a young woman Beck hired to work for the company; Sorenson later married Beck in Red Lodge, Montana, December 1, 1897; they had three children: Betty (born 1898, later Mrs. Doyle and Mrs. J. M. Roberson), Jane (born 1900, later Mrs. Nelson T. Johnson), and George Thornton Beck Jr. (born 1908). Bonner [p35] has her maiden name spelled 'Sorrenson,' which may be correct [See http://sheridanwyolibrary.org/wp-content/uploads/Old-Settlers-Club-Applications.pdf]. Edward S. Stokes (1841-1901) was at one time a railroad and oil magnate and businessman; Stokes was an owner of the Hoffman House, an elegant hotel in Manhattan. Horace C. Alger (1857-1906) was a banker from Sheridan, Wyoming, mayor of Sheridan in 1889, and candidate for Governor of Wyoming in 1898. Cody, Beck and Alger were responsible for developing the Shoshone Irrigation Company. Elwood Mead (1858-1936) was appointed Wyoming territorial engineer in 1888, and was Wyoming's first state engineer, serving until 1899. As such, Mead was intimately involved in the drafting and administration of Wyoming's water laws. Mead's engineering reports on the Shoshone River provided crucial backing for William F. Cody and his partners in the Cody Canal project. 'Foote" was likely Robert Foote (1834-1916), a state senator representing Johnson County, Wyoming, who led the effort against the Carey Act in Wyoming. Red Lodge, Montana, was the closest rail line to Cody, Wyoming. Swiss-born Peter Yegen (1860-1937) and Christian Yegen (1857-1935) came to Billings, Montana, and in 1882 opened a large store under the name of "P. Yegen and Co." "Sage" likely refers to Sage Creek, which lies east of Cody, Wyoming. "Irma" refers to Irma Flats, which is located south of the Buffalo Bill Reservoir along the south fork of the Shoshone River.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck</title>
<date when="1896-07-05">July 5, 1896</date>
<extent>9 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Buffalo Bill Letters to George T. Beck (Acc. #9972)</repository>
<idno>ah031362-70</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>9 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>9 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Beck, George Washington Thornton, 1856-1943</term>
<term>Nagle, S. V.</term>
<term>Nagle, F. A.</term>
<term>Sorenson, Daisy May</term>
<term>Salsbury, Nathan, 1846-1902</term>
<term>Stokes, Edward S., 1841-1901</term>
<term>Alger, Horace Chapin, 1857-1906</term>
<term>Mead, Elwood, 1858-1936</term>
<term>Foote, Robert, 1834-1916</term>
<term>Yegen, Christian, 1857-1935</term>
<term>Yegen, Peter, 1860-1937</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Shoshone Irrigation District (Wyo.)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2013-07-03"><name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Added annotation</change>
  <change when="2013-02-28"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2013"><name xml:id="lh">Houze, Lynn</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2013"><name xml:id="jj">Johnston, Jeremy</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2013"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00489.001"/>

<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio.</note>


<opener>
<dateline>July 5 1896<ref target="n01">1</ref></dateline>

<salute>Dear <persName xml:id="beck.g">George</persName></salute></opener>

<p>Your letter gave me great pleasure. And it seemed to lift a weight off me. That climate out there must be very productive in regard to liars if I am to <choice><sic>beleive</sic><corr>believe</corr></choice> one sentence in your letter or else you have quite a number of enemies. For I have heard that you were trying to <choice><sic>burry</sic><corr>bury</corr></choice> me out of sight and ten thousand other things from people you little suspect. And coming so seemingly straight from so many person&#8212; And knowing I did not deserve it I was <choice><sic>commenceing</sic><corr>commencing</corr></choice> to lay pipe


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.002"/>


<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>2</fw>

to right <choice><sic>my self</sic><corr>myself</corr></choice> and fight back for <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> not my nature to lay down and quit when I am not in the wrong. No one will apol<del>i</del>ogize quicker then I will when I am wrong</p>

<p>I openly confess that I have been dissatisfied with things you have not done. I have not been dissatisfied with but one thing you have done. I did not <choice><sic>approove</sic><corr>aprove</corr></choice> of <choice><sic>engageing</sic><corr>engaging</corr></choice> the Young Lady.<ref target="n02">2</ref> Not but that she is a Lady in every sense of the word. But it was no place for a Lady. The talk it would create in that wild country might ruin the <choice><sic>Ladys</sic><corr>Lady's</corr></choice>


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.003"/>

<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>



<fw>3</fw>


good name. When we get an office and a proper place for a Lady to work in and for her to stay Then I would be perfectly willing to give women the office work to do. But running up and down a <orgName xml:id="canal.c">ditch</orgName> with Hobos <choice><sic>makeing</sic><corr>making</corr></choice> all sorts of remarks it was no place for a woman. And should it ever be my good fortune to meet the Lady I will tell her so&#8212; that it was for her good <add>I objected</add> George. Its my opinion you could have saved the co a good many dollars if you had been more careful


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.004"/>

<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>4</fw>


in regard to detail. The Books were not kept as they should have been Everything was run to loose. When a load of goods arrived for us they were not properly checked or looked after. And the way they were disposed of either for our selves sold for cash or credit it was done too carelessly The work of <choice><sic>mooveing</sic><corr>moving</corr></choice> dirt or stone. I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> think our foremen worked to advantage for instance the two miles that the Graders have <add>been</add> at <del>aw</del> <add>has</add> been to long. George&#8212; I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> blame you for you have done every thing <choice><sic>concientiously</sic><corr>conscientiously</corr></choice> But <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> not your forte</p>


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.005"/>


<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>5</fw>


<p>You cant look over your work and see and close up leaks you are not careful enough to detail. You start it going and think its being done when its not. probably I am <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr></choice> particular but I <choice><sic>cant</sic><corr>can't</corr></choice> help it. I want Everything to <choice><sic>Moove</sic><corr>move</corr></choice> And every man and horse and tools in their place not left scattered around. And if the men under you know that you know <choice><sic>whats</sic><corr>what's</corr></choice> going on your self And that they will get rounded it they <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> attend to things you


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.006"/>


<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>6</fw>

would soon see things <choice><sic>mooveing</sic><corr>moving</corr></choice> differently. And if you would only let them see that you was on to your job You bet your men would soon change for the better. George this is only my opinion given with the best of friendship and I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> want you to take it only as its <choice><sic>ment</sic><corr>meant</corr></choice>.</p>

<p>George. I understand some of those Germans<ref target="n03">3</ref> Nagle<ref target="n04">4</ref> brought out are broke already. I wish you would have a talk with them and find out just how they are situated and if Nagle is treating them squarely. You might say <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> none of


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.007"/>


<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>7</fw>


our business But I say it is. I wish you would find out by <choice><sic>diging</sic><corr>digging</corr></choice> with a spade if you have no well auger by sending three men over on Sage creek<ref target="n05">5</ref> I feel sure water can be found let these men dig for water. I think Nagles next colony should be located there. I <choice><sic>beleive</sic><corr>believe</corr></choice> water can be got <choice><sic>withing</sic><corr>within</corr></choice> sixty feet at Irma<ref target="n06">6</ref> if some one would tell them to dig. A man must think what can be done for the Advantage of the <choice><sic>enterprize</sic><corr>enterprise</corr></choice> &amp; try it where it costs so little. I told <persName xml:id="salsbury.n">Salsbury</persName> of this but I fear he has forgotten it.</p>


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.008"/>


<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>8</fw>


<p>Foote<ref target="n07">7</ref> will be out at Red Lodge<ref target="n08">8</ref> about the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> if you can land him he will give you a check for $2000 Stokes<ref target="n09">9</ref> owes $1.000 I <choice><sic>havent</sic><corr>haven't</corr></choice> heard a word from any one about how things are or what is to be done or about how much we will have to have this pay day. only that a Doctor<ref target="n10">10</ref> wrote me from Red Lodge&#8212; &amp; Yegen<ref target="n11">11</ref> says we owe him a $1.000 which was news to me. You did not mention it in Chicago. I wish you would try to think up all who we owe. And when these bills come due I am <choice><sic>personaly</sic><corr>personally</corr></choice> <choice><sic>responsable</sic><corr>responsible</corr></choice> for Omaha people<ref target="n12">12</ref>. Graders &amp;c


<pb facs="wfc.css00489.009"/>


<note type="letterhead">F. E. Van Devort,<lb/>E. H. Bunstine.<lb/>Hotel Beckel,<lb/>Under New Management.<lb/>Dayton, Ohio. _____________ 189__ </note>


<fw>9</fw>


I am sure if you would give the business thought and action you would be able to keep the credit of our co better. We none of us are to blame if you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> let us know what you do. <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> your carelessness <choice><sic>thats</sic><corr>that's</corr></choice> giving our co such a bad name you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> mean to do it but <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> been your way of doing business all your life. And I should think you had seen the folly of it. Is <persName xml:id="alger.h">Alger</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="mead.e">Mead</persName> there. I <choice><sic>havent</sic><corr>haven't</corr></choice> heard a word from any one. </p>

<p>I hope to God Salsbury <choice><sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr></choice> catch the disease of <choice><sic>carelesness</sic><corr>carelessness</corr></choice> &amp; neglect that is so prevelant in that country</p>

<closer><salute>Yours&#8212;</salute> 

<signed>Col</signed></closer>

</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in Dayton, Ohio, on July 5, 1896. The day's entry in the 1896 Route Diary: "Dayton, Ohio. / Sunday, July 5. Arrived in town at 3.30 A. M. Two-mile haul to lot. Everything was put up in the morning. J. T. McCaddon, Jule Keen, Fred and Charles Hutchinson, and Orator J. J. McCarthy went to Cincinnati and paid a visit to the Pawnee Bill Wild West Show. They were entertained by Pawnee Bill, May Lillie, and Chief of Cowboys Heck Quinn, who is an old Wild West man. Annie Oakley remained over in Piqua last evening and joined us again to-day. James P. Anderson was seen sitting in the marque to-day for several hours figuring faithfully: he left the ground covered with paper and one piece was picked up containing the following figures: 4 days 96 hours, 5,760 minutes, 345,600 seconds. It was passed around the camp all day and no one solved the problem until it came to Mrs. George Fursman, of the Annex; to her, she said, it was as plain as day, and that Mr. Anderson was going home to Columbus, Ohio, next Friday, to see his wife. She was correct, for he left on Friday for Columbus. Heavy rain at 2 P. M., which lasted until 4 P. M. Orders were issued to-day that no employee would be allowed to ride on wagons either to or from lots."</note>

<note  xml:id="n02">Note 2: The "Young Lady" to whom Cody refers is Daisy May Sorrenson, a young woman who was a teacher in Marquette, Wyoming, and whom Beck hired to work for Shoshone Irrigation Company.  Beck later married Sorrenson in Red Lodge, Montana, December 1, 1897; they had three children: Betty (born 1898, later Mrs. Doyle and Mrs. J. M. Roberson), Jane (born 1900, later Mrs. Nelson T. Johnson), and George Thornton Beck Jr. (born 1908). </note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: "Germans" refers to the fifty or so German migrant families who arrived to settle in the Big Horn Basin; they were represented by S. V. Nagle. </note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: S. V. Nagle, an associate of the firm of F. A. Nagle Commission Merchants of Chicago, attempted to recruit settlers to the lands in the Big Horn Basin that were to be irrigated by the Cody Canal<!--link to Cody Canal-->.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: Sage Creek lies east of Cody, Wyoming, trending north-south and flowing into the Shoshone River northeast of Cody.</note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: "Irma" likely refers to Irma Flats, an area in the South Fork Valley outside Cody, Wyoming, that was named after Cody's daughter, Irma.  </note>

<note xml:id="n07">Note 7: "Foote" is Robert Foote (1834-1916), a Wyoming Senate democrat representing Johnson County, Wyoming, from 1895 to 1897. Foote led the effort against the Carey Act in Wyoming. </note>

<note xml:id="n08">Note 8: Red Lodge, Montana, lies 65 miles north of Cody and was the closest rail line to Cody, Wyoming.</note>

<note xml:id="n09">Note 9: "Stokes" is possibly Edward S. Stokes (1841-1901), at one time a railroad and oil magnate and businessman. Stokes was an owner of Hoffman House, an elegant hotel in Manhattan where Cody was often a guest. Cody may have wanted Stokes to invest in the Cody Canal<!--link to Cody Canal-->.</note>

<note xml:id="n10">Note 10: "Doctor" is not identified.</note>

<note xml:id="n11">Note 11: "Yegen" refers to P. Yegen and Co., a Red Lodge mercantile from which supplies were purchased for the irrigation project.</note>

<note xml:id="n12">Note 12: "Omaha people" are not identified.</note>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
