<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp11421">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Wild West in Berlin</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcribed and translated by</resp>
<name n="Stetler, Julia S.">Julia S. Stetler</name>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp11421</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>Eyewitness report. Author compares other ethnographic exhibits to the Wild West and explains the fascination with Native Americans. Stresses the authenticity of the show. Mention of Carl Henckel, the sketch artist. Description of Cody and reference to Cooper, also discussion of cowboys.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main" xml:lang="en">Wild West in Berlin</title>
<title level="j">Lokal Anzeiger</title>
<date when="1890-07-24">July 24, 1890</date>
<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
<extent></extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>McCracken Research Library, Buffalo Bill Center of the West</repository>
<idno>MS6.3776.44.01 (German scrapbook)</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p></p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="type"><p></p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>

<particDesc>
<listPerson>
<person></person>
</listPerson>
<listOrg>
<org></org>
</listOrg>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
<change when="2015"><name xml:id="fc">Christianson, Frank</name>; <name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name>; <name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article" xml:lang="de">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp11421.001"/>

<head>"Wild West" in Berlin.</head>
<byline>H.v.K.</byline> 

<p>Unsere Stadt ist nicht ungewohnt der Collectiv-Besuche fremder Völkerschaften. Uns der Gewohnheit könnte man vielleicht eine Uebers&#228;ttigung herlieten. Diese ist jedoch nur in einer gewissen Richtung hin vorhanden. Seit wir Colonialpolitik treiben, ist uns die Couleur &#8222;schwarz&#8221;, d.h. alle ist uns die Couleur &#8222;schwarz&#8221;, d.h. diejenigen Schattierungen welche man gemeinhin als schwarz zu bezeichnen pflegt, einigermassen &#8222;schnuppe&#8221; geworden. Unsere Jungens gaffen kaum noch einem Negerkn&#228;blein nach, und einem Kameruner oder Somali-Neger, wie fr&#252;her, die Zunge entgegen zu strecken, das w&#252;rde der &#8222;w&#252;rdigste&#8221; Berliner Gamin heute f&#252;r eine Verletzung der Nationalehre erkl&#228;ren. Ja, die schwarze Hautfarbe ist zu etwas Allt&#228;glichem, Gewöhnlichem geworden und deshalb können irgendwelche noch so exotische, noch so dicklippige, noch so heidenm&#228;&#223;ig und kultiviertes Futter verzehrenden Neger-Rassen bei uns als Schaust&#252;cke kaum noch auf hervorragendes Interesse rechnen. Höchstens einige auf &#8222;verlieben&#8221; besonders geeichte Berliner Jungfrauen schenken Ihnen ihre Herzen.</p>

<p>Etwas anderes ist es noch mit den Indianer- Rassen und allem, was mit dem Pr&#228;rieleben Nordamerikas zu tun hat. Obwohl die heutzutage beliebten Schnelldampfer den Begriff &#8222;Nordamerika&#8221; bereits in die Interessensph&#228;re der simpelsten Gewohnheitstouristen ger&#252;ckt haben, obwohl also amerikanische Dinge uns gar nicht mehr so &#8222;entfernt&#8221;, so exotisch, so fremdartig vorkommen, so gibt doch das Indianerwesen und alles, was drum und dran h&#228;ngt, eine ganz m&#228;chtige, unsagbare Anziehungskraft auf uns aus. Heute noch stehen wir, wie einst als Kinder, unter dem magischen Banne der Cooper‘schen Lederstrumpf Erz&#228;hlungen, und H&#228;uptlings- oder Squaw-Namen, wie &#8222;der flinke Hirsch&#8221;, die &#8222;weisse Taube&#8221; und dergl. haben f&#252;r uns einen von echter Urwaldpoesie verkl&#228;rten Klang. Darum-ich will das gleich vorausschicken-werden die Vorf&#252;hrungen, welche uns Mr. Cody, alias Buffalo Bill (wir w&#252;rden vielleicht &#8222;B&#252;ffel Wilhelm&#8221; sagen, aber das klingt h&#228;sslich) mit seinen ca. 200 Indianern und Cowboys bietet, hier in Berlin zweifellos einen gro&#223;en Erfolg erzielen. Wir bitten Eltern, auf ihre abenteuerlustigen Kinder Acht zu geben, damit sich bei denselben nicht eine krankhafte Prairie-Manie entwickelt. &#228;hnliches zeigte sich schon w&#228;hrend der Anwesenheit des wesentlich unbedeutenderen, mit Wild West kaum zu vergleichenden Wild Amerika des Dr. Carver.</p>

<p>Was wir bisher hier an Indianern gesehen haben, war nicht viel wert. Wer jemals in Amerika, in den West- und Nord-Staaten den bis zur öden Langweiligkeit zivilisierten Halbblutindianern begegnet ist, wer diese traurig herausstaffierten, an die stolzen Zeiten des Indianertuns erinnernden Watering-place-Indians (Kurbad-Indianer), wie man sie dort dr&#252;ben nennt, gesehen hat, der wird den richtigen Ma&#223;stab an das bisher hier bez&#252;glich der Indianer Schaustellungen gebotene legen können. Das Schönste auf dem gro&#223;en Prairiecamp, welches jetzt Buffalo Bill am Kurf&#252;rstendamm aufgeschlagen hat, ist die absolute Echtheit, welche jeder, nur einigerma&#223;en mit den einschl&#228;gigen amerikanischen Verh&#228;ltnissen daselbst an jeder Person und jedem Gegenstande, von dem stoischen Gesichtsausdrucke der verschiedenen Chiefs bis herab zur strafhaarige Skalplocke am Triumphg&#252;rtel des tapferen H&#228;uptlings konstatieren kann. Es ber&#252;hrt einen auch schon so amerikanisch &#8222;echt&#8221;,-wenn man am Eingang das in echtem Yankee Dialekt ausgesprochene Angebot der &#252;brigens sehr reichhaltig und instruktiv ausgestatteten &#8222;Pwogwaems&#8221; (Programms) erh&#228;lt, oder einen Blick auf die aus veritablen transatlantischen Gesichtern zusammengesetzte Musikkapelle wirft. &#252;brigens ist der Gesamteindruck, den man schon bei der heutigen Eröffnungsvorstellung gewinnt, ein f&#252;r einen Maler au&#223;erordentlich dankbarer. Wie ich höre, hat ein talentvoller M&#252;nchener Maler, namens Carl Henckel sich der gro&#223;en M&#252;he unterzogen, von all diesen Prairie-Menschen, Prairietieren, und Prairieszenen eine ganze Skizzensammlung und, wie ich selbst sah, eine &#228;u&#223;erst gelungene herzustellen. Es sind im Lager aufgenommene Original Aquarelle-die einzigen ihrer Art-in pr&#228;chtiger Lebensw&#228;rme, die in ihrer Gesamtheit ein ganzes St&#252;ck Kulturgeschichte aus dem Leben eines nach und nach zu Grunde gehenden Menschenstammes bilden und eine kolossale Reichhaltigkeit zeigen. &#252;brigens sind von diesem Skizzen k&#252;nstliche Lichtdruckbilder und Photografien angefertigt worden, welche leicht erreichbare und sehr wertvolle Souvenirs bilden.</p>

<p>Das lebendige Gesamtbild des freundlichen und feindlichen Zusammenlebens der aufstrebenden, tapferen neu-Amerikaner des wilden Westens mit den dahinsterbenden roth&#228;utigen Alt-Amerikanern, den einstigen Herren jener unabsehbaren L&#228;nderstrecken, welches man auf der gro&#223;en, von Logen und Trib&#252;nen umgebenen Rasenfl&#228;che am Kurf&#252;rstendamm, und ebenda selbst im &#8222;Camp&#8221;, der aus trefflichen Geb&#228;uden und Zelten errichteten Lagerstadt der Wei&#223;en und der Indianer, erh&#228;lt, ist ein ebenso anschauliches, wie reizvolles. Man f&#252;hlt die Natur, die wilde, machtvolle, ungeb&#228;ndigte Natur der Pr&#228;rie. Das ist doch noch etwas anderes, als die schönste, imponierendste Circuskunst. Nat&#252;rlich steht Buffalo Bill im Mittelpunkt des Interesses. Wenn der langhaarige, scharf&#228;ugige &#8222;Scout&#8221; mit dem breiten Schlapphut des westamerikanischen Rinderhirten (Cowboys) in die weite Arena reitet, stramm, stolz und doch mit fast geschmeidiger Eleganz, da wird er mit lautestem Jubel begr&#252;&#223;t. Man f&#252;hlt, es ist eben der Oberst W. Cody, ein Mann mit einer historischen Vergangenheit. Wenn man ihn ansieht, bl&#228;ttert man unwillk&#252;rlich verschiedene Seiten im Erinnerungsbuch zur&#252;ck und platziert diese interessante Gestalt schleunigst in irgend einen Cooperschen Indianer-Roman, f&#252;r den man ehedem geschw&#228;rmt. Auch der flinke und auf dem Pferde wunderbar gewandte König der Cowboys namens &#8222;Buck&#8221; Taylor erregt besonderes Interesse. Er hat jenes echte, verwegene, r&#252;cksichtslose Cowboy-Gesicht. Oh, es sind gar böse Gesellen unter diesen texanischen Jungens, welche ebenso rasch den Revolver auf den Menschen richten, wie sie dem B&#252;ffel den Lasso um die Hörner werfen. F&#252;nf Indianerst&#228;mme und einige Einzelh&#228;uptlinge, mehr oder minder gelb und zinnoberrot gemalt, mehr oder minder t&#228;towiert, mehr oder minder bekleidet, nebst den mexikanischen Vacheros, den amerikanischen Cowboys, der tollsten, wildesten, lustigsten Pferden der Welt und einer höchst drolligen, ungeberdigen B&#252;ffelherde, nicht zu vergessen einige schneidig reitende Damen, ein paar jugendliche B&#252;chsensch&#252;tzinnen par excellence und einige andere Pferde-und schie&#223;kundige Damen und Herren verschiedenen Kalibers---das sind die Hauptakteure der verschiedenen wilden Schauspiele, die man dort erlebt. Sie f&#252;hren die packendsten Szenen aus dem Pr&#228;rieleben aus und es scheint, Sie sind mit Leib und Seele bei der Sache. Auf die Einzelheiten des Programms, das so eigentlich alles umfasst, was in bösem und gutem Sinne im wilden Westen passieren kann, soll seinerzeit noch zur&#252;ckgekommen werden. F&#252;r heute möge das fl&#252;chtige Stimmungsbild gen&#252;gen, welches eben nur den Charakter dieser eigenartigen Schaustellung definieren soll. Eigentlich wirkt es gar nicht wie ein &#8222;Show.&#8221; Es ist gewaltig viel Natur darin, und das ber&#252;hrt doppelt angenehm.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="article" xml:lang="en">

<head>"Wild West" in Berlin</head>
<byline>H.v.K.</byline>
 <p>Our city is not unfamiliar with the mass-visits of exotic peoples. Being so used to it might perhaps even have led to an oversaturation. However, this oversaturation is only applied to a specific group. Ever since we have become a colonial power, Germans have become fairly indifferent to the color "black," meaning all those pigmentations that usually are characterized as "black." Our young boys hardly ever gawk at a black child, and sticking out one's tongue at a person from Cameroon or Somalia, like in the old days, would nowadays be seen as an injury to the national honor by most of the worthy Berliners. Yes, black skin has become mundane, an everyday occurrence. Therefore, even the most exotic, thick-lipped, heathen, or haute-cuisine-devouring races of blacks cannot guarantee the Germans' interest in these extraordinary exhibits anymore. At most, only a few Berliner virgins, who are desperate to "fall in love," might give them their hearts. </p>

<p>It is something entirely different with the Indian races and everything that has to do with prairie life in North America. Nowadays, the term "North America" has been put on every map due to the popular and fast steamboats, and thus has entered into the sphere of interest of even the most basic, leisurely tourists. Because of that, events in America are not as removed, as exotic, as strange, but still, the Indian character and everything surrounding it and connected with it exerts on us a most strong and inexplicable draw. Still today, just as we were as children, we are under the magical spell of Cooper's <hi rend="italic">Leatherstocking Tales,</hi> and the names of chiefs and squaws such as "Nimble Deer" and "White Dove" and so forth resound with the true poeticism of the wilderness. And this is the reason why&#8212;and I will say this ahead of time&#8212;the performances of Mr. Cody, a.k.a Buffalo Bill (we would translate it to "<hi rend="italic">B&#252;ffel-Wilhelm,</hi>" but that sounds ugly) with his 200 Indians and cowboys, will undoubtedly be extremely successful here in Berlin. We would ask parents to watch out for their adventurous children in order to prevent them from being infected with chronic prairie-fever. We have witnessed similar tendencies during the presence of the vastly less significant <persName xml:id="carver.w">Doc Carver</persName>, whose <hi rend="italic">Wild Amerika</hi> does not even come close to the <hi rend="italic">Wild West.</hi> Everything we have seen here so far in terms of Indians has been worth nothing. Those who have been to America, to the Western and Northern states, and have seen those haflblood-Indians, who have been civilized to a point of dreary boredom; those who have met these sadly decked-out "Watering-place-Indians" (<hi rend="italic">Kurbad-Indianer,</hi>) as they are called over there, who only remotely resemble the proud Indians from their heyday; only those who have seen it can rightly apply the correct measure to the Indian exhibits that have been here so far. The best part of the great prairie camp that Buffalo Bill has erected at <hi rend="italic">Kurf&#252;rstendamm</hi> is its absolute authenticity, and everybody who is vaguely familiar with the current American circumstances can witness it by looking at each person and object, from the stoic facial expressions of the different chiefs down to the lock of hair and scalp taken as punishment and attached to the triumph belt of the brave chief.  </p>

<p>The authentic American flair begins right at the entrance, where one is handed the program, which is detailed and educational and offered in a real Yankee dialect as "pwogwaems,"<ref target="n01">1</ref> or when one watches the band, which consists of authentic transatlantic faces. Incidentally, the overall picture that is presented at the opening performance today is more than appreciated by painters. As I have learned, a very talented painter from Munich named Carl Henckel has made the effort to prepare a collection of sketches of all these prairie-people, prairie-animals, and prairie-scenes, and as I was able to convince myself, the outcome is marvelous. The collection consists of original watercolors that were painted on location in the camp, and in their unique way they offer a genuine glimpse into the cultural history and life of a tribe of humans slowly going extinct, depicted with great detail and richness. These sketches, by the way, have been artificially reproduced and photographed and are easily obtainable and very valuable souvenirs.</p>

<p>The lively overall picture of the friendly and belligerent co-existence of the upcoming, brave new-Americans of the wild West with the slowly declining towards extinction, red-skinned old-Americans, the former masters of that vast land, is picturesque and exciting. And so is also the representation of the same in the large grassy arena at the <hi rend="italic">Kurf&#252;rstendamm,</hi> which is surrounded by grandstands, and also the "camp," which is the temporary home of the whites and Indians and consists of appropriate buildings and tents. You can feel nature, the wild, mighty, unbridled nature of the prairie. This is indeed something completely different from even the best circus performance. Of course Buffalo Bill is in the center of interest. When the long-haired, eagle-eyed "Scout" with the broad-brimmed hat of the West-American cow herder (Cowboys) rides into the arena, straight, proud and still with sleek elegance, he is welcomed with the loudest cheers. You can feel that this is the very Colonel W. Cody, a man with a historic past. Looking at him is like almost involuntarily turning back different pages in the book of memories and quickly placing this interesting character in a random Cooper Indian-novel that you once loved. Similarly, the swift, and on horseback wonderfully skilled, King of the Cowboys named <persName xml:id="taylor.w">"Buck" Taylor</persName> draws special attention. He has this authentic, rakish, uncompromising cowboy-face. Oh, there are some bad boys among the Texans, who are just as quick to point their revolver at you as they are to throw a lasso around the buffalo's horns. Five Indian tribes and a few single chiefs, more or less painted in yellow and red, more or less tattooed, more or less clothed, as well as Mexican Vaqueros, American cowboys, the craziest, wildest and funniest horses in the world and a highly amusing, stubborn buffalo herd, and not to be forgotten a few spirited lady-riders, a few youthful female trick shots par excellence, and a few other women and men versed in horsemanship and shooting of different caliber&#8212;these are the main performers of the various wild acts that can be experienced there. They demonstrate the most gripping scenes from the life on the Prairie and it seems that they are in it with their bodies and souls. We will come back another time to describe the details of the program, which includes pretty much everything good and bad that could possibly happen in the wild West. For today, this fleeting impression, which is meant to only define the character of this unique show, must suffice. In fact, it doesn't really feel like a "Show." There is a large amount of nature in it, which makes it twice as gripping.</p>

</div1>


</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: The German author spells the word <hi rend="italic">program</hi> phonetically.  "Es ber&#252;hrt einen auch schon so amerikanisch &#8222;echt",-wenn man am Eingang das in echtem Yankee Dialekt ausgesprochene Angebot der &#252;brigens sehr reichhaltig und instruktiv ausgestatteten &#8222;Pwogwaems" (Programms) erh&#228;lt."</note>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
