<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00453">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck, September 29, 1895</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>Supported in part by a grant from the Wyoming Cultural Trust Fund, a program of the Department of State Parks and Cultural Resources.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2013</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00453</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>BBWW performed in Baltimore, Maryland, September 30-October 1, 1895. Theo Heckert was a railroad contractor who had a "grading outfit" used in construction of the canal [See Patrick, p19]. Horace C. Alger (1857-1906) was a banker from Sheridan, Wyoming, mayor of Sheridan in 1889, and a candidate for Governor of Wyoming in 1898. Cody, Beck, and Alger were responsible for developing the Shoshone Irrigation Company.   George Bleistein (1861-1918), Buffalo, New York, owned the Courier Printing Company and provided printing for BBWW. Bleistein was also a partner and director in the Shoshone Irrigation Company. Daniel O'Day (~1846-1906) was vice-president of the National Transit Company and one of the five leaders of Standard Oil Company. O'Day's greatest achievement was engineering the transfer of the oil-carrying trade from the Empire Transportation Company to the Erie Railroad. He was instrumental in construction of the first oil pipeline in the state of New York in 1873 and in building the first pipelines from the oilfields in to New York City; O'Day served as president and/or director of many oil-related companies including National Transit Company, Northwestern Ohio Natural Gas Company, Atlantic Coast Realty Company, Buffalo General Electric Company, Buffalo Natural Gas Company, the National Fuel Gas Company, Federal Trust of Newark, People's Bank of Buffalo, Seaboard National Bank, and New York Produce Exchange Safe Deposit and Storage. Daniel O'Day was a friend of George Bleistein and a close personal friend of John D. Rockefeller. On p3 of this letter Cody asks about naming "streets" or "tracts" after both Northern and Southern Generals of the United States army. In letter dated September 25, 1895, he refers to naming streets. The initial plats of the town of Cody show that streets were named after generals; the main street through Cody is Sheridan Avenue, after General Philip Sheridan. Nathan "Nate" Salsbury (1846-1902) was an actor and head of the Troubadours, a traveling stock company which would eventually tour Europe and the United States. After Cody met Salsbury, the "Wild West" show venture would begin, and in 1884 Salsbury would become a partner as well as Vice-President and Manager of BBWW  until his death on December 24, 1902. William E. Hymer (~1853-1933) was one of the early members of the Shoshone Land and Irrigation Company. "Prest Perkins" probably refers to Charles E. Perkins (1840-1907), businessman and president of the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad. [The abbreviation for president during this era was "Pres't;" however, Cody rarely used apostrophes.] Colonel Allison Nailor (1836-1908?) was a friend of Cody's and was with him on his trip to the Grand Canyon in 1892. Henry Guy Carleton (1813-1901), the oldest son of Major General James H. Carleton, became a noted American humorist, journalist, author, playwright, and an amateur inventor of the 19th century. John M. Burke (d1917), a scout in the Indian wars, was WFC's publicity manager for the stage productions and the Wild West exhibitions.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to George T. Beck</title>
<date when="1895-09-29">September 29, 1895</date>
<extent>4 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, Buffalo Bill Letters to George T. Beck (Acc. #9972)</repository>
<idno>ah031298-301</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>4 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>4 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Carey Act of 1894</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Beck, George Washington Thornton, 1856-1943</term>
<term>Hymer, William Ebert, 1853-1933</term>
<term>Smith, Michael Hoke, 1855-1931</term>
<term>Warren, Francis E. (Francis Emroy), 1844-1929</term>
<term>Foote, Robert, 1834-1916</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Shoshone Irrigation District (Wyo.)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2013-07-01"><name>Weakly, Laura K.</name> Added annotation</change>
  <change when="2013-01-28"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofing</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2012"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00453.001"/>


<note type="letterhead">Accessible By Electric and Cable Cars To All Parts Of The City.<lb/>The Carrollton<lb/>J. P. Shannon, Manager.<lb/>Baltimore, Light &amp; German Sts.<lb/></note>

<opener>
<dateline>Baltimore, Md. Sep 29 1895<ref target="n01">1</ref></dateline>

<salute>My Dear <persName xml:id="beck.g">Beck</persName>&#8212;</salute>
</opener>

<p>2 letters from You. go up head&#8212; None from <persName xml:id="heckart.t">Heck</persName>. I sent <persName xml:id="alger.h">Alger</persName> $2.500 and will try to keep him in funds. You must let me know about how much money you will require each month and about how much it will cost to build the ditch to Sulphur creek<ref target="n02">2</ref>&#8212; And about how long it will take to do it. <persName xml:id="bleistein.g">Bleistein</persName> Says he thinks ODay<ref target="n03">3</ref> will come in with us. Now shall I try to get any more men in on ground floor. <persName xml:id="salsbury.n">Salsbury</persName> Says if you


<pb facs="wfc.css00453.002"/>


<note type="letterhead">Accessible By Electric and Cable Cars To All Parts Of The City.<lb/>The 
Carrollton<lb/>J. P. Shannon, Manager.<lb/>Baltimore, Light &amp; German Sts.<lb/>Baltimore, Md. _________ 189___<lb/></note>

<fw>2</fw>

can get the ditch built this fall to Sulphur creek headgate put in. Then he can borrow on it all the money we want. And it would be better than <choice><sic>takeing</sic><corr>taking</corr></choice> in to many on ground floor. What do you think? If we do this you must let me know how much money you will need this fall. And I want to know if work can be carried on during winter You know you must figure on lumber for head gate and to build us some kind of a house for head quarters this


<pb facs="wfc.css00453.003"/>


<note type="letterhead">Accessible By Electric and Cable Cars To All Parts Of The City.<lb/>The 
Carrollton<lb/>J. P. Shannon, Manager.<lb/>Baltimore, Light &amp; German Sts.<lb/>Baltimore, Md. _________ 189___<lb/></note>


<fw>3</fw>


winter. Also stable. What do you think of <choice><sic>nameing</sic><corr>naming</corr></choice> the tracts after leading Generals both sides of Army.<ref target="n04">4</ref> Did you get any Wagons or horses from the transportation <add>co</add> that you are turning over to our Co. and the horses &amp; outfit that <persName xml:id="hymer.w">Hymer</persName> had. If so keep account of them. Where did Heck locate his first camp&#8212; Are you living in a tent what do you do for a Cocktail? I wrote you that Bleistein. ODay. Salsbury. Nailor.<ref target="n05">5</ref> Young Perkins Son of Prest Perkins.<ref target="n06">6</ref> Henry Guy


<pb facs="wfc.css00453.004"/>

<note type="letterhead">Accessible By Electric and Cable Cars To All Parts Of The City.<lb/>The 
Carrollton<lb/>J. P. Shannon, Manager.<lb/>Baltimore, Light &amp; German Sts.<lb/>Baltimore, Md. _________ 189___<lb/></note>


<fw>4</fw>


Carlton.<ref target="n07">7</ref> <persName xml:id="burke.j">Burke</persName>. K. Christ knows how many more are coming out with me in December&#8212;<ref target="n08">8</ref> how will the weather be?</p>

<p>Will we get snowed in. will you have a house for us&#8212; if we bring our own whiskey. I must find out these things before I bring them. <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> fail to answer&#8212;</p>

<p>Wonder what Heck done with <orgName xml:id="company.t">Transportation Co</orgName>&#8212; When he left Sheridan. he never writes a word&#8212; well if he pushes on the <orgName xml:id="canal.c">ditch</orgName> I will let him off&#8212;</p>

<closer>
<signed>Bill</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note>Note 1: Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in Baltimore, Maryland, September 30-October 1, 1895; there was no performance on Sunday, September 29, 1895.</note>

<note>Note 2: Sulphur Creek is a natural streambed located west of Cody, Wyoming, flowing north toward the Shoshone River along the south side of Cedar Mountain.</note>

<note>Note 3: Daniel O'Day (c.1846-1906) was the vice-president of the National Transit Company and one of the five principals of Standard Oil Company. O'Day's greatest achievement may have been engineering the transfer of the oil-carrying trade from the Empire Transportation Company to the Erie Railroad. O'Day was instrumental in laying the first oil pipeline in the state of New York in 1873, building the first pipelines from the oilfields to New York City. O'Day acted as president and/or director of many budding banks and oil-related companies. Mr. O'Day was a close personal friend of John D. Rockefeller and George Bleistein<!--link to George Bleistein personography-->.</note>

<note>Note 4: Cody asks about naming "streets" or "tracts" after both Union and Confederate Generals. In a previous letter dated September 25, 1895, Cody also refers to naming streets in the first planned town site, and the initial plats of the town of Cody in that original location show the streets named for generals. In the town site's later and current location, the main street of Sheridan Avenue, named for General Philip Sheridan, is the only street honoring a general; the principal east-west streets were and still are named for founders of the town.</note>

<note>Nope 5: "Nailor" is likely Colonel Allison Nailor, Jr. (1836-1908), from Washington, D.C., who was a friend of Cody's and with him on Cody's trip to the Grand Canyon in 1892. Nailor and others were expected to join Cody on the hunt that he was planning for December 1895.</note>

<note>Note 6: "Prest Perkins" would likely have been Charles Elliott Perkins (1840-1907), then president of the Chicago, Burlington &amp; Quincy.  His son is referred to as "Young Perkins Son." In Cody's time, the term "president" was often written as "prest."</note>

<note>Note 7: Henry Guy Carleton (1813-1901), the oldest son of Major General James H. Carleton, became a noted American humorist, journalist, author, playwright, and an amateur inventor of the 19th century. </note>

<note>Note 8: The hunt Cody was planning for December that year.</note>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
