<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp06437">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Cowboy Craze</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp06437</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note><!-- notes  --></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">The Cowboy Craze</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Cads of London Feasting the Wild Westerners</title>
<title level="j">Omaha Daily Bee</title>
<pubPlace>Omaha, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<date when="1887-06-18">June 18, 1887</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>


</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Aristocracy (Social class)</term>
<term>Buffalo Bill's Wild West Company</term>
<term>Cowboys</term>
<term>Germany</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Alexandra, Queen, consort of Edward VII, King of Great Britain, 1844-1925</term>
<term>Beresford, Charles William De la Poer Beresford, Baron, 1846-1919</term> 
<term>Bismarck, Otto, F&#252;rst von, 1815-1898</term>
<term>Smalley, George W. (George Washburn), 1833-1916</term>
<term>William II, German Emperor, 1859-1941</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Hyde Park (London, England)</term>
<term>London (England)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2014-05-19"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription and proofreading</change>
  <change when="2014"><name xml:id="sh">Hanna, S.</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<pb facs="wfc.nsp06437.001"/>

<head type="sub">THE COWBOY CRAZE.</head>

<milestone unit="line"/>

<head type="sub">The Cads of London Feasting the Wild Westerners.</head>

<p>Correspondence Philadelphia Press: I was told yesterday of an amusing scene witnessed by an American gentleman. An English baronet with single eye-glass and very English accent was asking a couple of cowboys to dine with him.</p>

<p>"Be kind enough to give me your cards," said the baronet.</p>

<p>"Well, to tell the truth," replied the rather embarrassed young men, "we haven't got any."</p>

<p>"Oh, never mind*&amp;a mere formality cards are, you know. Not neccessary at all, my dear boys. Lady F---- will be delighted to meet you. What are your engagements for the week?"</p>

<p>The young fellows looked at each other and said: "Most any night would suit us, I guess."</p>

<p>"Delighted, you know. Well, say Friday night. We shall expect you Friday night. Quite informal. Never mind dress suits."</p>

<p>The two cowboys went, and I have no doubt behaved very nicely, but it will be surprising if the fuss being made over them here does not spoil some of them.</p>

<milestone unit="section"/>

<p>George W. Smalley<ref target="n01">1</ref> writes from London to the New York Tribune: "An episode of Buffalo Bill's career. All the world knows, by cable and otherwise, that he was on Lord Charles Beresford's<ref target="n02">2</ref> drag at the meeting of the Coaching club in Hyde Park.<ref target="n03">3</ref> He was the feature of that gathering. The princess of Wales<ref target="n04">4</ref> herself was less an object of interest, or, at any rate, of curiosity. But there was an unreported incident. Count Herbert Bismarck<ref target="n05">5</ref> was then in London as he is now. He went to the meet and was seen by Lord Charles, who hailed him and asked him to come up on his coach. Count Herbert accepted this invitation, climbed aloft and was assigned to seat behind the box seat. He observed in front of him and next to Lord Charles a big, powerful man with long hair and what is here called a sombrero. Presently he was introduced to this personage as Colonel the Hon. William F. Cody. The son of the imperial chancellor of Germany<ref target="n06">6</ref> possibly wondered who Colonel the Hon. William F. Cody was, and pretty certainly occupied his mind with speculations on the greatness of this unknown hero who was so conspicuously preferred before him. There is no human being stiffer than your Prussian on points of etiquette; none, on the whole, so stiff. When Count Herbert Bismarck returns to Berlin he will have it to relate that the man in whose favor he himself was relegated to a back seat, was an American, joint proprietor of an establishment sometimes called Cody's circus.</p>

<p>London, however, having some time since set up Buffalo Bill as an idol, and fallen down before and worshipped him, and burned incense before him, is still well content with its new image. He is liked as well as lionized. His nerves are not fluttered by contact with fashion. He takes what comes to him with coolness and as if it were quite a matter of course. Whether at luncheon or a dinner party or an evening crush, our long-haired handsome giant has every art of being at home. Why should he not? It must be easier to be the center of half a dozen pretty women's admiring attentions than a target for red Indian bullets. "Have you met Buffalo Bill?" queried one "smart" young man about town of another, "smarter," if not younger. "Yes, often." "What was he doing?" "Mostly playing poker with duchesses." This may be only a vivacious form of expressing the extent of Colonel Cody's intimacy with the most exalted society, but, with or without the poker, of the intimacy there can be no doubt.</p>


</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note>Note 1: George Washburn Smalley (1833-1916), a Boston lawyer from 1856 until 1861, was a newspaper correspondent and journalist and staff editor for the <hi rend="italic">New York Tribune.</hi></note>  

<note>Note 2: Lord Charles Beresford is Charles William De la Poer Beresford (1846-1919), the first Baron Beresford.</note> 

<note>Note 3: Located in west London, Hyde Park was originally owned by the British monarchy to satisfy the Royals' passion for hunting.</note> 

<note>Note 4: The Princess of Wales was Alexandra of Denmark (Alexandra Caroline Marie Charlotte Louise Julia, 1844-1925) who became Queen Alexandra when her husband, the Prince of Wales, became Edward VII, King of Great Britain in 1901.</note>  

<note>Note 5: Count Nikolaus Heinrich Ferdinand Herbert von Bismarck (1849-1904), the eldest son of German Chancellor Otto von Bismarck, served as Germany's Foreign Secretary of State from 1885 until 1890.</note> 

<note>Note 6: Otto Eduard Leopold (1815-1898), Prince of Bismarck, Duke of Lauenburg; known as Otto von Bismarck, he was an aristocrat and statesman, prime minister of Prussia (1862-1873, 1873-1890), and first Chancellor of the German Empire (1871-1890).</note> 

</back>
</text>
</TEI>
