<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.nsp03099">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Gossip from Abroad</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
<sponsor>This project is supported in part by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Geraldine W. &amp; Robert J. Dellenback Foundation.</sponsor>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.nsp03099</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>Excerpt from full text article.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="a" type="main">Gossip from Abroad</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">Royalty and Cowboys</title>
<title level="j">The Sun</title>
<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="1890-06-02">June 2, 1890</date>
<biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
<biblScope type="pp"></biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Newspapers</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>European Tours</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Aristocracy (Social class)</term>
<term>Cowboys</term>
<term>Horses</term>
<term>Kings, queens, rulers, etc.</term>
<term>Mustang</term>
<term>Nobility</term>
<term>Sharpshooters</term>
<term>Shooting</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term>Luitpold, Prince Regent of Bavaria, 1821-1912</term>
<term>Oakley, Annie, 1860-1926</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term>Austria</term>
<term>Bavaria (Germany)</term>
<term>Hungary</term>
<term>Munich (Germany)</term>
<term>Vienna (Austria)</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2015-10-05"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura K.</name> Initial encoding</change>
  <change when="2015"><name>Clark, Linda</name> and <name xml:id="sh">Hanna, Sam</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2015"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> and <name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>


</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="article">

<!-- <pb facs="wfc.nsp03099.001"/> -->

<head>GOSSIP FROM ABROAD.</head>
<milestone unit="line"/>
<head>ROYALTY AND COWBOYS.</head>
<p>Buffalo Bill, on his tour around the world, has lately been delighting the people of the old <hi rend="italic">Kaiserstadt</hi> Vienna, Austria. The Neues Wiener Tagblatt advises us how Mr. Grant, the American minister at the imperial court, hastened to pay his respects to our celebrated fellow-citizen, Colonel Cody, (Buffalo Bill,) at the latter's hotel, the Oesterreichischer Hof, after having, with his family, visited the cowboy exhibition on the preceding day in the company of Archduchess Elisabeth, the Duke and Duchess of Cumberland, the Princes of Isenburg and Radziwill and other members of the higher aristocary of Austro-Hungary. More than 7,000 persons attended the show, which in Vienna, as in other capitals of Europe, meets with immense success, and everywhere appears to be looked upon as the event of the season. Colonel Cody and his band are feted and treated royally by both princes and people. In Munich, Bavaria's capital, his Royal Highness, Prince Luitpold, the Prince-Regent of that kingdom, had a narrow escape from being trampled to death by one of Buffalo Bill's horses. Having attended a private exhibition of Miss Oakley's shooting at the camp, and remaining for some time after the performance in lively conversation with the amiable shootress, his Royal Highness was suddenly confronted by one of the wild mustangs, which Gus Uhl, the cowboy, unaware of the Prince's presence, had led into the inclosure. Miss Oakley, requesting the Regent to save himself by hasty flight, vainly set him the example by jumping over the barriers, while his Highness, not heeding her warning, was knocked down by the unceremonious animal. If it had not been for the presence of mind of Miss Oakley, who, leaping back into the arena, pulled royalty from below the infuriated horse, Bavaria might have had to bewail the loss of her beloved ruler. Thanks to the courage of the republican heroine, the potentate escaped with only a few contusions, but thoroughly frightened. His Royal Highness, in grateful remembrance of Miss Oakley's brave act and his lucky escape, presented the lady a magnificent bracelet set in brilliants, and Mr. Gus Uhl, the cowboy, who indeed appeared entirely innocent of the whole affair, received a golden cigar case as a souvenir from the princely visitor.</p>

</div1>
</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
