<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.lgl00004">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Contract with Bushy Top Pine</title>
<author></author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.lgl00004</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author></author>
<title level="m" type="main">Contract with Bushy Top Pine</title>
<date when="1906-01-31">January 31, 1906</date>
<extent>1 page</extent>
</bibl>

<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>NARA (Central Plains), Folder 047 Fairs and Expositions, BBWW Contracts, 1906-1911</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 printed page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p>
</condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>

<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
  <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
    <term>Texts</term>
  </keywords>
  <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
    <term>Records</term>
  </keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="subject">
<term>Show Indians</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term>Wild West Show Indians</term>
<term>Legal</term>
<term>Contracts</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2012-04-24"><name xml:id="jah">Heppler, Jason A.</name> Initial Encoding</change>
  <change when="2012-04-24"><name>Heppler, Jason A.</name> Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<pb facs="wfc.lgl00004_img_0"/>

<div1 type="contract">

<p>This Agreement Entered into this 31st day of January, 1906 by William F. Cody &amp; James A. Bailey, Proprietors of Buffalo Bill's Wild West, Parties of the first part, and an Indian Bushy Top Pine of Pine Ridge Agency, South Dakota, party of the second part.</p>

<p>Witnesseth, That the parties of the first part, have and by these presents do engage the party of the second part to accompany the exhibition (Wild West) of the parties of the first part, for exhibition purposes in Europe, the object being to give public exhibitions of American Frontier Life; and the party of the second part agrees to do whatever in reason and justice may be required of him while in the service of the parties of the first part, and which may be necessary and incident to such exhibition, not inconsistent with the laws of morality and the ordinary rules of propriety; and the parties of the first part agree to pay to the party of the second part, in lawful money of the United States, a monthly salary of $25.00 dollars, from the date of the first regular performance and until the last regular performance of the season. And it is further agreed that the pay for the services for the final month, under this agreement, shall be paid after the return of the said party of the second part to Pine Ridge Agency and in the presence of the Indian Agent. It is further agreed to that forty per centum of said monthly salary shall be retained by the parties of the first part until the close of the season and the return of the party of the second part to said Agency, when all of such retained pay together with any final payment then due and unpaid, shall be given and paid by the parties of the first part. And it is further agreed that if from ill health or being incapacitated the party of the second part shall fail to continue in service under the agreement until the end of the season, then any sum due him as retained pay and salary shall be paid up to that date, and this agreement cancelled.</p>

<p>The parties of the first part further agree to supply the said party of the second part the proper food and raiment, except one set of Indian Clothes, Head Dress, Moccasins, etc. to start with, and to pay all his needful incidental expenses from the date of leaving Pine Ridge Agency until his return thereto and to protect the said party from all immoral influences and surroundings, and provide all needful medical attendance and medicine and do all such other acts and things as may be requisite and proper for the health, comfort, and welfare of the said party of the second part and to return him to the said Agency at the expiration of this agreement, without cost to the party of the second part or to the Government of U. S.</p>

<p>The party of the second part agrees to keep sober and obey the rules and regulations governing the establishment of the party of the first part, failing to do so he will be returned to the Agency forfeiting all salary due him.</p>

<p>It is understood that the term "season" as used herein, shall mean the time fixed by the parties of the first part for the commencement and ending of the services of the party of the second part.</p>

<p>In Witness Whereof, The above parties have executed these presents at Pine Ridge Agency, South Dakota, the day and year first above written.</p>

<closer>
<signed>Wm McCune<lb/>
Agent for Cody &amp; Bailey</signed>

<signed>Jacob Killer<lb/>
Witness.</signed>

<signed>Bushy Top Pine x<lb/>
Party of the second part.</signed>


I certify, on honor, that I explained to the above named Indian the nature of this agreement and am satisfied that he fully understood the same at the time of signing it.

<signed>F. C. <unclear /><lb/>
Interpreter.</signed>

Pine Ridge Agency, S. D.
Approved
<signed>John R Brennan
U. S. Indian Agent.</signed>

</closer>

</div1>
</body>

<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
