<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="wfc.css00134">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to C. L. Hinkle, August 18, 1902</title>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<principal>Johnston, Jeremy</principal>
<principal>Christianson, Frank</principal>
<principal>Seefeldt, Douglas, 1964-</principal>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2012</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>William F. Cody Archive</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="module"></idno>
<idno type="project">wfc.css00134</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note>Letter and envelope. Curtis L. Hinkle was clerk of the Wyoming State Land Board in Cheyenne and friend to WFC. M. P. Pels [later in letter "Mr. Pell"] was President of Maxwell Land Grant Company. Shoshone Irrigation Company was organized in 1895 (incorporated in 1896) to run the Cody &amp; Salsbury Canal project [see Bonner]. "Mr. Bond" was likely Fred Bond, who succeeded Elwood Mead as Wyoming State Engineer [see Bonner, pp143-147]. "Hart Mountain" refers to Heart Mountain, just north of Cody, Wyoming. "Tynan" likely refers to Thomas T. Tynan, State Superintendent of Public Instruction in Wyoming in 1898 under Governor Deforest Richards [see p202, Bonner] and Mayor of Sheridan in 1914 and 1915. Mike Russell, South Dakota rancher and WFC's friend, sold his brand and branded horses to Cody, providing starter horses, the brand for Cody's Wyoming ranch, and the name for the ranch, TE Ranch, Ishawooa, Wyoming (the brand joins the "T" and "E" as one). BBWW performed in Boise, Idaho, August 18, 1902.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Cody, William Frederick, 1846-1917</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Cody to C. L. Hinkle</title>
<date when="1902-08-18">August 18, 1902</date>
<extent>1 page, plus envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>McCracken Research Library (MRL)</repository>
<idno>MS6.0141.02</idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 hand-written page, plus envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support>Buffalo Bill's Wild West letterhead</support>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="wfc1" script="rough" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

 <profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Texts</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Correspondence</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>Empire</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>


<revisionDesc>
  <change when="2012-06-21"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura</name> Added annotations</change>
  <change when="2012-02-20"><name xml:id="lkw">Weakly, Laura</name> Initial Encoding</change>
  <change when="2011"><name xml:id="lc">Clark, Linda</name> Proofreading</change>
  <change when="2011"><name xml:id="da">Adams, Deb</name> Transcription</change>
  <change when="2011"><name xml:id="gb">Boyce, Gary</name> Transcription</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="letter">

<pb facs="wfc.css00134.001" />

<opener>
<note type="letterhead">Buffalo Bill's Wild West</note>

<dateline>Boise. Ida.
<date>Aug 18th 1902<ref target="n01">1</ref></date>
</dateline>

<salute>My. Dear. <persName key="hinkle.l">Hinkle</persName>&#8212;</salute>
</opener>

<p>A Mr. M. P. Pels- President of the great Maxwell Grant in Southern Col and New Mexico-Will call on you.<ref target="n02">2</ref> To Know all about Cody and Salsbury Canal- We have decided to follow the upper Meade Quarry around the foot of <choice><sic>Hart</sic><corr>Heart</corr></choice> Mountain&#8212; this will join on both sides of the river about 120000 acres of irrigable land&#8212;<ref target="n03">3</ref> I know this is asking much of you and giving you extra work- but you wait till I land this enterprise I have the money in site in England to do this work&#8212; but if I can get it sooner here. I will take it. So try &amp; land Mr Pell. Introduce him to the <choice><sic>Govenor</sic><corr>Governor</corr></choice> and Board- and Mr Bond.<ref target="n04">4</ref></p>

<p>Will you please ask Mr. Tynan if he wants my application in writing for the rerental of those leased lands of mine in Big Horn Co&#8212;<ref target="n05">5</ref></p>

<p>Please let me hear from you </p>

<p>Mike Russell is still with me.<ref target="n06">6</ref></p>

<closer>
<salute>Yours Truly</salute>

<signed>W.F. Cody</signed>
</closer>

</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="wfc.css00134.002" />

<note type="letterhead">Buffalo Bill's Wild West</note>

<ab type="postmark">B-<unclear />O 1902 Aug 18 1&#8212;P</ab>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>C. L. Hinkle</addrLine>
<addrLine>Capital</addrLine>
<addrLine>Cheyenne.</addrLine>
<addrLine>Wyo.</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<note>Personal</note>
</div1>
</body>

<back>
<note xml:id="n01">Note 1: Buffalo Bill's Wild West performed in Boise on August 18, 1902.</note>

<note xml:id="n02">Note 2: The Maxwell Grant, which takes its name from Lucien B. Maxwell (1818-1875), the son-in-law of one of the original grant holders, became one of the largest private land holdings in the United States, covering over 1.7 million acres in southern Colorado and northern New Mexico. The tangled legal history of this tract begins in 1841, when the local Mexican governor issued the original grant to Maxwell's father-in-law Carlos Beaubien and his partner Guadelupe Miranda. The precise limits of the Mexican grant were the subject of much litigation until the Supreme Court decided the case in 1887. By then, Maxwell's claims were owned by the Maxwell Land Grant Company, which was under the control of Dutch investors. Martinus Petrus Pels (c. 1837-1906), a representative of the Dutch investors, served as general manager of the Maxwell Land Grant Company from 1888 to 1894.  Cody's attempt to persuade Pels to invest in the <orgName key="canl.cs">Cody-Salsbury Canal</orgName> did not succeed. </note>

<note xml:id="n03">Note 3: William F. Cody refers to Heart Mountain, whose summit is about ten miles northwest of Cody, Wyoming.  The river mentioned here is the Shoshone River, which was to be the water source for the Cody-Salsbury Canal.</note>

<note xml:id="n04">Note 4: The governor of Wyoming was then DeForest Richards (1846-1903). The "Board" Cody mentions is the Wyoming Board of Land Commissioners, which consisted of the state's governor, secretary of state, and superintendent of public instruction. The board supervised Carey Act irrigation projects in the state, in cooperation with the state engineer. Fred Bond (1856-1903) was then the state engineer.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">Note 5: Thomas T. Tynan (1860-1925), was Wyoming's superintendent of public instruction and a member of the Board of Land Commissioners from 1899 to 1907. Tynan later served as mayor of Sheridan, Wyoming, from 1914 to 1915.</note>

<note xml:id="n06">Note 6: The Irish-born Michael R. Russell (1847-1930) met William F. Cody in Kansas during the 1860s, and the two men formed a lasting friendship. Russell moved to Deadwood, South Dakota, in 1877 and took up business interests that included saloonkeeping and mining operations. About 1895, Russell sold Cody a herd of horses and the "TE" brand, which Cody used to establish his TE Ranch on the South Fork of the Shoshone River southwest of Cody, Wyoming.</note>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
