<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00779">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">[Unidentified Sender] to Orville Hickman Browning, February
          1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>[Unknown]</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00779</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
            the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U. S. copyright
            law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express
            written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for
            Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>[Unknown]</author>
          <title>[Unidentified Sender] to Orville Hickman Browning, February 1869</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1869-02" xml:id="dat1">February 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">365-368</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>

        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ames, Oakes">Oakes Ames</persName>
          <persName key="Rollins, E. H. ">E. H. Rollins</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-04-22" who="#crl">transcribed and encoded, then added the contract that was
        enclosed with the letter; updated the @facs</change>
      <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space
        between initials</change>
      <change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header
        information, revised encoding</change>
      <change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and
        replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-05" who="#nnk">checked</change>
      <change when="2011-03-09" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-11" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text type="letter">
    <body>


      <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00779.001.jpg" type="recto"/>

      <note type="authorial" place="top">(Documents, forms, &amp;c. in agreements bet. The United
        States, and the Union Pacific Rail Road)</note>
      <ab>February <space dim="horizontal" extent="3 letters"/> 1869.</ab>
      <ab>Hon. O. H. Browning,</ab>
      <ab>Secretary of the Interior.</ab>
      <ab>Sir:</ab>
      <ab>The Union Pacific Railroad Company, having been required by the Government of the United
        States, in addition to the deposit of Three millions of dollars, ($3,000,000:) of first
        mortgage bonds of the Company with said government in the Department of the Treasury
        thereof, as security for the due completion and equipment of its road;&#8212;Also, as a
        further security to the same end, to leave the lands given to the said company by the Acts
        of Congress providing for the building of the said Road, and the completion of its structure
        and equipments without taking out patents for the same until the Government shall be
        satisfied, upon proper examination of the said road, its structure and equipment, that the
        same have been completed according to the provisions of law, in the premises; and the
        company having executed the proper instrument in respect to the said required deposit with
        the Secretary of the Treasury:</ab>
      <ab>Now this is to declare that the said Company assents to the aforesaid requirement in
        respect to the lands given to the said Company <note type="authorial" place="left"
          >Stipulations bet. U. S. &amp; Union Pacific RR</note>
        <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00779.002_fullpage.jpg" type="verso"/> as aforesaid, that
        they shall remain without patents being taken out therefor until the Government of the
        United States, upon a proper examination of the actual condition of the road of said
        company, its structure and equipments, shall be satisfied to issue patents for said
        lands.</ab>
      <ab>In the name and by the authority of the said Company, this assent is given by us, the
        President and Secretary of said Company.</ab>
      <ab>We have the honor to be</ab>
      <ab>Very Respectfully,</ab>
      <ab>Your obd't serv'ts.</ab>
      <ab>(Agreement &amp;c. Union Pacific RR.)</ab>
      <ab>Know all men by these presents, That the Union Pacific Railroad Company, having been
        heretofore required to deposit with the Government of the United States in the Department of
        the Treasury of the U. S. the am't in the aggregate of three millions of dollars
        ($3,000,000) of their first mortgage bonds, as a guarantee that the structure &amp;
        equipment of the road of the said company shall be completed according to the provisions
        &amp; requirements of law respecting the same, and to make such deposits, from time to time
        as the said company shall receive the bonds of the U. S. issued to it on the completion of
        successive sections <note type="authorial" place="left">See p 381 seq.</note>
        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00780.002.jpg" type="recto"/> of the road as provided by law
        to an amount equal to one-half of the am't of said bonds of the U. S. to be so received by
        said Company.</ab>
      <ab>Now the said company in pursuance of said requirement, hereby declares &amp; agrees that
        the said first mortgage Bonds deposited, or to be deposited with the government of the U. S.
        in the Treasurey Dept. thereof, upon the requirement and in manner aforesaid, are and may
        &amp; shall be held by the government of the U. S. as security for the completion of the
        structure &amp; equipment of the road of the said Company, according to the provisions of
        the statutes of the U. S. providing for the building &amp; completion of said road, &amp;
        its equipments, &amp; to be so held until the Government of the U. S. on a proper
        examination of the actual completed road and equipments shall be satisfied to relinquish
        &amp; restore to the said company the said bonds, or such part thereof as it shall deem,
        from the actual condition of the said road, in its structure and equipments, it shall be no
        longer necessary to retain.</ab>
      <ab>And it is further declared &amp; agreed by the said Company, that in case the Government
        of the U. S. shall fail to be satisfied, upon a proper examination of the road, its
        structure &amp; equipments aforesaid, that the same are conformed to the requirements of the
        statutes providing <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.00780.003.jpg" type="verso"/> for the
        building of the said road and for its structure &amp; equipment, that it shall be the duty
        of the said Company to proceed to complete the said road, its structure &amp; equipments, to
        the satisfaction of the government of the United States &#08212; and that in default of its
        so doing, the said Bonds shall be held by the said Government, and shall be disposed of, and
        the proceeds thereof, if disposed of, applied to the proper completion of the said road, its
        structure &amp; equipment, as the Government of the United States shall by law direct &amp;
        provide.</ab>
      <ab>In witness whereof, the said Union Pacific RR. Co. has affixed its Corporate seal to these
        presents, and directed the execution thereof to be attested by its President this <space
          dim="horizontal" extent="4 letters"/> day of February, Eighteen hundred and sixty
        nine.</ab>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
