<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01286">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">W. A. Field to P. Phillips, 30 March 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>W. A. Field</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01286</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

       
        <bibl>
          <author>W. A. Field</author>
          <title>W. A. Field to P. Phillips, 30 March 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-03-30" xml:id="dat1">March 30, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">254-255</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Phillips, P.">P. Phillips</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-10" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-15" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-18" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01286.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>March 30, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>P. Phillips, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Washington, D. C.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>On the docket of the present term of the Supreme Court, there is No. 188, Bank of Louisiana, appellant, <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>. The United States&#8212;and No. 286, John C. Harris, <hi rend="underline">et</hi>. <hi rend="underline">al</hi>. appellant, <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>. The United States, both of which are the same case, brought up by appeal by different claimants of the same property, from the District Court of the United States for the Middle District of Alabama, in which Court it was condemned as forfeited to the United States under the Confiscation Laws. The case was tried in the District Court without a jury, although it seems, one of the claimants, at least, demanded a jury trial,&#8212; and it is sufficiently manifest that the seizure was upon land.</ab>
     <ab>These cases must go back and be tried according to the course of the common law. Mr. Chilton is Attorney of record in the first, and Mr. Thomas Wilson in the second&#8212;but I do not know the address of Mr. Wilson, though it may be in this city.</ab>       
            <ab>As you have sometimes appeared in the Supreme Court for Chilton, I desire to ask whether you feel authorized to do so in this case,&#8212;and, if so, whether there is any reason why it should be disposed of, on motion, next Friday?</ab>
            <ab>A letter similar to this has been
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Sup. Ct. cases N. 188, &amp; No. 286</note>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01286.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            addressed to "Thomas Wilson, Esq. Washington, D. C."</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>W. A. Field,</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
