<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01653">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Cornelius Cole, 23 January 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.01653</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                <persName xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</persName></note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to Cornelius Cole, 23 January 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-01-23" xml:id="dat1">January 23, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">586-587</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Cole, Cornelius">Cornelius Cole</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change when="2013-06" who="kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-06-05" who="#el">changed "A. T." to "Amos T." in TEI header</change>
            <change when="2013-03-13" who="#crl">checked, proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-12-10" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01652.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>January 23, 1871</ab>
<ab>Hon. C. Cole.</ab>
<ab>Acting chairman of the Committee on Appropriations.</ab>
            <ab>U.S. Senate</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I learn from some gentlemen who have spoken to you upon the subject that you desire my view upon the propriety of appropriating a sum of money (fifty thousand dollars has been suggested) for aiding in the detection and prosecution of crimes against the United States, to 
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01652.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            be expended under the direction of the Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>Generally, I disapprove of appropriations of so vague a character. But the reasons in favor of this proposition are strong. It is intended to employ persons who shall exert themselves to detect and prosecute a class of offenses which now no officer is likely to feel specially charged with. I refer particularly to prosecutions under the Acts known as the Enforcement Act, the Naturalization Act, and the Civil Rights Act.</ab>
            <ab>In some parts of the  country, the sufferers by the crimes punishable by these Acts are, for the most part, poor and ignorant men, who do not know how to put the law in motion, or who have some well-grounded apprehension of danger to themselves from the attempt to enforce it. In most of the other classes of prosecutions, there are persons within the range of whose official duties the business of prosecution comes, as in Internal Revenue offences, and offences against the Customs laws. But it is not so in the classes of cases to which I have referred ; and I think therefore that the law would be better enforced if the Attorney General had authority to employ persons who would learn facts, gather testimony, and prefer charges against the offenders in such cases.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">certain appropriation ($50000) considered.</note> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
