<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02294">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to John A. Minnis, 26 December 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02294</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to John A. Minnis, 26 December 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-12-26" xml:id="dat1">December 26, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno"></idno>
          <biblScope type="page">120-122</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Minnis, John A.">John A. Minnis</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-11-08" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-21" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-12" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02294.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>Dec. 26, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>John A. Minnis, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Attorney</ab>
            <ab>Montgomery, Ala.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letters of the 17th
                              
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02294.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            and of the 19th instants have been received.</ab>
            <ab>The sum which you indicate as the probable expense of Associate Counsel in the Ku Klux cases, ($10,000,) in the Northern and Middle Districts of Alabama, is so much beyond the means of this Department, in view of the claims of other Districts, that I am under the necessity of declining to employ assistant counsel on those terms. When you consider that the sum appropriated for all the expenses of all the courts of the U. S. and Territories, embracing the pay of witnesses and jurors, rent of buildings, compensation of Marshals, etc. is only Two million dollars, ($2,000,000,) you will perceive that ten thousand dollars, ($10,000) of extra expense in one class of cases in a part of Alabama, and similar expenses at the same time in other Districts similarly situated, would make a very serious encroachment on that fund.</ab>
            <ab>It should also be remembered that the execution of the Enforcement Laws must be entirely free from any plausible suspicion that they are used for the purpose of advancing any private pecuniary interests.</ab>
            <ab>Being very desirous, however, that these prosecutions should be energetic, and should be successful when against parties really guilty, I feel willing to go to this extent&#8212;to pay $2500 for assistance in the Middle           
            <note type="authorial" place="left">cost of extra counsel No. and Middle Ala.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.02294.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            District, and the same amount in the Northern District. And if you will indicate the gentleman whom you prefer in each District, I will promptly commission him.</ab>
            <ab>I think it better to employ Republican than Democratic lawyers. The former are more likely to have their hearts in the work. From all my information I incline to think that Mr. Lewis is the best man in the Northern District; but I desire to consult your wishes.</ab>
            <ab>Although the letter of appointment always reserves to this Department the right of determining what compensation will be reasonable, yet in order to avoid any misunderstanding I desire to limit the expectations of the appointees to such a maximum as the means of the Department will allow.</ab>
            <ab>Please answer definitely, stating whether, in your opinion, qualified gentlemen will engage to assist with an expectation of pay not exceeding the above amount, and indicating the individual whom you prefer in each District.</ab>            
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
