<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.03027">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to George S. Boutwell, 22 April 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.03027</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to George S. Boutwell, 22 April 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-04-22" xml:id="dat1">April 22, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">73-75</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-01-25" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-01-12" who="#ad">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-11-30" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.03027.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>April 22, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Under date of the 17th instant, you referred to me a letter from Mr. Robert Rae, complaining of certain proceedings of the District Attorney for the Northern District of Illinois, taken by that officer under instructions from this office in relation to the case of one David Muir.</ab>
            <ab>The facts are, that upon a trial in the U.S. Court for the Eastern District of Michigan, Mr. Muir produced a certificate of naturalization from the Superior Court of the city of Chicago, and claimed under it the privileges of an American citizen. The District Attorney for the Eastern District of Michigan, having reason to believe that this certificate was obtained by fraud on the part of Mr. Muir, so reported to this office, and the Acting Attorney General,
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">case of David Muir, Illinois</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.03027.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            in my absence, directed the District Attorney for the Northern District of Illinois to make the motion in the Superior Court of the city of Chicago to vacate the decree of naturalization which was supposed to have been fraudulently obtained.</ab>
            <ab>Whether such a motion can be entertained and granted by the court, and whether the facts of this case would sustain such a motion, are, as it seems to me, proper questions for the cognizance of the court. If Mr. Muir has had the benefit of American citizenship by virtue of naturalization fraudulently obtained, I think that the courts should set aside the judgment of naturalization. At least it seems to me that the effort to accomplish so desirable an object ought to be made.</ab>
               <ab>I see no object in Mr. Rae's communication, unless it be to prevent an inquiry into the supposed fraud on the part of Mr. Muir. It must be assumed here that the Superior Court of Chicago will do right, and will not vacate its previous judgment unless it was fraudulently obtained. And in case of such fraud the remonstrance of Mr. Muir, or of any person acting for him, will hardly be considered as entitled to respect in any Department of this Government.</ab>
            <ab>I do not, therefore, feel at liberty to recall the direction heretofore given by this Department
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.03027.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            to the District Attorney of the Northern District of Illinois in this matter.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
