<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01246">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">W. A. Field to Hamilton Fish, 7 March 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>W. A. Field</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01246</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName> 
<persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>W. A. Field</author>
          <title>W. A. Field to Hamilton Fish, 7 March 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-03-07" xml:id="dat1">March 7, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">229</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Fish, Hamilton">Hamilton Fish</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
<change when="2011-05-13" who="#vs">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-04-05" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-11" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01246.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>March 7, 1870.</ab>
           <ab>Hon. Hamilton Fish,</ab>
           <ab>Secretary of State.</ab>
           <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I enclose herewith a certificate of A. B. Maynard, Esq., U. S. Attorney for the Eastern District of Michigan, with two bills attached, one of Fran&#231;ois Carom, Esq. Police Magistrate of Windsor, Canada, for &#36;15, Canada currency, and one of Samuel S. Macdonald, Esq. county crown attorney, of Essex county, in the province of Ontario, Dominion of Canada, for &#36;10, both relating to services rendered in the attempted extradition of one Thomas Barr. The letter of Mr. Maynard to me enclosing these papers states that Thomas Barr was in jail in the city of Detroit, in June, 1869, awaiting trial in the District Court of the United States on the charge of passing counterfeit money&#8212;that he escaped from jail, and fled to Canada&#8212;that the U. S. Attorney sent his assistant to Windsor, Canada, to institute proceedings for his extradition&#8212;that two examinations were had there, when Barr consented to return to Michigan&#8212;and that he did return, was arraigned, and pleaded guilty&#8212;and is now in prison, serving out his sentence.</ab>
            <ab>I am of opinion that the amounts charged in the bills enclosed are reasonable and I send them to the Department of State, that if there is any appropriation for paying for services of this character, these bills may receive your consideration.</ab>
            <ab>Very resp. your ob't servt,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar, Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>(enc.)</ab>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Certain bills ag't U. S.</note> 
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
