<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00582">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to Lyman Trumbull, 25 June 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00582</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to Lyman Trumbull, 25 June 1868</title>

        
          <date cert="high" when="1868-06-25" xml:id="dat1">June 25, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">190-192</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Trumbull, Lyman">Lyman Trumbull</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-28" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-21" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-06" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

        
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00582.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>June 25, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. L. Trumbull,</ab>
            <ab>Chairman Judiciary Committee,</ab>
            <ab>United States Senate.</ab>
           <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I had the honor on the 17th of March last, to transmit to the President of the Senate a Report of the Chief Clerk of this Office, relative of the appropriations required by the office, a copy of which is herewith enclosed. Permit me now to call your attention to certain proposed legislation affecting this office.</ab>
            <ab>The Act making appropriations for the legislative, executive and judicial expenses of the government for the year ending June 30, 1869," makes a deduction in the amount asked for this Office of two temporary first-class clerks, and two thousand dollars in the contingent fund&#8212;but $5000: being allowed, instead of 7000: asked for by the Attorney General, and allowed by Congress for several years back. The estimates made for the office were as moderate as a respect for efficiency and promptness in the official work, would permit. A new law about to go into effect adds fresh reason for not cutting down the contingent fund, but rather makes it imperative that the estimated amount be increased. The Bill alluded to is Senate Bill No. 164 "to claims, and for other purposes,"&#8212; the fifth section of which abolishes the offices of Solicitor, assistant Solicitor, and Deputy Solicitor of the Court of Claims, and the Assistant Attorney General, now provided for
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00582.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            by law; authorizes the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, to appoint two Assistant Attorneys General&#8212;and makes it the duty of the Attorney General, with such two Assistants, to attend to the prosecution and defence of all matters and suits in the Court of Claims on behalf of the United States. The Attorney General is authorized to appoint two additional fourth-class clerks, and one clerk at a salary of $2000. This increase of force is comparatively liberal, regarded as merely clerical, but the professional assistance contemplated by the Act is as certainly inadequate, upon the best data that I have been able to collect, that the uncommon occasion doubtless exists for the immediate employment of special counsel for the several hundred cases now in course of preparation for the Court of Claims, as I learn.</ab>
            <ab>When you reflect that the regular business of this office is greater now than ever before, and that of the Court of Claims steadily increases, and is said to be much in arrear, that the incoming Attorney General, his two assistants, and the new clerks allowed him, will presumably enter upon this important business without previous connection with this office, or that of the Solicitor of the Court of Claims, you will understand the great embarrassment under which the incoming head of this office must labor, the delicacy of his responsibility, and the danger which must arise to the interests of the Government, both in the Supreme Court and the Court of Claims, for the inadequacy of the assistance allowed to that officer.
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.00582.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                These considerations are re&#239;nforced by the probability that delays of uncertain duration, incident to the filling of the new offices, even that of the chief law officer, will postpone due arrangements for the approaching terms of court.</ab>
            <ab>The circumstances plainly indicate the propriety of increasing rather than curtailing the amount to be allowed for the contingent expenses of the Attorney General's office. I respectfully suggest that the sum of $9000: be appropriated under that head.</ab>
            <ab>I venture, in the absence of adequate data, but sensible of the necessity of making this communication without delay, to recommend that for special counsel and other extraordinary expenses incident to the execution of the recent Act changing the relations between the Attorney General and the Court of Claims, a sum not less than Fifteen thousand dollars be appropriated.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>your obedient serv't,</ab>
            <ab><choice><sic>OH Browning</sic><corr>O. H. Browning</corr></choice></ab>
            <ab>Attorney General <hi rend="underline">ad</hi><hi rend="underline">interim</hi></ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
