<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01970">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 9 July 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01970</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 9 July 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-07-09" xml:id="dat1">July 9, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">594-595</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-20" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-01-27" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01970.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>July 9, 1869</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter, and the accompanying papers, all relating to the Internal Revenue case of A. W. Darling. I understand that the proposition is that the information of forfeiture be dismissed, each party thereto paying his own costs; that the money, amounting to about $19,000, now in the registry of the court, in the information for forfeiture, be applied in satisfaction <hi rend="underline">pro tanto</hi> of the judgment against Darling on the bonds, but that this amount of money be not received as a satisfaction in full of such judgment, and that all criminal proceedings now pending against Darling or others be unaffected by this compromise, and that the same is made without prejudicing the rights
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01970.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            of either the United States or the persons indicted, in regard to such criminal proceedings.</ab>
            <ab>As Darling is unable to pay the whole amount of the judgment on the bonds, and as the result of a new trial of the information of forfeiture is not certain, the proposed compromise seems pecuniarily for the interests of the United States. I do not certainly know whether there is, or is not, an informer who claims a share of whatever money may be recovered in the information of forfeiture. I infer from the letter of the District Attorney, found among the accompanying papers, that there is one.&#8212;If the compromise proposed is effected, the money received is in satisfaction <hi rend="underline">pro tanto</hi> of a debt of which an informer is entitled to no share. The United States have the legal right to proceed in this manner&#8212;but it ought, I think to be carefully considered, whether this is a case in which it is in every respect just to shut out any claim on the part of the informer. This consideration I leave entirely to the Department of the Treasury, and intend to express no opinion upon it, but to call attention to it, that it may not escape notice.&#8212;Understanding that terms of the proposed compromise as I have stated them, I recommend that they be accepted.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, &amp;c. &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar, Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
