<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01685">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to John Angel James Creswell, 4 February 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01685</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to John Angel James Creswell, 4 February 1871</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1871-02-04" xml:id="dat1">February 4, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">608-609</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Creswell, John Angel James">John Angel James Creswell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-07-26" who="#jw">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-12" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-02" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01685.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>February 4, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. J. A.J. Creswell,</ab>
            <ab>Postmaster General.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>You have referred to me certain documents from which it appears that one William J. Jones has procured from a judicial officer in the District of Columbia an injunction against one George Chorpenning alleging that Chorpenning is entitled to moneys from the Treasury, for some claim against the Post Office Department, and that Jones has an equitable right to a portion of said money. The object in delivering these papers to you seems to have been to induce you to prevent Chorpenning from drawing the money upon his claim. You are no party to the suit in which the injunction is obtained. The counsel for Jones concedes that you cannot properly be made a party.</ab>
            <ab>It is obvious that if the operations of the Department of this Government are liable to such impediments, the public business of the country cannot go on. I am unable to see how it is improper for you to be made a party to the suit in which the injunction issued&#8212;and how, at the same time, it is proper that you should regard the injunction. Such seems to be the claim of the counsel for Jones, in their letter to you of the 18th ult.</ab>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Opinion on certain Injunction &amp;c.</note> 
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01685.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>Every reason why the Postmaster General should not be made the direct object of such an injunction, is an equally good reason why he should not be bound to respect that injunction. If the injunction is binding upon him at all, he should have the right, and for the sake of the public interests with which he is charged, it should often be his duty, to appear in the case, and to move to dissolve such injunction. The doctrine of the counsel of Mr. Jones seems to be, that the head of a Department of this Government, in a matter connected with his official duties, must be subjected to all the disadvantages, and yet have none of the advantages, of a party to a suit between private persons. Such a doctrine is preposterous.</ab>
            <ab>I am of the opinion that you are under no obligation to regard the injunction in this case, and that you do whatever appears under the law to be your duty in regard to the dues of the Government to Chorpenning, as if no such injunction had been issued.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
