<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02519">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Benjamin Helm Bristow to Clarence A. Seward, 18 October 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Benjamin Helm Bristow</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02519</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Benjamin Helm Bristow</author>
          <title>Benjamin Helm Bristow to Clarence A. Seward, 18 October 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-10-18" xml:id="dat1">October 18, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">92-93</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Bristow, Benjamin Helm ">Benjamin Helm Bristow</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Seward, Clarence A.">Clarence A. Seward</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2012-01-12" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-11-02" who="#ad">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-21" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02519.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>Oct. 18, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>C. A. Seward. Esq.</ab>
            <ab>New York City.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have your letter of yesterday advising me that the case of Jones, <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>. Seward will probably be called for argument on demurrer on next Friday, and asking whether I can be present on that day.</ab>
            <ab>In reply I regret to have to say that my absence from the city at that time will be impracticable. The Attorney General is not now in the city, and I do not know certainly when he will return, but probably not before the latter part of next week. Quite a number of important cases in which the government is a party will be called for argument in the Supreme Court within the next fortnight, and on this account it is important that I should remain here.</ab>
            <ab>Not doubting your ability to
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of Jones, vs. Seward,</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">New York.</note>
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02519.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            conduct the argument of the case of Jones <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>. Seward, and to take care of the interest of the government therein, it will be left to our control.&#8212;</ab>
            <ab>Should you, however, desire that assistance of the District Attorney in the argument of the case, you will notify him to that effect, and request him to appear with you.</ab>
            <ab>Touching the matter of your retainer, I have not replied to your former letter for the reason that I desired to consult with the Attorney General. It seems from his letter to you that he entertained doubt whether your retainer would be payable out of the funds of this Department, or of the State Department; and inasmuch as I suppose the Secretary of State and the Attorney General have had some conference on this subject, I prefer to await his return rather than to determine the question myself. Of course there can be no doubt about your compensation, and it will give me pleasure to look to the matter on the return of the Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>B. H. Bristow, Solicitor General,</ab>
            <ab>&amp; Acting Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
