<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02348">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Ulysses S. Grant, 2 September 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02348</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Ulysses S. Grant, 2 September 1867</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1867-09-02" xml:id="dat1">September 2, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno"></idno>
          <biblScope type="page">444-445</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S.">Ulysses S. Grant</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2011-12-09" who="#mk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-10-26" who="#ad">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-19" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02348.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>September 2, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>General U. S. Grant,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War, <hi rend="underline">ad interim</hi>.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to return herewith the papers transmitted to this Office for the consideration of the Attorney General, by direction of the Secretary of War, on the 15th of April last, relative to the Title to certain tracts of land in the vicinty of Nashville, Tenn. sought to be acquired by the United States for the purpose of a National Cemetery.</ab>
            <ab>The tracts referred to are situated on and near the Gallatin Turnpike between
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02348.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            five and six miles from Nashville, and consist of lots Nos. 2, 3, 17, and 18, of what is known as the Craighead property, as laid down in the plan thereof recorded in the Chancery Court at that place&#8212;containing in all about 63 acres and 87 poles.</ab>
            <ab>The additional information furnished by these papers in compliance with the request of the Attorney General, of August 11, 1866, supplies all the evidence which it is deemed needful to have; and from a careful examination of the same, I am of opinion that the accompanying Deeds of Conveyance, executed by the Clerk and Master of the Chancery Court aforesaid in pursuance of the orders and decrees of that Court, therein recited, and bearing date respectively July 3, 1866, and January 28, 1867, will, when delivered, vest in the United States a good and valid Title in fee to the said premises.</ab>
            <ab>I am, Sir,</ab>
            <ab>Very Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
