<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00210">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">J. Hubley Ashton to James C. Kennedy, 2 May 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00210</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
          <title>J. Hubley Ashton to James C. Kennedy, 2 May 1867</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1867-05-02" xml:id="dat1">May 2, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">377</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ashton, J. Hubley">J. Hubley Ashton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Kennedy, James C.">James C. Kennedy</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-09" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-15" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-11" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
      
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00210.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
<ab>May 2, 1867.</ab>
<ab>James C. Kennedy, Esq.</ab>
<ab>Washington, D. C.</ab>
<ab>Sir:</ab>
<ab>Your letter of yesterday has been received. This Office is not advised of the character &amp; condition of the litigation to which you refer, &amp; cannot undertake to give any instructions relative to the suit against the Trustees of Bayne &amp; Co., mentioned in the letter of the Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>If such suit is to be brought by the United States, none other than the law officer of the particular District has authority to institute it; but the Secretary of the Treasury may associate with him, in the trial of the cause, such special counsel as he may choose to employ.</ab>
            <ab>If the District Attorney for Baltimore desires any instructions relative to the proposed litigation, it will be his duty to communicate directly with this Office.</ab>
            <ab>If you consult the Secretary of the Treasury, he will doubtless address the Attorney General on the subject of this case, &amp; state the particular instructions which he may desire to be sent to the District Attorney at Baltimore.</ab>
            <ab>It is manifestly proper that the Secretary of the Treasury should consider the subject-matter of your letter.</ab>
            <ab>The letters accompanying your communication are herewith returned.</ab>
<ab>Respectfully, &amp;c. yours,</ab>
<ab>J. Hubley Ashton,</ab>
<ab>Assistant Attorney Gen'l.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
