<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00737">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Oliver Ames and Oakes Ames to Orville Hickman Browning, 23 December 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Oliver Ames</author>
        <author>Oakes Ames</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00737</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Oliver Ames</author>
          <author>Oakes Ames</author>
          <title>Oliver Ames and Oakes Ames to Orville Hickman Browning, 23 December 1868</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1868-12-23" xml:id="dat1">December 23, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">331-332</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ames, Oliver">Oliver Ames</persName>
          <persName key="Ames, Oakes">Oakes Ames</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-02" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-07" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-14" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00737.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>December 23, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. O. H. Browning,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Interior.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>We understand that the result of the examination into the construction of the Union Pacific Railroad, and of the deliberations upon the subject, is, to require from that Company as a guarantee of the completion of the structure of the Road, according to the just expectations of the Government, that the lands given to the Company are to remain without taking out patents therefor, until the completion of the road, and that a deposit shall be made by the Company of their first mortgage bonds with the Government to the amount of $3,000,000, in the aggregate in parcels equal in amount to one half of the Bonds of the United States, which the company is to receive on the completion of the successive sections of the road. In assenting to this arrangement on the part of the Company, and in anticipation of the completion of the formal instrument to carry it into effect, to be prepared by the Attorney General, we desire now to say that we hold ourselves responsible for the deposit of the first mortgage Bonds of the Company, corresponding under the above arrangement, to the amount of Bonds of the United States we are presently to receive on two completed sections of the road, as soon as the necessary formalities on the part of the Company, in the
           
            <note type="authorial" place="left">See p.330 ante</note>
            
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00737.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            preparation and deposit of the Bonds, can be gone through with.</ab>
            <ab>Oliver Ames, President.</ab>
            <ab>Oakes Ames, Secretary.</ab>
             
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
