<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00029">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">J. Hubley Ashton to William A. Dart, 11 August 1865</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00029</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
          <title>J. Hubley Ashton to William A. Dart, 11 August 1865</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1865-08-11" xml:id="dat1">August 11, 1865</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book E</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">153</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ashton, J. Hubley">J. Hubley Ashton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Dart, William A.">William A. Dart</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-12" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-01-31" who="#nnk">checked</change>  
      <change when="2010-09-16" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00029.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Attorney Gen's Office.</ab>
            <ab>Aug. 11, 1865.</ab>
            <ab>Wm. A. Dart, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Attorney,</ab>
            <ab>Potsdam, St. Lawrence co. N. Y.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>You will please report to this office at your earliest convenience the authority for your charge of $252.25, in the case of United States v. 150 <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="js">bbs.</unclear> High wines claimed by T. S. Bradley of Peoria, Ill. in which a discontinuance was directed to be entered by the Secretary of the Treasury; and also, so far as you know, the authority for the Marshal's charge of $105.50 in that case.</ab>
            <ab>Both you &amp; the Marshal, it seems, charge the commissions on the value of the wines. With your bill a memorandum is presented in which the 11th sec. of the act of March 3, 1864 (12, Stat. 741.) is referred to as authorizing your charge of commissions. This office cannot suppose that you have looked at this statute. It manifestly does not warrant the application given to it.</ab>
            <ab>As at present advised the opinion of this Office is that you are entitled to but five-dollars for discontinuing the proceeding in the case under the Act of 1854.</ab>
            <ab>You will therefore present at once your views on this point, and also on the question raised as to the legality of the Marshal's charge.</ab>
            <ab>Before giving an opinion to the Secretary of the Treasury on the question of the legality of the respective charges of yourself &amp; the Marshal, it was deemed right to enable you, &amp; the Marshal through you, to make any proper explanation.</ab>
            <ab>The Att'y Gen. will thank you to give this subject your very earliest attention.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully your obd't serv't</ab>
            <ab>J. Hubley Ashton,</ab>
            <ab>Ass't Att'y Gen.</ab>
            
           </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
