<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00878">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 19 or 20 April 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00878</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 19 or 20 April 1869</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1869-04-19" xml:id="dat1">April 19 or 20, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">447-448</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-03" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-08" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-26" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00878.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>April ? 19 or 20, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have had the honor to receive your letter of the 16th ult, referring to me a communication from the 2d Comptroller in which numerous questions are suggested concerning a claim against the Government pending before that officer, in favor of Herman Kountze for certain mules alleged to have
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00878.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            been lost by capture by the Indians, while employed in the military service of the United States.</ab>
            <ab>The claim is preferred under the 2d Sec. of the Act of March 3, 1849, (9 Stat. 415,) which, in addition to other things thereby required to be established by the owner of the property, in order to bring a case within its provisions, casts upon him the burthen of showing that the loss was "without fault or negligence" on his part; and the only subject on which any doubt seems to exist in connection with the claim, is, as to the absence of any fault or negligence in the claimant. The question involved thus appears to partake rather of the nature of a question of fact, to be made out from the evidence submitted, than of a question of law; and it does not, as I conceive, appropriately fall within the province of the Attorney General to consider questions of this sort.</ab>
            <ab>Looking at the matter from this point of view, I feel reluctantly compelled to decline expressing an opinion upon the question proposed by the Comptroller, some twelve in number, many of  which, I may observe, appear to me to be very remotely connected, if at all, with what seems to be the real subject of inquiry presented. The papers are returned herewith.</ab>
            <ab>Very Respectfully, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
