<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01691">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Lyman Trumbull, 6 February 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01691</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Lyman Trumbull, 6 February 1871</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1871-02-06" xml:id="dat1">February 6, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">613-615</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Trumbull, Lyman">Lyman Trumbull</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-07-27" who="#jw">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-12" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-06" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01691.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>Feb. 6, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Lyman Trumbull,</ab>
            <ab>Chairman Judiciary Committee,</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Senate.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received a letter addressed to this Department, under date of the 3d instant, by the Clerk of the Senate Committee on the Judiciary, stating that he had been
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01691.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            directed by the Committee to request me to inform them "what was the entire compensation and fees of the U. S. District Attorney for the District of Louisiana, for the last fiscal year, giving the amount of each quarter separately."</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to inform your honorable Committee that upon an examination of the records of this Department, it appears that no returns of the fees and emoluments of the Attorney of the United States for Louisiana were made during the period from July 1st, 1869, to April 22d, 1870,&#8212;and that nothing was paid to him from the Treasury during that time. The only return rendered during the fiscal year was by the late Attorney, Mr. A. B. Long, from April 23d to June 30th, from which it appears that his fees and emoluments for that time amounted to $718 33/100.</ab>
            <ab>It may be proper for me to say, in this connection, that the semi-annual returns required by the Attorneys of the United States do not include the two <hi rend="underline">per centum</hi>, and other fees allowed to them by the eleventh and twelfth sections of the Act entitled "An Act to prevent and punish frauds upon the Revenue, to provide for the more certain and speedy collection of claims, in favor of the United States, and for other purposes," approved March
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Fees, &amp;c of U. S. Att'y in Louisiana.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01691.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            3d, 1863. (12th Stat. p. 741,) See also second Section of the Act of June 27, 1864, (13 Stat. P. 196.)</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
