<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00828">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">William M. Evarts to Joshua F. Bailey, 29 February 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>William M. Evarts</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00828</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>William M. Evarts</author>
          <title>William M. Evarts to Joshua Bailey, 29 February 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" notBefore="1869-02-28" notAfter="1869-03-01" xml:id="dat1">February 29, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">414-415</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Evarts, William M. M.">William M. Evarts</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Bailey, Joshua F.">Joshua F. Bailey</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-03" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-03" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-26" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

         
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00828.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>February 29, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Joshua Bailey, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Collector of Internal Revenue,</ab>
            <ab>4th District, New York.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I had the honor to receive in due course your two letters of the 27th of January last, and 5th of February inst, in which you unfold to me at length the history of the prosecution ag't George B. Davis, now pending in the Southern Dist. of New York, &amp; exhibit your relations to the complaint ag't him &amp; your natural &amp; proper interest that the regular prosecution of that case should make public the wickedness of the malicious accusations ag't you, which Davis was a party to, or made an instrument in. The considerations presented in your letters would have been both pertinent &amp; important if I had occasion to dispose of the case of Davis as presented for my interposition, by passing judgment upon the substance of the charges upon which he was indicted. I have however, as I have heretofore stated to you in a personal interview which you sought with me on the subject, regarded the single point before me as not involving nor even permitting any judgment except upon the simple one whether the prisoner should be remitted to an opportunity of returning to Canada,
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00828.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                from whence he had been invited to aid the investigations of the government into alleged frauds upon the Internal Revenue of the city of New York. I have come to a conclusion upon this point which I have communicated to Dist. Attorney Courtney, &amp; although I have not thought myself at liberty to be influenced in this conclusion by any personal relations or feelings, yet I have no hesitation in saying that I regret that the conclusion to which I have come, may disappoint what is a very just desire on your part, that the trial of Davis should exhibit in its true light the falsity &amp; malice of the imputations which he had cast upon you. By a perusal of my letter to Mr. Courtney, which he is quite at liberty to show you, you will understand the disposition I have made of the subject, and the grounds of it.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, &amp;c &amp;c</ab>
            <ab>Wm. M. Evarts,</ab>
           <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>Feb. 27, 1869.</ab> <!-- Should we assume that this is the correct date of the letter, and note it accordingly in the header? -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
