<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.03300">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to John Angel James Creswell, 24 August 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.03300</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to John Angel James Creswell, 24 August 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-08-24" xml:id="dat1">August 24, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">219-220</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Creswell, John Angel James">John Angel James Creswell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-02-14" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-05" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.03300.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Aug. 24, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. J. A. J. Creswell,</ab>
            <ab>Postmaster General.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received a letter addressed to this Department under date of the 20th inst. by C. Cochran, Jr. Esq. Superintendent of Mail Depredations, P. O. Department, enclosing for my information copies of correspondence in relation to James Gilmore, an escaped prisoner recently arrested for mail robbing in Missouri, showing the difficulty under which the agents of the P. O. Department labor in endeavoring to bring to justice persons charged with depredations upon the mails.</ab>
            <ab>I have carefully read this correspondence. There is no law providing compensation to a Marshal for services or expenses in capturing or endeavoring to re-capture an escaped prisoner. It is the duty of the keeper of the prison in which the prisoner is incarcerated to safely keep him, and in the event of his escape to use all diligence for his re-capture, and to defray all expenses incident to such re-capture. This duty is incumbent upon the keepers in view of the fact that the Government pays them for guarding and feeding its prisoners. There is, however, I regret to say, no statute compelling them to re-arrest persons who escape from their custody&#8212;and in some cases where they have failed to attempt the re-arrest, the U.S. Marshals have pursued the parties within their respective Districts, and their expenses have been allowed out of the Judiciary fund.</ab>
            <ab>When a prisoner escapes, and he is
            <note type="authorial" place="top" rend="none">pp. 182-3-4-5</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">mail robbing cases</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">see p. 209 ante</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">p. 242 seq.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.03300.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            believed to be in another District than the one in which he was arrested and committed, a copy of the warrant for his arrest and of the commitment, should be sent to the U.S. Attorney of the District in which the prisoner is supposed to be, in order that a warrant may be issued by the Court of that District for his apprehension and return to the place from which he escaped.</ab>
            <ab>I will write to the Marshal of Missouri relative to the case of Gilmore, and direct him to have copies of the warrant and commitment sent to the U.S. Attorney of the District of Arkansas, in which said Gilmore is supposed to be living.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman, Attorney Gen'l.</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
