<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01436">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Hamilton Fish, 19 October 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01436</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Hamilton Fish, 19 October 1870</title>

        
          <date cert="high" when="1870-10-19" xml:id="dat1">October 19, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">442-443</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Fish, Hamilton">Hamilton Fish</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-10" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-28" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-07" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

   
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01436.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>October 19, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Hamilton Fish,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of State.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>In answer to yours of the 14th inst., enclosing a private communication to you from Mr. Roberts, the Minister from Spain, in the United States, in relation to the steamer "Hornet," I have to say that on the 14th inst., having received from the District Attorney of the Southern District of New York a verbal statement that, in his judgment, the evidence against the "Hornet" was insufficient to condemn that vessel under our neutrality laws, I addressed to him a letter, a copy of which is herein enclosed.</ab>
            <ab>The letter of Mr. Roberts to you furnishes no new facts upon the subject. His reasoning makes out against the "Hornet" a case of suspicion, sufficient, perhaps, to justify the original seizure of the vessel&#8212;but not sufficient to authorize me to overrule the judgment of the District Attorney&#8212;the officer who, under our Government, is charged with the immediate direction of criminal and other proceedings on the part of the United States in his District. It was his judgment that the evidence against the vessel was altogether insufficient for conviction; and, as it is not the custom of this Government to oppress private parties with unfounded legal proceedings, and as the District Attorney of the Southern District of New York is a very competent officer, I felt bound to 
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of the "Hornet"</note> <note type="authorial" place="left">letter of Mr. Roberts, the Spanish Minister.</note> 
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01436.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            authorize the release of the vessel, in case an examination should satisfy him that the detention of her was unauthorized by the evidence.</ab>
            <ab>I return the letter of Mr. Roberts to you, as you requested.</ab>
            <ab>I am, sir, with great respect,</ab>
            <ab>Your obed't serv't.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>(two enc.)</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
