<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02647">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to W. A. Field, 6 December 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02647</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to W. A. Field, 6 December 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-12-06" xml:id="dat1">December 6, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">175-176</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-12-05" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-26" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-12" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02647.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Dec. 6, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>W. A. Field, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Boston, Mass.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 2d instant enclosing an account for moneys paid out by you in the defence of the case of Fredericks <hi rend="underline">et</hi> <hi rend="underline">al</hi>. <hi rend="underline">vs.</hi> Dickinson.</ab>
            <ab>It seems to me that this account is sent under a misapprehension of the view which I take of the matter, Mr. Dickinson, an Assistant District Attorney, having been sued on a cause of action growing out of his relation to the Government, in which he acted in manifest good faith, I felt authorized to furnish him with professional defence at the expense of the Government. But I do not see how I am authorized, out of the funds of this Department, to pay for expenditures by himself, or expenditures by yourself, not authorized by this Department in the defence. The furnishing of professional defence went to the very verge of what I understand to be my authority in the premises. To go further, and pay costs out of any funds under my control, seems to me unauthorized.</ab>
            <ab>I know of no law, regulation, or instruction, which required him to take into his own hands moneys tendered in satisfaction of an Internal Revenue claim. He was really acting more in the capacity of an Internal
            <note type="authorial" place="left">certain acc't disallowed</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02647.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            Revenue officer than of a District Attorney.</ab>
            <ab>I am obliged in these matters to act upon rules which would be safe and proper in general application. While the amount involved in this instance is small, and I should be gratified to direct payment without further question, I do not see how I can do so without acting upon a principle that would be mischievous. We can pay the counsel whom we specially employ, for their professional services. I do not know what right we have to go further. Your commission to appear as counsel was not understood as an instruction to pay any costs or expenses.</ab>
            <ab>If any considerations occur to you which can remove the difficulties, I shall be happy to learn them.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
