<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00793">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">William M. Evarts to John McAllister Schofield, 17 February 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>William M. Evarts</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00793</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>William M. Evarts</author>
          <title>William M. Evarts to John McAllister Schofield, 17 February 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-02-17" xml:id="dat1">February 17, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">379-380</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Evarts, William M. M.">William M. Evarts</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Schofield, John McAllister ">John McAllister Schofield</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-06" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-03-09" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-12" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00793.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>Feb. 17, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. J. M. Schofield,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I return herewith the communication addressed to the Hon. B. F. Butler, dated Feb. 16, inst. from your Dept., which you handed to me yesterday.</ab>
            <ab>I presume the subject-matter of this communication is the same as that involved in the case of the U. S. appellants ag't. Geo. U. Johnson, in the Sup. Court of the U. S., on appeal from the Court of Claims, which has been dismissed with your consent, pursuant to the advice contained in my letter to you of the 22d of Sept. last. By the judgment of the Court of Claims in that case, &amp; the dismissal of the appeal, the claimant has obtained a right to the payment of the rent which was allowed him for the premises of which he claimed to be the owner. You will find a Report of the case of Johnson ag't The U. S. in the 2 Court of Claims Reports p. 391, which gives a full account of the facts of the case, and the precise period of time for which rent was allowed by the Court.</ab>
            <ab>That the precise reference of this communication of Gen. Butler to your Dept. may have to the case already decided, I do not know; but you will perhaps be able to ascertain the object of his communication by a consideration of the facts of the case, which has been disposed
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Com. from B. F. Butler to War Dep't.</note>
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00793.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            of in the manner stated.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>Wm. M. Evarts,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
