<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01359">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to Henry A. Wise, 4 June 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01359</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to Henry A. Wise, 4 June 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-06-04" xml:id="dat1">June 4, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">337-338</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Wise, Henry A.">Henry A. Wise</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-06-22" who="#vs">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-05" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-12" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01359.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>June 4, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Henry A. Wise,</ab>
            <ab>Richmond, Va.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>James Madison, a private soldier in the 5th U. S. Cavalry, has been indicted, as I am informed, for the murder of Wm. P. Boley, and is to be tried at Lynchburg. James Madison, with Thomas Jones, was charged with the crime before a military commission, while Virginia was in military occupation by the United States, and Jones was convicted of manslaughter. Madison was not apprehended until after it was too late to try him by a military commission, and he is now held by the civil authorities. The War Department suppose that Madison may have some responsibility for the death of Boley, but are inclined to the opinion that there were such extenuating or mitigating circumstances as might reduce the character of this act to manslaughter. They wish to make some provision for his defence, so that his life shall not be endangered, because he is poor and friendless, and wish that some competent person should be employed to appear for him on his trial and make a suitable defence. It does not seem to them proper to incur a large expense, because it is not strictly the duty of the Government to defend the case. I suggested to the Secretary of War that it would be well to apply to you to know whether you could give some attention to the case at Lynchburg, or, if not, whether you could recommend some suitable lawyer at Lynchburg, to be employed for the
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of James Madison <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="js">prvt.</unclear> chg'd with murder</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="left">see p. 338 seq.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01359.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            purpose&#8212;and he authorizes me to make the inquiry. The fee which the Government would be willing to offer could not of course be a large one. Perhaps therefore we could hardly expect to secure the services of any gentleman not on the spot, where it would occasion him no unusual trouble or expense.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
