<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02915">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Lyman Trumbull, 18 February 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02915</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</persName>
        <persName xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</persName></note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Lyman Trumbull, 18 February 1871</title>        
          <date cert="high" when="1871-02-18" xml:id="dat1">February 18, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">4-5</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Trumbull, Lyman">Lyman Trumbull</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2013-06" who="kp">blessed</change>
      <change when="2013-05-03" who="#crl">added bibliographic data with microcopy and roll numbers</change>
      <change when="2013-03-15" who="#crl">checked, proofed</change>
      <change when="2012-11-26" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
       <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02915.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>Feb. 18, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Lyman Trumbull,</ab>
          <ab>Chairman of the Judiciary Committee,</ab>
          <ab>U.S. Senate.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I beg leave to call your attention to the subject of the official compensation of the Hon. Joel C. C. Winch, Judge of the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Texas.</ab>
          <ab>He was appointed to that office last October, during the recess of the Senate, under a temporary commission. He was nominated to the Senate, and has been rejected&#8212;and will hold until the end of the present session, unless he should be superseded by another appointment, for which nomination is now before the Senate.</ab>
<ab>An obstacle to the payment of his salary has been found in Sec. 2 of the Act of Feb. 9, 1863, (12 U.S. Stat. 646.) The accounting officers of the Treasury decline to pay it, on the ground that the vacancy existed while the Senate was in session last summer.</ab>
          <ab>The facts are these: John Appleton, of Maine, was nominated and confirmed, in May last. He declined, and has since died. I find in the office no evidence of the time
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Salary of Judge Winch, Texas</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02915.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            when he resigned, or when the resignation was accepted, I heard of the vacancy soon after I entered this office in July last, whether before or after the adjournment of Congress, I am unable now to remember. If it were before, the pressure of business at the close of the session prevented an immediate nomination.</ab>
          <ab>Judge Winch has been doing the business of the office, and I believe has been holding a court ever since an early date in November last. And it seems to me right that Congress should relieve him, under these circumstances, from the operation of that stern statute&#8212;and I respectfully suggest that provision by law be made of the payment of his salary.</ab>
          <ab>I address a similar letter to the Chairman of the Judiciary Committee of the House.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
      </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
