<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02444">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Joseph Watson, 2 September 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02444</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Joseph Watson, 2 September 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-09-02" xml:id="dat1">September 2, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">47</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Watson, Joseph">Joseph Watson</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-11-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-21" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-21" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02444.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Sept. 2, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Mr. Joseph Watson,</ab>
            <ab>P. O. box, 466</ab>
            <ab>Newport, R. I.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 22d ultimo.</ab>
            <ab>If I understand your case properly, it is this: that you, as informer, had a claim to half the proceeds of thirty-one barrels of condemned spirits, and to half the proceeds of the track of land on which the Distillery was situated; that proceedings for the forfeiture were instituted against both species of property; that in the former you asserted your claim as informer, and received your moiety; that in the latter you did not assert your claim in Court, and did not therefore receive the moiety; and now you desire me to give some directions to the District Attorney to aid you in recovering the latter moiety.</ab>
            <ab>I am not aware of any law which requires one to aid parties who neglect the timely assertion of their rights against the Government&#8212;and therefore, however meritorious may be your claim, I do not feel at liberty to take the action which you request. I presume you have counsel who will properly advise you in regard to the future prosecution of your claim. I return the printed book which you enclosed.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman, Attorney General.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">case of certain informer R. I.</note>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
