<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00150">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">J. Hubley Ashton to H. S. Fitch, 24 October 1866</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00150</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

       
        <bibl>
          <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
          <title>J. Hubley Ashton to H. S. Fitch, 24 October 1866</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1866-10-24" xml:id="dat1">October 24, 1866</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">191-192</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ashton, J. Hubley">J. Hubley Ashton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Fitch, H. S. ">H. S. Fitch</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-22" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-07" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-08-31" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00150.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>October 24, 1866,</ab>
            <ab>To</ab>
            <ab>H. L. Fitch, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Attorney,</ab>
            <ab>Savannah, Geo.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>My attention has been called by the Secretary of the Treasury to the probable fact of the custody, by the U. S. Marshal for your District, of certain railroad iron claimed to belong to the Brunswick &amp; Albany Railroad Co. of Georgia, which the Secretary directed to be restored to that Co. while in the possession of the Treasury agents as captured or abandoned property.</ab>
            <ab>The Secretary of the Treasury having determined that the said Co. is entitled to possession of this property, you will forthwith, on the receipt of this letter, if the same is in your possession, or under your control, surrender &amp; transfer it to the Collector of Customs at Savannah.</ab>
            <ab>If the said property is in the possession or under the control of the U. S. Marshal, you will forthwith, on the receipt of this letter, issue instructions to the Marshal, to surrender &amp; transfer the property to the said Collector of Customs.</ab>
           <ab>If judicial proceedings have been instituted for forfeiture of the property, &amp; no claim therefor has been filed in court, you will enter a discontinuance of those proceedings &amp; direct the Marshal immediately to surrender &amp; transfer the same to the Collector of Customs at Savannah.
               <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00150.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            That officer has received appropriate instructions in the premises.</ab>
            <ab>A copy of this letter will be sent to J.M Gurrard, Esq. the counsel of the B. &amp; A. RR. Co.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c</ab>
            <ab>J. Hubley Ashton,</ab>
            <ab>Asst. Att'y. Gen'l.</ab>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
