<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00567">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to Benjamin F. Wade, 13 June 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00567</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to Benjamin F. Wade, 13 June 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-06-13" xml:id="dat1">June 13, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">176-177</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Wade, Benjamin F. ">Benjamin F. Wade</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-28" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-21" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-05" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00567.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>June 13, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>The Honorable B. F. Wade,</ab>
            <ab>President <hi rend="underline">pro</hi><hi rend="underline">tempore</hi> of the Senate.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor herewith to lay before Congress, through you, the petition of Gabriel M. Thomas, of Pickens District, South Carolina, for such pardon and relief as shall remove his political disabilities, so as to enable him to enjoy all privileges of any other citizen of the United States, in holding any office of profit and trust, or exercising any other privilege allowed citizens of the United States, who never did participate in the rebellion; and also a paper which accompanied the petition, consisting of an official statement of F. A. Hoke, Assistant Assessor of the Third Internal Revenue District of South Carolina, in support of the petition: both being addressed to the President.</ab>
            <ab>Mr. Hoke, the Revenue Officer, states that Thomas is a good citizen, a farmer,&#8212; that he has acted in the capacity of Deputy Sheriff for the District; has served for a time as a volunteer in the rebel forces; that he is an ordinary man in point of education, and has never been in any public situation except that of deputy sheriff.&#8212; He does not state what was the military rank of Thomas, but it was probably not above the rank of Brigadier General&#8212;most probably that of a private. It is improbable also that this petitioner is among the few classes of persons excepted from the benefits of the President's Proclamation of Amnesty, of the 7th September, 1867. It is
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00567.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                not stated in these papers that Thomas has at any time, or under any of the several proclamations, by the present or the late President, availed himself of the pardon and amnesty offered therein, on condition of taking a prescribed oath of allegiance, though such is doubtless the fact. If so, he has already, so far as Executive agency could work that result, been restored to the plenary status of a loyal citizen of the United States. The Assessor states that Mr. Thomas's knowledge of that part of the country, and his experience as Deputy Sheriff, render him well-suited to the office of Deputy Marshal of the United States, a position which, he says, has been tendered Thomas, who could not accept it in consequence of the oath required by law of all United States officers. The Assessor declares that he has been anxious for Thomas to have the position of Deputy Marshal in order to aid him in suppressing illicit distillation in that country, and feels satisfied that Thomas would make an efficient officer of that kind. And with a view to these objects, he asks the President to remove Thomas's disabilities, so that he may accept the office.</ab>
            <ab>I have no information touching the matter or the pardon beyond the papers herewith. But as the public object sought by the petitioners, which seems to be worthy of attention, <choice><sic>canot</sic><corr>cannot</corr></choice>be promoted by the Executive, as they have erroneously supposed, I have thought it due them to give their Memorial a proper direction.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully, your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab><choice><sic>OH Browning,</sic><corr>O. H. Browning</corr></choice></ab>
            <ab>Attorney General <hi rend="underline">ad</hi><hi rend="underline">interim</hi>.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
