<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00745">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">William M. Evarts to Samuel Blatchford, 16 January 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>William M. Evarts</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00745</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>William M. Evarts</author>
          <title>William M. Evarts to Samuel Blatchford, 16 January 1869</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1869-01-16" xml:id="dat1">January 16, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">341-343</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Evarts, William M. M.">William M. Evarts</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Blatchford, Samuel">Samuel Blatchford</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-02" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-08" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-21" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00745.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>January 16, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Samuel Blatchford,</ab>
            <ab>Judge United States Court,</ab>
            <ab>New York City.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The case of John H. Egins is strongly pressed upon my attention as justly requiring the interposition of the Executive clemency, on the ground of doubt as to his guilt, and distrust of the truth or sufficiency of the testimony upon which he was convicted. I should not take the liberty of again referring the subject to you, after your reply to my former reference of the papers, had not an examination of the affidavits presented to me, on behalf of the prisoner made a considerable impression upon my own mind, in disturbance of entire confidence in the integrity or the accuracy of the evidence given at his trial. I am unwilling
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00745.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            however to proceed upon my own impression in this regard, notwithstanding my respect for the character &amp; position of those who, apparently, in a very disinterested manner, and in the interest of public justice, are urging the pardon of the prisoner, if, upon further consideration, the judge who tried the cause should preserve an undoubted satisfaction with the result of the trial.</ab>
            <ab>It is very obvious that there is nothing in the character of the witness Osborne that should attract confidence to his testimony, and the management of this case on the part of the prisoner seems to me an instance of the protection of the plainly guilty and inexcusable party upon whose implication of others whose conduct, but for his imputation of guilt, would be consistent with innocence. There is nothing in the papers before me which tends to explain the greater severity of the sentence upon Egins, than of that which was imposed upon Martin,&#8212;and I beg to call your attention to that point, as doubtless at the time of the conviction the grounds of this discrimination were apparent to the court.</ab>
            <ab>The crime in this case is of a nature that deserves punishment, and the application for pardon rests almost entirely upon the supposed doubts which the imperfect defense of the prisoner at the trial, the character of the witnesses against him, and the subsequent exhibition of proofs in the shape of
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00745.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            affidavits, throw upon the conviction. These grounds present always a case of the utmost solicitude to the Executive, that, on the one hand, innocence may not suffer from misfortune, and, on the other, that the judicial authority may not be impaired by unwarrantable encroachments upon its responsibilities. These public reasons must excuse me for again troubling you in this case.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient serv't,</ab>
            <ab>Wm. M. Evarts,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
