<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00351">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to R. W. Healy, 12 December 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00351</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to R. W. Healy, 12 December 1867</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1867-12-12" xml:id="dat1">December 12, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">608-610</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Healy, R. W. ">R. W. Healy</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-15" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-17" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-13" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00351.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>December 12, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>R. W. Healy, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>United States Marshal</ab>
            <ab>Montgomery, Ala.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letter of the 9th ultimo, addressed to the Solicitor of the Treasury, and that of the 4th instant, addressed to the Attorney General, are before us, touching the disposition proper to be made of funds arising as net proceeds from prosecutions under the confiscation laws&#8212;and communicating the fact that demands are made upon you for disbursements in favor of late officers concerned in such prosecutions, of sums in the nature of fees or emoluments, which appear to you to be unwarranted.</ab>
            <ab>I have to say, in the first place, that no disbursements will be made by you of the character mentioned in your communication of the 4th instant, nor of kindred
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00351.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            character, until otherwise instructed by this office.</ab>
            <ab>With regard to the disposition proper to be made of moneys in your hands, as mentioned in your letter of the 9th ultimo. I have to instruct you that it is your duty to pay such moneys into the Treasury of the United States, through the nearest designated public depository.</ab>
            <ab>The condemnations from which resulted the proceeds in your hands, were all, doubtless, had under either the Act of 6 August, 1861, (12 Stats. 319,) or the Act of 17 July, 1862, (12 Stats. 589.). The former directs no particular application of proceeds. The latter, however, directs the President to apply the proceeds to the support of the Army,&#8212;but also, (Sect. 7,) directs such proceeds to be paid into the Treasury for the purpose aforesaid.</ab>
            <ab>The Act of 3 March, 1849, "requiring all moneys receivable from customs, and from all other sources, to be paid immediately into the Treasury," etc. (9 Stats. 398.) Section 1st, seems applicable to the funds arising upon these confiscations. In designating the funds so to be paid in by you, it would be advisable, however, for you to distinguish them according to the act under which they have been realized. In a case where the libel charged under both acts, a further discrimination should be made, you will be entitled to information from the District Attorney as to what Act or Acts any particular prosecution was had under, which he will give you upon his responsibility. This discrimination of funds is believed to be necessary because of the difference between the two Confiscation Acts, as to the
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.00351.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            ulterior destination of the money.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Att'y Gen'l.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
