<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01810">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Joseph Henry, 7 April 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01810</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Joseph Henry, 7 April 1871</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1871-04-07" xml:id="dat1">April 7, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">700-702</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Henry, Joseph">Joseph Henry</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-08-10" who="#jw">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-13" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-09" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01810.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>April 7, 1871</ab>
            <ab>Joseph Henry, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of Smithsonian Institution,</ab>
            <ab>Washington, D. C.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received yours of the 5th instant, enclosing a copy of a deed of foundation between Horace Hawes, of San Francisco, California, and certain trustees, conveying property for the use of an institution to be known as the Mount Eagle University. One of the conditions
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01810.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
            upon which the grant is made is that from other sources certain sums of money shall be collected for the same object, as follows: $100,000 within fifteen years after the decease of the grantor; $500,000 within thirty years after his decease; $1,500,00 within fifty years after his decease;&#8212;$4,000,000 within one hundred years after the date of the deed, (February 24, 1871:) and in default of raising, collecting, or expending the said sums within the precise times and periods aforesaid, the grant as to a portion of the land, is to become void, and the granted property as the grantor, by deed or will, shall appoint; and in defect of such appointment in the heirs male of his body,&#8212;and in default of such heirs in the Government of the United States, for the use of the Smithsonian Institute.</ab>
            <ab>In behalf of the Board of Regents of the Institution, you have requested to be informed whether any steps should be taken to secure the interests of the Institution in relation to this bequest.</ab>
            <ab>It appears that the failure to raise, collect, and expend the said sums of money within the periods named,&#8212;the failure of Mr. Hawes to dispose of the property by deed or will,&#8212;and the failure of the heirs male of his body, are conditions which must precede the vesting of the property in the Government of the United States, for the use of the Institute.</ab>
            <ab>The first of these conditions cannot
                
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Contingent bequest of Mr. Hawes, of California, to the Smithsonian Institute.</note>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.01810.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                exist until, at least, fifteen years after the decease of Mr. Hawes, and none of these conditions may ever exist.</ab>
            <ab>I am of the opinion that no present action can be taken by the United States to secure the interests of the Institutions; but I suggest that a copy of the deed be filed in the archives of the Institution for use in the possible contingencies of the distant future.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
