<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00349">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Henry Stanbery to Ulysses S. Grant, 12 December 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00349</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
          <title>Henry Stanbery to Ulysses S. Grant, 12 December 1867</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1867-12-12" xml:id="dat1">December 12, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">605-606</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Stanbery, Henry">Henry Stanbery</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S.">Ulysses S. Grant</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-27" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-14" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-21" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00349.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>December 12, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>Gen. U. S. Grant, U. S.A.</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War, <hi rend="underline">ad interim</hi>.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letter of October 31, 1867, addressed to the Secretary of the Treasury, requesting that none of the papers of G. B. Lamar, the legal custody of which was then a question before this office, should be delivered to him, was communicated by the Secretary of the Treasury in his letter to me of the 1st November 1867,&#8212; whereupon the whole matter was treated as having been withdrawn from my consideration, and all the papers relating to it, were, with my letter of 5th Nov. 1867, transmitted to the Secretary of the Treasury, conformably to your request.</ab>
            <ab>It appears, however, that among the papers so transmitted were some which did not belong to those which were in question, and which, having been duly filed here by Mr. Lamar, after the reference, were subject to the exclusive discretion of this office, and ought not to have been transmitted, as happened by inadvertence. These papers comprised certain copies of the originals in question, which copies had been regularly made and delivered to Mr. Lamar by the Secretary of the Treasury in the
              <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00349.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
              exercise of his competent authority&#8212; and were, therefore, not subject in any sense to the discretion of the Government, except for the purposes of this office in the business of Mr. Lamar, then before me, upon the reference aforesaid of the question. When the reference was retracted, it would have been necessary to determine what would be a fit disposition to make of the papers so filed here by Mr. Lamar.</ab>
            <ab>I subjoin a schedule of the papers herein referred to, and anticipate, upon this explanation, that you will be pleased to separate them from the other papers, the subject of your letter to the Secretary of the Treasury, of October 31, 1867, and return them to this office, for such disposition as may be found proper, after due consideration.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab>Henry Stanbery,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <list><item>Schedule of papers:</item><item>1. Copy of the original warehouse Receipt for 28 bales of cotton, out of an invoice of 143.</item><item>2. Copy of the original warehouse receipt for SHH 38 bales.</item><item>3. Copies of the applications of Mr. Lamar to the Secretary of the Treasury, upon which No's 2 and 3 were furnished by the Secretary.</item><item>4. Copy of General Duncan's Report.</item></list>
           
            
          
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
