<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00812">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">William M. Evarts to Edward Jordan, 27 February 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>William M. Evarts</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00812</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>William M. Evarts</author>
          <title>William M. Evarts to Edward Jordan, 27 February 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-02-27" xml:id="dat1">February 27, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">400-401</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Evarts, William M. M.">William M. Evarts</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Jordan, Edward">Edward Jordan</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-03" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-03" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-21" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
          <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00812.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>Feb. 27, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Edward Jordan, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Solicitor of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to receive your letter of the 17th of February inst. and the accompanying papers, relating to proceedings on behalf of the United States against the Louisiana State Bank, for the proceeds of certain cotton and asking me to give such directions respecting the proceedings allowed to as I may deem expedient, or to express to you my advice as to the course to be adopted in the premises.</ab>
            <ab>I regard the subject of your letter, and the request for my advice and direction in the premises, as falling within the provision of the 10th Sect. of the Act of May 20, 1830, by which it is made the duty of the Attorney General of the U. S. at the request of the Solicitor of the Treasury, to advise and direct the said Solicitor as to the manner of conducting certain suits, proceedings &amp; prosecutions.</ab>
            <ab>I have accordingly made the proper  examination into the nature of the case, and the proceedings under consideration, and particularly have given that weight to the opinions and suggestions of the Hon. John A. Campbell, of New Orleans, found in one of the papers submitted to me which the distinguished ability and character of that gentleman should secure.</ab>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Confiscation case.</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">proceeds of certain cotton - U. S. ag't Louisiana State Bank</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00812.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>I have, upon this examination concluded, and so advise, that the confiscation proposed cannot be maintained, and should not, therefore, be attempted. If I had come to an opposite conclusion as to the legal nature of the claim, on the part of the U. S. and the result of its prosecution, I should still be of opinion that it was neither the interest nor the duty of the Government, in the present state of affairs, to insist upon the forfeiture of the property in question.</ab>
            <ab>I return the papers transmitted to me, &amp; advise that your action in the premises should be governed by the views which I have expressed.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, &amp;c. &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>Wm. M. Evarts,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
