<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01119">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to Lyman Trumbull, 11 December 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01119</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to Lyman Trumbull, 11 December 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-12-11" xml:id="dat1">December 11, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">145</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
      
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Trumbull, Lyman">Lyman Trumbull</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-06" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-10" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-09" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01119.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>December 11, 1869.</ab>
           <ab>Hon. Lyman Trumbull,</ab>
           <ab>Chairman of the Judiciary Committee,</ab>
           <ab>U. S. Senate.</ab>
           <ab>Sir:</ab>
           <ab>The President directs me to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of December 10, 1869, requesting him to furnish your Committee with the recommendations for Judges of the Circuit Courts in the respective Circuits, including those of other persons as well as of the persons nominated, and that he will furnish you with the ages of the nominees, if he has them&#8212;and instructs me to say, in reply, that a compliance with your request does not seem to him proper, or consistent with his official duty. In making a selection of officers of such high position, it can hardly be necessary to suggest, that he has not been governed by applications from persons who wished the appointment, nor confined his range of choice to those persons who would be willing to apply, or have applications made on the behalf&#8212;but has endeavored to ascertain by every means in his power, who, in his judgment, were the persons who ought to be nominated. He has no official information as to the ages of the gentlemen whose names have been sent to the Senate, and as he believes, no information not readily accessible to the committee.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar, Attorney General.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">declining papers</note> 
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
