<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01354">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 3 June 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01354</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 3 June 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-06-03" xml:id="dat1">June 3, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">330-333</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-06-22" who="#vs">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-05" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-12" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01354.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>Be it enacted, etc. That section seven of the Act approved March 3, 1865, entitled "An Act further to amend an Act entitled 'an Act for the collection of Direct Taxes in the Insurrectionary Districts within the United States, and for other purposes,' approved June 7, 1862," be
               
               <note type="authorial" place="left">Draft, &amp;c. referred to.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01354.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
           amended by adding thereto the following words, to wit: And provided further that in all cases where the owner of any land sold by the Board of Commissioners, his heirs or assigns, shall recover the same from the purchaser, his heirs or assigns, by the judgment of any Circuit Court of the United States, by reason of a failure, without his or their fault, or neglect, of the title of the purchaser, derived from said sale, such owner, his heirs or assigns, shall pay to the purchaser, his heirs or assigns, the amount of the taxes and penalties due to the United States on account of the land, when sold, together with interest on the amount of said taxes, at the rate of ten <hi rend="underline">per centum per annum</hi> from the time the taxes became due, and all the costs and expenses of the sale, and of any subsequent proceedings by the Tax Commissioners before such purchaser, his heirs or assigns, shall be evicted from, or turned out of possession of the land so recovered, and no writ to put such owner, his heirs or assigns, in possession, shall issue, until such payment is made; and the Secretary of the Treasury, on being satisfied that any purchaser, his heirs or assigns, has been evicted from or turned out of possession of any such land, by the judgment of such Circuit Court, in the manner before mentioned, is hereby authorized, out of any moneys in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, to repay to the person or persons entitled thereto, the remainder of money originally paid by the purchaser
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01354.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
           of the land so recovered, if the same has been paid into the Treasury, after deducting therefrom a sum equivalent to the whole amount which the owner, his heirs or assigns, is herein required to pay to the purchaser, his heirs or assigns, before eviction, the amount so deducted to be retained by the United States, as a payment of the taxes, penalties, interest and costs, due on account of the land so recovered. And any suit or action now pending, or which may hereafter be brought, in any State court, to recover the possession of any such lands on account of any alleged failure in the title derived from the United States under such sale, may at any time before the trial, or final hearing of the cause, be, by the defendant, or, if there be more than one, the defendants, removed to the Circuit Court of the United States, next to be held in the District where the land is situated, in the manner prescribed by an Act approved July 27, 1866, entitled "An Act for the removal of causes in certain cases from State Courts," without regard to the citizenship of the parties, or the value of the land, or the amount in dispute&#8212;and all the provisions of the last named Act respecting the manner and effect of the removal, the offering of good and sufficient sureties, and all other matters and things to be done to effect such removal, and the right of said Circuit Court to hear and determine the cause of removal shall apply with full force and effect to the suits the removal of which is herein
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.01354.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
           provided for&#8212;<hi rend="underline">Provided</hi>, the defendant, or, if there be more than one, the defendants, shall make it appear to the satisfaction of the Court of the State in which the petition for removal is filed, by filing an affidavit to that effect, or otherwise, that the validity of a title derived from a sale under the laws of the United States relating to direct taxes is involved in the suit, and that he is, or they are, interested in maintaining the validity thereof.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
