<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00739">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">William M. Evarts to William Fullerton, 23 December 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>William M. Evarts</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00739</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>William M. Evarts</author>
          <title>William M. Evarts to William Fullerton, 23 December 1868</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1868-12-23" xml:id="dat1">December 23, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">333-335</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Evarts, William M. M.">William M. Evarts</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Fullerton, William">William Fullerton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-02" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-07" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-14" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00739.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>December 23, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. William Fullerton,</ab>
            <ab>11 Pine street New York City.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letter of the 15th Dec. inst. calls my attention to a certain course of proceedings of Mr. A. A. Belknap, the special agent of the Treasury Department, in employing yourself and Mr. Knox, your partner, as counsel, and in giving assurances in the course of those proceedings, and in connexion with your and Mr. Knox's services as counsel, to certain parties, of protection against ill consequences to them, from the disclosures made by them. I do not conceive that I have any duty in respect of any of the prosecutions now pending in the Southern District of New York against any of the parties whom you name, growing out of these proceedings, or those assurances of Mr. Belknap. Your letter also calls my attention to the supposed authority which you had, in consequence of or in connection with, your investigations in the month of September last, and since, to give assurances to persons giving you information in aid of your investigations into frauds on the internal revenue, of "protection against criminal proceedings on account of their connection with the frauds disclosed." In a personal interview during your visit to Washington immediately after my reception of your letter, I called your attention to this statement of the extent of the protection
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00739.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            which you were authorized to give, or had given, to parties making disclosures as being beyond the scope of those assurances, or certainly, of the authority to make them, and stated to you that I understood the assurances that had been given, as I knew that authority to make them had been limited to protection against ill-consequences on account of, or by reason of, the disclosures that should be made. To this qualification I understood you to assent; and I mention it now only in due course of reply to your letter, the consideration of the subject between us, heretofore, having been had in the form of a personal interview. Recognizing, as I did, the propriety of making good the assurances of the government, in this sense and to this extent, I considered it my duty, in consequence of your communication, to address a letter to the Dist. Attorney, Mr. Courtney, calling his attention to these assurances, and to the claims made by you for their fulfilment&#8212;to the terms of which letter, upon its being read to you, I understood you to assent, as properly laying the subject before that officer. I yesterday received, under date of the 21st inst, a full communication from the Dist. Attorney, with copies of the indictments against Blaisdell and Eckel, and against Blaisdell, Eckel, Diezendorf, Schuyler and McClearen, giving a statement of the
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00739.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            circumstances under which the indictments had been found&#8212;and of the character and sources of the evidence upon which they had been procured. Upon the state of the matter thus presented, I felt satisfied that the proper observance of the obligations of the Government in the premises would not permit a withdrawal of the prosecutions&#8212;as, apparently, disclosures of the defendants, as made to you, had not furnished directly or indirectly the evidence for the indictments, and were not expected to form any part of the evidence on the trial.</ab>
            <ab>I have thought, however, that proper provision should be made to secure these defendants in the conduct of the trial by the prosecution, against the introduction of any evidence which should have been furnished by themselves in any disclosures they may have made to you, and that a full and accurate record of the trial should be preserved, in order that, in case of conviction, any further duty that might be claimed from the Government might be fulfilled, if the record of the trial showed the propriety of any further intervention.</ab>
            <ab>I beg to enclose a copy of my letter to the Dist. Attorney, for your information.</ab>
             <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obed't serv't,</ab>
            <ab>Wm. M. Evarts,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>[Letter enc.]</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
