<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00350">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Lyman Trumbull, 12 December 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00350</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Lyman Trumbull, 12 December 1867</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1867-12-12" xml:id="dat1">December 12, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">607-608</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Trumbull, Lyman">Lyman Trumbull</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-15" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-17" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-13" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00350.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>December 12, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Lyman Trumbull,</ab>
            <ab>Chairman Committee on the Judiciary, Senate of the United States.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>At the request of William Dorsheimer, Esq., United States Attorney for the Northern District of New York, and by direction of the Attorney General, I have the honor to communicate a suggestion of the former, for some additional legislation touching crimes committed on the great Lakes, out of the jurisdiction of any particular State. A copy of his draft of a Bill, and of his letter setting forth the circumstances which appear to show the expediency of further legislation, are herewith enclosed.</ab>
            <ab>Mr. Dorsheimer's main object appears to be to settle a doubt whether under the terms of the several statutes defining and punishing felonies, &amp;c. committed on the high seas, such offences, when committed on the great Lakes and inland waters are included in their provisions. That the admiralty and maritime jurisdiction of the United States extends to such waters has been so well settled by the Supreme Court that Mr. Dorsheimer is not understood to have in view any doubt of the jurisdictions, but only whether the crimes are adequately defined without the words Lakes, Etc., or equivalent words. If this is all, the Attorney General thinks that an Act simply declaring that the words high seas, river, haven, creek, basin, or bay, as used in the several acts, shall be construed to include any waters, whether fresh or salt, within the admiralty and maritime jurisdiction <choice><sic>of of</sic><corr>of</corr></choice>the United States and <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="km">each of the jurisdictions</unclear> of any particular
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00350.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            state, would answer the end.</ab>
            <ab>It may be worthy remark that a case is now pending in the territory of Washington, in which a doubt has arisen whether the words, "out of the jurisdiction of any particular State," as used in several criminal statutes at large should be construed to give the United States Courts exclusive jurisdiction where the offence was committed on the tide-water literally "out of the jurisdiction of any particular State," but yet within the body of a county of an organized Territory.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
