<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01123">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">W. A. Field to Charles F. Blake, 23 December 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>W. A. Field</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01123</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMulle</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

       
        <bibl>
          <author>W. A. Field</author>
          <title>W. A. Field to Charles F. Blake, 23 December 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-12-23" xml:id="dat1">December 23, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">148-149</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Blake, Charles F.">Charles F. Blake</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-06" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-10" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-10" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01123.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>December 23, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Charles F. Blake, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>No. 7 Warren street,</ab>
            <ab>New York City</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 22d of December, enclosing a letter from Gen. John A. Dix, all addressed to the Attorney General of the United States.</ab>
            <ab>I will thank you to send to this office a transcript of the record or papers in Court, in all these suits, that the Attorney General may see, on an inspection thereof, that they are such suits as he is by the first Section of the Act of July 27, 1868, required to appear in and defend. If they shall be found to be suits of that character, the Attorney General will probably authorize you to continue to act as counsel for Gen. Dix in defending these suits&#8212;your compensation to be determined and paid by the Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>I also desire to be informed whether you wish the aid of any counsel in defending these suits, and to ask your opinion as to whether they should not be removed to the Circuit Court of the United States
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of suits ag't. Gen. Dix.</note>   

                <note type="authorial" place="left">see p 157 seq</note>      
                


            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01123.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            before a trial is had in the State Courts. As the Constitutionality of the Act of March 3, 1863, so far as it provides the removal of similar suits from a State Court to a Circuit Court, after judgment on a verdict in a State Court, in such a manner that a trial both of law and facts can be had in the Circuit Court, has been denied in a case now pending before the Supreme Court of the United States&#8212;it is desirable to avoid that question in these suits, if it can be done.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>W. A. Field,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Attorney General</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
