<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01692">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Ulysses S. Grant, 4 February 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01692</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Ulysses S. Grant, 4 February 1871</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1871-02-04" xml:id="dat1">February 4, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H, 615-617</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">615-617</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S.">Ulysses S. Grant</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-07-27" who="#jw">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-12" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-06" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01692.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>Feb. 4, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>To the President.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have examined the Joint resolution for the relief of certain contractors for the construction of vessels of war, and steam machinery,&#8212;and, in reply to your inquiry whether any reasons exist why it should not receive your approval, I have the honor to submit the following suggestions.</ab>
            <ab>The Act of March 2, 1867, (14 U. S. Stat. at Large, p. 424,) directs the Secretary of the Navy "to investigate the claims of all contractors for building vessels-of-war and steam machinery for the same, under contracts made after the 1st day of May, 1861, and prior to the 1st day of January, 1864,&#8212;said investigation to be made upon the following basis: he shall ascertain the additional cost which was necessarily incurred by each contractor in the completion of his work, by reason of any change or alterations in the plans and specifications required, and delays in the prosecution of the work occasioned by the Government, which were not provided for
                
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Opinion on approval of certain Joint Resolution</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01692.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            in the original contract; but no allowance for any advance in the price of labor or material shall be considered unless such advance occurred during the prolonged time for completing the work rendered necessary by the delay resulting from the action of the Government aforesaid, and then only when such advance could not have been avoided by the exercise of ordinary prudence and diligence on the part of the contractor," etc.</ab>
            <ab>The resolution transfers the investigation to the Court of Claims, and repeals "so much of said Act as provides against considering any allowance in favor of any such parties for any advance in the price of labor and material when he could have avoided that advance by the exercise of ordinary prudence and diligence. The effect of the repeal will be to relieve contractors from the consequences of their own imprudence and negligence. I see no good reason for relieving contractors from the results of their own neglect of ordinary prudence and diligence&#8212;and therefore I am of the
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01692.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            opinion that the Joint Resolution may be properly referred to the reconsideration of Congress.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
