<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00488">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to Andrew Johnson, 26 March 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00488</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to Andrew Johnson, 26 March 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-03-26" xml:id="dat1">March 26, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">116-119</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Johnson, Andrew">Andrew Johnson</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-29" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-03-03" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-28" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00488.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>March 26, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>The President.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>In conformity to your directions, under date of the 14th inst. I have caused to be prepared, and have the honor herewith to submit, a table (marked A.) of offices and their respective tenures, comprising the following classes, which have been created by Congress, exclusively of all military and naval offices, all judges of the Constitutional Judiciary of the United States, all judges of the Court of Claims, all public
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00488.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            ministers, consuls, and other agents of foreign intercourse, and all inferior officers whose appointment is vested in the President alone, in Heads of Departments, or in Courts of Law, viz:</ab>
            <ab>1: Officers with a tenure definitely limited, i.e., with a term prescribed.</ab>
            <ab>2: Officers with a term prescribed, "unless sooner removed."</ab>
            <ab>3: Officers without a prescribed term, and <hi rend="underline">not</hi> expressly during pleasure.</ab>
            <ab>4: Offices without a prescribed term, and expressly during pleasure.</ab>
            <ab>As directed, the date of the Act of Congress creating the office in each instance is given in the table, with the volume and page of the public statutes, together with appropriate explanatory remarks.</ab>
            <ab>The inquiry is also made in your communication "what officers holding for a fixed period of time, and whose tenure is not expressed by law to be 'unless sooner removed,' have been removed&#8212;and when, and by whom?"</ab>
            <ab>This is understood as contemplating those officers only of whose appointments and removals the Attorney General would have official knowledge, and keep record.</ab>
            <ab>I am not able to ascertain with certainty at what precise period the incumbency of Territorial Judges, District Attorneys, and Marshals, became regularly a matter of official notice and supervision in the Attorney General's Office. Our files and records show several removals
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.00488.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            of Territorial Judges, the earliest being made by direction of President Lincoln in 1864. I herewith submit a table marked B. of all removals of record in this office of Territorial Judges.</ab>
<ab>It is believed that the record of previous removals of Territorial judges is in the Department of State. One removal came incidentally before the Supreme Court of the United States in 1854, 17 Howard, 284&#8212;United States, <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>: Guthrie. The court intimated no opinion touching the President's power of removal in the premises, the case going off on another point, notwithstanding that the former was very fully argued. Mr. Lawrence, of counsel, on that occasion, speaks as if the removal then in question was the first which had been made of a Territorial Judge, (page 298.) It was made on the 21 October, 1851, by President Fillmore, who acted upon the advice of Mr. Attorney Gen'l Crittenden, 23 January, 1851, (5 opinions Attorney's General, 288.) Mr. Attorney Gen'l Grundy had previously expressed his opinion, 1 February, 1839, that Territorial Judges could not be impeached as civil officers of the United States, in the sense of the constitution; (3 Opinions Attorneys Gen'l 409.)</ab>
<ab>A large number of removals have been made from time to time of District Attorneys and Marshals. But since 1820, (see Table A.) the tenure of District Attorneys of the United States&#8212;and from 1789 down, that of Marshals&#8212;has been for four years, unless sooner removed. The corresponding officers            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="nar.00488.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
            for Territories have, as believed, without exception, held, and still hold, by a similar tenure. No other officers except those whose appointment is vested in the Head of this Department, are under the supervision of the Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>It will be observed that all public ministers, consuls, &amp; other agents of foreign intercourse are wholly omitted from Table A. herewith. As they are officers of the United States, it may be necessary to explain that the most important of them are substantially of Executive creation, under the express diplomatic powers vested in the President by the Constitution, and in conformity to the law regulating the intercourse of nations.</ab>
            <ab>More to the point would not be pertinent here. It was, however, the subject of an ample exposition by Mr. Attorney General Cushing, 25 May, 1855. (7 Opinions Attorney's General, 186, et seq.)</ab>
            <ab>In submitting the accompanying lists, it is proper to say that no diligence of our limited official force could insure perfect accuracy, or complete <choice><sic>fulness</sic><corr>fullness</corr></choice>, in an abstract from the fourteen volumes of public statutes, of all the statutory provisions, both operative and obsolete, which designate offices and prescribe their tenures. Especially is it probable that the attempt to include transient offices for special purposes has but imperfectly succeeded in the brief time which could be allowed to this work.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>O. H. Browning,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General, <hi rend="underline">ad</hi> <hi rend="underline">interim</hi>.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
