<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.03060">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Columbus Delano, 9 May 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.03060</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to Columbus Delano, 9 May 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-05-09" xml:id="dat1">May 9, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">92-93</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Delano, Columbus">Columbus Delano</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-01-25" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-01-12" who="#ad">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-02" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.03060.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>May 9, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Columbus Delano,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Interior.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>In answer to your letter of the 8th instant, I have the honor to state that my recollection of what passed at the informal conference between us, in regard to the case of the Oregon and California Railroad, entirely agrees with your own. I did not, it is true, examine the case with the care and deliberation which I should have exercised if an opinion had been formally called for. But my impressions were, and still are, (subject, of course, to be reversed, if they appear incorrect, after deliberate consideration,) that the case of the Oregon and California Railroad had been properly adjudicated by Mr. Cox, your predecessor, and that a reversal of his decision by you should not be made, unless you should be most clearly satisfied that he was in error&#8212;inasmuch as the embarrassments growing out of contrary decisions, under such circumstances, would be most serious.</ab>
            <ab>The opinion of Mr. Smith, Assistant Attorney General, appears to me, from cursory examination, to be in correct exposition of the law of the case.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">case of Oregon &amp; California Railroad</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">Interior Dept.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.03060.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <ab>My opinion against the validity of the transfer of the rights of the Oregon Center Railroad Company, to the Willamette Valley Company, dated February 20, 1871, had relation exclusively to a case where the Act of Congress signified no intention of dealing with any company but the one named in the Act as grantee.</ab>
            <ab>The letter of the counsel for certain parties in interest, Mr. Chandler, to the President, complaining of your refusal to require the opinion of the Attorney General in the case of the Oregon and California Railroad, seems to me to have been written under an erroneous conception of the relation between the Attorney General and the Heads of other Departments. I think that the Attorney General should be called on for an opinion only when the Head of the Department in which the question arises, sees a good reason for the call, and not whenever a litigant before a Department desires the opinion.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">See 13 up 352/I</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
