<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00587">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to John McAllister Schofield, 2 July 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00587</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

       
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to John McAllister Schofield, 2 July 1868</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1868-07-02" xml:id="dat1">July 2, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">196-197</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Schofield, John McAllister ">John McAllister Schofield</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-28" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-22" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-07" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00587.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>July 2, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. J. M. Schofield,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I had the honor to receive your letter of the 29th ultimo, covering a copy of a communication addressed to you under date of the 24th ultimo, by Simon Stevens, relating to a suit now on appeal in the Supreme Court from the Court of Claims.</ab>
            <ab>It seems that this suit was decided in favor of the plaintiff, Stevens, and that an appeal was taken to the Supreme Court, solely at the instance of the former Secretary of War, Mr. Stanton. It was arranged that the case should be submitted at the last term, by stipulation of counsel, but circumstances which are mentioned by Mr. Stevens interfered with that purpose. Mr. Stevens now submits to the Secretary of War "that the matter be referred to Mr. Solicitor Norton, and to Mr. Trumbull, special counsel, to consider, under the circumstances, whether or not, in justice to the appellee, the appeal should not be withdrawn without delay."</ab>
            <ab>You therefore say to one:</ab>
            <ab>"I have the honor to request that you take the subject into consideration, and after conferring with Mr. Norton and Judge Trumbull, that you advise me whether, upon the whole case, the appeal taken by the government is well founded and can be prosecuted with any reasonable prospect of success."</ab>
            <ab>In reply, I have the honor to state
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00587.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                that under an Act of Congress which took effect yesterday, the Solicitors who have heretofore conducted the litigation of the government in the Court of Claims are disabled for official duty by the express abolition of their offices. I am unable, therefore, to make myself officially acquainted with this case except through a personal labor which more pressing duties pre&#246;ccupy. Provision having been made by the law for some assistance, however, in the business of the Court of Claims, it is deemed expedient to suspend action upon this case until there shall have been time enough to appoint indispensable public officers.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully, your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab><choice><sic>OH Browning</sic><corr>O. H. Browning</corr></choice></ab>
            <ab>Attorney General <hi rend="underline">ad</hi> <hi rend="underline">interim</hi></ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
