<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02542">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Benjamin Helm Bristow to Edwards Pierrepont, 27 October 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Benjamin Helm Bristow</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02542</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Benjamin Helm Bristow</author>
          <title>Benjamin Helm Bristow to Edwards Pierrepont, 27 October 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-10-27" xml:id="dat1">October 27, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">107-108</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Bristow, Benjamin Helm ">Benjamin Helm Bristow</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Pierrepont, Edwards">Edwards Pierrepont</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2011-01-28" who="#mk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-11-09" who="#ad">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-28" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02542.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <ab>Oct. 27, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Edwards Pierrepont,</ab>
            <ab>New York City.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have your letter of the 24th instant, relative to the criminal proceedings against Mr. Jackson, of the firm of Polhaimus &amp; Jackson, and requesting me to make personal examination of the accounts and correspondence between the firm and Hodge, or cause the investigation to be made by Judge Davis or some other "fair man," before proceeding to lay the case before the Grand Jury, to the end that Mr. Jackson may be saved the disgrace of an indictment.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Polhaimus &amp; Jackson</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">New York</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02542.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>In reply, I have to say that while strongly impressed with the belief that the facts and circumstances of which the Government is in possession absolutely demand that the case shall be laid before a Grand Jury, my conviction is not such as that I am unwilling to hear what may be said on behalf of Mr. Jackson. It is impossible, however, that I should give personal attention to this matter, and I have therefore forwarded a copy of your letter to District Attorney Davis, with request that he will carefully examine such papers as you may choose to submit for his inspection, as well as all other evidence within his reach, before submitting the case to the Grand Jury. I do not doubt that Judge Davis will act in the matter with the perfect fairness, and under the influence of a sense of official duty.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>B. H. Bristow, Solicitor Gen'l,</ab>
            <ab>&amp; Acting Attorney Gen'l.</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
