<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00434">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Edwin M. Stanton, 10 February 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00434</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Edwin M. Stanton, 10 February 1868</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1868-02-10" xml:id="dat1">February 10, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">81-82</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Stanton, Edwin M. ">Edwin M. Stanton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-29" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-17" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-28" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

       
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00434.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>February 10, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>To the Honorable,</ab>
            <ab>the Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The Attorney General has received your letter of this date, requesting that the United States Attorney for the District of New Mexico be instructed to defend General Getty and Surgeon McKee, of the Army, in a Chancery suit described in a letter which you enclose, dated 13 January, from Messrs. Ashurst and Elkins, solicitors for the complainants, addressed to the Surgeon General.</ab>
            <ab>It is the practice of this office to express the consent of the Attorney General, by way of instruction to a District Attorney, in any case in which his services, as special counsel, have been requested by the Head of a Department, as in the
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00434.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            present instance. It happens in this case, however, that the United States District Attorney (S. B. Elkins,) has been already retained on the other side,&#8212; a fact, which, perhaps, escaped your observation.</ab>
            <ab>Under these circumstances, the Attorney General anticipates your probable preference for other counsel.</ab>
            <ab>A copy of this letter, however, will be sent to District Attorney Elkins, and he will be instructed that if the United States is a party, or has an interest in the suit, it would not, after his discovery of that fact, be regular for him to engage in the case, unless upon the side of the defendants. A copy of our instructions is herewith.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Attorney General.</ab>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">see Ins. Book pp 20-28</note>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
