<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00653">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">J. Hubley Ashton to John McAllister Schofield, 3 September 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00653</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
          <title>J. Hubley Ashton to John McAllister Schofield, 3 September 1868</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1868-09-03" xml:id="dat1">September 3, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">241-242</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ashton, J. Hubley">J. Hubley Ashton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Schofield, John McAllister ">John McAllister Schofield</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-03" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-22" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-07" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00653.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>September 3, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. J. M. Schofield,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to enclose a copy of a telegram which was received at this office last evening, from the U. S. Marshal for the District of Kentucky, stating, as you will perceive, that, in the execution of civil process in revenue cases, in Larue, Nelson, and Marion counties, Kentucky, deputies of the Marshal were set upon and captured by armed men, and stating that Maj-Gen. Thomas is willing to give such assistance to the Marshal, in the execution of his process, as he can, with infantry, but that he has no mounted troops, necessary for the purpose desired.</ab>
            <ab>You have been advised by the Attorney General of his opinion that the law gives the Marshal power to command all necessary assistance in the execution of process within his District,&#8212; and that the military are not exempt from obligation to obey, in common with all, his summons, in case of necessity. This opinion was communicated to the United States Marshal for the Northern District of Florida, on the 20th ultimo, by the Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>The Marshal for Kentucky does not present any question as to his authority to use the military as a <hi rend="underline">posse</hi> nor does there seem to be any indisposition on the part of the commander of the military force in his district to allow the infantry troops to act
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00653.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
                as a <hi rend="underline">posse</hi> for the Marshall in the service of process; but the difficulty seems to be that the kind of troops that are wanted for service are not under the control of Maj-Gen. Thomas.</ab>
                <ab>You may, perhaps, under these circumstances, deem it right to give some orders to Maj-Gen. Thomas which will insure that proper sort of troops are within call of the Marshal, when he finds it necessary to use a military <hi rend="underline">posse</hi> in the execution of process.</ab>
            <ab>I should suppose that mounted infantry would be as serviceable as cavalry, in the cases stated by the Marshal; but the question is entirely one for you, whether you deem it proper to make any change in the character and disposition of the troops in the locality mentioned.</ab>
            <ab>I have advised the Marshal that the matter he presents is one of military cognizance, and that his communication has been referred to you for your consideration.</ab>
            <ab>I am, sir, very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab>J. Hubley Ashton,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Attorney General</ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
