<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.03469">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Columbus Delano, 13 November 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.03469</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to Columbus Delano, 13 November 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-11-13" xml:id="dat1">November 13, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">325-327</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Delano, Columbus">Columbus Delano</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-03-21" who="#mk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-01-31" who="#ad">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-16" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.03469.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Nov. 13, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. C. Delano,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Interior.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I enclose the account of Standish and Ballard, (Standish being Dist. Attorney for the Western Dist. of Michigan,) for professional services and expenses in representing the Government in certain cases in the State Court of Michigan, against James H. Kidd, and Osmond S. Tower, Registrar and Receiver at the Land Office at Ionia, Michigan, amounting to Two thousand four hundred and fifty three 39/100 dollars. The account seems to be made out against the Department of the Interior.</ab>
            <ab>The suits were first brought to my notice
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">Standish &amp; Ballard's bill, Mich.</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">see p. 288 ante</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">479</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.03469.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
            by a letter in January last from the District Attorney; requesting instructions as to whether or not he should appeal from an adverse decision in the lower court to the highest court.&#8212;He was instructed to take the appeal. I was not aware that his appearance in the case had been previously directed by any other Department; but it appears from his account that he was originally retained by the Land officers, and that on the 30th day of December, 1869, they, (Messrs. Standish and Ballard,) were directed by Mr. Cox, Secretary of the Interior, to proceed with the defence. Thus it appears that they have been employed by two Departments, to wit, that of the Interior, up to the time of the appeal, and since then by the Department of Justice.</ab>
            <ab>It seems to me just, therefore, that the expenses of the service should be borne by the two Departments according to the proportions of service rendered while the matter was under the direction of the one or the other. The bill rendered divides the fees in the matter of time about in the proportions of two parts prior to the appeal, and one part since the appeal. I therefore suggest that two thirds of the bill be paid by the Department of the Interior, and one-third by this Department. I am confirmed by your letter of the 9th inst. in the opinion that the bill rendered
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.03469.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            is extravagant, and am disposed to think Twelve hundred ($1200) dollars will suffice&#8212;of which Eight hundred, ($800,) dollars might properly be paid by the Interior Department, and Four hundred (400) dollars by the Department of Justice. In this case, of course, different sets of vouchers would be required.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
