<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02987">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to L. P. Poland, 29 March 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.02987</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to L. P. Poland, 29 March 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-03-29" xml:id="dat1">March 29, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">50-52</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Poland, L. P.">L. P. Poland</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-01-19" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-01-13" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-06" who="#jw">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v1" facs="nar.02987.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>March 29, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. L. P. Poland,</ab>
            <ab>House of Representatives.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have considered the application of George Howe, Esq. Solicitor for John Grant, who desires leave to institute proceedings in the name of the United States, at the relation of his client, John Grant, to annul sundry patents for land issues by the United States, on the ground that the patents were wrongfully obtained. His client is alleged to be the heir of John Tench, who was the assignee and owner of a Virginia military land warrant for six thousand acres. It is further alleged that about the year 1794, Tench delivered this warrant to R. L. Anderson, the principal surveyor in the District of Ohio, between the Little Miami and Scioto rivers, who
            
             <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">land patent case of John Grant, Ohio.</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">official participation declined.</note>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02987.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
            located it upon lands in that District and surveys were made in the name of Tench&#8212;and after this location and survey Tench disappeared, and is supposed to have died; that in the year 1823, a patent was issued for a portion of this land to one T. J. McArthur, a Deputy Surveyor under the United States; that between the years 1823 and 1847, patents for the whole Six thousand acres were issued to McArthur, Wallace, and Anderson, all principal or Deputy Surveyors of the United States; and that at that time persons employed in the Land office were prohibited from purchasing lands.</ab>
            <ab>The principal objection according to Mr. Howe the desired permission is impropriety of the Government appearing as a party in suits between private individuals where no Governmental interest is involved. Why should the Government appear as a party, either actual or nominal, in a law suit between Mr. Grant and Messrs. Anderson and others? If the Government, by its supposed exemption from the operation of the statute of limitations, could litigate with Messrs. Anderson and others more advantageously than Mr. Grant, no consideration occurs to me to justify the transfer of its immunity to Mr. Grant, for his benefit.</ab>
            <ab>Under the opinion of Mr. Legar&#233;
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v2" facs="nar.02987.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                (4 Opinions of Attorney General,) the pre&#235;mptioner can sue in his own name&#8212;and I recommend that course to Mr. Grant. The authorities cited in your ample brief go rather to establish the legality of Mr. Grant's claim than the propriety of an assertion of it through the name of the United States.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>              
                
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>