<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00592">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to Edward Jordan, 6 July 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00592</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

       
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to Edward Jordan, 6 July 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-07-06" xml:id="dat1">July 6, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">200-201</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Jordan, Edward">Edward Jordan</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-28" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-22" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-07" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00592.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>July 6, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Edward Jordan, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Solicitor of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>In your letter of the 12th ultimo, a case, arising our of the impressment by officers of the Government of the steamer B. M. Runyan, belonging to the Alton and St. Louis Packet Company, is submitted to me for my opinion on the questions of law arising in the premises.</ab>
            <ab>I would cheerfully respond to your request if I thought I could do so with entire propriety. But the advisory function of the Attorney General upon questions of law seems to me to be restricted in the Act creating this office, (1 Stat. 93,) to requisitions of the President, and requests of the Heads of Departments, touching matters that may concern their Departments. And though he has since been charged with the supervision of other officers, and required, (1 Brightly, 884,) "at the request of the Solicitor to advise with and direct" him,&#8212; yet, as in the case of District Attorneys and others, it is only "as to the manner of conducting the suits, proceedings, and prosecutions," referred to in the Statute.</ab>
            <ab>With these views, I have thought
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00592.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            fit to inform the Head of the Treasury Department of them, and that I would with pleasure consider the questions of law in the case, should he desire my opinion; and herewith return the papers with your letter for your convenience, should you desire to reach this office in the manner suggested.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully, your obedient servant</ab>
            <ab><choice><sic>OH Browning,</sic><corr>O. H. Browning</corr></choice></ab>
            <ab>Attorney General <hi rend="underline">ad</hi> <hi rend="underline">interim</hi>.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
