<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00399">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Henry Stanbery to William H. Seward, 13 January 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00399</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
          <title>Henry Stanbery to William H. Seward, 13 January 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-01-13" xml:id="dat1">January 13, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">45-46</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Stanbery, Henry">Henry Stanbery</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Seward, William H.">William H. Seward</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-29" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-24" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-23" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00399.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>January 13, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. William H. Seward,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of State.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Under date of the 29th November last, I expressed the opinion that the case of Gilson, the subject of your communication of the 21st September last, is within the provisions of the extradition Treaty with France, and stated that upon receiving a Report from the District Attorney of this District, further action would be had.</ab>
            <ab>I herewith enclose:</ab>
            <ab>1. Certified copies of the official bond of said Gilson, and of his requisition on the  Treasurer of the United States.</ab>
            <ab>2. Certified transcript of his account with the United States from the records of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>3. Copy of a letter from E. C. Carrington, Esq. United States Attorney for the District of Columbia, enclosing a certified copy of the information and warrant
                <note type="authorial" place="left">see Let. Book F p. 580</note> 
           <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00399.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
           for the arrest of said Gilson.</ab>
            <ab>4. Copy of a letter from R. W. Taylor, 1st Comptroller, to the Assistant Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>5. Letter from Morris B. Baer, one of Gilson's sureties.</ab>
            <ab>6. Printed copies of treaties between United States and France.</ab>
            <ab>I have already transmitted to you, with my communication of the 29th November, referred to above, a copy of my letter of instruction to the District Attorney of this District, which, with the other papers named, will furnish all the information in the possession of this office, relative to the above matter.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be,</ab>
            <ab>yours with respect, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>Henry Stanbery,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>[papers enc.]</ab>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
