<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02600">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Edwards Pierrepont, 17 November 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02600</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Edwards Pierrepont, 17 November 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-11-17" xml:id="dat1">November 17, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">142-144</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Pierrepont, Edwards">Edwards Pierrepont</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-12-05" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-26" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-28" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02600.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>Nov. 17, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Edwards Pierrepont,</ab>
            <ab>New York.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The Solicitor General, to whom your letter of the 11th instant, marked "personal and confidential" was addressed, not feeling at liberty to have any confidences withheld from the head of the Department to which he belongs, in     
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02600.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            relation to the official business of that Department, has handed the letter to me.</ab>
            <ab>You seem to suggest a possible implication of persons standing high in the community, in the frauds of Hodge. This furnishes an urgent reason for pressing the matter through a legal investigation. If such persons have been concerned in robbing the Government, either directly, or as aiders and abetters of another criminal, it is due to the public that there should be a disclosure, and that every form of redress known to the law civil or criminal, should be resorted to by the Government.</ab>
            <ab>Personally, I should be grievously shocked and mortified to learn that your suggestion is well founded. All the presumptions from a high character for integrity and for financial honor, are against the slightest suspicion of such guilt, in such parties. But all these presumptions must yield to proof; and proof in such cases must not be suppressed out of tenderness to those who may be affected by it.</ab>
            <ab>If there is a probable case against Polhaimus and Jackson, the District Attorney must carry the matter into court, and prosecute it there. Such an investigation will not hurt them unless they have so conducted themselves that they ought to be hurt. And if the investigation should implicate any other person, that person must be proceeded against in the same way. Unless this is done, the law
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Hodge's fraud (persons implicated)</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.02600.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            department of the Government will be faithless to the country.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
