<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01146">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to John H. Howe, 6 January 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01146</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to John H. Howe, 6 January 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-01-06" xml:id="dat1">January 6, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">164-165</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
     
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Howe, John H. ">John H. Howe</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-06" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-11" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-16" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01146.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>January 6, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. J. H. Howe,</ab>
            <ab>Chief Justice of Wyoming Territory</ab>
            <ab>Kewanee, Ill.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letter of Dec. 29, 1869, is received.</ab>
            <ab>It is impossible for me to determine whether the nature of the business for which you propose to visit Washington is so far important to the people of Wyoming Territory, and so peculiarly requiring your attention as to make it proper that you should receive leave of absence for the purpose of attending to it. The people of each Territory are represented at Washington by a Delegate chosen by them for that purpose, and it has not seemed to me as a general rule, that it is desirable that the Judicial officers of the Territories should come to Washington for the purpose of attending to business before Congress, or the Executive Departments. Instances of the kind heretofore occurring have sometimes led to unfavorable comments, and I am reluctant to give any official countenance to the practice. At the same time I can imagine a case in which it might be important for a Judge to communicate personally to a Committee of Congress, or to the Executive, the results of his experience in relation to matters within the range of his official duties; and with the suggestion
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Conditional Leave of absence.</note> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01146.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            I have made in the case of a gentleman of whose character I have received so favorable an impression, I am disposed to leave the matter to your own discretion. If there are matters of public interest, legal and not political in their nature, which you think so important as to require the Chief Justice of a Territory to leave his official post of duty to attend to them at Washington, I shall give my consent to your absence.</ab>
            <ab>I beg you to be assured that, in what I have expressed, there is nothing inconsistent with the highest respect for yourself personally and officially. But similar applications are made by other judges, and I only desire to state the general principles which, as it seems to me, should govern them.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
