<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02346">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Ulysses S. Grant, 15 August 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02346</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Ulysses S. Grant, 15 August 1867</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1867-08-15" xml:id="dat1">August 15, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno"></idno>
          <biblScope type="page">441-443</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S.">Ulysses S. Grant</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-12-06" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-28" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-16" who="#mk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02346.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>August 15, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>General U. S. Grant,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>General:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to return herewith
            all the papers relating to certain parcels
            of land, adjoining the grounds of Watervliet
            Arsenal, State of New York, sought to be acquired
            for the United States under the authority
            of a recent Statute&#8212;which papers were transmitted
            here by the Secretary of War on the 3d
            inst. for the purpose of aiding the Attorney General
            in the investigation of the Titles held by
            the proposed grantors of the premises, with a
            view to his passing upon their validity.</ab>
            <ab>The property referred to is more
            particularly described as Lots 63, 64, 65, 66, and
            south half of Lot 67, situated in the Village of 
            West Troy, formerly called Gibbonsville, in Albany
            County, New York, each of which Lots appears
            to be held by its present owner under a <hi rend="underline">lease</hi>
           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02346.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <hi rend="underline">in</hi> <hi rend="underline">fee</hi>, subject to a rent-charge vested in a
            different proprietor. From the abstracts and
            papers submitted, I arrive at the following
            Opinion:</ab>
            <ab>1; That the proposed conveyance of
            Lot 63 from W. J. Snyder and wife, together with
            a conveyance of the rent-charge thereon, from
            Alex. McAllister and wife, will vest in the United
            States a good and valid Title in fee to said
            Lot.</ab>
            <ab>2; That the proposed conveyance of
            Lot 64, from Peter Thalimer and wife, together
            with a conveyance of the rent-charge thereon,
            from the Trustees of Union College, will vest in
            the United States a good and valid Title in fee
            to said Lot, subject to the following apparent
            incumbrance, viz: a mortgage in favor of Jonathan
            C. Wright, to which reference is made in
            a Deed of said Lot from Henry Thalimer to
            the said Peter, dated March 1, 1851. This
            mortgage is not mentioned in the search
            certified<space dim="horizontal" extent="4 letters"/>by the County Clerk, which accompanies
            the papers.</ab>
            <ab>3; That the proposed conveyance of
            Lot 65 from Jane Hunter, Delia McKean, Elizabeth
            Austin, and others, together with a conveyance of
            the rent-charge thereon from Alex. McAllister
            and wife, will vest in the United States a good
            and valid Title in fee to said Lot, subject to the
            following incumbrances, viz:  an unsatisfied
            Judgment in favor of Wm. M. Bender against
            Geo. Hunter, dated July 27, 1857; and also a
            dower-estate in the rent-charge in favor of
            the wife of James Kidd, if living. The title to
            this rent is derived mediately from the said Kidd
            who, on the 1st of May, 1855, conveyed to John D.
            Livingston, by a Deed to which his wife was
            not a party; and the rent being an incorporeal
            hereditament, to which dower attaches, it accordingly
            passed to the present holder, subject to that
            incumbrance, to remove which a release from
            Kidd's wife, if living, is now required&#8212;or, if she
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02346.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            is dead, sworn evidence of the fact. These remarks
            will suggest the necessity of having the
            wives of Mr. McAllister and Mr. Dunlop unite with
            them in their conveyances to the Government, of the
            rents charged on Lots 63, 65, and 67.</ab>
            <ab>4; That the proposed conveyance of
            40 feet off the south side of Lot 66, from Laura
            O. Deming, and husband, together with a conveyance
            of the rent charge thereon from the Trustees of
            Union College, will vest in the United States a
            good and valid Title in fee to the premises, subject
            to the following incumbrances, viz:  A mortgage
            from the said Laura O., and husband,
            to Andrew Alexander, dated January 7, 1861,&#8212;and
            also one from same to same, dated December 30, 1863.</ab>
            <ab>5; That the proposed conveyance of
            10 feet off the north side of Lot 66, and the south
            half of Lot 67, from Martha Davis, together with
            a conveyance of the rent-charge thereon, from
            Archibald A. Dunlop and wife, will vest in the
            United States a good and valid Title in fee to the
            premises, subject to the following incumbrance, viz:
            a mortgage from the said Martha and husband
            to David Buel and others, dated March 11, 1851.</ab>
            <ab>No Tax-Search having been furnished
            respecting either of these Lots, the foregoing Opinion
            is to be taken subject to any Liens affecting the
            same, for unpaid Taxes, that may be discovered
            on a future examination, which should be
            made before completing the purchase.</ab>
            <ab>The incumbrances above pointed out
            should be satisfactorily removed and discharged
            by the proposed grantors, as also any
            Tax-Liens which may be found, before payment
            of the purchase-money for the property.</ab>
            <ab>I am, General,</ab>
            <ab>Very Respectfully, Yours, &#38;c.</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
