<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00929">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to A. E. Borie, 14 May 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00929</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to A. E. Borie, 14 May 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-05-14" xml:id="dat1">May 14, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">483-485</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Borie, A. E. ">A. E. Borie</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-06" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-03-15" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-25" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00929.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>May 14, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. A. E. Borie,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Navy.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of to-day, with enclosures, submitting certain papers in the case of Stover and Cheever, ag't the United States, and requesting me to furnish the Navy Department with an opinion whether or not that Department should pay the moneys due on account of the Fullahoma and Maumee into the hands of the receiver appointed by the Supreme Court of the State of New York.</ab>
            <ab>I have examined the papers enclosed with your letter, and find a copy of an order granted by Hon. Dan'l. P. Ingraham, Justice at a special term of the Sup. Court of the State of New York, held on the 26th day of June, in the year of our Lord 1868, in a case entitled "The New York Engine Works, <hi rend="underline">vs.</hi> Henry D. Stover." There are also what purport to be a copy of a Bill in Equity dated December 12, 1865, addressed to the Supreme Court of the State of New York, in a case entitled "The New York Steam Engine Works, <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>. The Stover Machine Company, Henry D. Stover, &amp; Ainsworth Brown," not certified to be a true copy, and with no
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of Claim of Stover &amp; Cheever, ag't U. S.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00929.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            certificate attached that the same has been filed in Court&#8212;and a copy, properly certified, of an order by the Court, in the last-named case, that it be discontinued. It seems therefore, that the order of Mr. Justice Ingraham was granted in another suit than that commenced by the Bill, of which you enclose an uncertified copy.</ab>
            <ab>I have read the opinion of Mr. Stanbery, late Attorney Gen'l. in this case, dated Feb. 19, 1868, and have examined what purports to be a copy of a contract for the construction of the Fullahoma. I find in the enclosure of your letter to-day no copy of the contract for the construction of the Maumee.</ab>
            <ab>Before determining the right of the receiver appointed by the Court to receive from the Dep't. of the Navy, the moneys due under these contracts, it is necessary that I have certified copies of all papers and proceedings in Court, in the cause in which the receiver has been appointed. If, on obtaining such certified copies, it appears that the Stover Machine works, and Mr. Stover and Mr. Cheever are parties to the suit, that the Court has jurisdiction over the subject&#8209;matter and the parties, and that the bill states a proper case for determining
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00929.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            the question of the rights of either of these persons, or of the corporation, to the moneys due from the Navy Department, then it would seem that the order of Mr. Justice Ingraham, hereinbefore mentioned, is a sufficient authority to authorize the Navy Department to pay said moneys to the receiver named in the order.</ab>
            <ab>It occurs to me that perhaps the above expression of opinion may be all that you desire&#8212;&amp; the papers enclosed with your letter are accordingly returned herewith.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, &amp;c. &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney Gen'l.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
