<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00546">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Hugh McCulloch, 26 May 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00546</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Hugh McCulloch, 26 May 1868</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1868-05-26" xml:id="dat1">May 26, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">163-165</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="McCulloch, Hugh">Hugh McCulloch</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-28" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-02" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-07" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00546.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>May 26, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Hugh McCulloch,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letter of the 25th instant, is just received, requesting me to inform you as to the precise grounds upon which the appeal in the case of The United States against Brulatour and others, from the United States Circuit Court of the Eastern District of Louisiana, was dismissed by the Supreme Court at the last term,&#8212;and whether such dismissal is, in effect, final or otherwise,&#8212;and if otherwise, what steps must be taken for the purpose of reviewing the appeal, in case your Department shall deem it expedient to take that course.</ab>
            <ab>1. I have the honor to inform you that the appeal, in that case, was dismissed on the motion of the appellees, upon one ground, to writ, that the case was one of law, and that the judgment, accordingly, could only be reviewed by writ of error.</ab>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00546.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>2. The dismissal of the erroneous appeal does not preclude a reviewal of the judgment of the Circuit Court upon a writ of error, if the record of the cause should present the question of law which arose, and was decided below in proper form for the decision of the Supreme Court. On looking into the record of the case, as brought up by the late appeal, I am inclined to think that the Supreme Court would say that there is no sufficient statement or finding of the facts by the Court below, such as is required when a case is tried, as this was, by the Court, without the intervention of a jury, to warrant an examination of the judgment of the Circuit Court. This question, however, I will not determine. The decisions of the Supreme Court as to the sufficiency of Records from Louisiana in cases tried by the Court without juries, are very numerous, and not harmonious; and the Court might conclude that the evidence spread upon this record, shows, with sufficient clearness, what the question of law decided by the Court below, really was. But, at all events, if a writ of error should be issued, the District Attorney should be instructed to take steps to obtain, if possible, by consent of parties, or otherwise, such a statement of the facts found by the Court as will present the legal questions for review clearly and distinctly&#8212;and to make such statement a part of the new record to be brought up by the writ of error.</ab>
            <ab>3. In reply to the third branch of your question, I would state that
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00546.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            the proper course to pursue in case your Department desire a review of this judgment, is, to direct the District Attorney to issue a writ of error, with proper citation, to the adverse parties.</ab>
            <ab>I would say, in conclusion, that the question of the propriety of bringing this case up again, by writ of error, is one which, we think, properly belongs to your Department. The substantial qusetion is one arising under the Revenue laws of the United States&#8212;and it may, or may not, be a question on which you desire the judgment of the Supreme Court.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully, Your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
