<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01213">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to William W. Belknap, 17 February 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01213</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to William W. Belknap, 17 February 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-02-17" xml:id="dat1">February 17, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">207-208</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Belknap, William W. ">William W. Belknap</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-29" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-08" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01213.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>February 17, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. W. W. Belknap,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully referring to a letter from the Secretary of War to the Attorney General, of October 4th last, I have to say that I requested the U. S. Attorney for Georgia to take charge of the defence of a suit named in that letter; and I suggested that the case should be removed from the State Court to a U. S. Court.</ab>
            <ab>I have received a letter from Andrew Sloan for A. T. Ackerman, Esq. the present U. S. Attorney for Georgia, dated the 10th inst.
                
            <note type="authorial" place="left">War Dept. case in Georgia.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01213.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            with a copy of a letter  of the Clerk of the State Court to him, and of a bill of costs in said suit enclosed therewith, which papers I enclose herewith.</ab>
            <ab>It appears that the clerk of the State Court, on receiving his costs, amounting to $49:<hi rend="underline">50</hi>, will transmit to the U. S. Attorney the papers in the case, that they may be entered in the U. S. Court; and the U. S. Attorney asks to be instructed in regard to the matter. I suppose he wishes to have the costs paid.</ab>
            <ab>As this suit is defended at the request of the Department of War, I send these papers to you that you may cause the bill of costs to be paid, and instruct the U. S. Attorney, if you see fit, to complete the removal of the suit from the State Court to the U. S. Court.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>(enc.)</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
