<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02629">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Roger M. Sherman, 28 November 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02629</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Roger M. Sherman, 28 November 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-11-28" xml:id="dat1">November 28, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">161-162</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Sherman, Roger M. ">Roger M. Sherman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-12-05" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-26" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-05" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02629.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Nov. 28, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Roger M. Sherman, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Care of E. C. Camp, Esq. U.S. Attorney</ab>
            <ab>Knoxville, Tenn.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>In answer to your letter of the 20th instant, I have to say that when you were sent forth there was no expectation of such an expense as you seem to think necessary in the prosecution of your Commission. It is a matter of propriety, on general accounts, and of necessity, in view of the limited funds at the command of this Department, that the strictest economy should be observed. This, I have no doubt, you are disposed to do.</ab>
            <ab>As at present advised, I do not
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Stokes &amp; Beatty fraud.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02629.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            feel authorized to direct the payment of Lieut. Clapp's expenses. There are some questions, both of law and Departmental propriety, growing out of his relations to the War Department, to be considered before that can be done. Yet I think that the suggestions which you have made on that subject are entirely reasonable, and if it shall be in my power to carry them out, I will ultimately do so.</ab>
            <ab>In regard to other frauds, in addition to those specially indicated when you left, you will of course gather all the information you conveniently can, while engaged in prosecuting the work on which you were sent.</ab>
            <ab>You will receive with this a check for $250, which, in addition to the amount you received at starting, I trust, will cover all the expenses of your trip.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
