<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00492">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to Andrew Johnson, 28 March 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00492</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to Andrew Johnson, 28 March 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-03-28" xml:id="dat1">March 28, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">121-122</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Johnson, Andrew">Andrew Johnson</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-29" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-03-03" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-28" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00492.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>March 28, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>The President.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Among the applications for pardon, which, in the usage of business have been referred by you, for examination in this office, is one in which the importance of the questions involved makes it proper to embody my views upon it in a formal Report.</ab>
            <ab>It appears that at the recent February term of the Circuit of the United States for the District of Kentucky, William Bell, a minor, was convicted of murder in the killing of Tony Cundiff, in Daviess County, Kentucky, on the 13th October, 1866. It also appears that a motion for a new trial is pending, and that the 14th of April, proximo, is set for the hearing, there being, as yet, no judgment entered, and no sentence passed.</ab>
            <ab>The prisoner is a white person and the deceased was a negro. It is shown by a certified abstract of the record that the prisoner demurred to the jurisdiction of the Court. The grounds of the demurrer are not given. But the court sustained the jurisdiction, as it otherwise appears, under provisions of the Civil Rights Act, of 6 April 1866. In this Act, no express provision is made for punishing the crime of murder, or any other felony&#8212;and it is therefore probable that the proviso therein for jurisdiction of the United States Courts, "of all causes civil and criminal" affecting persons who are denied, or cannot enforce in the State Courts, the rights secured by the Act, has been construed in favor of
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00492.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            jurisdiction in this case, with power to inflict the death penalty, for a homicide committed against the laws of Kentucky.</ab>
            <ab>It is evident that a novel and important juridicial doubt exists in the case, such as must have been contemplated by the Civil Rights Act itself, viz:</ab>
            <ab>"Section 10: And be it, Etc. That upon all questions of law arising in any cause under the provisions of this Act, a final appeal may be taken to the Supreme Court of the United States." (14 Stat. 29.)</ab>
            <ab>I would therefore recommend that no further action be had at present, and that as soon as you may be advised that a sentence of death, or other punishment, has passed upon the defendant, and that the proper steps are to be taken to procure a review of the matter in the Supreme Court of the United States, in conformity to the provisions of the Civil Rights Act, it would be expedient, and in my opinion just, that a respite should be granted to suspend execution until after a final decision by the Supreme National Court.</ab>
            <ab>With these views, I return the papers herewith.</ab>
            <ab>Very Respectfully</ab>
            <ab>OH Browning,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General ad interim</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
