<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00435">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Henry Stanbery to Ulysses S. Grant, 12 February 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00435</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
          <title>Henry Stanbery to Ulysses S. Grant, 12 February 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-02-12" xml:id="dat1">February 12, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">82-84</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Stanbery, Henry">Henry Stanbery</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S. ">Ulysses S. Grant</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-29" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-17" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-28" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00435.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>February 12, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>General U. S. Grant,</ab>
            <ab>U. S.A.</ab>
            <ab>General:</ab>
            <ab>A motion has been made, in the Supreme Court, by Mr. Black, to file an original Bill in that Court in favor of the State of Georgia, against yourself, General Meade, General Ruger, and Captain Rockwell. It charges all of you with unauthorized violations of the rights of the State of Georgia, in taking possession of certain real estate, railroad conveyances and moneys, belonging to the State, and seeks to enjoin you from further
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00435.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                interference with the State authorities, and to compel you to surrender the property so taken.</ab>
            <ab>The motion for leave to file this Bill will be made on Friday next, and should be resisted. The rules of Court require that you should receive notice of this application, which, I presume, has been given you, and been sent to the other defendants by the counsel for the State of Georgia.</ab>
            <ab>As the Bill is apparently brought against you and the other defendants in your individual capacity, I feel somewhat embarrassed in appearing in opposition to this motion without knowing your wishes on the subject. In the cases at the last term, brought against the Secretary of War and yourself, I was advised by Mr. Stanton that he, as well as yourself, wished me to appear in my official capacity to argue the motions made. Upon the present motion, I feel no sort of embarrassment in resisting it in consequence of my known opinions as to the constitutionality of the Reconstruction acts, as that question is not necessarily involved in this motion. But as, in the further progress of the case, if the Bill should be filed, that question may arise, it is very proper that you should be represented by special counsel of your own selection who may not feel the same embarrassment which I do in reference to it;&#8212; and I beg therefore to suggest to you the propriety of requesting the Secretary of War to retain such counsel.</ab>
            <ab>It may also be proper, especially on behalf of the other defendants, to ask a postponement of the hearing of the motion, to allow them the opportunity of being heard by
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.00435.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                counsel of their own selection. I beg you to advise me in the premises at your earliest convenience, that I may understand what course you wish to be pursued.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be,</ab>
            <ab>Very Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Henry Stanbery,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
