<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01087">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 26 November 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01087</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 26 November 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-11-26" xml:id="dat1">November 26, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">121-122</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-11" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-03-17" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-02" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01087.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>November 26, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I respectfully call your attention to my letter to you of the 6th inst. relating to the suit of Henry G. Hubbard, against Cornelius Brainard. I have been informed by the clerk of the Supreme Court that in all suits in that Court in which the Attorney General appears for either a Collector of Internal Revenue, or a Collector of Customs, no security from the Treasury Department is required, but that in accordance with the practice of that Department, it is understood by the clerk that the appearance of the Attorney General indicates that the Government has assumed charge of the prosecution, or defense, of the suit, and that the Department of the Treasury will be responsible for such fees to the clerk as may be due him from the officer for whom the Attorney General appears. If it is agreeable to you to continue this practice, I only desire to be informed whether you wish me to appear in this case; and I have to suggest whether it would not be agreeable to you for the Attorney General to appear as of course for Collectors either of Customs or Internal Revenue in the Supreme Court, whenever the U. S. Attorney has been directed by the Department of the Treasury to appear for such Collectors in the courts below, unless the Secretary of the Treasury
             <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of H. G. Hubbard ag't C. Brainard</note> 
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Question of U. S. Court clerk's fees.</note>
                    <note type="authorial" place="left">Att. Gen. to appear in certain cases.</note>
                        <note type="authorial" place="left">see p. 113 ante.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01087.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            expressly notifies the Attorney General that he does not desire him to appear in a particular case.</ab>
            <ab>I shall be pleased to receive your request in the case of Hubbard, <hi rend="underline">vs</hi>. Brainard, before the coming in of the Court on the first Monday of December next, if you wish me to appear in it.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient serv't,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
           
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
