<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01363">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to Robert C. Schenck, 9 June 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01363</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to Robert C. Schenck, 9 June 1870</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1870-06-09" xml:id="dat1">June 9, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">340-341</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Schenck, Robert C.">Robert C. Schenck</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-06-23" who="#vs">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-05" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-11-15" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01363.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>June 9, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Robert C. Schenck, M. C.</ab>
            <ab>Washington, D. C.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The District Attorneys make no report to this office of particular prosecutions, and I have therefore no information in relation to Capt. Cullen. I will venture to suggest that your friends can learn what they wish most directly, and avoid circuity and delay, by addressing Mr. Wm. Dorsheimer, the U. S. Attorney at Buffalo, N. Y.; and that if Capt. Cullen is found to be imprisoned for want of bail, they can then furnish him with bail at once. The time that it would take to investigate the merits of the case by correspondence carried on from Washington, makes the other course the most advisable.</ab>
            <ab>The instructions given to the U. S. Attorneys in Vermont and New York were that they should cause the <hi rend="underline">leaders</hi> of the Fenian attack on Canada to be arrested, prosecuted and punished; but to allow the poor dupes whom they had swindled and were leading to destruction, to disperse and escape. If Captain Cullen is a man of such worth and general good repute as seems probable from the telegram. I hope that he would not be found belonging to either class - but if he has been engaged as a leader in such a scheme of murder and robbery against our inoffensive
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01363.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            neighbors over the border, it is not of course, a matter that can be lightly dealt with.</ab>
        <ab>Very respectfully and truly yours,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
