<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.03529">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to William W. Belknap, 13 December 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.03529</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
                <persName xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</persName></note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to William W. Belknap, 13 December 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-12-13" xml:id="dat1">December 13, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">366-368</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Belknap, William W.">William W. Belknap</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change when="2013-06" who="kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-03-26" who="#mk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-07" who="#ad">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-20" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.03529.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>Dec. 13, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Wm. W. Belknap,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Mr. James R. Beckwith, District Attorney for Louisiana, has presented to this Department two certificates of the Circuit Court for Louisiana, (one in the case of E. B. Bishop vs. Garret J. Lydecker and others; the other in the case of Lewis Wolfley, vs. A. A. Humphries and others,) to the effect that $3000 would be a suitable compensation to Mr. Beckwith for his services in each case.</ab>
            <ab>Formal accounts, conforming to these certificates have not been presented
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">certificates of am'ts charged by Mr. Beckwith, N. O.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.03529.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            by Mr. Beckwith, but I suppose it is his intention that the certificates shall be taken here for the accounts. This informality can be readily corrected, but before addressing him on the subject I have thought proper to submit the accounts to you.</ab>
            <ab>In the instructions from this office dated August 3d, 1869, to the District Attorney to appear in the case of Bishop, vs. Lydecker and others, it was stated that the amount of compensation to be paid to counsel in this case is to be determined by the Secretary of War, and to be paid by the War Department.</ab>
            <ab>In the other case, the direction to appear was given in pursuance of the request in your letter of December 1st, 1870, and no reference was made to the Department by which the compensation should be paid.</ab>
            <ab>As the latter direction was after the Act establishing the Department of Justice took effect, I suppose that the compensation should be paid by this Department out of the Judiciary fund. It occurs to me, however, that the obligation which I understand to have been assumed by the War Department in the case of Bishop, vs. Lydecker is still in force, notwithstanding that Act.</ab>
            <ab>If you concur in these views, the compensation in the case of Bishop will be paid by the War Department, and in the case of Wolfley by this Department. But I have no means of judging of the reasonableness of the compensation claimed in the latter case, except
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.03529.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            the certificate of the Court, and will be obliged to you for any information which may be in the possession of the War Department, concerning the amount really involved in the litigation, the seriousness of the plaintiff's case, or any other circumstance proper to be considered in determining the compensation.</ab>
            <ab>Mr. Beckwith in his letter informs me that in each case the defence was successful.</ab>
            <ab>I will thank you to return the enclosures.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
