<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01641">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to George S. Boutwell, 17 January 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01641</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to George S. Boutwell, 17 January 1871</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1871-01-17" xml:id="dat1">January 17, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">577-579</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
       
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-10" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-31" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-10" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

         
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01641.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>January 17, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 13th instant, enclosing a communication to you from the Commissioner of Internal Revenue, urging the employment of special counsel in certain prosecutions in the Eastern District of Texas, ag't Frank W. Glenn and T. E. Tullis.</ab>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01641.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>In view of the manifest intention of Congress, expressed in the Act to establish the Department of Justice, that the regular professional force of the United States should as a general rule conduct the business of the Government in the Federal courts, and of the fact that there are no funds under the control of this Department out of which special counsel can be paid, except the Judiciary fund, which is based upon estimates not including the cost of special retainers, I do not feel at liberty to employ assistant counsel in new cases unless they be of extraordinary emergency. In this instance the only reason suggested by the Commissioner of Internal Revenue for the employment of special counsel is, that the cases are important, and that eminent legal talent has been employed for the defence. These conditions occur so frequently when the Government is party, that the custom of employing special counsel in such cases would impose a heavy expense upon the Government, and reduce the services of District Attorneys to a subordinate part of the representation of the Government in Courts.</ab>
            <ab>I think that the District Attorney ought to be adequate to all the ordinary demands upon them&#8212;and having no reason to suppose that this is not the case in the Eastern District of Texas I do not feel authorized to make the special engagement that is requested.</ab>
            <ab>As a further reason for declining I would suggest that I have no information
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">employing special counsel for The U. S. in Texas cases (employment declined)</note> 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01641.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            that counsel in that District suitable for such an employment, could be readily found, who are able to take the oath required of District Attorneys, and their assistants.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
