<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.03251">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to William W. Belknap, 5 August 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.03251</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to William W. Belknap, 5 August 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-08-05" xml:id="dat1">August 5, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">188-189</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Belknap, William W.">William W. Belknap</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-01-26" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-01-12" who="#ad">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-07" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.03251.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>Aug. 5, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Wm. W. Belknap,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>In answer to your letter of the 4th instant, submitting the correspondence in relation to the compromise of the claim of the United States against the Nashville &amp; Chattanooga RR. Company, I have the honor to say that I advise the compromise the terms of which are set forth in your letter, to wit: payment by the company of One million dollars, five hundred thousand payable in ten years from June 1, 1871, and five hundred thousand in twenty years from the same date, with interest on the whole amount
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">U.S. claim ag't the Nashville &amp; Chattanooga RR. Co.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.03251.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            at the rate of four per cent per annum payable semi-annually on the first days of December and June in each year; payments of principal and interest to be secured by a proper decree of the court in which the suit is pending.</ab>
            <ab>I give this advice because I learn that these terms are satisfactory to you, and to the special counsel who have been retained for the Government in the litigation&#8212;and because I learn that such assurances have been given to the defendant as would expose the Government to a plausible accusation of a breach of faith, if the terms should now be rejected. Not having been made minutely acquainted with the facts in the case, or with the terms of the compromise, until the parties supposed the arrangement to have been effected, I have not undertaken to form a judgment of my own, in the premises&#8212;and give this advice in order to satisfy the literal requirements of the law.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">p.92</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="bottom" rend="none">p 94</note>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
