<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01966">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 7 July 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01966</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 7 July 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-07-07" xml:id="dat1">July 7, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">591-592</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-20" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-01-27" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01966.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>July 7, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 6th inst. relating to the Internal Revenue case of Engelbrecht and Mayrisch Bros., and Ah Suca. It does not appear that any indictments have been found against these persons. It does appear that their stock was seized, January, 1865, and an information of forfeiture filed against it, and that subsequently an assessment of the taxes withheld was made, which, with the 50 per cent penalty added amounted to $7045:88. The stock seized was released upon a stipulation in the sum of $47616 30/100 in currency, or $25000 in gold&#8212;So far as I am able to form any opinion from the papers accompanying your letter, this seems to me a case that should have been vigorously prosecuted, and the persons should have been indicted, convicted and sentenced to imprisonment&#8212;and all this should have been done as soon as possible after it was discovered that they had rendered false and fraudulent returns. It is now more than four years since proceedings in this case were instituted, and the District Attorney has great doubts whether he can maintain the suit, although he has no doubt of the guilt of these persons - and he recommends that the offer made
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01966.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            by the Company be accepted.</ab>
            <ab>On the ground that through lapse of time it is probably impossible to try this case successfully, I recommend that the offer be accepted&#8212;but in cases like this where there seems to have been deliberate and systematic fraud, and where the same persons have, as it appears, probably committed the same kind of fraud before, the immediate prosecution of the case of forfeiture, and the indictment of the persons, and their imprisonment, if possible, is, I think, the best course to be taken.</ab>
            <ab>In some of the Districts, I am aware that the number of cases upon the dockets of the Courts of the United States renders such a course often impossible. The offer is in this case that the Company pay as tax an assessed penalty of $7045:88 in currency, and a specific penalty of $3500 in gold, and costs. It is entirely for the Department of the Treasury to determine whether this specific penalty shall be paid in gold, or in its equivalent in currency; but I can conceive that by accepting an equivalent amount in currency some embarrassing questions in regard to its distribution may be avoided.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be</ab>
            <ab>Very Resp. your obd't serv't,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
