<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00909">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">W. A. Field to D. W. Middleton, 7 May 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>W. A. Field</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00909</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>W. A. Field</author>
          <title>W. A. Field to D. W. Middleton, 7 May 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-05-07" xml:id="dat1">May 7, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">470</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Middleton, D. W. ">D. W. Middleton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-06" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-03-10" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-10-21" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00909.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>May 7, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>D. W. Middleton, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Clerk Supreme Court U. S.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>There is a suit originally brought in the District Court of the United States for the District of Ky., for the confiscation, under laws relating to the rebellion, of the life-interest of one Blanton Duncan, in certain land, in which, in the District Court, as I am informed, judgment was rendered for the U. S. The case, I am informed, was carried by writ of error from the District Court to the Circuit Court but whether it has been carried by writ of error from the Circuit Court to the Supreme Court, and if such writ of error has been brought, whether it was returnable at the last term of the Supreme Court, or the December term of 1869, I do not know. Nor do I know the title of the case. It was the subject-matter of quite a long debate in Congress at the last session, or the last but one. It occurs to me that you may know the name of the case, and can inform me whether it stands on the docket of your Court, or whether a writ of error returnable at the next December term of the Supreme Court has actually been brought. If you can give me this information you will greatly oblige me.</ab>
            <ab>Very Resp. yours,</ab>
            <ab>W. A. Field,</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Attorney General.</ab>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Confiscated property&#8212;Blanton Duncan&#8212;Kentucky</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">see Ins Book p. 268</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">also Ins. B. p.294.</note>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
