<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02195">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to D. T. Corbin, 23 November 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02195</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to D. T. Corbin, 23 November 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-11-23" xml:id="dat1">November 23, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno"></idno>
          <biblScope type="page">61-63</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Corbin, D. T.">D. T. Corbin</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-12-09" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-26" who="#ad">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-09" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02195.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Nov. 23, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>D. T. Corbin, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Attorney,</ab>
            <ab>Columbia, S. C.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The forms of indictment enclosed in your letter of the 17th instant have been carefully considered in this Department, and the only suggestion it is deemed worth while to make is that something like the matter of the enclosed memorandum shall be inserted at the proper places in forms one (I) and two, (II) and in the other forms when the cases are analagous.</ab>
            <ab>At the foot of the memorandum you will also find a list of authorities which may perhaps be serviceable to you.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">forms of indictment &amp;c.</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">S. C.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02195.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>It is not probable, in view of the pressure of business here, that I shall be able to attend the Court at Columbia. I will communicate on the subject of assistance in a day or two.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>(Memorandum.)</ab>
            <ab>In Forms 1 and 2, after "Approved May 31, 1870,<choice><sic></sic><corr>"</corr></choice> insert the following <hi rend="underline">in</hi> <hi rend="underline">lieu</hi> <hi rend="underline">of</hi> <hi rend="underline">the</hi> <hi rend="underline">Section</hi></ab>
            <ab>. . . . by unlawfully hindering, preventing and restraining divers male citizens of the United States of African descent, above the age of 21 years, qualified to vote at any election by the people in said county, district, and State, from exercising the right and privilege of voting&#8212;and by other unlawful means not allowing them, the said male citizens, to vote, at an election by the people, then and there being held, [ or, if the election was to take place at a future time, insert after "people," to be held on the <space dim="horizontal" extent="3 letters" quantity="3" unit="chars"/> day of <space dim="horizontal" extent="3 letters" quantity="3" unit="chars"/> A. D. 1871, within the county, district and state aforesaid;] against the peace and dignity of the United States, and contrary to the statute in such case made and provided</ab>
            <ab>As to the sufficiency of an indictment for conspiracy without specifying the particular persons intended to be injured, see also Rex v. De Berenger, 3 M &amp; T. 67; cited also Russ. on Crimes, 679. See also Commonwealth v. Haily,
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02195.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            7 Metcalf (Mass.) R. 506; Commonwealth <hi rend="underline">v</hi>. Judd, 2 Mass. R. 329.</ab>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
