<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02451">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to George D. Woods, 6 September 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02451</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to George D. Woods, 6 September 1871</title>

         
          <date cert="high" when="1871-09-06" xml:id="dat1">September 6, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microfilm 699 Roll 14 699, Roll 14 </idno>
          <biblScope type="page">51-52</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Woods, George D.">George D. Woods</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-11-04" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-11-03" who="#mk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-20" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

        
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02451.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>Sep. 6, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>His Excellency George D. Woods,</ab>
            <ab>Salt Lake City, Utah.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received, through your reference, the letter addressed to you dated the 28th ultimo, by U. S. Marshal Patrick, covering a communication addressed to him, under date of the 19th ultimo, by Col Trobri and, commanding at Camp Douglas, inviting his attention to the civil prisoners confirmed at that post, you refer these letters to me, and express the hope that some arrangement can be made by which such prisoners can be kept at the Territorial Penitentiary until their trial&#8212;there being no available county prison&#8212;and the penitentiary being the only place in which they can be safely kept.</ab>
            <ab>By the contract entered into by you and Marshal Patrick, for the subsistence and safe-keeping of Territorial convicts, it is agreed that the Territory "shall pay to the Government of the United States, the sum of one dollar and fifty cents for each and every day for each prisoner, so long as the said prisoners shall be so confined." This agreement has reference to persons who have been convicted in the Territorial Courts, and
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Prisoners, pay, &amp;c. in Utah.</note> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02451.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            sentenced to imprisonment thereby. If, however, the Territorial authorities will pay for keeping persons held for trial, at the same rate, and upon the same conditions, as for those specified in the contract, I know of no objection to their being placed in the Penitentiary, and under the control of the U. S. Marshal. I do not feel authorized to direct the Marshal to receive these parties arrested for violations of the Territorial laws, unless some arrangement can be made for the payment of their subsistence.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
