<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01923">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to William A. Richardson, 21 June 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01923</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to William A. Richardson, 21 June 1869</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1869-06-21" xml:id="dat1">June 21, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">534-536</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Richardson, William A.">William A. Richardson</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-08-22" who="#jw">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-02" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-01" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01923.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>June 21, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Wm. A. Richardson,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 19th inst. relating to the case of Baker, Beach, &amp; Company, arising under the Internal Revenue laws. It appears that an assessment was made upon this firm for deficiencies in their returns of manufactured tobacco, from May to November 1868, both inclusive, as follows:
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Tax</cell>
                    <cell>$4271:52</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Penalty, 50 pr cent</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="underline">2135:76</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Total</cell>
                    <cell>$6407:28</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
              </ab>
            
          <ab>An information for the forfeiture of property seized, being of the value of $750, was filed, and Baker, Beach, and Ware, the co-partners, were indicted, charged among other things with knowingly making false returns.
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Baker, Beach &amp; Co. offer to pay as tax&#8212;</cell>
                    <cell>$2865:24,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Specific penalty</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="underline">596:30</hi>,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Total</cell>
                    <cell>3461:54.</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            </ab>
            <ab>Payable, "one half cash down, the balance in three equal payments," in six, nine, and twelve months, in compromise of said assessment and suits. If this compromise is accepted, either the suits are to be discontinued on payment of one-half of the sum offered, and on the execution by Baker, Beach, &amp; Co. of an obligation to pay the remaining half at the times named;&#8212;
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01923.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            or the suits are to be continued for a year, and if at the end of that time the money offered is all paid, the suits are to be discontinued. Meanwhile, the instalments paid must either be held by the local officers of the United States, and paid into the Treasury; or, if paid into the Treasury, and the last instalment is not paid, the suits must be either prosecuted, and the amount received paid back, or the suits discontinued&#8212;although only a part of the amount offered has been paid. The practical difficulties in trying the cases, after having been continued for a year, must be considerable. If the suits are discontinued, on receiving one half, with an obligation on the part of Baker, Beach &amp; Company, to pay the remaining half, and there is a breach of the obligation, the United States must bring suit upon it. It is not agreed that Baker, Beach, &amp; Co. are to furnish sureties that they will perform their obligation&#8212;and, if they did furnish sureties, still the United States, a year hence, may be compelled to bring a suit with no certainty that a judgment obtained will be satisfied. It may be that the amount offered should be accepted, if payable immediately; but I cannot think it for the interest of the United States to give credit in compromising suits of this character&#8212;and I feel constrained to withhold
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.01923.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            my recommendation.</ab>
            <ab>The papers enclosed in your letter are returned herewith.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be, &amp;c. &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
