<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02948">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Fredrick T. Frelinghuysen, 9 March 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02948</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
            the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
            law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express
            written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for
            Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</persName>
        <persName xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</persName></note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Fredrick T. Frelinghuysen, 9 March 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-03-09" xml:id="dat1">March 9, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 702, Roll 1</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">24-26</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Frelinghuysen, Fredrick T.">Fredrick T. Frelinghuysen</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2013-06" who="kp">blessed</change>
      <change when="2013-05-03" who="#crl">added bibliographic data with microcopy and roll numbers,
        corrected date to March 9, 1871</change>
      <change when="2013-04-03" who="#crl">proofed, checked</change>
      <change when="2012-12-03" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="letter">
    <body>
      <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02948.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
      <ab>March 9, 1871.</ab>
      <ab>Hon. Fred'k. T. Frelinghuysen</ab>
      <ab>U.S. Senate.</ab>
      <ab>Sir:</ab>
      <ab>I have received your letter of the 8th instant, in reference to the case of Edward W.
        Blake, for whom a pardon has been asked, convicted of passing counterfeit money.</ab>
      <ab>I have examined the case, and do not feel at liberty to recommend a pardon. On account of
        the high character of the gentlemen who urge a pardon, I state to you more fully than is
        usual the reasons which have governed me in the matter.</ab>
      <ab>Blake was sentenced on the 17th of October, 1867 to ten years <note type="authorial"
          place="left">question of pardon of E. W. Blake, N. J.</note>
        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02948.002.jpg" type="recto"/> imprisonment. Instead of
        having served six years, as you have been informed, he has served less than three and a half
        years. <space unit="chars" extent="3"/> In the many papers which accompany the petition, I
        do not find anything which mitigates the offence.&#8212;It is affirmed that the sentence was
        more severe than had been usual in the District of New Jersey&#8212;"that certain statements
        were made to the Judge which led him to believe that the defendant was a dangerous
        criminal&#8212;that there is reason to believe that this fact was much exaggerated, and that
        Judge Field regretted the severity of the sentence."</ab>
      <ab>All this is too shadowy and indefinite to authorize an interference with the solemn
        official action of the Judge. He had the case before him when the facts were fresh, and when
        he had the benefit of hearing all that was presented on either side, and I think it is due
        to the Judiciary that the pardoning power should not shorten the sentences pronounced under
        such circumstances, unless there is strong evidence of inconsiderateness, or other mistake
        on the part of the Judge, or of facts which would have mitigated the sentence. Such evidence
        is not furnished to me. The District Attorney says that gentlemen have assured him of
        mitigating circumstances which would have reduced the term of his sentence, if they had been
        known. These circumstances, if they exist, <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.02948.003.jpg"
          type="verso"/> should be clearly proved to the pardoning power.</ab>
      <ab>Of all the circumstances stated in the papers as a ground for mercy, none seems to be well
        made out except that of good behavior in the Penitentiary. But this would hardly justify a
        release of nearly two thirds of the ten years sentence.</ab>
      <ab>I will also say to you that there is scarcely any offense for which, I think, that pardons
        should be so cautiously granted, as that of which Blake has been convicted. It is usually
        perpetrated with great deliberation. It has none of the palliations which belong to crimes
        done under a sudden impulse. The victims of the fraud are generally the poorer and the least
        intelligent classes in society. I think therefore that the law should usually be visited in
        all its severity upon such offenders.</ab>
      <ab>Blake is reported to be about fifty years old. The chances of reformation are, therefore,
        much less than in the case of young men of unsettled character.</ab>
      <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
      <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
      <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
