<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01302">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to William Martin, 4 April 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01302</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to William Martin, 4 April 1870</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1870-04-04" xml:id="dat1">April 4, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">263-266</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Martin, William">William Martin</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-06-21" who="#vs">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-16" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-11-23" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
      
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01302.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>April 4, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>William Martin, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Commissioner,</ab>
            <ab>Fremont, Dodge co. Nebraska.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 28th ultimo, in which you say that a gentleman named Willis Drummond came into your office, and "gave" me "as authority" for a certain statement made by him in regard to the proper manner in which you should perform the duties of your office of Commissioner in proceedings before you, arising under the Internal Revenue Laws.</ab>
            <ab>I am not aware that I have
            <note type="authorial" place="left">certain duties of U. S. Commissioners</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01302.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            ever expressed any opinion to Mr. Drummond, or expressed any opinion officially to any person, upon the duties of U. S. Commissioners in these cases, although I, in common with all lawyers, have, I suppose, an opinion in respect to what these duties are&#8212;but I have no right to direct or instruct Commissioners, because they are <hi rend="underline">quasi</hi> judicial officers, in no respect subject to the control of the Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>Neither do I understand that any United State Attorney has a right to control them in the performance of these duties&#8212;although I have no doubt that a United States Attorney can, in his discretion, decline to prosecute a case pending before them, and can ask leave to enter a <hi rend="underline">nolle</hi> <hi rend="underline">prosequi</hi> in it, when the United States are the prosecuting party&#8212;and that, ordinarily, any such request should be granted by the Commissioner&#8212;although there might be cases in which, if I were a Commissioner, I should refuse to grant it. I have not, however, supposed that a Commissioner, if he finds on the evidence submitted, that a crime against the laws of the United States, of which he has cognizance, has been committed,&#8212;and also finds that the person charged in the complaint is probably guilty of the crime charged, has any discretion in the matter, if the United States Attorney chooses to prosecute the charge.&#8212;If a person has committed even a
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01302.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            trivial offense under the Internal Revenue Laws, and is in legal form charged before you as Commissioner with having committed it, and you have jurisdiction to inquire into the charge, and it is proved that he is probably guilty of the offence charged, it seems to me that you, as Commissioner, must hold him to bail, or commit him to answer such matters and things as he may be required to answer at the next term of the United States Court in your District, and that it is only for the United States Attorney, in his discretion, to ask leave to dismiss the complaint, or to enter a <hi rend="underline">nolle</hi> <hi rend="underline">presequi</hi> in it, even on the payment of the license or taxes due, or taxable costs,&#8212;and that the United States Attorney, in the exercise of this discretion, is subject to the direction of the Attorney General, the Secretary of the Treasury, and the Commissioner of Internal Revenue. In those Districts where the United States Attorney, or his assistant, is not present at hearing, before Commissioners, unless the case is an important one, because the distance between his residence, and that of the place of hearing, is too great to make it convenient for him to attend, I do not know that the United States Attorney could not by certain rules indicate to a Commissioner what the Attorneys practice would be in reference to discontinuing proceedings, on payment of special taxes or costs, and that this might be done by the Commissioner, in the absence of the Attorney or his Assistant, pursuant to these rules,&#8212;and perhaps, if the parties
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.01302.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            were strictly guarded, no very great harm could come from it, or any very serious objection be urged against it.&#8212;But you are a Commissioner appointed by the Circuit Court&#8212;and if any persons have a right to instruct you in these matters, they are the judges of that Court.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
