<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01897">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to J. F. Bullitt, 5 June 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01897</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to J. F. Bullitt, 5 June 1869</title>

        
          <date cert="high" when="1869-06-05" xml:id="dat1">June 5, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">514-515</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Bullitt, J. F. ">J. F. Bullitt</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-10" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-11" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-01-25" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01897.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>June 5, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>J. F. Bullitt, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Louisville, Ky</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 24th inst. relating to the case of Blanton Duncan, and which you wrote as his attorney. You are correct in the statement that the joint resolution passed by Congress is not the resolution of which a copy was enclosed in my letter to Attorney Bristow, of May 20th ult. on which the instructions contained in that letter were based, and which I then supposed to be the resolution passed;&#8212; but the resolution passed is the same as published in the Globe, a copy of which you sent me in your letter.</ab>
            <ab>This resolution seems to contemplate no discontinuance of the suit, and from the debate upon it in the Senate I infer the intention was that Mr. Duncan should prosecute the suits in reference to all money in the custody of the court not paid into the Treasury of the United States;&#8212; that the property other than money should be restored to him and he should release all claims to the money paid into the Treasury and all claim for damages. I do not now see how this intention can be exactly carried out without legislation; if you can suggest to me any method, I should be pleased to have you do so.&#8212; If this cannot be done, I do not feel at liberty to make any other
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01897.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            proposal than that contained in my letter of the 20th ultimo.</ab>
            <ab>Very Resp. yours,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General</ab>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
