<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00532">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to Hanna &amp; Knefler, 12 May 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00532</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to Hanna &amp; Knefler, 12 May 1868</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1868-05-12" xml:id="dat1">May 12, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">154-155</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Hannna &amp; Knefler">Hanna &amp; Knefler</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-26" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-02" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-07" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00532.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>May 12, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Messrs. Hanna &amp; Knefler,</ab>
            <ab>Counsellors at Law,</ab>
            <ab>Indianapolis, Ind.</ab>
            <ab>Gentlemen:</ab>
            <ab>It appears that the late Attorney General received a communication from you, under date of the 14th February last, representing that serious bad faith had been practised in procuring a pardon for one John Ebner, who had been convicted of violating the Internal Revenue Laws, and asking that the President should be advised to revoke the pardon on grounds of fraud. By direction of Mr. Stanbery, a copy of your communication, and also of other papers in the case, was sent to the District Attorney on the 5th March last, with instructions looking to a thorough investigation of the matter upon which your suggestion was founded. Mr. Stanbery's object appears to have been to ascertain whether the representations which had induced him to recommend that said pardon be granted, upon payment of all costs of prosecution, were substantially fraudulent.</ab>
            <ab>I have received the Report of the District Attorney, dated 1st instant, with a mass of evidence, touching, in the main, the guilty acts alleged on trial. I have considered, together with this Report and its enclosures, your communication aforesaid, the petitions upon which the application was made for the pardon, the report of the former pardon clerk of this Office to the late Attorney General, and other papers of the case.</ab>
            <ab>It is not
            
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">ante p 96 Ins. B. " 25 seq p 155</note> 
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00532.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            my duty to pronounce any opinion upon the expediency of issuing a pardon upon such a state of facts. I can only say that upon a careful examination of all the papers submitted for my consideration, it does not appear that the late Attorney General's recommendation of a pardon was procured by fraudulent practices.</ab>
            <ab>A copy of this communication is furnished to the District Attorney, under this date.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully, your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab>O. H. Browning,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General <hi rend="underline">ad</hi> <hi rend="underline">interim</hi></ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
