<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02614">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Robert McPhail Smith, 24 November 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02614</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Robert McPhail Smith, 24 November 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-11-24" xml:id="dat1">November 24, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">152-153</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Smith, Robert McPhail">Robert McPhail Smith</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-12-05" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-26" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-28" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02614.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>Nov. 24, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>R. McPhail Smith, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Nashville, Tenn.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Your letters of the 19th and 20th instants, to me, and of the 21st instant to the Solicitor General, have been received.</ab>
            <ab>Though there is no obligation upon this Department to disclose the reasons why a change is made in a public office, I have no objection to stating the reasons for your suspension, so far as I am acquainted with them. You are aware that last spring very grave charges were made against you&#8212;and having some reason to distrust the motives of those who made them, I refused to act upon them until you should have a full opportunity for an explanation or denial. You promised to meet the charges, but never did, so far as I now remember, possibly for the reason that I was absent from Washington at the time when you visited this
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Case of R. McP. Smith</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Tenn.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02614.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            city. I refer to this simply to show my indisposition to advise the removal of an officer upon unproved charges of personal adversaries.</ab>
            <ab>The transaction which has been lately brought to my notice in the Thomas case obliged me to suggest to the President the propriety of a change. Your explanation of that matter was not satisfactory, and according to the standard of professional ethics which is recognized here, the Government should not be represented by a gentleman who has made so serious a mistake.</ab>
            <ab>I was not moved in the slightest degree by any thing in the Stokes and Beatty case, but my action was taken from my own views of propriety, without any suggestion whatever any suggestion whatever from the persons whom you supposed to have prompted it.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">430</note>
            
                       
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
