<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00123">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Henry Stanbery to J. D. Smith, 3 October 1866</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00123</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
          <title>Henry Stanbery to J. D. Smith, 3 October 1866</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1868-10-03" xml:id="dat1">October 3, 1866</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">174</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Stanbery, Henry">Henry Stanbery</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Smith, J. D. ">J. D. Smith</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-18" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-08" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-08" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00123.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>October 3, 1866.</ab>
            <ab>To</ab>
            <ab>J. D. Smith, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Attorney, Northern Dist.</ab>
            <ab>Montgomery, Ala.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Complaints have been made to the Government that improper prosecutions are being instituted in your District for violations of the law respecting the use of stamps.</ab>
            <ab>You are hereby instructed (by request of the Secretary of the Treasury,) to commence no prosecutions for failure to affix stamps to instruments issued <hi rend="underline">prior</hi> to the establishment of the Collection District, &amp; that none be commenced for omissions <hi rend="underline">since</hi> that time, unless a fraudulent intent can be clearly proved.</ab>
            <ab>Your attention is called to those provisions of the statute which authorize Collectors to remit penalties in cases of this kind, upon payment of the proper stamp duties, whenever it is proven to their satisfaction that the omission of the necessary stamps was without any fraudulent intent. By the Act of July 13, 1866, it is provided that an instrument issued unstamped, at a time when, &amp; in a place where, no collection District was established, may be stamped by the party who issued it, or by any party having an interest therein, at any time prior to Jan. 1, 1867,&#8212;and the legal effect of such stamp is the same as though affixed by the Collector.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c</ab>
            <ab>H. Stanbery,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <ab>[A duplicate of the above was this day sent to L. V.B. Martin, U. S. Attorney, Mobile, Ala.]</ab>
            
            
            
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
