<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00743">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">William M. Evarts to John Jay, 14 January 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>William M. Evarts</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00743</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>William M. Evarts</author>
          <title>William M. Evarts to John Jay, 14 January 1869</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1869-01-14" xml:id="dat1">January 14, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">339-340</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Evarts, William M. M.">William M. Evarts</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Jay, John">John Jay</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-02" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-07" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-21" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00743.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>January 14, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>John Jay, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>President Union League Club,</ab>
            <ab>26th street &amp; Madison av.</ab>
            <ab>New York City.</ab>
            <ab>Dear Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The record in the Rosenberg case was not printed until Monday last. On that day, I moved the court to advance it for argument, &amp; named the first Tuesday in February as the earliest day that my previous engagments in court would permit of my attention to the argument, and as being probably as early a day as
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00743.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            I could expect the attendance of the opposing counsel. If it is the intention of persons interested in the prosecution to furnish to me a complete brief in the cause, or the attendance of Associate counsel, I shall be obliged by your providing me with the brief, &amp; putting me in communication with the associate counsel as soon as possible.</ab>
            <ab>No entry has been made on the docket, of any counsel for the defendant, in the case, and I am not advised to whom I should communicate with respecting this assignment of the cause, or its future argument. As no publication of the assignment of the cause has been made in the newspapers, so as to attract the attention of opposing counsel, you will be so good as to see that notice is given to such counsel, and that I am advised at once whether they will be prepared to attend on the day assigned.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient serv't,</ab>
            <ab>Wm M. Evarts,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
