<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00520">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Hugh McCulloch, 29 April 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00520</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Hugh McCulloch, 29 April 1868</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1868-04-29" xml:id="dat1">April 29, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">143-144</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="McCulloch, Hugh">Hugh McCulloch</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-25" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-01" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-05" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00520.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>April 29, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Hugh McCulloch,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor herewith to refer some papers filed in this office by the Hon. Thos. C. McCreery, United States Senate, with a view of invoking Executive clemency for the relief of Messrs. Wm. P. Mobberly, and Thos. Monarch, obligors in a bond of $2000: given by them as sureties, of and with Wm. H. Mobberly and Richard Monarch, tobacco manufacturers and partners, conditioned upon the faithful observance of the latter of the Internal Revenue laws. Upon a breach of condition, the stock and other property of the principals, amounting, it is said, to $15,000: was seized, forfeited and sold, by the government. Judgment also, in a separate action, has passed upon this bond, against the petitioners.</ab>
            <ab>The case is represented to be one of hardship to two very worthy citizens, residing at a distance from the scene of the fraud, and wholly innocent of it. It is stated that the satisfaction of this judgment would exhaust their property in their old age, their sons having also lost all of theirs by their own fault. The District Attorney recommends relief, and I believe it ought to be granted. Nevertheless, though the penalty is for an offence against the United States, yet the existing judgment is simply the record of a debt in favor of the Untied States, arising upon a civil action at law. Under these circumstances, it is very questionable whether
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00520.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            the pardoning power could reach it; but it is supposed to resemble the cases which fall within the remitting power of the Secretary of the Treasury, and the Commissioner of Internal Revenue.</ab>
            <ab>I therefore respectfully refer the papers, consisting of transcripts of the bond, judgment, and proceedings <hi rend="underline">in</hi> <hi rend="underline">rem</hi>, an affidavit marked A, and the petition of the parties addresed to the President.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Your obedient serv't,</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
            <ab>Assistant Attorney Gen'l.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
