<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01479">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to William T. Jones, 14 November 1870</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01479</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to William T. Jones, 14 November 1870</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1870-11-14" xml:id="dat1">November 14, 1870</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">468-469</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Jones, William T.">William T. Jones</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-06-24" who="#vs">checked</change> 
      <change when="2011-02-22" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-12-07" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01479.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>November 14, 1870.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Wm. T. Jones,</ab>
            <ab>Asso. Justice Supreme Ct. Wyoming Terr.</ab>
            <ab>Cheyenne.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 4th instant, requesting leave of absence from the Territory of Wyoming for sixty days from and after the 20th instant.</ab>
            <ab>The desired leave is granted for the period of thirty days from the 20th instant.</ab>
            <ab>This is allowed, on account of the private business in Indiana which you allege as one of the reasons for your application. The other reason, to wit, your desire to spend some time at Washington during the next session of Congress, in the interest of the citizens of Wyoming Territory, is regarded as insufficient to justify the leave which you desire. While holding the commission of Judge, your time should be mainly devoted to the duties which that Commission requires. And, however valuable your services in Washington might be to the people who have elected you as their Delegate, I do not think that, while serving them here in advance of your regular term, you should be receiving pay from the Government for performing another public service which can only be properly performed in your Territory.</ab>
            <ab>I have felt bound, therefore, to abridge the term for which you desire leave
            <note type="authorial" place="left">concerning leave of absence</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01479.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            of absence, allowing sufficient time for the private occasions which will call you to Indiana.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
