<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01623">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to W. P. Kellogg, 12 January 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01623</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to W. P. Kellogg, 12 January 1871</title>

          <date cert="high" when="1871-01-12" xml:id="dat1">January 12, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book H</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">568-569</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T. ">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Kellogg, W. P. ">W. P. Kellogg</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-10" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-03-29" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-12-09" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
          
            
           
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01623.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <ab>January 12, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. W. P. Kellogg,</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Senate.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Before receiving yours of yesterday on the subject of the compensation of the U. S. Attorney in Louisiana, I sent to the Judiciary Committee of the Senate a letter expressing the opinion that the proposed legislation would be unwise. That opinion was the result of general views, and not resting upon any minute knowledge of the amount of compensation received under the existing law.</ab>
    <ab>The letters of Mr. Beckwith to you show that the actual compensation is much less than I had supposed it to be. On account of the frequent changes in that office, the emolument returns have not been so full and regular as to show what the receipts have generally been.</ab>        
            <ab>I think that the Government should always have in that office a lawyer of sufficient ability, to compete with the best professional minds that will be arrayed against it in that District&#8212;and that his compensation should be adequate. It is one of the most important points in the country, and I confess I am somewhat puzzled by the reported smallness of compensation, in comparison with that which seems to be received in other Districts of less apparent importance. Yet I think that the compensation of these officers should
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Compensation Dist Atty U. S. Louisiana&#8212;&amp;U. S. Atty's generally</note> 
                <note type="authorial" place="left">see p. 563 ante.</note>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01623.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                be fixed by general, rather than by special laws; and I hope that some legislation will soon be had, raising the compensation everywhere to a respectable amount&#8212;and that then Mr. Beckwith will find it for his interest to continue in the office.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
