<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01974">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 6 July 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01974</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</author>
          <title>Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar to George S. Boutwell, 6 July 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-07-06" xml:id="dat1">July 6, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">602-603</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood ">Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-08-23" who="#jw">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-04-20" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-01-27" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01974.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>July 6, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I had the honor to receive your letter of the 30th of May last, with the accompanying papers, relating to a claim of C. A. Perry, &amp; Co., against the United States&#8212;in which you request my opinion upon the legal questions involved therein.</ab>
            <ab>On examination, I have not been able to find any statement of the facts of the case among the papers&#8212;nor, indeed, any statement from an official source of the precise questions on which my opinion is desired.</ab>
            <ab>It appears that this claim after having been reported upon adversely by the Third Auditor to the Second comptroller, was deemed by the latter officer, though concurring in the views of the former, to be a proper matter for judicial investigation&#8212;and the papers were accordingly transmitted by him to the Secretary of the Treasury for reference to the Court of Claims, under the provisions of the 7th Section of the Act of June 25, 1868, (15 Stat. 75.) But the counsel of claimants subsequently suggesting a different course, namely, that the claim be referred to this office with the question, "What constitutes an impressment into the public service under the
            
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Claim of C. A. Perry &amp; Co.</note> 
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.01974.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
            Act of March 3, 1849"?&#8212;the comptroller, it seems, adopted the suggestion to refer the case here,&#8212;and thereupon, at his instance, the papers were transmitted to me by you.</ab>
            <ab>This is all the information which the papers afford respecting the "questions involved" in the case;&#8212;and it will be observed that the single question there proposed does not purport to emanate from any official source&#8212;and is, besides, purely an abstract one. The report of the Auditor does not set out the case, but presents rather a commentary upon the evidence at large. So, likewise, does the communication of the Comptroller.</ab>
            <ab>Under these circumstances, I feel reluctantly compelled to return the papers in the case without any expression of opinion, as requested in your letter. But I assure you that upon being furnished with a statement of the facts of the case, as they may be found to be by the Comptroller, or may be agreed upon, together with the questions of law arising thereon, touching which my opinion is desired, I shall be happy to consider the questions, and give my opinion.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be,</ab>
            <ab>yours respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>E. R. Hoar,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
