<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02403">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Abraham Stow, 15 August 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02403</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
          <title>Amos T. Akerman to Abraham Stow, 15 August 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-08-15" xml:id="dat1">August 15, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">22</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Stow, Abraham">Abraham Stow</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-11-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-10-21" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-14" who="#ad">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02403.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           
            <ab>Aug. 15, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Abraham Stow, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>No. 35 Park Place</ab>
            <ab>Brooklyn, N. Y.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>At length, I have been able to give some examination to your communications asking that the Government defend the suit of Woolhopter against yourself. As at present advised, I do not see that, under the law, I am at liberty to assume the defence. The transaction out of which the suit grows, was entirely of a private character. Your account is that you bought cotton of Woolhopter, paid for a small part of it, and then that the cotton, or its proceeds, was taken from you by U. S. officials. Woolhopter sues you for the purchase money.</ab>
            <ab>You think that inasmuch as the Government got the cotton from you, it ought to assume the defence of this suit. I know of no authority for assuming such defence. But if you should be compelled to pay for the cotton which the Government took, it seems to me that the question may then come up, whether the Government should not indemnify you.</ab>
            <ab>I have caused some investigation to be instituted in the Treasury Department, and if anything should be produced which changes my present views, I will communicate further with you.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Cotton case of Woolhopter ag't A. Stow</note>
            
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
