<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02695">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Amos T. Akerman to Todd R. Caldwell, 26 December 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nar.02695</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mk">Melanie Krupa</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Amos T. Akerman</author>
                    <title>Amos T. Akerman to Todd R. Caldwell, 26 December 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-12-26" xml:id="dat1">December 26, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
                    <biblScope type="page">201-202</biblScope>
                    <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Akerman, Amos T.">Amos T. Akerman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Caldwell, Todd R.">Todd R. Caldwell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="scribe">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2012-09-25" who="#el">automated clean-up and final check of file</change>
            <change when="2012-12-05" who="#mk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-12-05" who="#ad">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-09-30" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.02695.001_fullpage.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>Dec. 26, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>His Excellency Todd R. Caldwell,</ab>
            <ab>Raleigh, N. C.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>On the first instant the President referred to me, for investigation, a memorial endorsed by you from certain officials and citizens of the county of Cleveland, N. C., complaining of the arrest and imprisonment of one Allen Bettis, Chairman of the Board of County Commissioners of that county.</ab>
            <ab>I have made investigation, and learn that Bettis was arrested by the military upon overwhelming proof of his connection with the Ku Klux Klan in York county, South Carolina. At the time of his arrest it was supposed by the officer that he was a citizen of South Carolina; but it was afterwards learned that he lived in Cleveland, N. C., and very near the State line. On the 24th of November last, he was turned over to the U.S. Marshal, and by the Marshal taken before Samuel T. Poinier, U.S. Commissioner, and released by the Commissioner on giving bail to appear before the U.S. Circuit Court for South Carolina, and answer to any indictment that might be preferred against him for violation of the Enforcement Acts of Congress.</ab>
            <ab>It appears that no law has been violated by the U.S. authorities in the case of Mr. Bettis, and that he is held to answer a regular accusation of crime.</ab>
            <ab>The statement of the memorialists
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">Case of Allen Bettis,</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">N. C. (S. C.)</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="none">see Ex B'k A, 407</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02695.002_fullpage.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            that Bettis is willing to be tried by his peers in his own State, and claims that he, in justice, should be tried in his own State, is entirely inapplicable to the facts. His alleged offenses having been committed in South Carolina, he is liable for them in that State only.</ab>
            <ab>The memorialists probably conceived that under the Enforcement Law, no arrest could be made by the military outside of the District in which the <hi rend="underline">habeas</hi> <hi rend="underline">corpus</hi> is suspended. You will perceive, however, by the examination of Section third of the Act of April 20th, 1871, that the right to employ the military in making arrests is not limited to such District. In the present case the President being authorized to use the military for the suppression of the unlawful combination in South Carolina, a member of such a combination in that State is not protected from military arrest by getting over the State line. Mr. Bettis has been delivered to the Marshal of the proper District, to be dealt with according to law, which is exactly what the third section directs to be done. The proper District is that in which the alleged offences were committed.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>A. T. Akerman,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
