<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00136">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">J. Hubley Ashton to James M. Carlisle, 17 October 1866</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00136</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>J. Hubley Ashton</author>
          <title>J. Hubley Ashton to James M. Carlisle, 17 October 1866</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1866-10-17" xml:id="dat1">October 17, 1866</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">182-183</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Ashton, J. Hubley">J. Hubley Ashton</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Carlisle, James M.">James M. Carlisle</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-09" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-08" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-08-31" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00136.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>October 17, 1866.</ab>
            <ab>To</ab>
            <ab>James M. Carlisle, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Washington.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>Before pronouncing on the petition of Peter Targarona "for pardon, &amp; remission of forfeiture," the Attorney General would like to hear the views of the party's counsel upon several points which appear, upon a cursory examination, to be involved in the case.</ab>
            <ab>Targarona was the owner of a steamer "Capital," during a period when it was in the military employment of the insurgent forces. The boat was seized &amp; libelled in the proper U. S. Court, was bonded by the claimant, &amp; before the final decree, was lost by disaster. The Court condemned the property, &amp; decreed the payment of its appraised value in conformity to the stipulations of the bond. The object of Targarona now is to procure such Executive interposition as shall exonerate him &amp; his  sureties from the payment imposed by the decree.</ab>
            <ab>The prosecution was had under the confiscation law of 6th August 1861, in which property tainted by certain disloyal acts of owners, is made "lawful subject of prize &amp; capture," (12. Stats. 319.) Targarona intervened at the trial, denying the material allegations, &amp; asserting continuous loyalty, while the evidence does not seem to have proved his voluntary service in aid of the rebellion. The statute cited imparts no additional power of remission
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.00136.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            to the Executive, while the general power of mitigation given in the subsequent Act for the Confiscation, etc. of 17 July, 1862, (12 Stats. 592.S13,) is by way of proclamation. Other powers of remission of penal forfeitures, given by statute, are mostly for revenue, or criminal cases.</ab>
            <ab>The following considerations seem to arise:</ab>
            <ab>1: The particular executive power of interference invoked by this petition.</ab>
            <ab>2: If there be such a power, whether the exercise of it must not be predicated on guilt in the petitioner, subsisting at the time.</ab>
            <ab>3: Whether in the personal history of this petitioner, there have been guilty acts, not heretofore amnestied, by general proclamation, which may enter into this question.</ab>
            <ab>4: Whether, &amp; in what manner &amp; degree, the fact of a definitive sentence of condemnation &amp; forfeiture by a Court of competent jurisdiction, should affect whatever power of remission the party invokes for his relief.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully</ab>
            <ab>Your obd't serv't,</ab>
            <ab>J. Hubley Ashton,</ab>
            <ab>Ass't. Att'y. Gen'l.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
