<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00891">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">W. A. Field to John A. Rawlins, 1 May 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>W. A. Field</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00891</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>W. A. Field</author>
          <title>W. A. Field to John A. Rawlins, 1 May 1869</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1869-05-01" xml:id="dat1">May 1, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">457-458</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Rawlins, John A.">John A. Rawlins</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-05-05" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-08" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2010-10-28" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00891.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>May 1, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. John A. Rawlins,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of War.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I send enclosed herewith a copy of a letter received form E. W. Andrews, dated April 1st ult., and relating to an action of ejectment brought in the Circuit Court of Jefferson county, West Virginia, to recover about twenty-one acres of land, situated on the Potomac river, and hitherto supposed to belong to the United States.</ab>
            <ab>In this letter of Mr. Andrews it is stated that Mr. Smith, U. S. Attorney for West Virginia, employed Mr. Andrews, with the sanction of Mr. Stanbery, then Attorney General. I do not find from the records of this office that Mr. Andrews was employed by the Attorney General, and
                
                <note type="authorial" place="left">Harper's Ferry ejectment suit</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="left">see Index Letter Book H. p. 32</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00891.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            I am led to suppose that the War Department has, directly, authorized his employment.</ab>
            <ab>I am anxious only that the proper direction be given in the case, and, if the War Department has control of it, I desire that the Department will communicate directly with Mr. Andrews and Mr. Smith, and so inform this office. If, hitherto, the control of the case has been with this office, I will, on receiving from you an expression of your opinion as to what direction should be given, reply to the letter of Mr. Andrews.</ab>
            <ab>I have the honor to be,</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>W. A. Field,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
