<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00564">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Orville Hickman Browning to William Henry Trescott, 10 June 1868</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00564</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        
        <bibl>
          <author>Orville Hickman Browning</author>
          <title>Orville Hickman Browning to William Henry Trescott, 10 June 1868</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1868-06-10" xml:id="dat1">June 10, 1868</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">173-174</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Trescott, William Henry">William Henry Trescott</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-28" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-02-21" who="#km">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-30" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

         
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00564.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>June 10, 1868.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Wm. Henry Trescott,</ab>
            <ab>Charleston, S. C.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have received your letter of the 1st instant, in which you mention, and commend for such relief as may be consistent and practicable, the case of Mr. Gourdin, the surviving and responsible surety of Col. Hamilton, formerly Marshal for the District of South Carolina, against whom, and his sureties, a claim for a balance on his accounts has been prosecuted to judgment by the United States. You state that certain items of account were allowed by the jury in favor of the defendant, against whom their verdict was for the sum of $2000, a less sum than would have been assessed by them in favor of the United States, had they rejected said items. Under these circumstances, the District Attorney, as you are understood, contemplates taking an appeal, and
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00564.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                the defendants are desirous to escape the anxiety and expense of further litigation, believing the existing judgment to be fair and just to all parties.</ab>
            <ab>In reply, I have to say that the immediate supervision of all proceedings for the collection of debts, dues and demands for the United States, is vested by law in the Solicitor of the Treasury. The supervision by this Office is general, and becomes special by way of exception, usually at the instance of some other branch of the government, or that of the District Attorney or Marshal, or when a suit regularly reaches the Supreme Court.</ab>
            <ab>The supervision of the Secretary of the Interior in relation to Marshals, extends to their accounts, but not to the control of proceedings which may grow out of them. If the proposed appeal is directly to the Supreme Court, the Attorney General may exercise his discretion whether to dismiss it or not when it comes into that Court. But at present the case does not seem to be such as to make the occasion a proper one for my interference.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully, your obedient servant,</ab>
            <ab><choice><sic>OH Browning</sic><corr>O. H. Browning</corr></choice></ab>
            <ab>Attorney General <hi rend="underline">ad</hi><hi rend="underline">interim</hi></ab>
            
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
