<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00240">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to Ulysses S. Grant, William H. Seward, Gideon Welles, Hugh McCulloch, Orville Hickman Browning, A. W. Randall, 17 August 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00240</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to Ulysses S. Grant, William H. Seward, Gideon Welles, Hugh McCulloch, Orville Hickman Browning, A. W. Randall, 17 August 1867</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1867-08-17" xml:id="dat1">August 17, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">467-468</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S. ">Ulysses S. Grant</persName>
          <persName key="Seward, William H. ">William H. Seward</persName>
          <persName key="Welles, Gideon">Gideon Welles</persName>
          <persName key="McCulloch, Hugh">Hugh McCulloch</persName>
          <persName key="Browning, Orville Hickman ">Orville Hickman Browning</persName>
          <persName key="Randall, A. W. ">A. W. Randall</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-11" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-16" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-09" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00240.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <ab>August 17, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>Circular Letter sent to,</ab>
            <ab>Gen. U. S. Grant, Acting Secretary of War,</ab>
            <ab>Hon. W. H. Seward, Secretary of State,</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Gideon Welles, Secretary of the Navy,</ab>
            <ab>Hon. H. McCulloch, Secretary of the Treasury,</ab>
            <ab>Hon. O. H. Browning, Secretary of the Interior,</ab>
            <ab>&amp; Hon. A. W. Randall, Post Master General.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have been directed by the President to address to each of the Heads of Departments the following communication:</ab>
            <ab>Your attention is respectfully invited to the enclosed slip from the <hi rend="underline">New</hi> <hi rend="underline">York</hi> <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> of the 15th inst. purporting to be a communication from a correspondent of that paper, writing from this city, in which he professes to recite at length a number of affidavits, &amp; also a petition for the pardon of one, Dunham, &amp; states that he copied them all from the originals, which, he says, are on file in the Attorney General's Office, the Bureau of Military Justice, &amp; the War Department&#8212;&amp; says also that they are
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00240.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            on file in the proper Departments, where, he furthermore states, many more documents of the like character are on file.</ab>
<ab>I have to state, for the information of the Heads of the several Departments, that there has not been found, upon due investigation, any papers corresponding to, or resembling in any degree, those recited in this publication, in the archives of the Attorney General's Office, except those which were recited in full in a Report from this Office, addressed to the President, under date of the 5th inst., in relation to an application for the pardon of Charles A. Dunham.</ab>
<ab>The President instructs me to say that if any documents or papers resembling those recited in this publication are in the archives of the Government, he desires that they be immediately submitted for his personal examination.</ab>
<ab>In the event of there not appearing to be in the Department committed to your charge, any papers or documents corresponding with the publication referred to, the President further directs me to request that your Report may be as prompt as your convenience will allow.</ab>
<ab>I have the honor to be,</ab>
<ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
<ab>Your ob'dt serv't,</ab>
<ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
<ab>Act'g Attorney General.</ab>            
           
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
