<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.01953">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">W. A. Field to George S. Boutwell, 30 June 1869</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>W. A. Field</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.01953</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>W. A. Field</author>
          <title>W. A. Field to George S. Boutwell, 30 June 1869</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1869-06-30" xml:id="dat1">June 30, 1869</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book G</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">571-572</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Field, W. A. ">W. A. Field</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Boutwell, George S.">George S. Boutwell</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-04-20" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-01-24" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.01953.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <ab>June 30, 1869.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. Geo. S. Boutwell,</ab>
            <ab>Secretary of the Treasury.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>I have considered the Internal Revenue case of W. D. Smart, of Tennessee, submitted by your letter of the 29th inst. From the letter of the Commissioner of Internal Revenue found among the papers accompanying your letter, I understand the proposed compromise to be that Smart pay, as tax, Seventy three 50/100 dollars ($73;50;)&#8212;in compromise of his liabilities for fines and penalties, two hundred dollars, ($200);&#8212;and that he pay all costs. These should, I think, be taxed in the legal manner by the proper officers. The property informed against and condemned, I understand, is not included in this compromise, but may be sold pursuant to a warrant from the court, and the proceeds paid into the registry of the Court, thence to be distributed according to law.</ab>
            <ab>This understanding of the terms of the compromise renders it unnecessary for me to consider whether the provisions of the Internal Revenue laws authorizing the compromise of cases, or of suits or proceedings in courts, authorize the remission, in whole or in part of a forfeiture of property by a decree of a court, for a violation of the Internal
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.01953.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            Revenue laws in those cases where the property has never been released on stipulations, and so the title to the property has become by the decree vested in the United States, to be sold under the warrant of the Court, and the proceeds to be distributed according to law. </ab>
            <ab>If the compromise proposed, is such as I understand it to be, I recommend its acceptance.</ab>
            <ab>The papers are herewith returned.</ab>
            <ab>Very Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>your obedient serv't,</ab>
            <ab>W. A. Field,</ab>
            <ab>Acting Attorney General.</ab>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
