<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.02528">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Benjamin Helm Bristow to James B. McKean, 24 October 1871</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Benjamin Helm Bristow</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.02528</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ad">Anthony Dreesen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Benjamin Helm Bristow</author>
          <title>Benjamin Helm Bristow to James B. McKean, 24 October 1871</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1871-10-24" xml:id="dat1">October 24, 1871</date>
          <idno type="callno">Microcopy 699, Roll 14</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">98-100</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Bristow, Benjamin Helm ">Benjamin Helm Bristow</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="McKean, James B.">James B. McKean</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2012-01-12" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-11-09" who="#ad">proofed</change>
      <change when="2011-09-23" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.02528.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <ab>Oct. 24, 1871.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. James B. McKean,</ab>
            <ab>Chief Justice,</ab>
            <ab>Salt Lake city, Utah<choice><sic></sic><corr>.</corr></choice></ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The President has handed me your letter of the 9th instant, addressed to him,&#8212;and directs me to say in reply that it is the disposition of his Administration to furnish all possible and available means for the enforcement of law in the Territory of Utah.</ab>
            <ab>I think you are mistaken in supposing that the declination
            <note type="authorial" place="left">Utah&#8212;enforcement of law in, &amp;c.</note>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.02528.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            of Col. John H. Wickizer, to whom was tendered the office of District Attorney, is based solely, or even chiefly, upon the ground that the Postmaster General would not consent to his acceptance, while he held the office of Postal Agent. The letter of Col. Wickizer to this Department places his action upon other, and altogether different, considerations.</ab>
            <ab>The President would be glad to fill the office at once, by the appointment of a man of superior talents and energy in his profession, and if such an one is known to you as being willing to accept the office, I will thank you to suggest his name. Of course the chief difficulty in procuring the services of a competent District Attorney lies in the inadequacy of compensation provided by Congress. Over this, the Executive Department of the Government can have no control. We are not at liberty to increase the compensation allowed by statute to District Attorneys. But under the Act of August 2, 1861, re&#235;nacted by the Act of April 10, 1869, the Attorney General is authorized to employ and retain assistants to the District Attorneys whenever in his opinion the public interest may require it.</ab>
            <ab>In view of the importance of public business in your District, the President directs that counsel be employed under the authority of this Act of Congress. Deeming it advisable to have the services of counsel resident
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nar.02528.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            in the Territory, and familiar with the laws thereof, I will thank you to suggest a suitable person for this employment. Your early attention to this matter will greatly oblige.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully, &amp;c.</ab>
            <ab>B. H. Bristow, Solicitor Gen'l</ab>
            <ab>&amp; Acting Attorney Gen'l.</ab>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left">30</note>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
