<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>



<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00248">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">John M. Binckley to F. J. Herron, 27 August 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>John M. Binckley</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00248</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>

        <bibl>
          <author>John M. Binckley</author>
          <title>John M. Binckley to F. J. Herron, 27 August 1867</title>

          
          <date cert="high" when="1867-08-27" xml:id="dat1">August 27, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">478-479</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Binckley, John M.">John M. Binckley</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Herron, F. J. ">F. J. Herron</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2011-03-11" who="#nnk">checked</change>    
      <change when="2011-02-17" who="#js">proofed</change>
      <change when="2010-09-13" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
          </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nar.00248.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
           <ab>August 27, 1867.</ab>
           <ab>F. J. Herron, Esq.</ab>
            <ab>Marshal of the U. S. for Dist. of Louisiana, New Orleans, La.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>With your communication of the 19th inst. just received, came copies of the record in the case of George W. Griffin, et al. Vs. Mark Hoyt, J. H. McKee &amp; others, in Chancery, in the Circuit Court of the United States, and a copy of an order dated on the 8th inst. purporting to have been issued by authority of Major-General Sheridan, commanding in the Fifth Reconstruction District, in which, among other things, it is set forth that in a certain matter, which is the subject thereof, the Circuit Court of the United States had decided that it had no jurisdiction, and that, in consideration of that fact, and of other circumstances, the Sheriff of the parish of St. Charles is commanded, upon certain terms and conditions, to put certain parties into possession of an estate named therein. You state, in substance, that the estate referred to is the same which is the subject of the litigation aforesaid, and that at the time when the said order was executed, it was lawfully in your custody, under authority of the Court, and that the order is mistaken in supposing that the jurisdiction of the Court had been completely disclaimed.</ab>
            <ab>I have to instruct you, in reply, that this office will not presume to inquire into the jurisdiction of a Court of the United States, and that case will not therefore be considered with respect to jurisdiction, in which the Court alone has the power to decide. But the laws of
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nar.00248.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
            the United States for the enforcement of process of the Courts of the Union, it is the duty of the Law Department to put in motion, according to their several provisions. If, therefore, any civil process in your hands, by authority of the Court, has been obstructed, or if you have been dispossessed of property which was in your possession by authority of the Court, it is your duty to report the circumstances to the District Attorney, with the names of all parties whomsoever who are implicated, to the end that they may be prosecuted according to law, and without respect to persons.</ab>
            <ab>Respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>your obed't serv't,</ab>
            <ab>John M. Binckley,</ab>
            <ab>act'g. Atty. Gen'l.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
