<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nar.00266">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Henry Stanbery to Samuel G. Courtney, 1 November 1867</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>nar.00266</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
            reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U. S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
            Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
            been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
          changes to this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Henry Stanbery</author>
          <title>Henry Stanbery to Samuel G. Courtney, 1 November 1867</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1867-11-01" xml:id="dat1">November 1, 1867</date>
          <idno type="callno">Entry 10, Record Group 60, Letter Book F</idno>
          <biblScope type="page">529</biblScope>
          <orgName xml:id="nar">National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Stanbery, Henry">Henry Stanbery</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Courtney, Samuel G. ">Samuel G. Courtney</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="scribe">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>       <change when="2011-12-20" who="#el">removed spaces surrounding em-dashes and inserted space between initials</change><change when="2011-11-17" who="#el">checked file for values of @facs, further revised header information, revised encoding</change><change when="2011-11-15" who="#el">changes to TEI header, including punctuation of titles and replacing initials with full names when possible</change>
      <change when="2010-09-28" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nar.00266.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <ab>November 1, 1867.</ab>
            <ab>Hon. S. G. Courtney,</ab>
            <ab>U. S. Attorney,</ab>
            <ab>S. District, New York.</ab>
            <ab>Sir:</ab>
            <ab>The following communication has been received from the Secretary of War, <hi rend="underline">ad int.</hi>:</ab>
            <ab>"Information has been received from Hon. Chales A. Dana, of New York City, late Assistant Secretary of War, that suit has been instituted against him by Mr. G. B. Lamur, of Savannah, Georgia, on account of the arrest and imprisonment of the latter, by order of this Department, in 1865. As any part had by the Mr. Dana in these proceedings was in the performance of his duty, as a public officer, I have to request that the U. S. Dist. Attorney for the Southern District of New York be instructed at once to take charge of the case, and the requisite authority is hereby given for the employment of counsel, should such be necessary for the proper defense of the suit."</ab>
            <ab>In accordance with the above request of General Grant, and in conformity with the practice of this office, you are hereby instructed at once to take charge of the case in defense of the suit. If you desire extra counsel, the War Department will give the requisite authority for the employment thereof.</ab>
            <ab>Very respectfully,</ab>
            <ab>Henry Stanbery,</ab>
            <ab>Attorney General.</ab>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
