<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="bos.00019">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Mary Whitall Smith to Walt Whitman, 25 July
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Mary Whitall Smith</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>bos.00019</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Thomas Donaldson</author>
                        <title xml:id="td">Walt Whitman the Man</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Francis P. Harper</publisher>
                            <date when="1896">1896</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">234&#8211;236</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Whitall Smith</author>
                    <title>Mary Whitall Smith to Walt Whitman, 25 July 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-07-25" xml:id="dat1">July 25, 1885</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="bos">The Alice and Rollo G. Silver Collection in the Special
                        Collections at Boston University</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitall Smith, Mary" ref="loc.02189_n1">Mary Whitall
                        Smith</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-11" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-07-15" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-06-03" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-01" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2015-01-29" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">London,</name>
                    <date when="1885-07-25">July 25, 1885.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Before any more days pass I must write and tell thee of our visit to Tennyson,<ptr
                    target="n0625"/> which took place day before yesterday.</p>
            <p>We sent him thy letter from Lord Mount Temple's, where we were staying. His son
                Hallam wrote to us from the Isle of Wight, asking us to come Wednesday morning. So,
                Wednesday, about half past eleven, papa and Alys and I alighted at his front door,
                where a huge, curly dog overwhelmed us with caresses. Tennyson was not in, but Lady
                    Tennyson<ptr target="n0903"/> received us and talked with us until he came. We
                were walking in the old-fashioned flower garden when we met him, and almost the
                first thing he said was a "deep remark." He said that he was walking out one evening
                looking at the stars, so absorbed that he fell into a puddle; but he noticed
                afterward that the star was in the puddle also! Thereupon we all tried to think of
                something witty in reply. Something about poet's feet tangled among stars would have
                been appropriate, but as none of us thought of that reply till afterward, we had to
                let the opportunity slip. We walked with him and with his son all about the garden
                for about an hour. He showed us a tree planted by Gambetta,<ptr
                    target="bos.00019_n1"/> and talked to me about Turgeineff,<ptr
                    target="bos.00019_n2"/> and asked all about thee.</p>
            <p>As we were going away, he told me to give thee his love. His home is a large,
                rambling, old-fashioned house full of interesting pictures and engravings. It has a
                look of being lived in, and all the arrangements were "casual," as English people
                say. Hats and walking-sticks were lying about in chairs and dogs raced in and out at
                their pleasure.</p> 
            <p>Tennyson's "den" is up at the top of a narrow, winding stair&#8212;a large, sunny room,
                lined with books and having a lovely view of Freshwater Bay, framed in the dark
                green branches of the cedars of Lebanon. They insisted upon our staying to lunch,
                but made us promise not to put anything in any newspaper about it.</p>
            <p>Tennyson seems to have a horror of notoriety, and he told us a great many stories of
                the annoyances to which he had been subjected from curious, inquisitive, and
                gossiping visitors.</p>
            <p>The chief impression that his conversation made upon me was of a keen and eager mind
                (he has a wonderful memory for facts) and a keen sense of humor. He tells a funny
                story as well as anyone I ever heard. We came away soon after lunch, having had a
                most interesting visit, for which we all felt very grateful to thee..., Alys<ptr
                    target="loc.05908_n1"/> looks forward to going to see thee when she comes home
                in September, and to showing thee the photograph of himself which Tennyson gave her,
                with his autograph beneath.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>With much love, I am, thy friend,</salute>
                <signed>Mary Whitall Smith</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
