<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00379">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Julia Elizabeth Stilwell, 21 October 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00379</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">169-171</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Julia Elizabeth Stilwell, 21 October 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-21">October 21, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Stilwell, Julia Elizabeth">Julia Elizabeth Stilwell</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-30">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington<ptr target="duk.00379_n100"/>
               </name>
                  <date when="1863-10-21">October 21 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear friend,<ptr target="duk.00379_n2"/>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Jimmy is getting along favorably as usual but of course somewhat slowly. I was with him night before last, &amp; am going again this afternoon. It requires a good deal of patience in him to lay so steadily confined in bed, but he still has the good luck to continue remarkably free from any acute suffering. Night before last he had some pain &amp; swelling in the foot &amp; leg below the wound, but nothing of serious account. They bandaged it pretty tightly, &amp; that seemed to relieve it. Jim wished me to write to <hi rend="italic">you</hi> this time, &amp; I promised him night before last to do so. I wrote at that time from the hospital to your parents at Comac, &amp; sent the letter yesterday. Jim is dissatisfied unless I write pretty often, whether there is any thing to write about or not&#8212;My friend, I rec'd your note about your folks getting your dear brother's body from down in Virginia.<ptr target="duk.00379_n3"/> Dear friend, the rebels have lately advanced upon us, as you doubtless know, &amp; held Culpepper &amp; thereabout for many days past&#8212;but the rumor now is that they are falling back, &amp; that Meade will probably take possession of his old ground<ptr target="duk.00379_n4"/>&#8212;but at present I doubt if any thing could be done&#8212;the authorities here do not grant passes yet, they are stricter than ever&#8212;</p>
            <p>Dear friends all, I would say to you as I have written to Jimmy's parents, that I shall try to keep watch of the boy, as I shall probably continue in Washington for some time yet&#8212;&amp; if any thing should occur I will write to you&#8212;as it may be some reliance to you &amp; make you feel less uneasy, to feel that Jim can have nothing occur in his case without your being informed&#8212;though as far as now appears, he will go on favorably, &amp; his wound is likely to heal so that he can sit up, &amp; then gradually move about, &amp; so in due time be able to travel&#8212;</p>
            <p>So, my friend, farewell for present, &amp; I pray that God may be with you, &amp; though we are strangers I send my love to you &amp; all Jimmy's sisters &amp; brothers in law&#8212;for in times of trouble &amp; death folks draw near in spirit regardless of being separated by distance, or of being personally strangers&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>care Major Hapgood, paymaster U S A | cor 15th &amp; F st | Washington | D C.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
