<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00376">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Reuben Farwell to Walt Whitman, 21 November 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Reuben Farwell</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00376</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">139-140</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Reuben Farwell</author>
               <title>Reuben Farwell to Walt Whitman, 21 November 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-11-21">November 21, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Farwell, Reuben">Reuben Farwell</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-13">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-09-03">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-10">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Kind Uncle &amp; Friend</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Yours came to me on Friday last much sooner than I<ptr target="duk.00376_n100"/> expected </p>
            <p>Because my being so negligent of course I supposed you would act
the same to me</p>
            <p>Last week I was sick so that the house was obliged to hold me very tight  It is kind of a curious thing for me. I can not go out in to the open air with out taking cold</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will call at Armory Square when in Washington. I have been thinking about going there this winter to wile a way some of these lonesome days</p>
            <p>My Folks have some objections to my going where I have been so often for the last three years. But there is nothing like geting used to a thing or too</p>
            <p>The least stormy weather here drives us in to the house&#8212;But the rainyest night on Picket in Virginia we had to stand any how. Even a snow storme or too we have had here then I thought about being by the side of a snug fire all curdleed up in a little heap half froze to death</p>
            <p>A good warme bed a fellow gets at home besides other fixens throwed in. I hardly evr thought of these when I Enlisted &amp; perhaps I may try the self same opperations again. This is a curious world to live &amp; sport in   There will be no Young ladies after this war closes.</p>
            <p>Because they are a fraid some of the loved ones will come home crippled &amp; they will Marry while they think about it  Mostly of the Softer Sex will be old Maids waiting so long. I presume some of them are tired</p>
            <p>Yes I will tell her all about you one of these times &amp; that before she is Married which wont be a great while. Well Uncle I hope this may find you still alive &amp; well</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>My best respects To you, My Uncle</salute>
               <salute>Adieu till next time</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
