<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00336">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 1 February 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00336</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">83</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 1 February 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-02-01">February 1, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-05">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Camp near Falmouth <lb/>Va. </name>
                  <date when="1863-02-01"> Feb 1st /63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Here we are yet in camp just the same as you left us, and I think by the appearance of things here we are likely to stay for some time. I have my log hut partly finished and should have had it completed long ago, but after I had cut the logs and had them brought here, orders came for us to be ready to move the next day so I used the logs for fire wood, and since then, the weather has been so stormy I could not do much to it. I suppose we will go on picket tomorrow, so that I wont have a chance to do anything to the house untill Wednesday, but I shall finish it this week, and as soon as I get it done, I want you to come down and see me. Frank Butler<ptr target="duk.00336_n1"/> is helping me build it and is to occupy apartments in it. Your last letter to me is dated Jan 27th. You speak of haveing sent one the previous Saturday, encloseing one from home, and some money. I have not received it. I got a letter from Mother a day or two ago. She says they are all getting along after the old sort. Han has not got home yet, but Mother says she expects her before a great while.</p>
            <p>We had a regular old Northern snow storm last week, but it is nearly gone now but the mud is quite plenty just about hear. Capt Sims tells me to night that he has been promised a leave of absence for 10 days and will probaly start for Brooklyn in a day or two  I suppose he will call on you in Washington.<ptr target="duk.00336_n2"/> As soon as he gets back, I shall apply, and if I dont get it I dont know but I will send in my resignation  as it is hardly a fair shake for some to go home two or three times a year while others cant get away at all, but I dont blame Sims at all for going whenever he can get a chance.</p>
            <p>Walt I think you had better write on to Mother and let her send you (by express) $20 of my money and bring it on here to me when you come, for if I go home I shall want it, as I may not have a chance to get my pay in Washington.</p>
            <p>Tom<ptr target="duk.00336_n3"/> recd. a letter from you to night. Write as soon as you get this. Good night     G.W.W.</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
