<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00391">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, June
                    1867</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Charles Hyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00391</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Charles Heyde</author>
                    <title>Charles Heyde to Walt Whitman, June 1867</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1867-06" xml:id="dat1">June 1867</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">The Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Charles L.">Charles L. Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-26" who="#al">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-10-17" who="#el">updated sourceDesc</change>
            <change when="2010-12-20" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-08" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00391.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">Burlington</name>
                    <date when="1867-06">June 1867</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Walter Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letters etc, to your sister are received—and have been duly handed to
                her—</p>
            <p>When I peruse her mother's letters to you, and note the infirmity of the hand, I
                experience considerable indignation at a daughter, who comparatively well, and
                having ample time and convenience, so far deliberately continues to neglect her
                obligation to the same, and in fact exhibiting <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#br">no</unclear> emotion.</p>

            <p>But it is only a matter of a time, (or pecuniary considerations <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#el">how</unclear> much longer I shall
                tolerate the personal indignities I <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice>.</p>
            
            <p>To state the latest: this morning (Sunday) I got up and prepared my own breakfast as
                usual (and after having went over my garden (until 10 o'clock,
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00391.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                I quietly took a chair and sat down to
                enjoy a perusal of the New York Times. Han occupied another window, in her most
                negligent manner, peeping through the blinds at church goers; and because I did not
                look up at every remark and chafed some at the interrogation (which should have
                ceased) I was attacked with the usual personalities. I threw down the paper
                indignantly, and seizing my boots and coat retired to the kitchen, and shut the
                door, to escape further <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">provocation</unclear> and to prepare to leave the house.</p>
            
            <p>But I was pursued there, and could not escape without forcing my way; but I came out
                of the encounter with the back of my right hand so badly lacerated by her nails, that I am
                compelled to bandage it. And this is from your gentle seeming, simple seeming
                    sister,
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00391.003.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                
                who is so
                plausible and ductile before strangers—</p>
            
            <p>I procured her a book from the library, last evening, for her Sunday's reading (a
                novel) and managed all for her comfort as well as I could.</p>
            
            <p>She wound up her most miserable outrageous <choice>
                    <orig>behaviour</orig>
                    <reg>behavior</reg>
                </choice> by mean inferences toward a poor child of a girl, who now lies <choice>
                    <orig>allmost</orig>
                    <reg>almost</reg>
                </choice> at the point of death and whose has been declining for months—And whose
                brothers, <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">3</unclear> good, kind
                hearted men have helped me often (with material aid) in my struggles in this
                place.</p>
            
            <p>I sent a flower to her, the other day, of a kind she had craved when she was in
                health, and a pupil under my care—And this was <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">referred</unclear> to—But it is a mean <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="5" unit="chars"/> subterfuge, and Han lies—knowingly—She
                knows how this family has befriended—But Han has 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00391.004.jpg" type="verso"/> no gratitude within
                herself—and never had any sympathy for me.</p>
            
            <p>I never urged her to marry yet I have ever treated her in purest principle. I have
                nursed her in sickness, made every thing as agreeable and convenient as possible for
                her household work—taken half a woman's work upon myself. I have
                struggled within myself and solely. She is too mean. She is
                unjust—a liar, <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="br">slovenly</unclear> at times, without a parallel, for a woman without
                children. She is for herself, and herself only.</p>
            <p>I meet with much respect from the citizens of this place, and increasing
            encouragement—I shall exhibit my hand to a person, with whom she once
                lived. It will scarcely be credited, the persistent, vulgar and provoking meanness I
                have so long endured.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>C. L. Heyde</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>