<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00330">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 20 October 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00330</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">71-72</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 20 October 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-10-20">October 20, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-24">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Pleasant Valley, Md </name>
                  <date when="1862-10-20"> Oct 20th/62</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Everything is quiet on the Potomac, and we are still encamped here in Md. I am well and comfortable with the exception of an attack of homesickness which I cant seem to shake off.</p>
            <p>Mother why the deuce dont some of you write to a fellow,  Your Past letter is dated the 5th and I have written since then,  the last letter I wrote, filled 8 or 9 pages, did you get it.</p>
            <p>I want very much to know when you have heard from Hann. and if she has recovered from her sickness and is comeing home soon, and Mary, do you ever hear from her. And Mother I want to hear from all of you at home, have you got a good stove, and plenty of coal, and how about buckwheat cakes and sich. Matt and Sis, I hope are right Smart, and can <hi rend="italic">you</hi> fly around, Mamy as lively as when I left home.</p>
            <p>Where in thunder does all the troops go, that the papers say are leaving New York, and the other Citys every day. Why dont they send em, out to the front, and let us old veterans come home, and see our Mammies. We ought to have force enough now, to go right ahead and balsmather the seceshers. I dont like the idea of fighting the same ground over three or four times but I supose its all right. The nights here are cool, but the days are splendid,  us officers have been furnished with wall tents and as we have plenty of blankets we get along very well, but the men are not as well provided for. I am still in command of our company as Capt Francis<ptr target="duk.00330_n1"/> has not returned yet, although his time was up two days ago. We were ordered, one day last week, to be ready to move at five minutes notice, and as we had heard artillery fireing all the morning, we thought, we was in for annother fight, but it turned out to be some of our folks out on a reconnoissance somewhere near Charlestown Va, but as they did not find the Rebels in very strong force, we were not sent over, and I hardly think, from present appearences that we will leave here for some days yet. I wonder whats the reason they dont pay us off. Uncle Sam aint busted up is he,  it wouldent be much wonnder if he did though for he is swindled right smart, I recon. Well Mamy its getting cold so I will stop and go to bed. Maby you think I aint got no bed, but I have, and a bedstead too, made with four croched sticks drove in the ground, thus and my bed is a genuine corn husk Mattress which I think is a good deal healthier than feathers.<ptr target="duk.00330_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Good Night Mother, and much love to all. write as soon as you get this,</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Lieut G. W. Whitman Co. D <lb/>51st Regt N.Y. Vols. Ferreros <lb/>Brigade, Sturgis Division, <lb/>9th Army Corps, Reasan Valley Md</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
