<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00763">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Peter Doyle to Walt Whitman, 21 September
                    1868</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Peter Doyle</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00763</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Peter Doyle</author>
                    <title>Peter Doyle to Walt Whitman, 21 September 1868</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1868-09-21" xml:id="dat1">September 21, 1868</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter" ref="n0752">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc> 
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-21">added correspondent info</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-03-03">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-10-01">checked, revised</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-06-08" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk_am.00083_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington</name>
                    <date when="1868-09-21" rend="right">Sept 21 <lb/>1868</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I was very happy when i received your letter of the 18, &amp; glad to hear you
                arrived safe &amp; doing so well</p>
            <p>Since you went away i have had a very bad cold, &amp; i was afraid it would bring on
                the chills so i got off to day to get myself all right. There was a very exciting
                game of <choice>
                    <orig>Base Ball</orig>
                    <reg>Baseball</reg>
                </choice> Played here to day, between the Nationals, &amp; the Olympics, both of this
                city, i went out to see them &amp; enjoyed it very much when the game ended the
                score stood Nationals 21, Olympics 15 old <choice>
                    <orig>Base Ball</orig>
                    <reg>Baseball</reg>
                </choice> Players say it was one of the best games they ever saw.</p>
            <p>I also visited the Capitol this <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk_am.00084_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> morning both Houses Adjourned without transacting any business
                until the 16.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of October but from what i can learn
                they will not meet then I took up the Star Paper this evening to send you some news
                but i find so many things i came to the conclusion to send you the Paper</p>
            <p>John Surratt's trial commenced he to day but the counsel for the defense was not ready
                they then Postponed the trial until tomorrow.</p>
            <p>I have been very busy this week with new conductors learning them them the art of
                Rail. Roading one of them in Particular his name is Jas Ingraham, he had an
                introduction to you he was connected with a Female seminary in Ohio but sickness
                &amp; other reverses has brought him down a little in the world i lend him <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk_am.00085_large.jpg" type="rector"/> 15 dollars for
                to commence work with. Let me know if you have come across our Worthy President Mr.
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nnk">Dimning</unclear> in your
                travels as he went to New York last Saturday. The Black Crook runs here yet to very
                good Houses the Richings opera troupe Playes here next week but i see by the bills
                there is no new Pieces the same old <choice>
                    <sic>Playes</sic>
                    <corr>Plays</corr>
                </choice> as last season.</p>
            <p>nothing else here in way of Amusements. The Republicans are Preparing for a grand
                Mass Meeting here to morrow night to consist of Washington Georgetown &amp; Alexandria
                it is supposed that Mr Colfax will address the meeting</p>
            <p>In my other letter i wrote you that my mother was sick i am happy to state that she
                has got entirely well. i also sent you an extract from <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="duk_am.00086_large.jpg" type="verso"/> the Cronicle in the Star of the
                same date there is a small piece which i send this time</p>
            <p>Henry Hunt sends his love &amp; best regards &amp; thinks it very kind of you to
                think of him so far away</p>
            <p>Dave also sends his love &amp; by the way i must not forget your California friend (i
                mean Coles driver &amp; also the Californian on 7<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> street RR Hassett No 7 driver also sends his love</p>
            <p>I would write more but i am afraid you tired of this already</p>
            <p>no more at Present but</p>
            <closer rend="right">
                <salute>Remain</salute>
                <salute>Yours</salute>
                <salute>Forever</salute>
                <signed>Pete</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
