<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00342">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 29 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00342</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">Civil War Letters of George Washington Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Durham, North Carolina</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1975</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">95-97</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 29 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-29">May 29, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare Book,
Manuscript, and Special Collections Library
</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-20">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Heusonville Ky.</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-29">  May 29th/63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>My last letter home, was written from Lancaster and dated somewhere about the 16th or 18th of May. Since then we have been on the move again, as you see by the heading of this.<ptr target="duk.00342_n100"/> We left Lancaster on the morning of the 23d,<ptr target="duk.00342_n2"/>marched about 11 miles and bivouaced at a place called Crab Orchard and stopped untill the morning of the 25th when we came on about 10 miles further and bivouaced near the Villiage of Stamford. Next morning we started on again and after a march of 10 miles more we arrived and pitched our camp at this place. We have a first rate camping ground, in a grove just outside this town, and are takeing things very comfortable. Our Regt. is the only troops here, the rest of our Brigade<ptr target="duk.00342_n3"/> being at Stamford. Of course we dont know how long we shall stay here, or which way we will move next,  We do picket duty on the roads, about the country here, and our chief business is, to look out for rebel Cavelry raids, as they have been in the habit of dashing through these small country towns, stealing horses and Cattle and everything else they wanted. We had quite an excitement the first night after our arrival here. We put up our tents, on the afternoon of our arrival, and I was promising myself a good nights sleep (as we were all pretty tired after our march, and the work of pitching camp) but about 9 O clock at night we were ordered to strike tents immediately, so we had to turn out and take down and load tents, pack trunks, and get ready for a move, which we did at short notice. As soon as the things were all loaded, I enquired around to try and find out what the fuss was all about, and when I did find out I felt mad enough I can tell you. It seems that somebody had passed our pickets, who said he was carrying dipatches, to somebody, who was stationed somewhere, and that the dispatches were from General Carter,<ptr target="duk.00342_n4"/>and that the rebs had crossed the Cumberland River, and were in strong force, at a place called Liberty about 10 miles from here, and were comeing on this way. As soon as I heard the yarn I said it was a devilish foolish hoax, as I was satisfied that the enemy could never get as far in the State, as Liberty, without our hearing of it. and I dident like the idea of loseing my nights sleep for nothing. The wagon train started off towards the rest of our Brigade, and we fell in and marched about ½ a mile, and halted and stayed in the road all night. Next morning we came back here, and encamped again.</p>
            <p>Mother I have not heard from you in quite a long time,  I had a letter from Walt a few days ago,  he said that all at home, was going on the same as usual. Andrew he thought would go to Newbern with Cornell<ptr target="duk.00342_n5"/>  Mary I hear has been down and paid you a visit,  Walt says, probaly, Mary will go on to Burlington for Hannah, and bring her home. Mother, how are you getting along,  does the rheumatism bother you much now. Mattie, and Sis, Walt says are first rate,  Jess, and Ed, I suppose can take their rations regular. Jeff wrote to me three or four weeks ago,  he says that as long as I dont hear from home I may know that all is right. That wont do Jeff,  its a pretty good way to get off, but I dont see it.</p>
            <p>The news from Grant, down at Vicksburg is very encouraging,<ptr target="duk.00342_n6"/>  I only hope it wont turn out like the news of the capture of Richmond. If it should turn out, that Vicksburg is certain to fall into our hands in this campaign it will be a heavy blow to the rebs.</p>
            <p>I have just got Jeffs letter of the 22d. Mother I am very sory to hear that you are again troubled with rheumatism,  I hope you wont attempt to work untill you get well,  how about the vapor baths  do you take them now, but I hope you are better by this time. Andrew to  Jeff says  is quite bad  I hope he will take good care of himself, and soon get well,  All the rest I am glad to hear are getting along first rate and are in good health, I hope,  as Han (according to Heydes letter) has commenced to get well she will soon be able to come home,  Take good care of yourself dear Mother, and let me hear from you often,</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Much love to Mattie, and Sis, <lb/>and all the rest,</salute>
               <signed>Geo. W. Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
