<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00393">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 10 October 1877</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="vm">Vince Moran</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00393</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               
                <bibl>
                    <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
                    <title>Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 10 October 1877</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1877-10-10" xml:id="dat1">October 10, 1877</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">The Trent Collection of Walt Whitman Manuscripts, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Charles L.">Charles L. Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>        
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2013-12-12" who="#nhg">added annotation pointers</change>
            <change when="2013-09-09" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-19" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-10" who="#ab">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-11-09" who="#vm">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00393.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Burlington.</name>
                    <date when="1877-10-10" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Oct.</abbr><expan>October</expan></choice> 10 1877</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Brother Walter</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I would advise you to write to Han somewhat of an advising letter;<ptr target="n0299"/> what her prospects might be with her brother George:<ptr target="n0700"/> she has <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> very kind letters from his wife, inviting her to visit them.</p>
            
            <p>The trouble I have with her <unclear reason="cut off" cert="low" resp="#vm">is</unclear> past endurance: She invades my room, with such offensive <unclear cert="medium" resp="#vm"><choice><sic>demeanoar</sic><corr>demeanor</corr></choice></unclear> at times, that I am forced to quit my painting and take to the street: and then she assumes jealousy, and during my absence ransacks my papers, trunks and portfolios for scraps of poetry, composition of a date that have past my memory, and these she brings forward
                      
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00393.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>and reads to me, and berates me with, applying them to some one individual or other, at the present time, whichever comes into her head; like one possessed by a very devil. I am driven from my bed at midnight, and to the outside, in the piazza, where I sometimes sit, for hours. I cannot submit to it any longer. She smells my coat, when I come home, my gloves, my handkerchief and declares that I have been abed somewhere: Of course I can go to the hotel, and it would occasion no surprise; The neighbours have become so familiar with 
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00393.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/><choice><abbr>Genl</abbr><expan>General</expan></choice> Henry, that they will have no communication <unclear reason="covered" cert="medium" resp="#nhg">or</unclear> intercourse, with her. Half my time is passed in gardening, and portions <gap reason="cut off" extent="1 word" quantity="2" unit="chars"/> the rest waiting upon her, from the grocery. A evening she goes out, in the rain and darkness and returns at bed time, with scandal stories, of sexual demoralisation&#8212;whoring truly, and she does not take the smallest interest or thought of how I am to <choice><sic>mantain</sic><corr>maintain</corr></choice> myself, Keep this shelter over her and the sheriff from fore-closing&#8212;she shows nothing but the most uncompromising vagaries&#8212;I have lived like a dog&#8212;and can
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00393.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            prove it. She <choice><sic>allway</sic><corr>always</corr></choice> did have some mean provoking uncalled for scandalous reflection.</p>
            
            <p>I am sorry to be compelled to give such a lamentable story. It would not appear well in print. She is identified with yourself <gap reason="cut off" extent="1 word" quantity="1" unit="char"/> I shall do the best I can for her. I cannot afford to hire a studio away from the house&#8212;I have no support here scarcely&#8212;,</p>
            
            <p>I am seriously thinking of returning to my former profession, in New York, but such circumstances <unclear reason="cut off" cert="low" resp="#nhg">as</unclear> I have narrated could only so greatly discourage me. I enclose some papers that she has just raked up, to give you a fair idea of my grievances and her vagaries.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">CL Heyde</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
