<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="hyb.00015">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Richard Watson Gilder, 26 November 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>hyb.00015</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Richard Watson Gilder, 26 November 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-11-26" xml:id="dat1">November 26, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The current location of the manuscript of the letter is unknown. A microfilm image of the letter was obtained from Rutgers University</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">the enclosure is in the Trent Collection of Walt Whitman Manuscripts, Duke
                        University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Gilder, Richard Watson">Richard Watson Gilder</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-28" who="#nhg">updated ID and orgName, added images, updated transcription</change>
            <change when="2014-04-10" who="#kc">updated ID</change>
            <change when="2013-05-16" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2013" who="#gt">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-04" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-26" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="prc_af.00003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="center">431 Stevens Street</name>
                    <name type="place">Camden New Jersey</name>
                    <date when="1880-11-26" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Nov:</abbr><expan>November</expan></choice> 26 '80, p m</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Gilder</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I wonder if you can help me in the matter of <choice><abbr>wh'</abbr><expan>which</expan></choice> the enclosed two pp. are a statement&#8212;<choice><sic>Havn't</sic><corr>Haven't</corr></choice> you connected with your establishment some one learn'd in copyright law &#38; its infractions, that could take the thing in hand? <hi rend="italic">injunct</hi>  Worthington or something?<ptr target="hyb.00015_n1"/></p>
            
            <p>&#8212;I have sent a duplicate of the two pages to John Burroughs&#8212;&#38; asked him to call &#38; see you&#8212;I am <choice><abbr>ab't</abbr><expan>about</expan></choice> the same as of late years but unable to travel &#38; mainly helpless.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
            
            <postscript>
                <p>Nothing must be done involving heavy fees, as I couldn't pay them</p>
            </postscript>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk_am.00239_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <date when="1880-11-26" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Nov:</abbr><expan>November</expan></choice> 26 1880</date>
                </opener>
                                
                <p>R Worthington 770 Broadway New York about a year ago <choice><abbr>bo't</abbr><expan>bought</expan></choice> at auction the electrotype plates (456 pages) of the 1860&#8211;'61 edition of my book <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi>&#8212;plates originally made by a young firm <hi rend="underline">Thayer &#38; Eldridge</hi> under my supervision there and then in Boston, (in the spring of 1860, on an agreement running five years.) A small edition was printed and issued at the time, but in six months or thereabout Thayer &#38; Eldridge failed, and these plates were stored away and nothing further done;&#8212;till about a year ago (latter part of 1879) they were put up in <choice><abbr>N Y</abbr><expan>New York</expan></choice> city by Leavitt, auctioneer, &#38; bought in by said Worthington. (Leavitt, before putting them up, wrote to me offering the plates for sale. I wrote back that said plates were worthless, being superseded by a larger &#38; different edition&#8212;that I could not use them, the 1860 ones, myself, nor would I allow them to be used by any one else&#8212;I being the sole owner of the copyright.)</p>
                
                <p>However it seems Leavitt did auction them &#38; Worthington <choice><abbr>bo't</abbr><expan>bought</expan></choice> them (I suppose for a mere song)&#8212;W. then wrote to me offering &#36;250 if I would add something to the text &#38; authenticate the plates, to be published in a book by him. I wrote back (I was in St Louis at the time, helpless, sick) thanking him for the offer, regretting he had purchased the plates, refusing the proposal, &#38; forbidding any use of the plates. Then &#38; since I thought the matter had dropt. But I have to add that about September 1880 (I was in London
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk_am.00240_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="duk_am.00241_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    
                    Canada at the time) I wrote to Worthington, referring to his previous offer, then declined by me, and asking whether he still had the plates &#38; was disposed to make the same offer; to which I <choice><abbr>rec'd</abbr><expan>received</expan></choice> no answer. I wrote a second time; and again no answer.<ptr target="hyb.00015_n2"/></p>
                
                <p>I had supposed the whole thing dropt, &#38; nothing done, but within a week past, I learn that Worthington has been slyly printing and selling the Volume of <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> from those plates (must have commenced early in 1880) and is now printing and selling it. On <choice><abbr>Nov.</abbr><expan>November</expan></choice> 22, 1880, I found the book, (printed from those plates,) at Porter &#38; Coates' store, <choice><abbr>cor:</abbr><expan>corner</expan></choice> 9th &#38; Chestnut Sts. Philadelphia. P &#38; C told me they procured it from Worthington, &#38; had been so procuring it off &#38; on, for nearly a year.</p>
                
                <p>First I want Worthington effectually stopt from issuing the books. Second I want my royalty for all he has sold, (though I have no idea of ever getting a cent.) Third I want W. taken hold of, if possible, on criminal proceeding.</p>
                    
                <p>I am the sole owner of the copyright&#8212;&#38; I think my copyright papers are all complete&#8212;I publish &#38; sell the book myself&#8212;it is my sole means of living&#8212;what Worthington has done has already been a serious detriment to me.&#8212;Mr Eldridge, (of the Boston firm alluded to) is accessible in Washington D C&#8212;will corroborate first parts of the foregoing&#8212;(is my friend)</p>
                
                <closer>
                <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
                
                <signed>431 Stevens Street</signed>
                
                <signed>Camden New Jersey</signed></closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="duk_am.00242_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>    
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
