<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03048">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 29 June
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03048</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 29 June 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-06-29" xml:id="dat1">June 29, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-02" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-05" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-12" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-18" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03048.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1882-06-29" rend="right">June 29, 1882.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'Rah! I have yours of yesterday. It is just delightful to know you have a
                publisher, or rather publishers, though I have felt sure from the turn things have
                taken within two or
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03048.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     three days, that you will not want for publication. I am sure
                there is going to be a big row.</p>
            <p>Rees, Welsh &#38; Co. promise well. Only be sure your contracts are in form. Will it
                be advisable to have a long contract? You <hi rend="underline">may</hi> have a better offer yet.
               
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03048.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                     I hope Rees,
                Welsh &#38; Co only have <hi rend="underline">life</hi>. If they take advantage of the present uproar, and
                advertise you on the crest of this wave, they may secure a great sale. A publisher
                with money, ardently believing in your book, "fresh, vehement and true," as Thomas
                Davis says the
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03048.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Irish guard were at Fontenoy, devoted to your interest, and on the <hi
                    rend="underline">qui vive</hi> to turn everything to swell the fame of his
                venture, might effect a sale which would be tremendous.</p>
            <p>I am delighted at your
                prospect.</p>
            <p>I earnestly hope
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03048.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                they will print Bucke's book also. It will help. I wrote for him, in a whirl of
                bitter work and many cares, a long helter-skelter sort of an introduction, for my old
                pamphlet, which he was to print as an appendix. He thought my prolegomena good,
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03048.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     and I was sorry I
                could not make it better, but if Rees, Welsh &#38; Co. publish his book, I will
                strive to refurbish my contribution and make it better.</p>
            <p>Dr. Channing wrote me from Providence a fortnight ago, in great indignation at
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03048.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                     what had been
                done to you, and proposed to reprint "The Good Gray Poet" in Boston at his expense.
                I explained (did I tell you this?) that I had promised the republication to Bucke
                and could not in honor take it away from him. Besides, I felt it would not be as
                timely as I could wish. The thing
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03048.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     for a pamphlet will be my letters
                upon Oliver Stevens and company, when we get to a stopping point, which will be some
                time during the summer. I propose to print them under the caption, "The Suppression
                of Leaves of Grass," and they will make a good tender or pilot-fish to your
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03048.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    
                publishers'
                venture.</p>
            <p>After long cogitation, I have concluded, from internal evidence, and feel that I can't
                be mistaken, that "Sigma" is simply Stoddard, and I am going to answer him now and
                give him hell. The way I shall manage it, I think you will approve.
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03048.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     The <hi rend="underline">rationale</hi>
                     of his infamous communication, is to give a
                basis through the vilest calumniation, to the tottering action of Oliver Stevens
                and Marston. I mean to point out this fact, and exterminate his effort, announcing
                that I do so simply as preliminary
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03048.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                     to the arraignment of Marston, who
                has thus far escaped scourging, but shall presently know the meaning of the word
                knout. Then I shall go for Marston.</p>
            <p>Also Tobey, the Boston postmaster. He shall have
                a sample of the Day of Judgment. When I heard that George
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03048.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     Chainey's lecture on you had been
                suppressed, I at once wrote to him and got the facts by telegraph. Then I went to
                see Col. Ingersoll, and we had a red-hot time over the outrage, and arranged for a
                session with the Postmaster General on the subject. Today, we have seen him, and
                Ingersoll was magnificent. The Postmaster had, however,
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03048.015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    
                heard nothing of the matter (you
                will understand this chenanigan when you read the accompanying copy of a letter I
                have just received from Chainey) and said Chainey must write him a letter. So we
                telegraph to Chainey accordingly, and this afternoon Ingersoll
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03048.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     will concoct a
                letter to the <choice><abbr>P.M.</abbr><expan>Postmaster</expan></choice> General, with my assistance, and we will put in a copy of
                this letter of Chainey's. I think we can manage Howe, which will score heavily for
                us in the game.</p>
            <p>I'll keep you posted. Pretty soon, I will have a petition started in Boston for the
                
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.03048.017_large.jpg" type="recto"/>removal of
                Tobey; also Marston and Stevens. This will make Rome howl. Even if we can't effect
                the ruin of these scoundrels, it will make a prodigious uproar to roll up several
                thousand signatures against their retention, and meanwhile I will subject them to
                the
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.03048.018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>noble art of
                composition, and my pen will blacken them forever.</p>
            <p>Depend upon it, we are going to have music. I hope I shall see everything the press
                has. I saw the Boston Sunday Herald, with your rendition poem printed with splendid
                effect. Shall watch the Boston papers. Charley was going up to Boston, and would
                have made me an exhaustive report on the <hi rend="underline">roots</hi> of the matter, but unluckily has been
                ordered to Memphis. Too bad!</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc.03048.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc.03048.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
