<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03070">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 20 February
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03070</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 20 February 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-02-20" xml:id="dat1">February 20, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-06-04" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-25" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-19" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-12-12" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03070.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes June 18 1888</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Life-Saving,</name>
                    <date when="1883-02-20" rend="right">February 20, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have sent you the <hi rend="underline">MS</hi> of my letter to Bucke. It goes this day by Adams' Express,
                addressed to you.</p>
            <p>I sent you a card this morning just before your letter came. There is not the least
                bit of "pestering" in the matter, and of course I appreciate the necessity for
                despatch. I only got
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03070.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     the <hi rend="underline">MS</hi> from R M. B. on Saturday, and
                set to work revising it the next day. I am so driven with work, and so weary and
                worn, that I cannot always be as quick as I would like to in these offices. The
                collection of my anti-Comstock letters has been positively prevented up to date, by
                simple lack of time. I shall soon have some let up. We have had a horrid fight with
                the Navy, and
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03070.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                flaxed them awfully&#8212;rousing Congress and the Seaboard upon them. I send you a
                pamphlet, which has some of the shrapnel we swept their decks with. The paper on
                Life-Saving transfer is mine&#8212;some touches in the others. I was thinking of you
                when I wrote the first and third of my three reasons against transfer.</p>
            <p>I am rejoiced that the G. G. P. still seems
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03070.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     good in your eyes. I should be
                glad to leave out some sentences in the last page, and originally intended to, but
                thinking it over, could not see my way clear, inasmuch as the whole publication is a
                matter of history, and ought to stand, follies and all, and several of my abusive
                critics at the time quoted the very passages I want to omit, for animadversion,
                which makes it more difficult
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03070.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    
                now to withdraw them. Do you see my dilemma? The sentences
                sending the pamphlet to a number of persons named on the last page, are an
                absurdity, yet I don't see very well how I can honorably back out of it now, and
                escape twitting. How does this view strike you?</p>
            <p>It was Bucke's wish that I should write the prefaratory letter I send, and I accepted
                the
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03070.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> chance of
                supplementing the pamphlet with a few remarks upon the Harlan transaction; of paying
                my respects to some of your recent critics, teaching them that there are blows to
                take as well as give; and of putting you, where you properly belong, in the line
                of succession from Shakespeare, which will make some of our literati howl. I hope
                you will think it good, and
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03070.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                     effective. Like everything I write, it has been done in a
                hurry, and without those leisures of the soul which are requisite to satisfactory
                work.</p>
            <p>I trust it will be in good type. Where is it to go? The pamphlet, of course, belongs
                to the appendix. Let me have proof of all, which I will return promptly.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="underline">MS</hi>. on copying press paper is my little
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03070.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     tilt with Lanman, and should come
                on <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the pamphlet in the appendix. Bucke wanted it at first, but in his last
                letter thinks it best to omit it, although he leaves it to me. Now I think it ought
                to go in, as it finishes the Harlan affair handsomely. But do as you think best. It
                is a rather crushing rejoinder to Lanman, and a punishment to Stoddard, who is
                awfully mean, and it has a good effect of <hi rend="underline">tone</hi> after the
                fiery pamphlet.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03070.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
           
            <p>I hope Bucke's book will be a success. It comes in good time. He has a rare chance. I
                aimed, also, in my contribution to the volume, to add to its interest and
                attractiveness.</p>
            <p>I see by the extracts in Sunday's <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> that you are in the Carlyle and Emerson
                letters. Did you see it? I shall
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03070.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     want to see the volume. The
                letter, as printed, is very characteristic of Emerson&#8212;his reserve, his
                shrinking, like a woman's, because of rebuff; his deceptive concessions to the
                enemy, in a vein of pleasantry, almost like irony, almost like a sneer, when he says
                the book "wanted good morals so much" that he did not send it. Of
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03070.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                     course, some
                people will take a different view. But I think I understand Emerson's real feeling,
                which is in his first letter to you, and there is no denying it.</p>
            <p>I am suspicious of Professor Norton as an editor of this correspondence. I hope he
                would not suppress things favorable to you, but have little faith in him since I
                read a sketch of his lecture on Greek art, in
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03070.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     which he held that the later Greek
                sculpture began to be indecent with nudity&#8212;the great or earlier Greek being
                always draped, as in the work of Phidias; which precious assertion made me think of
                the Panathenaic frieze of Phidias where a row of soldiers charges, all naked, and the
                phallus in each man not only bare, but erected&#8212;stiff with valor&#8212;which is
                good for Professor Norton! Selah! I must close. More anon.</p>
            <closer>
                
                <signed rend="right">W.D.O'C</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
