<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05281">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 10 February
                    [1881]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt> 
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05281</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 10 February [1881]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-02-10" xml:id="dat1">February 10, 1881</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 3-4 Reel 2-3</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt
                    Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-09-15">checked transcription against images</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-07" who="#ss">images added, enclosures added, annotations
                adjusted</change>
            <change when="2014-05-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-04-17" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-18" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-02-27" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.00991_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">'81</note>

                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date when="1881-02-10" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Feby</abbr><expan>February</expan></choice> 10.</date>
                        <name type="place">Glasshouse <lb/>Shinrone <lb/>Ireland</name>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>

                <p>Thank you very much<ptr target="n1027"/> for the article in the <choice>
                        <abbr>N.A.</abbr>
                        <expan>North American</expan>
                    </choice> Review, received this morning.<ptr target="loc.05281_n1"/> I was
                    delighted with it. I agree entirely with all you say there about the American
                    poets&#8212;</p>
                <p>&#947;&#972;&#957;&#953;&#956;&#959;&#957; &#948;&#8050;
                    &#960;&#959;&#953;&#951;&#964;&#8052;&#957; &#7938;&#957; &#959;&#8016;&#967;
                    &#949;&#8021;&#961;&#959;&#953;&#962; &#7956;&#964;&#953;<ptr
                        target="loc.05281_n2"/></p>
                <p>And while I was staying in Dresden lately I heard a great deal of Wagner's music,
                    and was greatly struck with the resemblance of the artistic impression he
                    leaves, to yours. There is another great artist in whom I am sure you would have
                    noticed the spirit of the new influence if you could stand for an hour in a
                    roomful of his paintings in the London gallery&#8212;I mean Turner. Nature with
                    him is something quite different from what passes for Nature in most landscape
                    painters&#8212;alive and free, and full of divinity and mystery&#8212;no ind<gap reason="damage"/>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.00992_large.jpg" type="verso"/>work&#8212;his
                    immense audacity all the more striking because not in the least theatric, (as,
                    e.g. Victor Hugo's).</p> 
                <p>The Land League has taken the first step towards destruction. It has declared
                    open war against honest dealing. I send you a letter of mine to the "Freeman's
                    Journal" (the Home Rule and Catholic newspaper of Ireland)<ptr target="loc.05281_n3"/>&#8212;which by a
                    strange coincidence appeared on the very day in which a report was published of
                    the meeting of the Central Committee of the League in which the previous
                    principle of the League&#8212;fair rents&#8212;was abandoned. I send you a bit
                    of Mr. Dillon's<ptr target="loc.05281_n5"/> speech on the occasion. I believe
                    this new manifesto of the League a most unwise as well as immoral step&#8212;it
                    will instantly sift out the good men. What a monstrous thing it is to say that
                    if a landlord differs from his tenant on the rightness of a political act like
                    Davitt's arrest,<ptr target="loc.05281_n4"/> the tenant is absolved from his
                    duty of paying his debts! Michael Davitt is a man whom nearly every one honours
                    &amp; many love. He is incapable of doing anything <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                        facs="loc_af.00993_large.jpg" type="recto"/> unworthy, but he is very
                    capable of doing something for which the Government would be compelled to arrest
                    him. He is well-known to be a rebel; and though his arrest would be a hateful
                    &amp; shameful act, if only done on grounds which everyone is aware of, yet I
                    believe the Government is in possession of information which cannot yet be
                    revealed, but which will show their action to have been a sad political
                    necessity. I hope he will soon be released again.</p>
                <p>I have sent an order for &#163;1-7-0. for the Leaves of Grass&#8212;on 'Camden Post Office.' Please acknowledge by
                    postcard when you are paid. I have the receipt.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed rend="right"><hi rend="underline">T W H Rolleston</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_af.00994_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_af.00996_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure" subtype="printed">

                <head type="main-authorial" rend="center"><hi rend="bold"><handShift rend="printed"
                        />TOTAL REPUDIATION OF RENTS.</hi></head>
                <head type="main-authorial" rend="center"><handShift rend="printed"/>TO THE EDITOR
                    OF THE FREEMAN.</head>
                <dateline><name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>Glasshouse, Shinrone,</name>
                    <date when="1881-02-06"><handShift rend="printed"/>Feb. 6.</date></dateline>
                <p>
                    <handShift rend="printed"/>SIR&#8212;At more than one late meeting of the Land
                    League it has been put before the peasantry as a possible, or even probable,
                    contingency that they shall be called upon by their leaders to combine in a
                    universal strike against all rent whatsoever. This course, as a return blow for
                    the expected evictions, has actually been suggested and defended not long ago by
                    a Catholic priest at a public meeting. Surely it behoves the leaders of the
                    agitation to see that no ground is given to the tenantry for supposing that such
                    a proposal could ever be authoritatively endorsed by the central committee of
                    the League. For it would be, indeed, a lamentable thing if the League should
                    allow itself to be exasperated by anything the Government or the landlords may
                    do into justifying the accusations of dishonest teaching which are at present so
                    freely and so falsely showered upon it. A tenant has
                    undoubtedly a perfect right to refuse to pay an unjust rent&#8212;to
                    allow himself to be taxed for the improvements, extending often to reclamation
                    of waste soil, which his own energy and labour have effected. The law of
                    contract does not touch that question at all, for the contracts were made upon
                    the false assumption that landlords have an absolute proprietorial right in the
                    soil which they are said to own;&#8212; and it seems ridiculous to say that the
                    tenantry of a district have not a right to unite in refusing to hold social
                    intercourse with persons who, by taking farms from which others have been
                    unjustly evicted, prevent the landlords from suffering the natural consequences
                    of powers wrongfully held and tyrannously used. But, sir, although the
                    principles of property in land cannot be the same as those of property of a
                    movable and unlimited description, still it is certain that if any man has any
                    right to anything, the landlords of Ireland have a right to a just profit out of
                    their acres, or a just compensation if they are to be handed over to a peasant
                    proprietary. And if the tenants should, as is proposed, universally refuse to
                    pay any rent to any landlord, it would be nothing less than an act of national
                    dishonesty such as might well make every honourable Irishman ashamed of his
                    country. Let no one try to persuade himself that the act would not be dishonest
                    at all. If not dishonest, then in Heaven's name let it be done at once! Let not a
                    single tenant be kept for a day out of a penny of what is rightly his. Why,
                    indeed, should he not go to his landlord's house and take back by force, or by
                    lawful stealth, the money of which he has been unjustly defrauded? But this has
                    never been proposed; and the fact that total repudiation has always been kept in
                    reserve has a stroke of revenge for a Coercion Bill, or a week Land Bill, shows
                    that its proposers have some consciousness of its essentially unprincipled
                    nature.</p>
                <p> And even as a stroke of revenge how futile it would be, and how futile if
                    regarded as a step towards a solution of the land question! Does anyone
                    seriously think that the Government would be moved to do justice to Ireland
                    because the Irish do injustice to their landlords? The Government does not care
                    one straw for the Irish landlords as landlords. It cares a great deal more for
                    the tenantry as tenantry. Undoubtedly, many landlords would be ruined; but the
                    Government would not find that fact in the least intolerable. They would simply
                    wait unitl the dishonest combination had broken up, as it inevitably would, by
                    internal disagreements; and then assert, with irresistible force, the supremacy
                    of the moral law. And then the last state of the Irish tenantry, in spite of the
                    short-lived prosperity which they might enjoy, would be many times worse than
                    the first. They would have alienated their warmest and most powerful
                    sympathisers, and brought into action against their cause a force which no
                    political or social combination has ever successfully resisted, <gap
                        reason="cut away"/> aversion of all righteous men.&#8212;I am, sir,</p>
                <signed rend="right"><gap reason="cut away"/> William Rolleston.</signed>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure" subtype="printed">
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_af.00995_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p><unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">thrown</unclear> into a panic of such proceedings. Now, when speaking
                    here last Friday I advised the people belonging to any branch of the League to
                    strike entirely against the payment of rent when an attempt was made to break
                    up the organisation in their neighbourhood (hear, hear). I wish to have that
                    point distinctly understood. I conceive it to be a very important point in the
                    carrying out of our policy. I don't mean that the arrest of any individual in a
                    neighbourhood should be taken as a challenge, and the cause of a strike against
                    rent. But I do mean that the anticipation of the Coercion Act to cause arrest of
                    the leading Land Leaguers of the neighbourhood, the officers of the executive,
                    the secretaries or presidents of a branch, in that case I do say that all the
                    members of the branches are bound by their loyalty to the organisation; and if
                    they don't mean to prove themselves to be cowards, and to give up the battle
                    entirely, to accept that as a challenge of war, and to resist by every means in
                    their power short of physical force, which they are not in a position to use
                    with success (hear, hear), but every other means (and I don't go into all the
                    means, I leave that to their ingenuity to devise) to resist and obstruct the
                    levying of rent in that neighbourhood, until the Leaguers in their
                    constitutional action are set at liberty again, when they can revert to the
                    original policy of the League&#8212;that is, fair rents. Now, I would wish to
                    note here that I am thoroughly convinced if the members of the local branches of
                    the League adopt that policy that their position is absolutely impregnable. It
                    don't matter if our central office be broken up&#8212;if we all be
                    arrested&#8212;if all our organisers are arrested&#8212;if the people stand by
                    that one advice&#8212;or rather two pieces of advice&#8212;to maintain over the
                    country, in the local leagues, the <choice>
                        <sic>the</sic>
                        <corr/>
                    </choice> policy which we have taught during the past year, and bring the
                    organisation to bear in their neighbourhood, to adopt it in all proper cases by
                    declaring war on the landlords and obstructing by every means in their power the
                    payment of any rent at all (applause) &#8212; these two methods, or plans of
                    action, coupled with the determination not to be driven into acts of violence,
                    personal violence of any kind (hear, hear) which would give the Government an
                    excuse; if this is acted on the result will place the people in a perfectly
                    impregnable position (hear, hear). I would also say&#8212;and I think this is a
                    matter of the greatest importance in the view of the proceedings of certain
                    gentlemen who call themselves justice of the peace&#8212;that wherever a landlord <hi rend="underline">makes himself prominent in persecuting
                        the Land Leaguers, or makes himself prominent, in rejoicing at the arrest of
                        Mr. Davitt,</hi> or any other unconstitutional proceedings of the
                    Government, that it is the duty of the League in his neighbourhood to accept
                    such proceedings&#8212;such prosecution on his part&#8212;or such obvious
                    insults to the people, as a declaration of war; and they should organise on his
                    estate a thorough strike <choice>
                        <sic>againstrent</sic>
                        <corr>against rent</corr>
                    </choice>, so as to bring him to reason. You see that our policy always has been
                    to act in a way consistent with the strongest dictates of morality, even of
                    those who hold that landlords are entitled to a fair rent, on which there is
                    some difference of opinion. We accept that distinction of morality up to the
                    present. We have said to the people as long as the landlords have acted with
                    some show of fairness to act towards them with fairness and justice; but where
                    the landlords approve openly of the present coercion&#8212;of the Government, or
                    make themselves the instruments of persecuting men who have committed no breach
                    of the law, and availing themselves of monstrous powers, treat those men as
                    criminals, we must declare war upon them by whatever means lie to our hand. If
                    we <unclear reason="cut away" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">h</unclear>ad greater power <unclear reason="cut away" resp="#nhg" cert="high">we</unclear> would declare
                    war upon them in a very short, effectual, and swift way (hear, hear). But we
                    must recognise the situation as practical men, and must not play into their hands, but must simply use the <gap
                        reason="cut away"/> lie to our bands; and remember <gap reason="cut away"/>
                    perfectly justified morally <gap reason="cut away"/> when they adopt the <gap
                        reason="cut away"/> have <gap reason="cut away"/> Now.<gap reason="cut away"
                    /></p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
