<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04055">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 27 January 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04055</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">171&#8211;172</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 27 January 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-01-27" xml:id="dat1">January 27, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-01" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">112 Madison Ave.,</name>
                    <date when="1879-01-27" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Jan.</abbr><expan>January</expan></choice> 27, '79.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Are you never coming?<ptr target="n0259"/> I do long &#38; long to see you. I am beginning to like New York better than I did and to have pleasant times. Had some friendly chats with Kate Hillard<ptr target="n0302"/> last week, &#38; went with her to call on Mrs. Putman Jacobi,<ptr target="n1508"/> who has a little baby 3 weeks old &#38; is still in her room, but has got through very nicely&#8212;She talks well, doesn't she? &#38; has a face with plenty of individuality in it. Also we went together on Saturday again to one of Miss Booth's<ptr target="n3017"/> receptions, &#38; there met Mrs. Croly,<ptr target="n1507"/> &#38; had the best talk about you I have had this long while. I like her cordiality&#8212;we are going to her reception on Sunday &#38; to one at Mrs. Bigelow's<ptr target="n1509"/> Wednesday. It is true there is not much that can be called social enjoyment at these crowded receptions, but they enable you to start many acquaintanceships, some of which turn out lasting good. We had some fine harp playing &#38; a witty recital at Miss Booth's. Miss Selous is back in America. I should not wonder if she comes on here soon. Bee<ptr target="n1512"/> is living at the Dispensary now, instead of in the Hospital, &#38; finds the comparatively outdoor life&#8212;&#38; the freedom from being "whistled" for all hours of the day and night as she was there&#8212;a wonderful refreshment. That coloured lady, Mrs. Wiley, whom you met once at our house, is her fellow labourer &#38; room mate at the Dispensary. Bee likes her much. I am not sure whether you know the Gilders?<ptr target="n1034"/> We spent a couple of hours delightfully with them yesterday afternoon. She has a very attractive face, a musical voice, &#38; such a sweet smile. They are going to Europe for a four months' holiday this spring. I admire the simple, unconventional way in which they live. Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> is working away in the best spirits. He is going to paint that bowling alley subject on a large scale. Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> is sitting by me with her nose in the French Dictionary, working away at a novel of Balzac's. I have had scarcely any letters from England lately!&#8212;and the papers bring none but dismal tidings; nevertheless I don't believe our sun is going down yet awhile&#8212;we shall emerge from this dark crisis the better, not the worse, because compelled to grapple with the evils that have caused it, instead of passively enduring them. Please give friendly remembrance from me to your brothers &#38; sister. Have you been at Kirkwood lately, I wonder? I suppose Timber Creek is frozen over. Good-bye, dear Friend. Write soon, or better still Come!</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">A. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
