<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00827">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 13 May 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="lh">Luke Hollis</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00827</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">222&#8211;223</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 13 May 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-05-13">May 13, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#lh" when="2009-08-26">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-07">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1864-05-13">May 13 1864 | 2 o'clock p m</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wrote you a hurried letter late yesterday afternoon, but left it myself at the P O in time for the mail&#8212;you ought to have got it this forenoon, or afternoon at furthest&#8212;I sent you two letters yesterday&#8212;I hope the carrier brings you your letters the same day&#8212;I wrote to the Brooklyn postmaster about it&#8212;</p>
            <p>I have heard from George up to Tuesday morning last, 10th, till which time he was safe&#8212;the battle of Friday 6th was very severe&#8212;George's co. K lost one acting Lt Sturgis killed, 2 men killed, 4 wounded&#8212;as I wrote yesterday I have seen here Corp Fred Sanders of Co K who was wounded in side, nothing serious, in Friday's fight, &amp; came up here&#8212;I also talked with Sgt Brown,<ptr target="loc.00827_n1"/> co F, 51st&#8212;rather badly wounded in right shoulder&#8212;Sanders said when he left Tuesday morning, he heard (or saw them there, I forget which) the 51st &amp; its whole division were on guard duty toward the rear&#8212;the 9th Corps however has had hard fighting since, but whether the division, or brigade the 51st is in, was in the fights of Tuesday, 10th (a pretty severe one,) or Wednesday I cannot yet tell, &amp; it is useless to make calculations&#8212;&amp; the only way is to wait &amp; hope for the best&#8212;as I wrote yesterday there were some 20 of 51st reg't killed &amp; 50 wounded in Friday's battle, 6th inst&#8212;</p>
            <p>I have seen Col LeGendre, he is here in Washington, not far from where I am&#8212;485 12th st is his address&#8212;poor man, I felt sorry indeed for him, he is badly wounded &amp; disfigured, he is shot through the bridge of the nose, &amp; left eye probably lost&#8212;I spent a little time with him this forenoon&#8212;he is suffering very much&#8212;spoke of George very kindly, said "your brother is well"&#8212;his orderly told me he saw him (George) Sunday night last well&#8212;Fred McReady is wounded in hip, I believe bone fractured, bad enough, but not deeply serious&#8212;I cannot hear of his arrival here, if he comes I shall find him immediately &amp; take care of him myself&#8212;he is probably yet at Fredericksburgh, but will come up I think<ptr target="loc.00827_n2"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Yesterday &amp; to-day the badly wounded are coming in&#8212;the long lists of <hi rend="italic">previous arrivals</hi>, (I suppose they are all reprinted at great length in N Y papers)<ptr target="loc.00827_n3"/> are of men ¾ths of them quite slightly wounded, &amp; the rest hurt pretty bad&#8212;I was thinking, mother, if one could <hi rend="italic">see</hi> the men who arrived in the first squads, of two or three hundred at a time, one wouldn't be alarmed at those terrible long lists&#8212;Still there is a sufficient sprinkling of deeply distressing cases&#8212;I find my hands full all the time, with new &amp; old cases&#8212;poor suffering young men, I think of them, &amp; do try, Mother, to do what I can for them, (&amp; not think of the vexatious skedaddlers &amp; merely scratched ones, of whom there are too many lately come here)&#8212;</p>
            <p>Dearest Mother, I hope you &amp; all are well&#8212;you must keep a good heart&#8212;still the fighting is very mixed, but it <hi rend="italic">seems steadily turning into real successes for Grant</hi>&#8212;the news to-day here is very good&#8212;you will see it in N Y papers&#8212;I steadily believe Grant is going to succeed, &amp; that we shall have Richmond&#8212;but O what a price to pay for it&#8212;We have had a good rain here &amp; it is pleasanter &amp; cooler&#8212;I shall write very soon again&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
