<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00393">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 16 April 1860</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00393</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">15-17</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 16 April 1860</title>
               <date when="1860-04-16">April 16, 1860</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-14">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Jamaica</name>
                  <date when="1860-04-16">April 16th 1860</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I was at home yesterday as usual  everything is going on about the same. Andrew has recovered in a great measure,<ptr target="loc.00393_n1"/> so that he sits up and would probably have been out-doors but the weather has been very wet and cold here for the last week. Mother herself I think is not very well. she has a bad cold that seems to pull her down. I have got one of the worst colds I ever had, and feel extremely unlike myself, still anything of that kind sits lighter on me than on one of Mother's age, and this morning Ed. seemed to be quite sick, that is he couldn't eat and complained of a bad pain in his side, however Mother put a mustard plaster on him and he felt considerably better when I left home.</p>
            <p>Mattie and George, the rest of "the family" are well. The Mr Brown<ptr target="loc.00393_n2"/> who has rented the lower part of the house has sent a number of things to the house, carpets &amp;c. Mother has let him fix the front parlor and she has emigrated and taken posession of your room. The Moore people<ptr target="loc.00393_n3"/> have not moved yet, and I believe do not intend to till 7 of May</p>
            <p>The Water Works men are all trembling in our boots, the [prospects?] being that we are all going to be kicked out, neck and heels, from the chief down to the Axeman. It seems that Mr F. Spinola<ptr target="loc.00393_n4"/> started a bill at Albany some time last winter trying to oust the new commissioners (King, Lewis &amp;c &amp;c)<ptr target="loc.00393_n5"/>  well someone made an amendment casting out the present old Com. the new Com. Chief Eng. &amp;c all the way through, and appointing Mr McElroy<ptr target="loc.00393_n6"/> in place of Mr Kirkwood.<ptr target="loc.00393_n7"/> It has passed one house, and I guess the chances are abt even for its passing the other, as Wells the Contractor<ptr target="loc.00393_n8"/> is helping it with all the power he can muster. I think it will be a dark day for the B. W. W. if he succeeds, but I suppose to the victor belongs the spoils. I know I ain't going to worry, if it does go through.<ptr target="loc.00393_n9"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mother wants me to be sure and tell you that you must bring her one of those books by the authoress of "Consuelo"<ptr target="loc.00393_n10"/> also Redpath's "<hi rend="italic">John Brown</hi>"<ptr target="loc.00393_n11"/>  she says you needn't send them as that would involve cost, but to surely remember to bring them with you when you come home.</p>
            <p>I read your letter at home.<ptr target="loc.00393_n12"/> I am glad that you are having so good a time and that your book has such a good prospect of success. I sincerely hope you will meet with no disappointment.</p>
            <p>Write me again Walt. I like much to hear how you are getting along. I shall write to you again probably next week. Mattie sends her love.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Your affectionate Brother Jeff.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
