<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00614">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Benton H. Wilson to Walt Whitman, 16 December 1866</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Benton H. Wilson</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00614</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">214-215</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Benton H. Wilson</author>
               <title>Benton H. Wilson to Walt Whitman, 16 December 1866</title>
               <date when="1866-12-16">December 16, 1866</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Wilson, Benton H.">Benton H. Wilson</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-13">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-18">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear Friend Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="loc.00614_n100"/> received your kind and welcome leter of the 13th inst and I assure you I was very glad to hear from you again and to hear that you are in good health and hope you will escape from any more attacks of Neuralgia.</p>
            <p>I wish if agreeable to yourself to keep up a regular correspondence between us, and perpetuate the friendship commenced in Armory Square Hospital. I think it will be of benefit to me morally and perhaps will not be of any detriment to you.</p>
            <p>A few days ago I picked up a paper through my Friend Hamilton containing an article regarding Walt Whitman the Poet which was the first intimation I had of your being an author. I will send you the paper if you wish. I would like very much to read your works for I have heard my Father speak a few days ago of your Leaves of Grass and says it is well suited to the American People. Father has been here visiting me for a few days but has gone away now. he borrowed Leaves of Grass, of a friend of his here several years ago I believe, I have never seen any of your works. The weather has been very Cold for the past week and this morning it commenced to snow and has not stopped yet at 4 P.M. and I think we are going to have some sleighing for Christmas. I hope our political troubles will soon cease and the country get settled but I can not endorse the policy of President Johnson for I do not believe it is right to place the rebels in office or to allow them to vote until they are thoroughly repentant.</p>
            <p>I must draw my letter to a close for this time, and hope I shall hear from you soon again. I hope you will have a merry Christmas and a happy New Year.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>With love I remain your sincere Friend.</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
