<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00886">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Lewis K. Brown, 1 August 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00886</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cwl">The Correspondence, Volume I: 1842&#8211;1867</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1961</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">119-121</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Lewis K. Brown, 1 August 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-08-01">August 1, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Brown, Lewis K.">Lewis K. Brown</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-03-04">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-25">proofread and modified; need to return to address queries</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington </name>
                  <date when="1863-08-01">August 1 1863</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Both your letters have been received, Lewy<ptr target="loc.00886_n2"/>&#8212;the second one came this morning, &amp; was welcome, as any thing from you will always be, &amp; the sight of your face welcomer than all, my darling&#8212;I see you write in good spirits, &amp; appear to have first-rate times&#8212;Lew, you must not go around too much, nor eat &amp; drink too promiscuous, but be careful &amp; moderate, &amp; not let the kindness of friends carry you away, lest you break down again, dear son&#8212;I was at the hospital yesterday four or five hours, was in ward K&#8212;Taber<ptr target="loc.00886_n3"/> has been down sick, so he had to lay abed, but he is better now, &amp; goes around as usual&#8212;Curly<ptr target="loc.00886_n4"/> is the same as usual&#8212;most of the others are the same&#8212;there have been quite a good many deaths&#8212;the young man who lay in bed 2 with a very bad leg is dead&#8212;I saw Johnny Mahay<ptr target="loc.00886_n5"/> in ward E&#8212;poor fellow, he is very poorly, he is very thin, &amp; his face is like wax&#8212;Lew, I must tell you what a curious thing happened in the chaplain's<ptr target="loc.00886_n6"/> house night before last&#8212;there has been a man in ward I, named Lane, with two fingers amputated, very bad with gangrene, so they removed him to a tent by himself&#8212;last Thursday his wife came to see him, she seemed a nice woman but very poor, she stopt at the chaplain's&#8212;about 3 o'clock in the morning she got up &amp; went to the sink, &amp; there she gave birth to a child, which fell down the sink into the sewer runs beneath, fortunately the water was not turned on&#8212;the chaplain got up, carried Mrs Lane out, &amp; then roused up a lot of men from the hospital, with spades &amp;c. dug a trench outside, &amp; got into the sink, &amp; took out the poor little child, it lay there on its back, in about two inches of water&#8212;well, strange as it may seem, the child was alive, (it fell about five feet through the sink)&#8212;&amp; is now living &amp; likely to live, is quite bright, has a head of thick black hair&#8212;the chaplain took me in yesterday, showed me the child, &amp; Mrs Jackson, his wife, told me the whole story, with a good deal I havn't told you&#8212;&amp; then she treated me to a good plate of ice cream&#8212;so I staid there nearly an hour &amp; had quite a pleasant visit. Mrs Lane lay in an adjoining room.</p>
            <p>Lew, as to me &amp; my affairs there is nothing very new or important&#8212;I have not succeeded in getting any employment here yet, except that I write a little (newspaper correspondence &amp;c), barely enough to pay my expenses&#8212;but it is my own fault, for I have not tried hard enough for any thing&#8212;the last three weeks I have not felt very well&#8212;for two or three days I was down sick, for the first time in my life, (as I have never before been sick)&#8212;I feel pretty fair to-day&#8212;I go around most every day the same as usual. I have some idea of giving myself a furlough of three or four weeks, &amp; going home to Brooklyn, N Y, but I should return again to Washington, probably. Lew, it is pretty hot weather here, &amp; the sun affects me&#8212;(I had a sort of sun stroke about five years ago)&#8212;You speak of being here in Washington again about the last of August&#8212;O Lewy, how glad I should be to see you, to have you with me&#8212;I have thought if it could be so that you, &amp; one other person &amp; myself could be where we could work &amp; live together, &amp; have each other's society, we three, I should like it so much&#8212;but it is probably a dream&#8212;</p>
            <p>Well, Lew, they had the great battle of Gettysburgh, but it does not seem to have settled any thing, except to have killed &amp; wounded a great many thousand men&#8212;It seems as though the two armies were falling back again to near their old positions on the Rappahannock&#8212;it is hard to tell what will be the next move&#8212;yet, Lewy, I think we shall conquer yet&#8212;I don't believe it is destined that this glorious Union is to be broken up by all the secesh south, or copheads north either&#8212;</p>
            <p>Well, my darling, I have scribbled you off something to show you where I am &amp; that I have rec'd your welcome letters&#8212;but my letter is not of much interest, for I don't feel very bright to-day&#8212;Dear son, you must write me whenever you can&#8212;take opportunity when you have nothing to do, &amp; write me a good long letter&#8212;your letters &amp; your love for me are very precious to me, for I appreciate it all, Lew, &amp; give you the like in return. It is now about 3 o'clock, &amp; I will go out &amp; mail this letter, &amp; then go &amp; get my dinner&#8212;So good bye, Lewy&#8212;good bye, my dear son &amp; comrade, &amp; I hope it will prove God's will that you get quite well &amp; sound yet, &amp; have many good years yet&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Address my letters care Major Hapgood, paymaster U S A, cor. 15th &amp; F st Washington D C&#8212;</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
