<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00842">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to N. M. and John B. Pratt, 10 June 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00842</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">263-264</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to N. M. and John B. Pratt, 10 June 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-06-10">June 10, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Pratt, N. M.">N. M. Pratt</persName>
               
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               
               <persName key="Pratt, John B.">John B. Pratt</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-09">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-14">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1865-06-10">June 10, 1865.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Mr. &amp; Mrs. Pratt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As I am visiting your son Alfred<ptr target="loc.00842_n1"/> occasionally, to cheer him up in his sickness in hospital, I thought you might like a few words, though from a stranger, yet a friend to your boy. I was there last night, and sat a while by the bed, as usual, &amp; he showed me the letter he had just received from home. He wrote to you yesterday. He has had diarrhea pretty bad, but is now improved &amp; goes about the hospital&#8212;but as the weather is pretty hot &amp; powerful in the midst of the day, I advised him not to go outdoors much at present. What he wants most is rest, and a chance to get his strength again. I expect he will improve by degrees, &amp; I hope it will not be very long before he will be sent home&#8212;though I don't know, as I am only a friend, occasionally visiting the hospitals. Alfred has good accommodations where he is, &amp; a good doctor, &amp; nursing&#8212;so you must not worry about him. I shall stop &amp; see him a little every day, as he likes to have me, &amp; I like him too. Poor young men, there are hundreds &amp; thousands of them here, wounded or sick, in the great army hospitals&#8212;many of them suffering with amputations &amp; wounds&#8212;others with sickness, &amp; so faint &amp; weak, this weather&#8212;it is enough to make one's heart bleed&#8212;</p>
            <p>As to Alfred, he is comparatively well off, there are so many with bad wounds &amp;c.&#8212;the deaths are quite frequent. He will soon be restored, according to present appearances.</p>
            <p>We are having very hot weather here, &amp; it is dry &amp; dusty&#8212;The City is alive with soldiers from both the Army of the Potomac &amp; the Western Armies, brought here by Sherman. There have been some great Reviews here, as you have seen in the papers&#8212;&amp; thousands of soldiers are going home every day.</p>
            <p>You must write to Alfred often, as it cheers up a boy sick &amp; away from home. Write all about domestic &amp; farm incidents, and as cheerful as may be. Direct to him, in Ward C, Armory Square Hospital, Washington, D. C. Should any thing occur, I will write you again, but I feel confident he will continue doing well. For the present farewell.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
               <address>
               <addrLine>Washington <lb/>D C</addrLine>
            </address>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
