<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00584">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William Wilde Thayer to Walt Whitman, 19 April 1861</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>W.W. Thayer</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="bb2">Brett Barney</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00584</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William Wilde Thayer</author>
               <title>William Wilde Thayer to Walt Whitman, 19 April 1861</title>
               <date when="1861-04-19">April 19, 1861</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Thayer, William Wilde">William Wilde Thayer Thayer</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-12-13">changed 'W. W. Thayer' in TEI header to 'William Wilde Thayer'</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#bbb" when="2010-04-02">corrected </change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-12-14">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-09-23">added encoding for page breaks</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-07-29">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-07">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> 
                  <name type="place">Forest Hill</name> 
                  <date when="1861-03-19">April 19/61</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My Dear Walt.</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Family sickness has prevented an early reply to yours of 12th rec'd three or four days ago.<ptr target="loc.00584_n100"/>
         </p>
            <p>Horace Wentworth has bought of the assignees the stock of T&amp;E.<ptr target="loc.00584_n2"/> In said stock are Plates of Leaves of Grass.  These plates were included in a lot of plates sometime ago mortgaged to Isaac Tower for money we raised of him.  The mortgage purports to belong to Isaac Tower but from all we have seen Wentworth was the real mortgagee &amp; used Tower for a blind&#8212;so that the plates are in W's hands fast &amp; tight.  The assignees threatened at one time to break up the mortgage so as to have Tower's claim come in on a par with those of the general creditors.  But as Wentworth has now possession of our old stock and is actually doing business at 116 Wash. Street, the presumption is that some compromise has been effected between Tower (?) &amp; the assignees <pb facs="loc.00584.002.jpg" type="verso"/>Wentworth/Tower may have consented to release the mortgage &amp; have thus secured a good bargain from the assignees.&#8212;The upshot is that your plates are in Wentworth's hands.&#8212;</p>
            <p>I think you had best correspond with Wentworth &amp; he will answer by hand of our old book keeper Mr. Honeybun whom W. has hired&#8212;</p>
            <p>As Wentworth is an illiterate man and knows not <hi rend="italic">real</hi> merit in literature I think he will not be inclined go to expense extra to make additions to L of G and yet he may&#8212;can't tell.  You had best write him.  He is a man who loves to be wiley sometimes &amp; therefore may defer giving you a <choice>
               <sic>deffinite</sic>
               <corr>definite</corr>
            </choice> answer to your questions of him&#8212;especially in view of the present unsettled condition of the Country. Even <pb facs="loc.00584.003.jpg" type="recto"/>after he makes a promise, the fulfilment is often very tardy<ptr target="loc.00584_n3"/>.&#8212;</p>
            <p>He is our, or rather <hi rend="italic">my</hi> bitter and relentless enemy &amp; therefore it would be a difficult matter for either myself or Eldridge to get any satisfactory knowledge of his intentions with regard to you.</p>
            <p>Things are decidedly uninteresting with me.  I have known the want of money sadly since our failure and the value of true friendship.  I have suffered much mentally; have endured severe discipline; my darling wife has been sick a great deal, and though uncomplaining at my misfortunes, yet worried and <choice>
               <sic>harrassed</sic>
               <corr>harassed</corr>
            </choice> by our deprivations.  I have been unsuccessful in getting employment, though I now hope for a clerkship in our Boston Post office.&#8212;I have the "war fever" very severely, which unlike other fevers with me preys inward and does not show <pb facs="loc.00584.004.jpg" type="verso"/>itself externally.  Nothing but the home duties which <hi rend="italic">for the present</hi> are absolute, prevent a speedy offering of myself to the Government as a soldier.  True I might not prove strong enough for much hard work but I <hi rend="italic">could</hi> fire my gun once and die, for my country.</p>
            <p>My soul swells as I contemplate the mighty issues involved in this contest.  They are not merely the stability of this Government, but the Abolition of slavery which alone is to send this nation to a most glorious destiny.  Either under one confederacy or two, we shall have no peace until slavery is crushed out, even if negotiations for peace between the two sections, permit slavery to still live.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Thayer desires to be remembered to her dear friend Walt Whitman with her best regards for that genial soul and strong man.  She would once more like to meet <pb facs="loc.00584.005.jpg" type="recto"/>him face to face.&#8212;I'm sure I would.</p>
            <p>I have intended many times to write you and as often "backed out."  I wrote you one letter and did not send it because It was not appropriate to your feelings &amp; my own circumstances.</p>
            <p>My dear Walt I am not yet <hi rend="italic">conquered</hi>.  I have everything external to crush me and stinging poverty to freeze my heart, but my <hi rend="italic">day is coming</hi>.  Perhaps for a year I shall live an isolated life, but the events are now combining that shall <choice>
               <sic>develope</sic>
               <corr>develop</corr>
            </choice> for me a destiny unlike my past career.  I know not where my "star" will travel, but that it will course through space &amp; hover over the particular <pb facs="loc.00584.006.jpg" type="verso"/>field of my marked out labors I do not doubt. That field will be extensive and arduous, but not in business life.  I live in hope, golden hope that stands by me still.</p>
            <p>Wentworth has done all he could to prejudice the creditors against us and has lied about us so that many think we are swindlers.  I guess if we had been neither Charley nor myself would be as poor as we are.  The assignees acknowledged after examining our affairs that we have not committed the wholesale robbery ascribed to us by W.&#8212;Yet with all my personal enemies to traduce me, I care not, for conscious within, that their aspersions are unfounded I can afford to be victorious and live.  I <hi rend="italic">will not</hi> be crushed.  I <hi rend="italic">will</hi> live.  God bless you my dear man. How I wish <hi rend="italic">I</hi> could bless you <hi rend="italic">substantially with</hi> a <hi rend="italic">hundred</hi> "spot" but who knows but that in the future I may <pb facs="loc.00584.007.jpg" type="recto"/>be able to be a substantial friend to you.&#8212;Well good bye for now.  I will write you again soon.  Charley sends regards.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>Yours Truly</salute>
               <signed>W.W. Thayer</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>
               <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#kk">Newcomb</unclear> has proved himself a damned traitor to our interests.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
