<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00817">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 10 April 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00817</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">209&#8211;210</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 10 April 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-04-10">April 10, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-03">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2009-09-02">updated annotations according to new correspondence sytlesheet guidelines</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-03">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1864-04-10">April 10th 1864.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I rec'd your letter &amp; sent the one you sent for George immediately&#8212;he must have got it the next day&#8212;I had got one from him before yours arrived&#8212;I mean to go to Annapolis &amp; see him&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, we expect a commencement of the fighting below very soon, there is every indication of it&#8212;we have had about as severe rain storms here lately as I ever see&#8212;it is middling pleasant now&#8212;there are exciting times in Congress<ptr target="loc.00817_n1"/>&#8212;the Copperheads are getting furious, &amp; want to recognize the Southern Confederacy&#8212;this is a pretty time to talk of recognizing such villains after what they have done, and after what has transpired the last three years&#8212;After first Fredericksburgh I felt discouraged myself, &amp; doubted whether our rulers could carry on the war&#8212;but that has past away, the war <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be carried on&#8212;&amp; I would willingly go myself in the ranks if I thought it would profit more than at present, &amp; I don't know sometimes but I shall as it is&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, you dont know what a feeling a man gets after being in the active sights &amp; influences of the camp, the Army, the wounded &amp;c.&#8212;he gets to have a deep feeling he never experienced before<ptr target="loc.00817_n2"/>&#8212;the flag, the tune of Yankee Doodle, &amp; similar things, produce an effect on a fellow never such before&#8212;I have seen some bring tears on the men's cheeks, &amp; others turn pale, under such circumstances<ptr target="loc.00817_n3"/>&#8212;I have a little flag (it belonged to one of our cavalry reg'ts) presented to me by one of the wounded&#8212;it was taken by the secesh in a cavalry fight, &amp; rescued by our men in a bloody little skirmish, it cost three men's lives, just to get one little flag, four by three&#8212;our men rescued it, &amp; tore it from the breast of a dead rebel&#8212;all that just for the name of getting their little banner back again&#8212;this man that got it was very badly wounded, &amp; they let him keep it&#8212;I was with him a good deal, he wanted to give me something he said, he didn't expect to live, so he gave me the little banner as a keepsake&#8212;I mention this, Mother, to show you a specimen of the feeling&#8212;there isn't a reg't, cavalry or infantry, that wouldn't do the same, on occasion&#8212;</p>
            <p>Tuesday morning April 12th
Mother, I will finish my letter this morning&#8212;it is a beautiful day to-day&#8212;I was up in Congress very late last night,<ptr target="loc.00817_n4"/> the house had a very excited night session about expelling the men that want to recognize the Southern Confederacy&#8212;You ought to hear the soldiers talk&#8212;they are excited to madness&#8212;we shall probably have hot times here not in the Army alone&#8212;the soldiers are true as the north star&#8212;I send you a couple of envelopes, &amp; one to George&#8212;Write how you are, dear Mother, &amp; all the rest&#8212;I want to see you all&#8212;Jeff, my dear brother, I wish you was here, &amp; Mat too&#8212;Write how sis is&#8212;I am well as usual, indeed first rate every way&#8212;I want to come on in a month, &amp; try to print my "Drum Taps"<ptr target="loc.00817_n5"/>&#8212;I think it may be a success pecuniarily too&#8212;Dearest Mother, I hope this will find you entirely well, &amp; dear sister Mat &amp; all.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
