<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05585">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Alfred Janson Bloor to Walt Whitman, 9 June
                    1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Alfred Janson Bloor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05585</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Alfred Janson Bloor</author>
                    <title>Alfred Janson Bloor to Walt Whitman, 9 June 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-06-09" xml:id="dat1">June 9, 1879</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 3-4 Reel 2-3</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Bloor, Alfred Janson">Alfred Janson Bloor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-13" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-08-05" who="#ss">checked, corrected, annotated</change>
            <change when="2014-07-24" who="#bbb">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_ej.00619_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">Holsman Mansion<lb/> Passaic, New Jersey</name>
                    <date when="1879-06-09">9 June '79</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Mr Whitman,<!--<ptr target="med.00639_n2"/>--></salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I got yours of the 24th ult. &#38; also the 
                pamphlets of mine I lent you, therein mentioned&#8212;for which thanks.</p>

            <p>I enclose a copy of the selections you made from my journal, and also an account of
                the information Miss Harris gave me as to what she knew of Mr. Lincoln's
                assassination.<ptr target="loc.05585_n1"/></p>

            <p>Since seeing you I have been all the time intending, but have never yet found leisure
                to hunt thoroughly for those loose sheets which I used sometimes to resort to,
                partly because I was accustomed to write my journal in a hurry&#8212;leaving spaces
                to be filled up at the first opportunity thereafter, &#38; then found I had not left
                myself enough room; and partly as a matter of
                precaution, Washington being most of the war-time virtually, &#38; now &#38; then
                literally, a besieged city; and during the war I wrote a good deal that would not
                have been pleasant to some readers, who might have made things uncomfortable for
                me.</p>

            <p>What has added to my delay in forwarding, is that having an invitation the week
                before last to a morning reception <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc_ej.00620_large.jpg" type="recto"/> at the house of a lady in
                town&#8212;an old Washington friend of both of us&#8212;I thought it possible I might
                meet the former Miss H. there (though she lives in Albany) &#38; get the whole story
                over again from her own lips. It did not happen so however.</p>

            <p>Once written, it was not worth while to amend what I said about the actors, which I
                see you really thought it worth while to print. It was written, like everything else
                of mine, outside of my professional work, (&#38; some of that,) hurriedly, &#38; it
                strikes me I have in my portfolios much that is better than that, unprinted.</p>

            <p>As might be expected, your "May Afternoons" makes excellent reading. (By the way, I
                had my hand somewhat in the making of the Central Park&#8212;having been appointed on
                its architectural staff in 1859 &#38; professionally connected with it until the war). But why,
                studying the Park equipages, should you count on seeing anything in the way of
                "'style' that fully justified itself"?&#8212;and why
                should your "top-loftical" friends, perched up
                on the barouche seats, be otherwise than "ill at ease." Nineteen out of twenty of
                the equipages in the Avenue &#38; Park 
                (those that are not owned by livery stable
                    keepers&#8212;horses, drivers, military cockades &#38;
                all&#8212;though a civilian feels just as happy with one on the coachman's hat)
                belong to men who have made all their money by <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_ej.00621_large.jpg" type="verso"/> less or more&#8212;generally
                more&#8212;questionable coups d'affaires within a decade&#8212;who know the chances
                are they will lose it within a year&#8212;and who are brothers or cousins of more or
                less remote degree, of the journeymen who made their carriages &#38; of the coachman
                who sits on the box. Just as fast (with of course many honorable exceptions) as they
                have made their money, the men have lost their true manliness &#38; the women have
                smothered their real graces in millinery &#38; pearl powder. There is neither an
                aristocracy nor a peasantry in this country&#8212;nothing but a bourgeoisie,
                connected from top to bottom by blood &#38; marriage. The nearest approach to the Old
                World's "higher classes"&#8212;in the sense of the possessors of the culture that
                is likely to come <hi rend="underline">with</hi> birth or <hi rend="underline"
                    >to</hi> genius&#8212;consists of men
                    of letters, art &#38; other
                professions, &#38; of the descendants of colonial families of importance&#8212;and
                few if any of these have money enough to compete with the shifting wealth that comes
                &#38; goes in the hands of commerce &#38; finance. I have had a little to say on
                these matters in a paper recently published, which I read before the N.Y. Municipal
                Society. I will try to spare you a copy if you would like to see it.</p>

            <p>I dare say your correspondence is heavy enough; but I should like to know, at least
                by a postal card, that you have <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_ej.00622_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> received the within. In the summer I run away from office
                interruptions to write&#8212;but it makes no difference whether you address as above,
                or to my office in the city, as my letters are forwarded every day. I suppose however
                I will be apt to get anything a few
                hours earlier if addressed to this place, for I am at present not going to the
                office more than twice a week.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Yours faithfully</salute>
                <signed>A.J. Bloor</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
