<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01436">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">V. D. Davis to Walt Whitman, 26 April 1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>V. D. Davis</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01436</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>V. D. Davis</author>
                    <title>V. D. Davis to Walt Whitman, 26 April 1883</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1883-04-26" xml:id="dat1">April 26, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Davis, V. D.">V. D. Davis</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-18" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-12" who="#no">checked, corrected transcription</change>
            <change when="2014-11-10" who="#ak">corrected transcription and encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-07-18" who="#ss">Transcribed, encoded and annotated.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01436.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">36 South Hill Road</name>
                    <name type="place">Liverpool, S.</name>
                    <date when="1883-04-26">26.4.83.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I posted to you the other day a copy of the London "Inquirer", containing a notice of
                your "Specimen Days &#38; Collect," which I wrote some little time ago.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.01436_n1"/>--> Since then I have been very glad to learn that the book
                is already republished in England, &#38; that a new edition of "Leaves of Grass" is
                to follow.</p>

            <p>I hope you will not consider it an impertinence in quite a young man to write as I
                have done, but I have found so much refreshment &#38; real delight in your books,
                that I was anxious to do what I could to extend the good gift to others.</p>

            <p>If you have time &#38; patience to read my review I should be extremely obliged if
                you would tell me whether <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01436.002_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>there are any mistakes in the statement of facts as to your life.
                It is so easy to be led into inaccuracies, which ought to be corrected.</p>

            <p>I have the "Leaves of Grass" constantly by me, &#38; in the intervals of other work
                am trying to make a study of the book. It seems to me distinctly one of the
                prophetic messages of our day&#8212;a <hi rend="underline">real</hi> voice of our
                best manhood, absolutely free from anything conventional, such as we need to make us
                feel the true grandeur &#38; infinite capabilities of our life, &#38; the divine
                beauty of the universe.</p>

            <p>I am not sure that I altogether understand your message yet, especially with regard
                to the present evil in the world. It seems to me that in the degradation of women,
                &#38; the brutal selfishness of so many men, we have a form <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc.01436.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> of evil that <hi rend="underline"
                    >ought not</hi> to be suffered with patience, or hidden under the soothing light
                of Hegelian Pantheism. On the contrary I feel that it is a
                part of our life where the exercise of human freedom must come in, &#38; feeling
                that this is evil for which we are personally responsible, determine to be rid of it
                as far as we are concerned, &#38; to do what we can to uphold the right principle of
                life, honour for women, continence for men, &#38; the home the centre of all good &#38; sacred
                influence. This I think is essential to the growth of a strong &#38; healthy life,
                morally as well as physically, &#38; to the full enjoyment of all that is good &#38;
                beautiful in the world.</p>

            <p>I shall not be surprised if you have just the same feeling&#8212;but, as I say, I do
                not think I have quite understood the whole of your message yet, &#38; sometimes it
                has seemed to me as though <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01436.004_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> you were too well satisfied with the present condition of our
                life, in such a way as to leave the poisonous canker of vice slowly eating its way
                through society, content to enjoy the <hi rend="underline">picturesque</hi> side of
                even the lowest form of life, instead of rousing men in the strength of their moral
                capacity really to <hi rend="underline">be</hi> men, &#38; to set right whatever is
                wrong through their fault.</p>

            <p>I am afraid you may be much troubled by unknown correspondents, but you have spoken
                to me so much as a friend through your poems, that I feel almost inclined to claim
                the right of friendship in saying what I have&#8212;&#38; I trust that I shall not
                have caused you any annoyance.</p>

            <p>If you can give me any help with regard to the above question, I shall esteem it a
                great kindness; &#38; in any case I assure you of my lasting gratitude for all we
                have received at your hands.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>Believe me</salute>
                <salute>yours very truly</salute>
                <signed rend="right">V. D. Davis.</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
