<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00946">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 18 August 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
<persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00946</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 18 August 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-08-18">August 18, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2014-08-23" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-12">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">added encoding for page breaks</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00946.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Little Compton R. I.</name>
                  <date when="1864-08-18">August 18. 1864. Thursday.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Walt,&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter to Wm. of July 24. he forwarded to me in a letter that I got last evening.<ptr target="loc.00946_n1"/> How glad I was to get it, and to know that you are so much better. I hope you still continue to gain, I hope you are <hi rend="italic">well,</hi> but I do not really expect you to be wholly well until the cool autumn days come, that I so dread, &amp; shrink from.</p>
            <p>I am very glad to get this letter, dear Walt, for I had really begun to wonder why you had so wholly forgotten me. Not one line to <pb facs="loc.00946.002.jpg" type="verso"/>me have you written since leaving Washington, and now that I am away from there I have to wait for news of you in this long, roundabout way. After seeing you every day, &amp; so much of you those last days when you were sick, it seems doubly strange not to have had a word from you. You will not think me foolish if I tell you that it hurt me a little, will you? You know what a foolish, absurd person I am, where I love anyone as I do you, and knowing this, and now I having confessed, you will pardon.</p>
            <p>Did you like my picture? You told William you got my letter, so you must have got the picture enclosed. <pb facs="loc.00946.003.jpg" type="recto"/>It was in my first letter&#8212;I have sent you three, this is my fourth to you, have you got them all? It was too bad that we could not have a good quiet chat on the boat, for I spent the long afternoon there, &amp; it was a very good place for a nice talk.</p>
            <p>I am so glad that there is some hope of your book coming out soon. I long to see it.</p>
            <p>Just think, Walt, of my being a <hi rend="italic">lion</hi> down here on your account, because it is known that I have the honor of your acquaintance. Such is the fact, &amp; I was made to talk two entire evenings about you, &#8212;it is so funny, some time I will <pb facs="loc.00946.004.jpg" type="verso"/>tell you all about it.</p>
            <p>The bathing here is good, &amp; the ocean&#8212;oh! so good. I board at a farm house, &amp; keep as you do early hours,&#8212;up at 6 or earlier &amp; to bed at 9. I have been here two weeks, &amp; am so brown that I could easily pass for a good "contraband," I nearly live out doors. The rocks tempt me, &amp; there I sit &amp; see the waves &amp; foam dash up over them, &amp; it breaks into fine spray, &amp; is so beautiful. I never <hi rend="italic">loved</hi> the sea so much, &amp; I though before I loved it more than any <hi rend="italic">thing.</hi>  How I wish you were here! It would cure you Walt, &amp; how much I should like it. Little <pb facs="loc.00946.005.jpg" type="recto"/>Jeannie enjoys it much, for she has hens, chickens, ducks &amp; the horse to feed. She says tell Walt "I hope he has got all over the sickness, <hi rend="italic">entirely."</hi> She sends love too.</p>
            <p>So it seems that Burnside is Court-martialed&#8212;events seem to prove that Irvinton was right in what he said of Burnside. Charlie says that the Officers say any Commander but Burnside would have taken Petersburg at the last attack.<ptr target="loc.00946_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Howells tells me he has seen your mother, &amp; he is enthusiastic about her.<ptr target="loc.00946_n3"/> Thinks her such a grand old lady as one sees only once in a lifetime.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="loc.00946.006.jpg" type="verso"/>Good bye.</p>
            <p>It is breakfast time, for you must know I have written this before breakfast,&#8212;so good morning, &amp; good bye. How I wish you were here!</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With love always&#8212;</salute>
               <signed>Nelly.</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Have you seen a pretty little poem by Juliette H. Beach called
<hi rend="italic">Claire&#8212;</hi> It was published in the Leader I judge, &amp; I saw it copied;&#8212;from it, I infer that she has a new baby, a girl too.<ptr target="loc.00946_n4"/> Good bye.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nelly.</signed>
            </closer>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
