<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04210">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 20 June 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04210</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">181&#8211;182</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 20 June 1879</title>

                    <date cert="high" when="1879-06-20" xml:id="dat1">June 20, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-01-26" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Glasgow</name>
                    <date when="1879-06-20" rend="right">Friday, June 20, 1879.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>We set foot on dry land again Wednesday morning after a good passage<ptr target="n0259"/>&#8212;not a very smooth one&#8212;and not without four or five days of seasickness, but after that we really enjoyed the sea &#38; the sky&#8212;it was mostly cloudy, but such lovely lights and shades &#38; invigorating breezes! and as we got up into northern latitudes, daylight in the sky all night through. The last three days we had glorious scenery&#8212;sailed close in under the Giant's Causeway on the north coast of Ireland&#8212;great sort of natural ramparts &#38; bastions or rock, wonderfully grand. Then we sailed on Lough Fozle to land a group of Irish folk at Moville&#8212;some of them old people who had not seen Ireland for forty years, and who were so happy they did not know what to do with themselves. And what with this human interest, and the first getting near land again and the rich green-and-golden gorse-covered hills &#38; the setting sun streaming along the beautiful lough with golden light, it was a sight &#38; a time I shall never forget. Then we entered the Firth of Clyde &#38; sailed among the islands&#8212;mountainous Arran, level Bute&#8212;&#38; on the other hand the green hills of Ayr, with pleasant towns nestled under them, sloping to the Clyde&#8212;this was during the night&#8212;we did not go to bed at all it was so beautiful&#8212;&#38; then came a gorgeous sunrise&#8212;&#38; then the landing at Greenock &#38; a short railway journey to Glasgow, the tide not serving to bring our big ship up so far. We had very pleasant (&#38; learned withal) companions on the voyage&#8212;the Professor of Greek &#38; of Philosophy from Harvard and a young student from Concord, all of whom we have seen since we landed and hope to see often again, especially the young student, Frank Bigelow, who is a very nice fellow. Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> enjoyed the voyage much &#38; so did Giddy.<ptr target="n0890"/> Glasgow is a great, solidly built city, very pleasant [in] spite of smoky atmosphere&#8212;full of sturdy, rosy-cheeked people with broad Scotch accent. We have been rushing about shopping&#8212;have not yet seen Per.&#8212;shall meet him at Durham in a week's time &#38; spend a month together there where he will be superintending your works. Meanwhile we are going to Edinburgh for a few days. I kept thinking of you on the voyage, dear friend, &#38; wondering how you would like it&#8211;&#38; whether you could stand being stowed away in the little box-like berth at night. I should recommend any American friend coming over to try this line&#8211;we had a fine ship&#8211;fine officers &#38; crew&#8211;&#38; the latter part, fine scenery. Love to your Brother &#38; Sister &#38; to Mr. Burroughs.<ptr target="n0129"/> Address to me for the present.</p>
            
            <list><item>Care Percy C. Gilchrist<ptr target="n2000"/></item>
            
            <item>Blaenavon</item>
            
            <item>Poutzpool</item>
            
            <item>Mon.</item></list>
            <closer>
                <salute>Love from us all. I shall write soon again. Good-bye dear Friend.</salute>
                <signed rend="center">A. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
