<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00412">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 9 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00412</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">54&#8211;55</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 9 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-09">May 9, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-09-04">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-09">May 9th 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Although I know Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00412_n1"/> intends to write you to-day and send you a little money yet I thought I would jot you a note. My main object is to ask you if you can possibly hear anything of Lane's nephew (or boy as he calls him) as he has always been with him and Lane loves him like a son)  He belongs to the 20th Conn. and was in the 12th Army Corps under Gen Birney<ptr target="loc.00412_n2"/>  The letter of his Company I forget but think it was K. Lane is quite cast down about him, mostly from not hearing from him at all. The boys name is "Horace G. Tarr."<ptr target="loc.00412_n3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Walt, if you should by any chance or inquiry come across him or any news from him wont you please write Lane for I feel real sorry to see him so cast down. I see by some of the papers that quite a number of the 20th Conn. are at Washington in hospital</p>
            <p>I feel thankful indeed that George did not have to go through the dangers of this battle although we know not what is in store for him where he is.<ptr target="loc.00412_n4"/> I do so hope he will be spared to us and that he will come home without ever being injired.</p>
            <p>Everything is moving the same as usual at home  of course we all feel pretty well down-hearted at the news but then we try to look on it in the most favorable light. God only knows what will be the next. I had certainly made up my mind that we should meet with partial success certainly, but it seems otherwise<ptr target="loc.00412_n5"/>
            </p>
            <p>I suppose you are overcrowded with work just now  I cannot see Walt how you can stand it. I am sure that I could never get used to all the scenes of pain and horror that you have to witness  Tis well though that you can do so, for I know that you are doing a great deal of good.</p>
            <p>I suppose you do not have much time to write home  We do not hear from you but seldom now. I suppose however that as long as we dont hear, everything is going as usual with you. We have not heard from either Han or George since I last wrote you  I am getting along first rate just now, make quite a little money and every thing goes well  Mother and Mat and Sis and all are well and send love. Write me Walt</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionatley Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
