<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01878">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William Michael Rossetti to Walt Whitman, 16
                    December [1867]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William Michael Rossetti</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01878</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William Michael Rossetti</author>
                    <title>William Michael Rossetti to Walt Whitman, 16 December [1867]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1867-12-16" xml:id="dat1">December 16, 1867</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rossetti, William Michael">William Michael Rossetti</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-08-08" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-05-03" who="#al">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-10" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01878.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">56 Euston Sq. <lb/>London, N.W.</name>
                    <date when="1867-12-16">16 Decr.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>The receipt of your letter of 3 Decr. this morning <choice><abbr>wd.</abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> have made me feel miserable were it not that before then the matter had already been set right, &amp; my letter notifying that fact very nearly (no doubt) in your hands by this time. My first letter to you was written too much from the impulse of the moment; &amp;, finding soon after from
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01878.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
the publisher's statement that the original plan of the selection <hi rend="underline">could</hi> not be altered, I felt that it was also much better it <hi rend="underline">should</hi> not be altered. I congratulate myself therefore on being quite at one with you concerning that point. Not one syllable of any one of your poems, as presented in my selection, will be altered or omitted: that is the first intention &amp; the final result.</p>
            
            <p>Pray believe me however that, while I understand the latitude your first letter <choice><orig>honoured</orig><reg>honored</reg></choice> me with in its wildest sense, I still meant to take all proper precautions before acting upon it. I wrote
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01878.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
at once to Mr. Conway enquiring whether he put the same interpretation upon it; &amp; his letter in reply (18 Nov., now before me) replies—"I agree with you that Whitman's letter gives you all the liberty you <choice><abbr>cd.</abbr><expan>could</expan></choice> desire." I am now perfectly satisfied that it <choice><abbr>wd.</abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> have been most undesirable for you to give or for me (even if given) to act upon such liberty.</p>
            
            <p>To be <choice><orig>honoured</orig><reg>honored</reg></choice> by your friendship is as great a satisfaction &amp; distinction as my life has presented or ever can present. I respond to it with all warmth &amp; reverence, &amp;; the Atlantic seemed
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01878.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            a very small space between us while I read &amp; re-read your letter.</p>
            
            <p>I read your paper on Democracy (received a few days ago) with great pleasure &amp; interest. I have always felt—&amp; did so markedly while our own recent Reform discussions were going on—one main truth involved in your paper: That, after one has said that such &amp; such people or classes are not exactly fitted to make the best use of political enfranchisement, one has said only a small part of the truth, the further point remaining that to induct these people or classes into the combined 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01878.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                national life, &amp; to constitute that life out of them along with all other classes, is an enormous gain. The consequence is that, with the intensest respect &amp; admiration for Carlyle, I find constantly that to acquiesce in the express views he takes of late years of particular questions <choice><abbr>wd</abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> be simply to abnegate my own identity.</p>
            
            <p>The selection goes on smoothly <choice><orig>tho</orig><reg>though</reg></choice> not fast—the proofs now approaching their close. I suppose the volume will not fall much if at all short of 400 pp.—You may possibly have seen the advertisement of it repeated several times in publications here, as enclosed
    
    <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01878.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
    
    (slip cut from the Athenaeum). The "Portrait" is a re-engraving (head &amp; shoulders only, I believe) of the one in the first Leaves of Grass, <choice><abbr>wh.</abbr><expan>which</expan></choice> was a capital piece of art work. I have not yet seen the reproduction, but trust to find it adequately done.</p>
           
            <closer>
                <salute>Always yours,</salute>
                <signed>W. M. Rossetti</signed>
            </closer>               
        </body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01878.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01878.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
    </text>
</TEI>