<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04051">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Beatrice Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 12 August 1878</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Beatrice Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04051</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">156&#8211;158</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Beatrice Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Beatrice Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 12 August 1878</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1878-08-12" xml:id="dat1">August 12, 1878</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Beatrice">Beatrice Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-06" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-26" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-19" who="#gt">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-01-31" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">New England Hospital</name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Codman Avenue</name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Boston Highlands</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Hospital life is beginning to seem a long-accustomed life.<ptr target="n0260"/> I enjoy all the duties involved &#38; all the human relations. Even getting up in the night is compensated for by yielding a sense of importance &#38; independence. I sleep in a large room with three windows, &#38; three beds in a row. Breakfast at 7, &#38; we are supposed to have seen all our patients before breakfast, but do not keep to that rule.</p>
            
            <p>After breakfast, round to count pulses &#38; respirations, note condition, dress any wound, in charge, etc. At &#189; past 8 o'clock go the rounds with the resident physician (Dr. Berlin), all the students, &#38; superintendent of nurses. Then put up medicine, each for her own patients (about 8 in no.), give electricity, etc. If one's patient has an ache or pain, the nurse whistles for the student (my whistle is 2). She sees the patient orders what is necessary, or if serious reports to Dr. Berlin. Then there is some microscopic work, &#38; copying out the history &#38; daily record of the case &#38; making out the temperature charts more than fills in the day. At 8 o'clock we all in conclave report about our patients &#38; talk over any interesting case. One of my patients has empyema following pleurisy. I inject into her chest about a doz. of different preparations. Several of my patients (I have all the very sick just now) require very careful watching.</p>
            
            <p>In the evening we go round again &#38; count pulses &#38; respirations &#38; note temperatures. If a very sick patient, in the middle of the day; also take pulse, etc. The number of visits depending on the need &#38; the competency of the nurse. I like introducing lint into wounds (such simple ones as an incised abscess of the breast) with the probe, because if I take trouble enough I can do it without hurting the patient, much to the patient's surprise.</p>
                
            <p>The other day Mr. &#38; Mrs. Marvin called to see me with Mrs. &#38; Miss Callender&#8212;I enjoyed their visit much. To-day Mr. Marvin drove over to fetch me to lunch, &#38; I had a beautiful drive over to Dorchester; in the afternoon a game of lawn tennis, a stroll down to the creek, &#38; drive home by Forest Hill Cemetery &#38; Jamaica Pond. The air was fresh after a shower &#38; golden-tinted, &#38; the drive through beautiful lanes &#38; country. All were friendly &#38; it was refreshing to emerge from the little hospital world. Mr. Marvin's cordial face greeted me when I was speaking to some patients in hammocks, under the trees, the day he called, much to my surprise.</p>

            <p>I was to-day feeling the need of a little change of air &#38; scene, so that the visit was most opportune.</p>
             
            <p>Mr. Morse<ptr target="loc.04051_n1"/> is working away desperately at the bust of you; he feels as if he would get on famously if he could only catch a glimpse of you. Now might not you come to Boston on your way to Chesterfield, ride up in the open horsecars (a very pleasant ride) to see me also and give Mr. Morse the benefit of a sitting? How I wish we could get Mrs. Stafford<ptr target="n0817"/> in here; the patients get most excellent care. I have great confidence in Dr. Berlin &#38; in the attending physician. I do not want her to come for a month, because Dr. Berlin has just gone away for a vacation.</p>
                
            <p>I fear no mere visiting once a day of a doctor will do her any good&#8212;she needs hygienic treatment&#8212;massage (a woman works here every day on the patients who need rubbing &#38; massage), feeding up (I have never yet seen a patient whom we could not make eat, appetite or not, by aid of beef-tea &#38; milk), perfect rest, &#38; judicious treatment.</p>
            
            <p>Dr. Berlin is a learned, charming woman of 28&#8212;she takes advanced views, gives no medicine at all in some cases, &#38; if any, few at a time, but efficient. She is perfectly unaffected, very intelligent, &#38; has been thoroughly trained. She is a Russian.</p>
            
            <p>Please give my love to Mrs. Whitman  &#38; remember me to Colonel Whitman.<ptr target="n0700"/> This afternoon, when driving with Mr. Marvin, I thought of the pleasant drives I have had with Colonel Whitman.</p>
                
             <closer>
                  <salute>Yours affectionately,</salute>
                  <signed rend="right">Beatrice C. Gilchrist.</signed>
             </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>If it were not for records accumulating mountain high I should have time to write to my friends.</p>
                    </postscript> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
