<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03976">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Harry Stafford to Walt Whitman, 13 January 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Harry Stafford</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="vm">Vince Moran</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03976</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Harry Stafford</author>
                    <title>Harry Stafford to Walt Whitman, 13 January 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-01-13" xml:id="dat1">January 13, 1879</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Stafford, Harry">Harry Stafford</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-04-24" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-23" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-16" who="#ab">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-11" who="#ej">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-12-05" who="#vm">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00139.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Laurel Hills <choice><abbr>N.J.</abbr><expan>New Jersey</expan></choice></name>
                    <date when="1879-01-13"><choice><abbr>Jan</abbr><expan>January</expan></choice> 13th 1879.<ptr target="loc.03976_n1"/></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>       
            </opener>
            
            <p>As I have been hard at work ever since I was up to see you,<ptr target="n0590"/> I thought I would write a few lines to let you know how I am getting on with it (threshing I mean) we will finish by Saturday, if nothing happens, and I will be very glad of it for I am very sick of it. Mont.<ptr target="n0910"/> is helping me, he is as bad against as I am. Father<ptr target="n0852b"/> went to the city with a load of straw today; perhaps he will be over in time to stop and see you. I believe the work is doing me good in some ways for it is making me eat more than ever</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00140.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>You will not know me when you see me. I am getting so brown and fat.</p>
            
            <p>Mont. received your papers today, those giving the account of the execution, it went over to Glendale before he got it. He was much pleased with it.</p>
            
            <p>Dear Walt I have saved enough out of that dollar you gave me to come up and see you. I have been trying to find a day to come up and see you but cannot until we finish threshing. I have been thinking it all over and will be up on Tuesday, next, one week from tomorrow if nothing happens. I want to spend the day with you, and have a good talk, have some good cigars for me. (I know you will, won't you?) Debbie and Joe,<ptr target="n1011"/> were home yesterday and stayed all day. Capt. Townsend and wife<ptr target="n1048"/> were over
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00141.jpg" type="recto"/>
                too. Lizzie<ptr target="nyp.00417_n3"/> was over Saturday afternoon, stayed until late and of course I went home with her, had a good time with her, I told her about you sending your love to her, she sends you back the same, she says she would like to see you.</p>
            
            <p>I have been home ever since I was up to see you: there is but very little news about here now, everything is the same as when you left here. Father is about the same as when you were down. Mother is well and all the rest of the folks. Mont and all the rest sends their love to you. Will have to close as Ed<ptr target="n0589b"/> wishes to close up the store. Will be up Tuesday if nothing happens.</p>
                       
            <closer>
                <salute>Ever your true friend,</salute>
                <signed>Harry L. Stafford</signed>
            </closer>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00142.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_gt.00065.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_gt.00066.jpg" type="verso"/>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
