<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00415">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 13 June 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00415</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">59-61</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 13 June 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-06-13">June 13, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-20">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-06-13">June 13 63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your letter yesterday morning.<ptr target="loc.00415_n1"/> I am extremely glad to hear that your health continues so good. Walt I have thought considerable of the idea that you speak of, that of your giving lectures<ptr target="loc.00415_n2"/>  I fear that you would not meet with that success that you deserve. Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00415_n3"/> and I talked about the matter and both came to the conclusion that it would be much better if you could be appointed dispensing agent, or something of that kind, for some of the numerous aid societies,<ptr target="loc.00415_n4"/> and he said that he would go and see Storrs<ptr target="loc.00415_n5"/> and some other of the big guns of those societies in this city and see if it could not be done. What do you think about it. Do you think it could be accomplished.?</p>
            <p>Everything is going along well with us at home. Mother is not troubled hardly any with her rheumatism and I am in hopes she will get the best of it entirely. Mattie is well and in first-rate spirits, she often speaks of you and says she would like very much to see you. Hattie is growing as nicely as it is possibly for a child to grow. You would love dearly to take a stroll with her now I know  Andrew has not yet gone to Newbern<ptr target="loc.00415_n6"/> but thinks that they will get off the fore part of the coming week. Jess and Ed are just the same as ever. We were all much pleased with the idea that you would come home to make us a visit, I do so hope that you can carry it out.<ptr target="loc.00415_n7"/> do try Walt, for me  all want to see you very much</p>
            <p>I am glad you wrote Mother about the way in which you board for I have often and often thought how you was doing in that respect and I sometimes thought I ought to do something in the matter, precisely what or how I never could tell. I am real glad my dear Walt that you are among such good people. I hope it will be in the power of some of our family to return their Kindness some day. I'm sure twould be done with a heartfelt gratitude  Tis pleasant, too, to think that there are still people of that kind left.<ptr target="loc.00415_n8"/> You, of course, still continue your hospital "practice" as you might call it. I wish we were able to send you more money than we do but almost everyone you meet is a contributor to some of the aid societies and that is the way in which they are (thinking) doing good</p>
            <p>Well, Walt, you and I cannot agree in regard to "Uncle Abe"<ptr target="loc.00415_n9"/>  I cannot think that he is the man for the place or he would have surrounded himself with men that could do something. He lends himself to the speculators, in all the ways that it can be done. He says "yes" to the last man or "No" as that man wants him to. Everything he does reminds me of an old woman. I hope that the country will last long enough for this damned war to fall through   It seems nothing but an immense bubble, only of a desperate character</p>
            <p>We have not heard from Han lately  I wrote you that we had had a letter from George. I fear for George now  I am afraid that they have sent the 51st to Vicksburgh.<ptr target="loc.00415_n10"/> I do hope that George may escape but I fear not  It seems as if he had been so lucky that it could not continue till the end. If you can learn anything of the 51st write me will you  All send their love, good night dear brother</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Yours affectionately Jeff.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
