<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04619">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">G. H. Whitaker to Walt Whitman, 10 June 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>G. H. Whitaker</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04619</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>G. H. Whitaker</author>
                    <title>G. H. Whitaker to Walt Whitman, 10 June 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-06-10" xml:id="dat1">June 10, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitaker, G. H.">G. H. Whitaker</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-12-12" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-12-10" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-05" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-10-29" who="#kc">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.02419_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington D.C.</name>
                    <date when="1880-06-10">June 10<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline"
                                >th</hi></hi> 1880</date>. <name type="place">Walt
                                Whitman,</name>
                                <name type="place">Camden <choice>
                            <abbr>N.J.</abbr>
                            <expan>New Jersey</expan>
                        </choice></name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I hope the name subscribed hereto is not altogether forgotten by you; although when
                you were here we met but rarely, and since your change of residence we have not met
                at all.</p>

            <p>I remember as though it were yesterday the first time I met you and the audacity with
                which I stopped you on Pennsylvania Avenue and introduced myself to you. <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.02420_large.jpg" type="verso"/>I realize now more
                than I did then that it was audacity. But in my little intellectual life "Leaves of
                Grass" had been so much to me that I could not meet and pass you without saying
                something to you.</p>

            <p>It has long been a thought of mine that there ought to be a volume of selections from
                your works put before the public. I have often thought that many who know nothing of
                your writings and who have perhaps have been kept by popular criticism from reading
                your complete works, would, if they once caught a glimpse of the beauty and strength
                found there, read more extensively <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc_vm.02421_large.jpg" type="recto"/>to their own pleasure and
                advancement and your profit.</p>

            <p>Three or four years ago I spent an evening with
                two gentlemen friends of mine, and the conversation turning upon your works, a copy of
                which was upon the table beside me, I spoke somewhat at length in your favor reading
                extracts hastily selected from the volume at hand. The circumstance passed from my
                mind but a few days since one of the gentlemen referred to the occurrence saying he
                should never forget that evening as it was the beginning of his acquaintance with
                your writings from which he has since derived great pleasure <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc_vm.02422_large.jpg" type="verso"/>This incident has suggested that
                perhaps I could prepare a volume of selections from your poems which would supply
                what I have felt to be a need and which would be acceptable to the public. I,
                therefore, have written this note to ask your permission to put such a volume of
                selections before the public in some graceful form to come out in time for the holy
                days.</p>

            <p>A gentleman of literary tastes Mr. C. C. Adams, now of New York but formerly connected with
                the Treasury Department here will join me in this work. We propose that the entire
                proceeds from the sale of the book shall be yours as long as you live, stipulating
                only that in case of your death (which we pray <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc_vm.02423_large.jpg" type="recto"/>may long be deferred) the profits
                thereafter arising shall come to us.</p>

            <p>If you sanction our project it will be a work of love and gratitude and we shall
                labor to make you friends who shall so love you that they shall want to know more of
                you and to read you further.</p>

            <p>We do not propose an extensive work, nothing like an emasculated or expurgated
                edition of your poems, but we intend to cull detached thoughts and pictures for
                others, and our object will be to do the work before us in such a manner as only to
                enhance a fuller reading.</p>

            <p>I hope our proposition <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.02424_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>will meet with your approval. We know that there are many more
                competent to discharge the work we would like to accomplish but there are none who
                would labor more reverently and lovingly to win you friends and lovers than we.</p>

            <p>Wishing you health, comfort and friends in your remaining years.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I am very truly
                    your friend &amp; admirer</salute>
                <signed>G.H. Whitaker</signed>
                <address><addrLine>Address.</addrLine>
<addrLine>US Patent Office</addrLine>
<addrLine>Washington D.C.</addrLine></address>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
