<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04053">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 5 January 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04053</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">166&#8211;168</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 5 January 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-01-05" xml:id="dat1">January 5, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-23" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-01-31" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">112 Madison Ave.<ptr target="n0259"/></name>
                    <name type="place">New York</name>
                    <date when="1879-01-05"><choice><abbr>Jan.</abbr><expan>January</expan></choice> 5, '79.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> has told you of our difficulties in getting comfortable quarters here&#8212;and also that we seem now to have succeeded&#8212;not indeed in the way I most wished &#38; hoped we had&#8212;in 19th St., taking rooms &#38; boarding ourselves&#8212;so that we could have a friend with us when &#38; as we pleased. It seems as if that were not practicable unless we were to furnish for ourselves. Certainly our experiences there of using another's kitchen were discouraging&#8212;it was so dirty and uncomfortable that we were glad to take refuge in a regular boarding house again before one week was out. It seems to me more difficult to get anything of a medium kind in New York than elsewhere I have been&#8212;if it isn't the best, it is very uninviting indeed. Herby is enjoying his work and companionship at the League very much. We stand the cold well&#8212;how does it suit you? Is your arm free from rheumatic pains? When you come to Mr. J. H. Johnstons,<ptr target="n0336"/> which will be very soon I hope, we shall be quite handy, and have a pretty, sunny room&#8212;a sitting room by day!&#8212;with a handsome piece of furniture which is metamorphosed into a bed at night&#8212;and a large dressing closet with hot &#38; cold water adjoining&#8212;all very comfortable. O how wistfully do I think of one evening in Philadelphia, last winter. I shan't begin really to like New York till you come and we have had some chats together. I have news from England which makes me rather anxious. The Blaenavon Co., to which Per.<ptr target="n2000"/> is chemist, has gone into liquidation&#8212;&#38; I don't know whether it will continue to exist&#8212;or how soon in these dull times he may find a good opening elsewhere. Should things go badly for him, either Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> and I will return to England to share [our] home with him there, or else I want him to take into serious consideration coming out here, instead of our going back. Of course it would be a risky thing for him to do with wife<ptr target="n3006"/> &#38; child, in these times, unless some definite opening presented itself, but I cannot help thinking that, being an expert in his profession, with first rate training &#38; experience, and iron work &#38; metallurgy promising here to have such enormous developments, he would be sure to do well in the end; and meanwhile we could rub on together somehow. However, we shall see. I have laid the matter before him, he &#38; his dear little wife wrote me a very brave, cheery letter when they told me the bad news&#8212;&#38; I shall have an answer to mine, I suppose, by the end of the month. Kate Hillard<ptr target="n0302"/> read an amusing paper on Swinburne<ptr target="n0610"/> at a meeting of the Woman's Club in Brooklyn&#8212;&#38; we had some fine music too. For the rest, I have not yet presented any introductions here.</p>
            
            <p>Have had some beautiful glimpses of the North &#38; East River effects of the shipping at sunset, &#38;c.&#8212;Have subscribed to the Mercantile library,&#8212;&#38; are beginning to feel at home. Herby &#38; Giddy had been to hear Mr. Frothingham<ptr target="n1504"/> this morning, &#38; were much interested. Bee<ptr target="n0260"/> missed us sorely at first&#8212;but writes&#8212;when she does write, which is but seldom&#8212;pretty cheerily. Friendly remembrance to your brother &#38; sister. I wonder where Hattie<ptr target="n0911"/> &#38; Jessie<ptr target="duk.00343_n2"/> are spending their holidays. Love from us all. Good-bye, dear friend.</p>
                
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">A. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Had a letter from Mr. Marvin<ptr target="n0830"/>&#8212;all well&#8212;he is doing the Washington letter of a N. Eng. paper. Hopes &#38; trusts you are really going to Washington.</p>
                    </postscript>      
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
