<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03698">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Robert P. Stewart to Walt Whitman, December 1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Robert P. Stewart</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03698</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Robert P. Stewart</author>
                    <title>Robert P. Stewart to Walt Whitman, December 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-12" xml:id="dat1">December 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 15</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Stewart, Robert P." ref="n5000">Robert P. Stewart</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-13" who="#ss">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-08-06" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-07-09" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-06-12" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-12" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-11-21" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-27" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03698.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name>R. P. Stewart</name>
                    <name type="place">89 Philbeach Gdns</name>
                    <name type="place">Earls Court</name>
                    <name type="place">London.</name>
                    <date when="1885-12"><hi rend="underline">Decr 1885</hi></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I can give you no title
                that would not be a mockery. I write this&#8212;representing the rising generation to tell
                you that from us you get what you long for Speechless passionate love I seem to see
                now through all dark London young men issuing from houses with "Leaves of Grass" in
                their hands &#38; grandness <unclear reason="illegible" resp="ss" cert="medium" instant="false">&#38; war</unclear> written determinedly on their faces.&#8212;I dont know what to say to you&#8212;to give
                you any notion of the good you have done me &#38; again I think I speak for hundreds
                of my age <hi rend="underline">21</hi>. I have read criticisms reviews of your
                works <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03698.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> &#38; as I
                half expected none of them had the least idea who you were I believe we
                will&#8212;perhaps when you have gone from us though I trust not be able to
                vindicate your right to stand alone as the sun of this century &#38; Goethe Kant,
                Spencer Ruskin &#38; the rest of the mighty will have to live as priceless beautiful
                satellites, but yet as satellites. For months I have been bursting with things to
                say to you but now I cannot say a word. In all criticisms upon you the most
                delightful to me is Ruskins. The marvellous clear vision he has is wonderful &#38;
                his honesty is wonderful for the leader&#8212;<hi rend="underline">in a minor
                    sense</hi>&#8212;of the opposite school. You dont like being called the leader of a
                school&#8212;but you are if your teaching amounted to no more than&#8212; "<hi rend="underline"
                    >You must find out for yourself</hi>"&#8212;If I might be
                allowed <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03698.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> to
                criticize, I cant make out, why you have said nothing about children&#8212;Is not the
                education of them one of if not the most important thought for the future. I do hope
                you will yet be spared to say something about this or rather to put a tendency
                towards children in your book.&#8212;I never read or criticize your Book from the standpoint
                of what the words say, but go to it as I go to the bible in spirit &#38; in truth.&#8212;&#38; fish out for
                myself tendencies which help in curious unexpected ways. Perhaps the most important
                idea I have got from you in a way I never understood it before is <hi
                    rend="underline">Learn to love</hi> I write this chiefly to tell you that the
                new generation admire you in a very different way from the last. What they <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03698.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> may do years
                hence I dont know&#8212;I have left to the end to ask you if it is true the awful
                rumours going about that you are starving. The thing is too ghastly to be true&#8212;Millions &#38; millions of money would never repay the work you have done for us
                &#38; especially for us young men. I am quite poor myself but could I know get money
                for you easily if you are in the least want of it. I think I know you well enough to
                know that you will not mind saying you do want some money if you do. I can hardly
                expect an answer to this if you do not,&#8212;as you must have all your time occupied but if
                you can find time to write a line telling me how you are I shall be very grateful. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Your very affect friend</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Bob. Stewart</hi></signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
