<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00478">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 23 February 1885</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00478</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">179-182</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 23 February 1885</title>
               <date when="1885-02-23">February 23, 1885</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
                  <date when="1885-02-23">Feb 23rd 1885</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have had such hard work for the last six weeks that I have hardly had time to answre the regular business letters but to day thought I would "drop you a line" at any rate&#8212;</p>
            <p>Just now I am having rather a bad time in keeping up the water&#8212;so large a portion of the people let the water run to prevent freezing of the pipes&#8212;and our city&#8212;being so hilly that I cannot keep the water on the high points&#8212;still unless we have more than another week of this extremely cold weather we shall get through all right.<ptr target="loc.00478_n1"/>
            </p>
            <p>We talk of you often and wonder how you get on if you have anything like as bad a winter as we have  I hope you take it easy and get on without much trouble. I have not been able to get out as much this season as usual&#8212;we have had the cold so long and so bad that I was forced to keep in doors to a great extent.</p>
            <p>I saw by yesterday's paper that Kingsley,<ptr target="loc.00478_n2"/> of Brooklyn, had given up&#8212;poor fellow, all his keen striving and jobbing and talk is over forever  He would have been happier, I think had he remained more like he was when he first came to Brooklyn&#8212;</p>
            <p>I mail you to-day a little picture of a new stand pipe tower that I am going to build this next year<ptr target="loc.00478_n3"/>&#8212;we have let the work and shall commence on it as soon as the weather will let us. The design has been cut and changed&#8212;and re-made, till I got it to look as I thought it ought. The young man that made it has good taste and I think when finished it will look as well as anything of the kind in the country. The total cost will be about eighty thousand dollars complete. Let me know Walt how it looks to you please&#8212;All the lower part is to be of granite&#8212;and above that brick work&#8212;of the best bricks and workmanship. There will be nothing particularly grand about it except its proportions&#8212;That is I hav'nt attempted to make any wonderfully fine carving or anything of that kind  I shall be terribly disappointed if it fails to look well when built as I have carried out several things in opposition to the opinions of fellows who have the reputation of knowing all about such things&#8212;Well in a year from now, if we all live, we will know how it will be</p>
            <p>Walt, if you have a copy of your "Author's Edition" of your book that you can send me I would esteem it a great favor if you will write in it "A. J. Chaphe,<ptr target="loc.00478_n4"/> from the Author" and send it to me. Chaphe intends to get all your books as soon as he can get a little money ahead&#8212;but I would like to give him this one  He has read all my copies&#8212;and is interested in them to a great extent.</p>
            <p>Hat and Jess keep pretty well and we all get on in the regular old way</p>
            <p>A few weeks ago Willard Arnold<ptr target="loc.00478_n5"/> called at my office&#8212;he was in St Louis a week&#8212;with one of the dramatic Companies  I saw him often&#8212;did'nt go to the play but had him down to the house. Willard is in many respects the same as when a boy&#8212;he asked all about you&#8212;and well remembered many of the walks we all used to take on Sundays years and years ago.</p>
            <p>A few days ago I had a letter from Bill De Voe,<ptr target="loc.00478_n6"/> who is now located at Springfield, this state. Bill sent me a young mocking bird&#8212;his home is at a small town on the red-river in La. but he is running a surveyor's office at Springfield</p>
            <p>I dont know whether I shall be able to get East this spring or not but I intend to make the effort. I feel the need of a vacation badly. I note what a terrible disaster you had in Philadelphia a few days since<ptr target="loc.00478_n7"/>&#8212;in some way it seemed to me the most heart rending of anything of the kind I ever read about. I suppose because it was a family dwelling perhaps. All send love to you dear Walt.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Aff., Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
