<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00764">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Thomas Jefferson Whitman, 13 February 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00764</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">73-75</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Thomas Jefferson Whitman, 13 February 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-02-13">February 13, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-13">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-12">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Office Major Hapgood, cor 15th &amp; F. sts. | Washington,</name>
                  <date when="1863-02-13">Feb. 13th '63.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Nothing new&#8212;still I thought I would write you a line this morning. The $4, namely: $2 from Theo. A. Drake and 2 [from] John D. Martin,<ptr target="loc.00764_n1"/> enclosed in your letter of the 10th came safe. They too will please accept the grateful thanks of several poor fellows, in hospital here.</p>
            <p>The letter of introduction to Mr. Webster,<ptr target="loc.00764_n2"/> chief clerk, State Department, will be very acceptable. If convenient, I should like Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00764_n3"/> to send it on immediately. I do not so much look for an appointment from Mr. Seward as his backing me from the State of New York. I have seen Preston King<ptr target="loc.00764_n4"/> this morning for the second time&#8212;(it is very amusing to hunt for an office&#8212;so the thing seems to me just now&#8212;even if one don't get it)&#8212;I have seen Charles Sumner three times&#8212;he says every thing here moves as part of a great machine, and that I must consign myself to the fate of the rest&#8212;still [in] an interview I had with him yesterday he talked and acted as though he had life in him, and would exert himself to any reasonable extent for me to get something. Meantime I make about enough to pay my expenses by hacking on the press here, and copying in the paymasters offices, a couple of hours a day&#8212;one thing is favorable here, namely, pay for whatever one does is at a high rate&#8212;I have not yet presented my letters to either Seward or Chase<ptr target="loc.00764_n5"/>&#8212;I thought I would get my forces all in a body, and make one concentrated dash, if possible with the personal introduction and presence of some big bug&#8212;I like fat old Preston King, very much&#8212;he is fat as a hogshead, with great hanging chops&#8212;the first thing he said to me the other day in the parlor chamber of the Senate, when I sent in for him and he came out, was, "Why, how can I do this thing, or any thing for you&#8212;how do I know but you are a secessionist&#8212;you look for all the world, like an old Southern planter&#8212;a regular Carolina or Virginia planter." I treated him with just as much hauteur as he did me with bluntness&#8212;this was the first time&#8212;it afterward proved that Charles Sumner had not prepared the way for me, as I supposed, or rather, not so strongly as I supposed, and Mr. King had even forgotten it&#8212;so I was as an entire stranger. But the same day C. S. talked further with Mr. King in the Senate, and the second interview I had with the latter, (this forenoon) he has given me a sort of general letter, endorsing me from New York&#8212;one envelope is addressed to Secretary Chase, and another to Gen. Meigs,<ptr target="loc.00764_n6"/> head Quartermaster's Dep't. Meantime, I am getting better and better acquainted with office-hunting wisdom, and Washington peculiarities generally.</p>
            <p>I spent several hours in the Capitol the other day&#8212;the incredible gorgeousness of some of the rooms, (interior decorations &amp;c)&#8212;rooms used perhaps but for merely three or four Committee meetings in the course of the whole year,) is beyond one's flightiest dreams. Costly frescoes of the style of Taylor's Saloon in Broadway,<ptr target="loc.00764_n7"/> only really the best and choicest of their sort, done by imported French &amp; Italian artists, are the prevailing sorts (imagine the work you see on the fine China vases, in Tiffany's&#8212;the paintings of Cupids &amp; goddesses &amp;c. spread recklessly over the arched ceiling and broad panels of a big room&#8212;the whole floor underneath paved with tesselated pavement, which is a sort of cross between marble &amp; china, with little figures drab, blue, cream color, &amp;c). These things, with heavy, elaborately wrought balustrades, columns, &amp; steps&#8212;all of the most beautiful marbles I ever saw, some white as milk, others of all colors, green, spotted, lined, or of our old chocolate color&#8212;all these marbles used as freely as if they were common blue flags&#8212;with rich door-frames and window-casings of bronze and gold&#8212;heavy chandeliers and mantels, and clocks in every room&#8212;and indeed by far the richest and gayest, and most un-American and inappropriate ornamenting and finest interior workmanship I ever conceived possible, spread in profusion through scores, hundreds, (and almost thousands) of rooms&#8212;such are what I find, or rather would find to interest me, if I devoted time to it&#8212;But a few of the rooms are enough for me&#8212;the style is without grandeur, and without simplicity&#8212;These days, the state our country is in, and especially filled as I am from top to toe, of late with scenes and thoughts of the hospitals, (America seems to me now, though only in her youth, but brought already here feeble, bandaged and bloody in hospital)&#8212;these days I say, Jeff, all the poppy-show goddesses and all the pretty blue &amp; gold in which the interior Capitol is got up, seem to me out of place beyond any thing I could tell&#8212;and I get away from it as quick as I can when that kind of thought comes over me. I suppose it is to be described throughout&#8212;those interiors&#8212;as all of them got up in the French style&#8212;well enough for a New York [incomplete]</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
