<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05119">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 14 August
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05119</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 14 August 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-08-14" xml:id="dat1">August 14, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 17, Reel 10-11</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H." ref="n1027">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-18" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-07-10" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-04-29" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-07" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-22" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-19" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01029_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">pictures sent Sept. '82. | &#38; wrote postal card</note>
            <opener>    
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1882-08-14" rend="right">August 14th/82</date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">29 Lange Strasse<lb/> Dresden</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear master</salute>
                
            </opener>
            <p>I wish you could send me, if you have them loose, a few of your
                portraits, especially of the shirt-sleeves one&#8212;or perhaps you could tell
                me where they are to be had, if they are attainable to the public? I should like
                also to have a couple of copies of a brief autobiographical note of which Edward
                    Dowden<!--<ptr target="n0199"/>--> gave me a copy some time ago&#8212;intended to
                accompany presentation copies of the L. of G.<ptr target="loc.05119_n2"/> I am just
                home from a summer's walking-tour in Switzerland, where I, and a friend who lives
                here, had a glorious time together. Anything more bracing and invigorating than the
                air on the high mountain passes it is impossible to conceive. We went over one
                glacier, where my friend distinguished himself by falling into a crevasse. As we
                were all roped together&#8212;two guides and ourselves, he was extricated without
                much damage. Scenery on the glacier the
                    'Tschingel' was marvellous. It is a vast lake of ice, probably some 200
                feet deep, lying <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01030_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                high among the peaks of the Bernese Oberland. It is mostly covered with a thin
                coating of snow, but at one point it pours down through a break in the
                mountain-wall, by a kind of gorge or ravine, into a deep valley. It has the
                aspect then of a river, not a lake; and at this point there is no snow&#8212;the
                ice being heaped up into enormous ridges &#38; pinnacles like a river when there is
                a long reach of rapids, only in the glacier everything is much vaster&#8212;the
                waves as big as a terrace of houses, with deep chasms between them walled as far as
                one can see with gleaming ice. The ice is only semitransparent &#38; is of a very
                strange pale green hue. The wild, tossing confusion of the ice-river
                contrasted strangely with the absolute stillness and immoveability, broken only, now
                &amp; then, when some great block would totter over and come thundering down into the
                valley, hurling huge fragments &#38; splinters into the air as if they were dust.</p>
            <p>I am working now at an essay on the L. of G. which I am to read before a literary
                society here. <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.01031_large.jpg" type="recto"
                />Shall introduce quotations liberally &#38; see what they think of my translation.
                If I like this essay when it is done I will publish it here in pamphlet form &#38;
                send it well about Germany.<ptr target="loc.05119_n3"/> I suppose you got a page of
                translation I sent you some time ago?<ptr target="loc.05119_n4"/></p>
            <p>I hope all is going well with you. Heard some months ago of an intended prosecution
                of the new edition&#8212;but I suppose that was a mere 'canard.'<ptr
                    target="loc.05119_n5"/></p>
            <p>Much interest here about the English in Egypt.<ptr target="loc.05119_n6"/> A shameful
                business altogether, which makes me thankful that I am not an Englishman except
                against my will. The other European governments feel some satisfaction at the course
                taken&#8212;whenever might is the order of the day despotism feels securer, &amp; they
                like to see England, the home of liberty, acting as unjustly as any dynasty with its
                traditions of iniquity. They do not yet fully comprehend that English liberty is
                regarded as being only fit for Englishmen.</p>
            <p>I suppose you have seen <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_af.01032_large.jpg" type="verso"/> Swinburne's new
                vol. Tristram of Lyonesse.<ptr target="loc.05119_n7"/> There seems some fine verse
                in it&#8212;especially the ode to Athens, but I have not read it thoroughly yet.</p>
            <p>Now farewell, with all good wishes &#38; greeting. Please do not forget about the
                portraits and Note.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute rend="right">Yours sincerely</salute>
                <signed rend="right">T.W. Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
