<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00803">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Elijah Douglass Fox, 21 November 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00803</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">186-188</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Elijah Douglass Fox, 21 November 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-11-21">November 21, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Fox, Elijah Douglass">Elijah Douglass Fox</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-02">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-30">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1863-11-21">Saturday night Nov 21, '63<ptr target="loc.00803_n100"/>
               </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear son &amp; comrade,<ptr target="loc.00803_n2"/>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wrote a few lines about five days ago<ptr target="loc.00803_n3"/> &amp; sent on to Armory Square, but as I have not heard from it I suppose you have gone on to Michigan. I got your letter of Nov 10th,<ptr target="loc.00803_n4"/> &amp; it gave me much comfort. Douglass, I shall return to Washington about the 24th, so when you write direct to care of Major Hapgood, paymaster U S A, Washington D. C.&#8212;Dearest comrade, I only write this, lest the one I wrote five days ago may not reach you from the hospital. I am still here at my mother's, &amp; feel as if [I] have had enough of going around New York&#8212;enough of amusements, suppers, drinking, &amp; what is called <hi rend="italic">pleasure</hi>&#8212;Dearest son, it would be more pleasure if we could be together just in quiet, in some plain way of living, with some good employment &amp; reasonable income, where I could have you often with me, than all the dissipations &amp; amusements of this great city&#8212;O I hope things may work so that we can yet have each other's society&#8212;for I cannot bear the thought of being separated from you&#8212;I know I am a great fool about such things, but I tell you the truth, dear son. I do not think one night has passed in New York or Brooklyn when I have been at the theatre or opera or afterward to some supper party or carouse made by the young fellows for me, but what amid the play or the singing, I would perhaps suddenly think of you&#8212;&amp; the same at the gayest supper party, of men, where all was fun &amp; noise &amp; laughing &amp; drinking, of a dozen young men, &amp; I among them, I would see your face before me in my thought as I have seen it so often there in Ward G, &amp; my amusement or drink would be all turned to nothing, &amp; I would realize how happy it would be if I could leave all the fun &amp; noise &amp; the crowd &amp; be with you&#8212;I don't wish to disparage my dear friends &amp; acquaintances here, there are so many of them &amp; all so good, many so educated, traveled, &amp;c., some so handsome &amp; witty, some rich &amp;c., some among the literary class&#8212;many young men&#8212;all good&#8212;many of them educated &amp; polished, &amp; brilliant in conversation, &amp;c<ptr target="loc.00803_n5"/>&#8212;&amp; I thought I valued their society &amp; friendship&#8212;&amp; I do, for it is worth valuing&#8212;But, Douglass, I will tell you the truth, you are so much closer to me than any of them that there is no comparison&#8212;there has never passed so much between them &amp; me as we have&#8212;besides there is something that takes down all artificial accomplishments, &amp; that is a manly &amp; loving soul&#8212;My dearest comrade, I am sitting here writing to you very late at night&#8212;I have been reading&#8212;it is indeed after 12, &amp; my mother &amp; all the rest have gone to bed two hours ago, &amp; I am here alone writing to you, &amp; I enjoy it too, although it is not much, yet I know it will please you, dear boy&#8212;If you get this, you must write &amp; tell me where &amp; how you are. I hope you are quite well, &amp; with your dear wife, for I know you have long wished to be with her, &amp; I wish you to give her my best respects &amp; love too.</p>
            <p>Douglass, I haven't written any news, for there is nothing particular I have to write. Well, it is now past midnight, pretty well on to 1 o'clock, &amp; my sheet is most written out&#8212;so, my dear darling boy, I must bid you good night, or rather good morning &amp; I hope it may be God's will we shall yet be with each other&#8212;but I must indeed bid you good night, my dear loving comrade, &amp; the blessing of God on you by night &amp; day, my darling boy.<ptr target="loc.00803_n6"/>
            </p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
