<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01581">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 25 September
                    1868</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01581</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">45–47</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 25 September 1868</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1868-09-25" xml:id="dat1">September 25, 1868</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2011-08-01" who="#el">updated WWA ID referring to Doyle's letter</change>
            <change when="2011-03-01" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-20" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">N. Y.</name>
                    <date when="1868-09-25" rend="right">Sept 25 <lb/>'68 <lb/>3d letter.</date><ptr target="loc.01581_n1"/>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Boy,</salute><ptr target="loc.01581_n2"/>
            </opener>

            <p>I rec'd your second letter yesterday—it is a real comfort to me to get such
                letters from you, dear friend. Every word does me good. The <hi rend="italic">Star</hi> came all right, &amp; was quite interesting. I suppose you got my
                second letter last Wednesday. There is nothing new or special to write about
                to-day—still I thought I would send you a few lines, for Sunday. I put down
                off hand, &amp; write all about myself &amp; my doings, &amp;c. because I suppose
                that will be really what my dear comrade wants most to hear, while we are separated.</p>

            <p>I am doing a little literary work, according as I feel in the mood—composing on
                my books. I am having a small edition of the Leaves of Grass for 1867, fixed up
                &amp; printed. This &amp; some other things give me a little occupation. Upon the
                whole though I don't do much, but go around a great deal—eat my rations every
                time, sleep at night like a top, &amp; am having good times so far, in a quiet way,
                enjoying New York, the society of my mother, &amp; lots of friends. Among other
                things I spend a portion of the day, with the pilots of the ferry boats, sailing on
                the river. The river &amp; bay of New York &amp; Brooklyn are always a great
                attraction to me. It is a lively scene. At either tide, flood or ebb, the water is
                always rushing along as if in haste, &amp; the river is often crowded with steamers,
                ships &amp; small craft, moving in different directions, some coming in from sea,
                others going out. Among the pilots are some of my particular friends—when I
                see them up in the pilot house on my way to Brooklyn, I go up &amp; sail to &amp;
                fro several trips. I enjoy an hour or two's sail of this kind very much indeed.<ptr target="loc.01581_n3"/> My mother
                &amp; folks are well, &amp; are engaged just these times in the delightful business
                of moving. I should assist, but have hired a substitute in the shape of a stout
                young laboring man.</p>

            <p>I send you, by mail, a copy of <hi rend="italic">the Broadway</hi>, with the piece
                    in<ptr target="loc.01581_n4"/> the same as I had in the car one day. It will not interest you
                much, only as something coming from me.</p>

            <p>I think of you very often, dearest comrade, &amp; with more calmness than when I was
                there—I find it first rate to think of you, Pete, &amp; to know that you are
                there, all right, &amp; that I shall return, &amp; we will be together again. I
                don't know what I should do if I hadn't you to think of &amp; look forward to.<ptr target="loc.01581_n5"/>
            </p>

            <p>Tell Tom Hasset,<ptr target="loc.01581_n6"/> on No. 7, that I wish to be remembered to him
                particular. Pete, I hope this will find you entirely well of your cold. I am glad to
                hear that your mother is all right of her cold. This is the time of year when they
                are apt to be pretty troublesome. I should like to have seen that match played
                between the Nat. &amp; Olympics.<ptr target="loc.01581_n7"/>
            </p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>