<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

   <TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03063">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 19 August 1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03063</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 19 August 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-08-19" xml:id="dat1">August 19, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-08" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-23" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-19" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03063.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.<ptr target="loc.03063_n1"/></name> 
                    <date when="1882-08-19" rend="right">August 19, 1882.</date>                    
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got your card of the 6th, and duly the new edition of the book arrived, for which I am much obliged. I have now all the editions, except the second, which I hope to possess some day.</p> 
            <p>The weather has been until yesterday so fearfully oppressive that I have unwittingly delayed acknowledging
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03063.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                the book, having been almost sick with the heat. I sent a blast against Comstock, to the <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> on Friday, apropos of his threats in that paper of the 6th, which I suppose you saw. They may not print it, or they may tomorrow. Whitelaw Reid being away, is against me. We shall see. The article is brief, but a scorcher. I debated before sending it, holding your interests in consideration, but 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03063.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                concluded that Comstock means mischief, and thought prudent to make him feel the talon as a warning. If he meddles with your book in New York, I will do my utmost in all directions to have him removed from his Post Office Agency, and I think I can raise a tempest that will darken him forever, if I try.</p>
            <p>It is splendid, the way the Rees <choice><sic>Welch</sic><corr>Welsh</corr></choice> edition sells. I am delighted.</p>
            <p>Much obliged for 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03063.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                your interest about the Florio Montaigne. I only asked because I saw Welsh dealt in old books. There has been a boom in Montaigne of late years, and it is not so easy to get hold of the earlier editions now. I have been re-reading him lately. It is immense. I can hardly doubt that Bacon is the true author&#8212;the book so fits into his scheme. That chapter, "On Some Verses in Virgil", is tremendous, and backs you greatly.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03063.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I thought Gilder of the <hi rend="underline">Critic</hi> was a friend of yours. His taking up for that miserable Chadwick against me, misrepresenting and falsifying my argumentation, was anything but friendly.</p> 
            <p>The Unitarian <hi rend="underline">Index</hi> did a rascally thing lately in reprinting Chadwick's letter verbatim, without my reply. Dr. Channing went up to Boston and saw Underwood, the editor, and 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03063.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                gave him a piece of his mind (the Dr. thinks it "a crushing reply."). Underwood excused himself for not printing my answer on the ground that it was too "personal"!!!!! When you remember how Chad. assailed me as a liar, you will appreciate this delicious reason! Upon hearing of it, I wrote Underwood a note in which I gave him cantharides, or as the Long 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03063.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                Island boys say, "hell under the shirt". To which he rejoined in a whining letter, saying he meant to do me no injustice, and would print a reply from me to Chadwick if I would write him one, and make it short! In conclusion, he begged me to remember that his paper was "small". To which I had a mind to answer, "Very." But I have not again written him, being quite satisfied with letting him know what I thought 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03063.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                of his fair-play.</p>
            <p>Dr. Bucke has written me about his book. Can anything be done to make Rees Welsh publish it? I wish it could be done. Now is the time, when public interest has been awakened, and persecution is yet possible.</p>
            <p>That is a sick article of Gordon's you sent me. But we'll have something to say on that point yet.</p>
            <p>Goodbye. I hope to hear that the third edition is already called for!</p>
            <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully</salute>
            <signed>WDO'C.</signed>
            <salute>Walt Whitman</salute></closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03063.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <postscript><p>P.S. I have a card from John Burroughs on his return.</p>
            <p>I was sorry to see the item in the Tribune of the 15th, saying that your book had been proscribed by Trinity College, Dublin, through the efforts of one Galbraith, described as a Fellow of the College, and a damned low fellow too, I should say. The news 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03063.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    made me fear the possible effect here. Strange that I cannot find the alleged letter to Marston in any of the Boston papers. It was in Dublin, either at this College or the University, that Tyrrell lectured on you, glorifying the book they now proscribe. "So runs the world away."</p>
                <closer>
                <signed rend="right"><hi rend="underline">WDO'C</hi></signed>
            </closer></postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03063.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="left">see notes Oct 16 &amp; 17 1888</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03063.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
