<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01701">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, [27
                    November 1871]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01701</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date><biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">141–143</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, [27 November 1871]</title>
                    <date cert="low" when="1871-11-27" xml:id="dat1">November 27, 1871</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Library of Congress</orgName>
                    
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-10-17" who="#el">corrected encoding of notes</change>
            <change when="2011-03-29" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-11-17" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <salute>Dear Friend</salute><ptr target="loc.01701_n1"/>
            </opener>

            <p>Your long waited for letter brought me both joy &amp; pain; but the pain was not of
                your giving. I gather from it that a long letter which I wrote you Sept. 6th<ptr target="loc.01701_n2"/> after I had received the precious packet, a letter in which I opened all my
                heart to you, never reached your hands: nor yet a shorter one which, tortured by
                anxiety &amp; suspense about its predecessor, I wrote Oct. 15,<ptr target="loc.01701_n3"/> it, too, written out of
                such stress &amp; intensity of painful emotion as wrenches from us inmost truth: I
                cannot face the thought of these words of uttermost trust &amp; love having fallen
                into other hands. Can both be simply lost? Could any man suffer a base curiosity, to
                make him so meanly treacherously cruel? It seems to cut and then burn me. </p>

            <p>I was not disappointed at the shortness of your letter &amp; I do not ask nor even
                wish you to write save when you are inwardly impelled &amp; desirous of doing so. I
                only want leave and security to write freely to you. Your book does indeed say
                all—book that is not a book but, for the first time, a man complete, godlike,
                august, standing revealed the only way possible, through the garment of speech. Do
                you know, dear Friend, what it means for a woman, what it means for me to understand
                these poems. It means for her whole nature to be then first kindled; quickened into
                life through such love, such sympathy, such resistless attraction, that thenceforth
                she cannot choose but live &amp; die striving to become worthy to share this divine
                mans life—to be his dear companion, closer, nearer, dearer than any man can
                be—for ever so. Her soul stakes all on this. It is the meaning, the
                fulfilment, the only perfect <choice><sic>developement</sic><corr>development</corr></choice> &amp; consummation of her nature—of
                her passionate, high, immortal aspirations—her Soul to mate with his for ever
                &amp; ever. O I know the terms are obdurate—I know hard to attain to this
                greatness, the grandest lot ever aspired to by woman. I know too my own
                shortcomings, faults, flaws. You might not be able to give me your great love
                yet—to take me to your breast with joy. But I can wait. I can grow great &amp;
                beautiful through sorrow &amp; suffering, working, struggling, yearning, loving so,
                all alone, as I have done now nearly three years—it will be three in May since
                I first read the book, first knew what the word love meant. Love &amp; Hope are so
                strong in me, my souls high aspirations are of such tenacious, passionate intensity,
                are so conscious of their own deathless reality, that what would starve them out of
                any other woman only makes them strike out deeper roots, grow more resolute &amp;
                sturdy in me. I know that "greatness will not ripen for me like a pear." But I could
                face, I could joyfully accept the fiercest anguish, the hardest toil, the longest,
                sternest probation, to make me fit to be your mate—so that at the last you
                should say "this is the woman I have waited for, the woman prepared for me: this is
                my dear eternal comrade, wife—the one I so much want." Life has no other
                meaning for me than that—all things have led up to help prepare me for that.
                Death is more welcome to me than life if it means that—if then, dear Sailor,
                thou sailing upon thy endless cruise, thou takest me on board—me, daring all
                with thee, steering for the deep waters, bound where mariner has not yet dared to
                go: hand in hand with thee, nestled close—one with thee. Ah that word
                    enough<ptr target="loc.01701_n4"/> was like a blow
                on the breast to me—breast that often &amp; often is so full of yearning
                tenderness I know not how to draw my breath. The tie between us would not grow less
                but more beautiful, dear friend, if you knew me better: if I could stand as real
                &amp; near to you as you do to me. But I cannot like you clothe my nature in divine
                poems &amp; so make it visible to you. Ah foolish me! I thought you would catch a
                glimpse of it in those words I wrote—I thought you would say to yourself
                "perhaps this is the voice of my mate" &amp; would seek me a little to make sure if
                it were so or not. O the sweet dreams I have fed on these three years nearly,
                pervading my waking moments, influencing every thought &amp; action. I was so sure,
                so sure if I waited silently, patiently, you would send me some sign: so full of
                joyful hope I could not doubt nor fear. When I lay dying as it seemed, still full of
                the radiant certainty that you would seek me, would not lose [me], that we should as
                surely find one another there as here. And when the ebb ceased &amp; life began to
                flow back into me, O never doubting but it was for you—never doubting but that
                the sweetest, noblest, closest, tenderest companionship ever yet tasted by man &amp;
                woman was to begin for us here &amp; now. Then came the long long waiting, the hope
                deferred: each morning so sure the book would come &amp; with it a word from you
                that should give me leave to speak: no longer to shut down in stern silence the
                love, the yearning, the thoughts that seemed to strain &amp; crush my heart. I know
                what that means—"if thou wast not gifted to sing thou wouldst surely die." I
                felt as if my silence must kill me sometimes. Then when the Book came but with it no
                word for me alone, there was such a storm in [my] heart I could not for weeks read
                in it. I wrote that long letter<ptr target="loc.01701_n5"/> out in the Autumn fields for dear life's sake. I knew I might
                and must speak then. Then I felt relieved, joyful, buoyant once more. Then again
                months of heart-wearying disappointment as I looked in vain for a letter—O
                the anguish at times, the scalding tears, the feeling within as if my heart were
                crushed &amp; doubled up—yet always afterwards saying to myself "if this
                suffering is to make my love which was born &amp; grew up &amp; blossomed all in a
                moment strike deep root down in the dark &amp; cold, penetrate with painful
                intensity every fibre of my being, make it a love such as he himself is capable of
                giving, then welcome this anguish, these bitter deferments: let its roots be watered
                as long as God pleases with my tears."<ptr target="loc.01701_n6"/>
            </p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Annie Gilchrist</signed>
            </closer>

            <postscript>
                <p>50 Marquis Road <lb/>Camden Sqr. N. W. <lb/>London</p>
            </postscript>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>