<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00816">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 5 April 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00816</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">207&#8211;208</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 5 April 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-04-05">April 5, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-04">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2009-09-01">updated annotations according to new correspondence sytlesheet guidelines</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-03">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1864-04-05">Tuesday afternoon April 5th | '64</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got a letter from Jeff yesterday&#8212;he says you often work too hard, exposing yourself, I suppose scrubbing &amp;c. and the worst of it is I am afraid it is true&#8212;Mother, I would take things easy, &amp; let up on the scrubbing &amp; such things, they may be needed perhaps, but they ain't half as much needed as that you should be as well as possible, &amp; free from rheumatism &amp; cold<ptr target="loc.00816_n1"/>&#8212;Jeff says that sis has had the chicken pox&#8212;has she got all over it&#8212;I want to hear&#8212;So Nance<ptr target="loc.00816_n2"/> has had another child, poor little one, there don't seem to be much show for it, poor little young one, these times.</p>
            <p>We are having awful rainy weather here&#8212;it is raining to-day, steady &amp; spiteful enough&#8212;the soldiers in camp are having the benefit of it, &amp; the sick, many of them&#8212;there is a great deal of rheumatism &amp; also throat diseases, &amp; they are affected by the weather&#8212;I have writ to George again, directed to Knoxville&#8212;Mother, I got a letter this morning from Lewis Brown,<ptr target="loc.00816_n3"/> the young man that had his leg amputated two months or so ago&#8212;(the one that I slept in the hospital by several nights for fear of hemorrhage from the amputation)&#8212;he is home at Elkton, Maryland, on furlough, he wants me to come out there, but I believe I shall not go, he is doing very well&#8212;there are many very bad now in hospitals&#8212;so many of the soldiers are getting broke down after two years, or two &amp; a half, exposure, &amp; bad diet, pork, hard biscuit, bad water or none at all, &amp;c &amp;c&#8212;so we have them brought up here. O it is terrible, &amp; getting worse, worse, worse&#8212;I thought it was bad to see the wounded, but to see these I sometimes think is more pitiful still&#8212;</p>
            <p>Well, mother, I went to see the great spirit medium Foster, there were some little things some might call curious perhaps, but it is a shallow thing &amp; a humbug&#8212;a gentleman who was with me was somewhat impressed, but I could not see any thing in it worth calling supernatural&#8212;I wouldnt turn on my heel to go again &amp; see such things, or twice as much&#8212;we had table rappings &amp; lots of nonsense&#8212;I will give you particulars when I come home one of these days&#8212;</p>
            <p>Jeff, I believe there is a fate on your long letter, I thought I would write it to-day, but as it happens I will hardly get this in the mail I fear in time for to-day&#8212;O how I want to see you all, &amp; sis &amp; Hat&#8212;Well I have scratched out a great letter, just as fast as I could write&#8212;</p>
            <p>Wednesday forenoon&#8212;Mother, I didn't get the letter in the mail yesterday&#8212;I have just had my breakfast, some good tea &amp; good toast &amp; butter&#8212;I write this in my room, 456 Sixth st.&#8212;the storm seems to be over&#8212;dear Mother, I hope you are well &amp; in good spirits&#8212;Write to me often as you can &amp; Jeff too&#8212;any news from Han?</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
