<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00458">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 25 December 1872</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00458</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">150-151</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 25 December 1872</title>
               <date when="1872-12-25">December 25, 1872</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis </name>
                  <date when="1872-12-25">Dec 25th /72</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Merry Christmas to you all&#8212;and many of them&#8212;We to-day, have been experiencing about as cold weather as one can stand  For the last four or five days it has been terrible cold&#8212;but yesterday it was a little too much for anything  10, 12 and down to 20 below Zero has been our experience&#8212;what do you think of that?</p>
            <p>Mattie received your letter all right&#8212;Mat is feeling about the same&#8212;no better, nor do I see that she fails much more&#8212;she keeps her bed about half her time&#8212;she has no appetite&#8212;has not eaten anything for two months&#8212;except her raw eggs and whiskey<ptr target="loc.00458_n1"/>&#8212;this seems to be about the only food that agrees with her&#8212;</p>
            <p>We have had this horse disease here<ptr target="loc.00458_n2"/>&#8212;but not as bad as you have had it East I guess&#8212;my horse has been very sick&#8212;I thought at one time I would lose him but he is getting well again now  I hav'nt used him for abt three weeks&#8212;nor shall I be able to unless the weather changes, for a long while to come.</p>
            <p>Nothing new&#8212;I was up to Chicago for a couple of weeks or so ago&#8212;saw Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00458_n3"/> up there&#8212;he seems to like it west&#8212;he looks first-rate and has plenty to do&#8212;I judge from what he says all his people like it at Milwaukee</p>
            <p>I was sorry to hear that George had been discharged from the Brooklyn payroll&#8212;I suppose however that when they have pipes to make he will get the work again&#8212;will he not<ptr target="loc.00458_n4"/>&#8212;I do not hear from Brooklyn any more&#8212;have not heard for a long time&#8212;I had a letter from Joe Barkeloo<ptr target="loc.00458_n5"/> yesterday telling me that she was about to start for Europe&#8212;I suppose she has gone ere this&#8212;did you hear from her</p>
            <p>Mattie speaks of you all very often&#8212;she would like above all things to see you and have a talk&#8212;but she is altogether too sick to undertake the journey just now. I was sorry, very sorry, that you made up your mind that you would not come this way&#8212;as I thought, and still believe, that it would have done you both good&#8212;but as the season now stands of course it would be impossible on account of the weather</p>
            <p>I suppose you have quite quiet times&#8212;as of course you do not go out much&#8212;and I hardly expect you make many acquantances&#8212;how do you like Camden&#8212;I cannot tell how 'tis in the winter&#8212;but I remember it last summer as being very pleasant and quiet&#8212;How does Ed get along without a church to attend&#8212;or has he obtained a "situation"</p>
            <p>The children are well as can be and have been fixing up their christmas all day  They all send love&#8212;Mat and all&#8212;I hope dear Mother that your arm is not so bad as it was. We think that Mattie is getting better of her lameness&#8212;at one time she could not use her arm at all</p>
            <p>All send love to Loo &amp; George and hope you will write when you can&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
