<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04279">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William Roscoe Thayer to Walt Whitman, 12 October
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William Roscoe Thayer</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04279</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William Roscoe Thayer</author>
                    <title>William Roscoe Thayer to Walt Whitman, 12 October 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-10-12" xml:id="dat1">October 12, 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 17</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender"> 
                    <persName key="Thayer, William Roscoe" ref="n3104">William Roscoe Thayer</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-15" who="#smb">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-07-10" who="#smb">final check</change>
            <change when="2015-06-12" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-12" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-11-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-14" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00573_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">68 Mt. Auburn Street.</name>
                    <name type="place">Cambridge, <choice><abbr>Mass<hi rend="superscript">tts.</hi></abbr><expan>Massachusetts</expan></choice></name>
                    <date when="1885-10-12">1888, <choice><abbr>Oct<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>,</abbr><expan>October</expan></choice> 12</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> Many times during the past four or five weeks I have thought of your cordial
                invitation to me to write to you, but I have waited until I have got settled into my
                new mode of life before availing myself of the pleasure. Since I saw you I have
                spent nearly a fortnight at Mt. Desert&#8212; an island which in small space combines
                every variety of scenery&#8212;ocean and cliffs, mountain and lake, forest and
                beach&#8212; an <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00574_large.jpg" type="verso"/> epitome
                of what those who love beautiful landscape (and seascape) prize most. I wished, as
                I stood on the top of Green Mountain, the highest point on the island, and looked
                down upon a view of indescribable beauty &amp; variety that I could by some magic
                have brought it all before your eyes, because I suspected that in Camden you would
                have given much for such a sight and also for many a long breath of the fresh brisk
                breeze. I can't describe to you the mysterious fascination the ocean has for me, or
                how <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00575_large.jpg" type="recto"/> I was stirred
                and pleased to hear once more the tone from his "husky-haughty lips"<ptr target="loc.04279_n1"/>&#8212; those
                ceaseless chatterers and orators. </p>
            <p> As you are probably aware Bar Harbor, the chief place on Mt. Desert, has become a
                fashionable resort. A few years ago the natives, (like most of the Maine folk, dull,
                cloddish creatures) passed from season to season in unbroken monotony, content to
                grab a few vegetables from ill-tilled, rocky, soil and to live on smoked fish. Not so
                long before them the Indians themselves built their wigwams and hunted game in the
                forests. </p>
            <p> Now, you meet the rich <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ss" cert="high"
                    >idlers</unclear>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00576_large.jpg" type="verso"/> from Boston, New
                York, Chicago and other cities, during their gorgeous turn-outs along well-kept roads. French cooks
                poke their white caps from the kitchen windows of costly villas, and French millinery adorns
                fashionable ladies. In the season&#8212;that is during part of July and the whole of
                August&#8212;big hotels are crammed with thousands of visitors, and social
                extravagance reaches so high a level as in Fifth Avenue in winter. Of all this I saw
                but little, because most of the gay people had left, but I could not help
                contrasting the unsatisfying <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.00577_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> showiness and gilded insincerity of some of the drawing rooms I
                visited, with the homelike simplicity and comfort of your little parlor, where I
                found "plain living and high thinking"<ptr target="loc.04279_n2"/> embodied. For that privilege I shall long be
                grateful. </p>
            <p> Well, I came back from Mt. Desert feeling much better in body and spirits, having
                exchanged some of the heaviness and weariness contracted in Philadelphia for the
                beneficient effects wrought by crisp air, blue skies, endlessly fascinating play of
                color and shadows in sea and slopes, and old ocean's tranquilizing drone. Without
                much trouble I found a sunny room in Cambridge <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc_vm.00578_large.jpg" type="verso"/> and having at last got my books
                within reach I begin to feel at home. It is pleasant to be my own master again, and
                to be able, for the present at least, to follow my inclinations. If I am reading I need not hurry
                to reach the office, or submit to other interruption; if I wish to walk, the day and
                the night, and roads leading in all directions, are mine. Occasionally comes the
                desire of writing but the proper moment has not yet accompanied it, and I do not
                force myself, suspecting that as I gradually outline the strain upon mind and body
                which nearly four years of <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.00579_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> constant journalistic drudgery caused, the impulse to write will
                need no coaxing. </p>
            <p> I attend several courses at the University, chiefly upon historical subjects. Good
                fortune for me has been James Russell Lowell's<ptr target="n3105"/> consent to conduct a course dealing
                with Dante and Cervantes. I have as yet met him but once, but then I was charmed by
                him. You won't detect pedant or such about him, but a splendid example of a
                cultivated American, who knows the best that other lands and times have to offer,
                but who is still American. I look forward to a closer acquaintance with him.
                Certainly, it will be impossible to meet such a man <pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="loc_vm.00580_large.jpg" type="verso"/> frequently without getting much
                good. I find it of inestimable value to see in operation traits and principles over
                which men theorize interminably. Better, one example of nobility than fifty recipes
                for it. And so, in Mr. Lowell, one has a remarkable pattern of the man of broad
                culture. When I remember that he dared to lift his voice against slavery years ago,
                when to do so was dangerous to one's body and particularly difficult for those who
                belonged to the social circle in which he and Wendell Phillips were brought
                up&#8212;when I remember this, and witness the well-deserved honor of his later
                years, I think he must stand among <pb xml:id="leaf005r"
                    facs="loc_vm.00581_large.jpg" type="recto"/> the few thoroughly fortunate poets
                who have received during their lifetime what usually is bestowed upon poets' memory.
                Of course you are familiar with Lowell's "Commemoration Ode"<ptr target="loc.04279_n3"/>&#8212;a poem, it seems
                to me&#8212;in which the best Americanism gets itself uttered in memorable fashion. </p>
            <p> I was very glad to receive several weeks ago an account of the horse and phaeton. I
                am sorry that I knew nothing of the surprise beforehand so that I might have had the
                pleasure of being among those who planned the gift. I hope you are able to drive
                every day, and that from your new point of view you will make some observation that
                you will share with your <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_vm.00582_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> friends. Do you discover a different aspect in nature and men now
                that you look down upon them from the seat of your vehicle? I earnestly wish that
                this new possession may bring you much pleasure and improve your health. </p>
            <p> I have given the newspapers so little attention during the past month&#8212;merely
                glancing at its telegraphic news from day to day&#8212;that I haven't seen anything
                that might interest you, which you have not also seen; but I shall soon be more
                regular in skimming the English &amp; American weeklies, and I will send you
                whatever I deem <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_vm.00583_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                you would care to have. I am reading&#8212;among a dozen books&#8212;Lewes's "Life
                of Goethe,"<ptr target="loc.04279_n4"/> bright, easy and entertaining. Like everything that pertains to Goethe
                this account of him has an especial charm for me.&#8212;But I must stop, first,
                because you may find my garrulity tedious, and second, because the clocks have
                tolled midnight. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Very truly</salute>
                <signed>William R. Thayer.</signed>
            </closer> 
            <postscript> 
                <p> P.S. It occurs to me to remind you of that letter of Sidney Lanier<ptr target="n0888"/> which we spoke
                    of in one of our talks&#8212;and yet I feel that I have but slight claim upon
                    your good nature. </p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_vm.00584_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
