<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00414">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 27 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00414</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">57-59</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 27 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-27">May 27, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-20">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-27">May 27th 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mother recived your letter of last Tuesday, this morning<ptr target="loc.00414_n1"/>  We were glad to hear from you  indeed I began to think that the hospitals had got the better of you, as we had not heard in so long. I mailed you a letter from Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00414_n2"/> to-day containing some money. I suppose Mr Lane would have written you before but he met with quite a serious accident last Sunday  His little boy, abt 5 years old, fell from the balcony down in the area on the stone steps and hurt his head pretty bad. The Dr's hardly know how bad he is hurt, but think he will recover. Dr Ruggles<ptr target="loc.00414_n3"/> who was called in says that it is hardly possible to say how it will go with him for abt 10 days  It is a great blow to Mr Lane as he was his favorite child. I am in hopes that it is not so serious as we at first supposed. With us every thing is the same as usual. Mother is quite well  Mattie is well yet but how long she will continue so is a question,<ptr target="loc.00414_n4"/> she is getting along first rate. she has a young girl to help her do the house work and is in the best of spirits  Hattie is getting along finely growing well and has perfect health. She has grown wonderfully since you left. I think you would hardly know her. A few days since she had quite a bad fall, or rather it might have been one but she luckily escaped without doing herself much harm  She fell in the yard and hit her forehead on the little curb stones that are set on edge along the sides of the walks. She cut quite a gash in her forehead but it has entirely healed up and indeed hardly leaves any mark now</p>
            <p>We had a letter from George written abt the time that yours was<ptr target="loc.00414_n5"/>  I answered it at once. When you write to George tell him that I write him quite often although he does not seem to get them. Andrew thinks he will go down to Newbern the last of this week. He will go down with Jim Cornwell.<ptr target="loc.00414_n6"/> Andrew is going to take charge of the building of some fortifications I believe. Andrew's health is not good although I think he is better than he was and I think he would get well easy enough if he took better care of himself and did not drink so much. His family are all well. We or rather Mother had a <hi rend="italic">letter</hi> from Heyde the other day reading thus  "Your letter received. Han is better to-day than she has been for months&#8212;Charlie"  That was all there was in it. Rather short and sweet wasn't it.</p>
            <p>We are having what might be called first-class weather here to-day, athoug[h] we have had that same cold, damp North east wind that you spoke of  Everything in the country looks well and I guess that we shall have large crops unless something unlikely occurs. We are anxiously expecting to hear from Vicksburg and begin to fear that it is going to turn out like the Victories of the Army of the Potomac although Grant aint in the habit of doing such things either.<ptr target="loc.00414_n7"/> I hope and pray that he may be successful  I cannot agree with you Walt in relation to the President. I think that he is not a man for the times, not big enough  He dont seem to have even force enough to stop bickerings between his own Cabinet and Generals nor force enough to do as he thinks best.<ptr target="loc.00414_n8"/> We begin also to fear that Hooker did not win a <hi rend="italic">very great victory</hi> either or he would hardly lie idle so long during the best part of the year.<ptr target="loc.00414_n9"/> No, A. L.<ptr target="loc.00414_n10"/> is not the man and I hardly know if we have one that is equal to the thing. Write me  you have almost forgotten me. All send their love,</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionately Jeff.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
