<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00404">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 2 April 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00404</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">40-42</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 2 April 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-04-02">April 2, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-08-28">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-04-02">April 2nd 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I intended to have written you yesterday but did not have an opportunity. Everything is going along all right with us except Andrew is real sick with his throat.<ptr target="loc.00404_n1"/> He cannot talk at all and eats but with the greatest agony. He has had some doctor attending him that I think has treated him very badly. I am going to have him have an interview with Dr Ruggles<ptr target="loc.00404_n2"/> this Eve, and hope he will be able to do something for him at once. Andrew, himself, seems to think that he is a gone case, but I cannot think as badly of him as that. I will write you again tomorrow what Ruggles says.</p>
            <p>Mother received your last letter with the shin plasters all right, and in regard to your papers, Mss &amp;c they are all carefully put up, everything, even the smallest scrap is packed up so you will certainly find everything that you left at home all right<ptr target="loc.00404_n3"/>
            </p>
            <p>About George. We do not hear from him. He wrote mother that he would certainly write her again befor he left Newport News and as long as she did not hear from him she might be sure that he was there. I have an idea that the 51st were left behind, although it is hard to tell about it. I should write to George to-day if I <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> that he was still down to Newport News.<ptr target="loc.00404_n4"/> Walt I should like to have letters from you much oftener  I am real worry to hear that the trouble in your head has again made its appearence. I can tell how you must feel for I am having something of the same kind myself but in a much milder form than you are. Dr Ruggles has been quite sick with the same thing but has recovered. Indeed almost everyone that I know has had a bad time with cold &amp;c in the head. I hope dear Walt that you will speedily recover. Mother is as well as usual  Mattie is also quite well. We have not heard from Han for some little time. I suppose that she is about the same and I fear that she will be a long time in getting well.<ptr target="loc.00404_n5"/> Hattie is as well and interesting as usual. Yesterday she had an immensely bad fall on the back part of her head. She was sitting in the chair at the sewing machine and reached over to get a small piece of stuff to stitch, leaned too far and fell striking the back part of her head pretty hard against the frame of the Extension table leaves  We bathed her head for a long time with cold water and this morning although the swelling was not all gone she appeared abt as well as usual. I was much frightened though at first I can tell you.</p>
            <p>Walt do you ever have a chance to get hold of any of the scientific reports that Uncle Sam prints. Would it be possible for you to obtain a copy of the Pacific R. R. Exploration &amp;c Reports.<ptr target="loc.00404_n6"/> I should like much to get hold of anything in that line, and would be much obliged to you if you could get them for me. I find them of great use in giving me ideas about my business and they are too cursed costly to buy  Look around you and if you catch anything send it along will you</p>
            <p>I will write you again to-morrow</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Yours Affectionately, Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
