<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05693">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 1 April
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05693</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 1 April 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-04-01" xml:id="dat1">April 1, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-25" who="#nhg">added images, updated transcription</change>
            <change when="2014-11-17" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-10" who="#ak">corrected transcription and checked encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-11-10" who="#no">checked, added period in closing salute</change>
            <change when="2014-07-23" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded and annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03281.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes Sept 2 &amp; 4, 1888</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Providence, R.I.</name>
                    <date when="1883-04-01">April 1, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:<!--<ptr target="n2002"/>--></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got your letter of the 29th, and in the afternoon of the same day (March 30) the
                package of books came.<!--<ptr target="loc.05693_n1"/>--> It was very kind in you to send
                them. As Dr. Channing's<!--<ptr target="loc.00945_n5"/>--> family are ardent friends of you
                and your book, and have no recent issues, I turned over to them one copy of the
                poems and the copy of "Specimen Days"&#8212;you know I have both myself ("Specimen
                Days," I regret to say, I have never found time to read, but shall, from the copy you
                sent me, when I return to Washington, 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03281.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                as I shall have more leisure this spring and
                summer than I had in the dreadful months of labor when the book came.) The other
                copy of the poems, I shall reserve for some one who shall prove to be worthy: and I
                hope this disposition of your kind gift will please you.</p>
            <p>The Channing family are staunch adherents, and the girls (Mary and Grace&#8212;Mary
                was recently married and is living in Cambridge&#8212;) both gave their cousin, Col.
                    Higginson,<!--<ptr target="nyp.00440_n9"/>--> (whom I have gone for so savagely in the
                Introductory) a round talking-to on your account, apropos of his article in <hi rend="underline">The
                Woman's Journal</hi>. But Higginson is incorrigible. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03281.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                I imagine, however, that the
                rhinosceros spear I have planted and turned by steam in his hide (in the
                Introductory) will startle his supercilious composure, especially what I say about
                his Port Royal experience, and I guess he will be mad as a wet hen. All right:
                people that live in porcelain towers or crystal palaces, shouldn't throw stones at
                the "lower <hi rend="underline">h</hi>orders," such as we are,&#8212;we whose armorial legend is "'eave 'arf
                a brick at 'im!"</p>
            <p>It was very kind to send Karl Elze's<!--<ptr target="n3085"/>--> book, which I have read
                (you know I am a very rapid reader) and will return 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03281.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                to you by express. I knew him
                already by his life of Byron,<!--<ptr target="n0135"/>--> which I own, and the best thing
                in which is his perfectly exterminating analysis of Mrs Stowe's<!--<ptr target="n3062"
                />--> (or rather Lady Byron's) ridiculous slander. Otherwise in this Byron book, as in
                the one on Shakespeare, he is a perfect Bismarck<!--<ptr target="n0087"/>--> phillistine,
                with a head of wood just larded with brains. The lack of political freedom, inducing
                proclivity to aristocratic ideas, and utter lack of sympathy with democratic or
                republican thought, makes all the Germans, even the great ones, (and Elze is not
                great), perfectly worthless whenever they approach topics connected with 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03281.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                the
                questions of liberty and humanity; and Shakespeare cannot be successfully approached
                in criticism except in connection with the mighty human movement which made the life
                of his age&#8212;"the world-bettering age," as one of the great Elizabethan men
                calls it. Hence this supper of sawdust, such as <choice>
                    <sic>Carl</sic>
                    <corr>Karl</corr>
                </choice> Elze and others like him, sets for us. A dull fellow, moreover, which
                only partly accounts for his slurring notice of Hugo's magnificent book on
                Shakespeare&#8212;Bismarckism being accountable for the rest of it. However, what
                paralyzes all Shakespearean criticism, Elze's, as well as the rest, is the
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03281.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                obstinate
                consideration of the work with that Stratford chucklehead and his chucklehead
                biography. If we had no notion whatever of the author, we should fare better in
                understanding the work than we do with William Shakespeare on our brains like an
                incubus. To know a man is to know his book. To be dead sure in advance that Barnum
                wrote <hi rend="underline">Hamlet</hi> and <hi rend="underline">The Tempest</hi>, is to be dead sure of knowing little or nothing of
                those works forever.</p>
            <p>I have heard nothing yet about the Heywood trial.<!--<ptr target="n3086"/>--> You and
                    McKay<!--<ptr target="syr.00031_n3"/>-->
                <hi rend="underline">did perfectly right</hi> in keeping aloof and not contributing
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03281.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                to
                the defence. Your connection could not help him and might hurt you. "Against
                stupidity the gods themselves are powerless," says Euripides, and Heywood is
                certainly a champion jackass. I am sorry for him, but his bed is his own making, and
                he should have known what Comstock could do to him if he advertised war on the
                ovaries. I only hope we shall escape the consequences of his folly.</p>
            <p>I suppose the correction has been made, but I noticed in Bucke's<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>-->
                Latin motto the error of the diphthong &#339; (in the fourth line) in the word
                pr&#230;clarius. It should be &#230; (AE), not &#339;. Munro spells it <hi rend="underline">praeclarius</hi>, not
                using 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03281.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
                the diphthong character at all, which is sensible.&#8212;It is a glorious
                    epigraph.<!--<ptr target="loc.05693_n2"/>--></p>
            <p>I have just been down to the Post Office, and got your letter of yesterday,<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05693_n3"/>--> but not the revise, which will not come until tomorrow
                morning. I am rejoiced at what you say of my contribution, but feel <hi
                    rend="underline">dreadfully</hi> at the prospect your letter opens, of my
                paragraphing being changed. I could bear with equanimity anything but
                that&#8212;especially the breaking up of my running account of the great books into
                paragraphs. <hi rend="underline">That</hi> I never can like. The effect will be
                horrible. Besides, you told me I was to have my way.</p>
            <p>I will write you again after 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03281.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
                I get the revise. <hi rend="underline">I expect to leave here tomorrow
                evening and arrive in Washington on Tuesday afternoon:</hi> so unless you hear to the
                contrary, address me at the Office of the Life Saving Service, as usual.</p>
            <p>I leave heavy-hearted, for Jeannie is very feeble, and I fear the worst.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05693_n4"/>--> Yet I must go on to Washington, even if I have to return
                again. I can only hope that she will revive as the days go on (illness has its ebbs
                and flows) and be able to journey home. At present, she is too ill and 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03281.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
                weak to leave
                her bed.</p>
            <p>I shall probably return you the revise from Washington, though I may be able to look
                over it before I leave, if I get it tomorrow morning. Thanks to Protestantism,
                Sunday knocks post office usages endways. The post office can only be open for an
                hour on God's day, so that I get your letter, but not the proof, there not being time
                for the officials to overhaul postal matter of the second or third or fourth class
                until Monday!</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Goodbye,</salute>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed>W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
