<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01486">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Edward Dowden to Walt Whitman, 23 July
                    1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Edward Dowden</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01486</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Edward Dowden</author>
                    <title>Edward Dowden to Walt Whitman, 23 July 1871</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1871-07-23" xml:id="dat1">July 23, 1871</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Dowden, Edward">Edward Dowden</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2010-12-14" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-04" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01486.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">Montenotte</name>
                    <name type="place">Cork, Ireland</name>
                    <date when="1871-07-23">July 23 1871</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wished to send you a copy of the July No of the Westminster Review containing an
                article by me which attempts a study of one side of your work in literature. I wrote
                to Mr. W. M. Rossetti to enquire for your address &amp; he tells me that he has
                already forwarded a copy to you. But I will not be defrauded by Mr. Rossetti of the
                pleasure I had promised 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01486.004.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                myself &amp; therefore you must accept a second copy of the Review (which I post
                with this letter) &amp; do what you like with it.</p>

            <p>I ought to say that the article expresses very partially the impression which your
                writings have made on me. It keeps, as is obvious, at a single point of view &amp;
                regards only what becomes visible from that point. But also I wrote more cooly than I
                feel because I wanted those, who being ignorant of your writings are perhaps
                prejudiced against them, to say "Here is a cool, judicious, impartial 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01486.005.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                critic who finds a
                great deal in Whitman—perhaps, after all, we are mistaken." Perhaps this will
                be unsatisfactory to you, &amp; you would prefer that your critic should let the
                full force of your writings appear in his criticism, &amp; attract those who are to
                be attracted, &amp; repel those who are to be repelled, &amp; you may value the
                power of repulsion as well as that of attraction. But so many persons capable of
                loving your work, by some mischance or miscarriage or by some ignorance or removable
                error fail in their approach to you, or do not approach at all. 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01486.006.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                that I think I am justified in my attempt.</p>
            
            <p>You have many readers in Ireland, &amp; those who read do not feel a qualified
                delight in your poems—do not love them by degree, but with an absolute, a
                personal love. We none of us question that yours is the clearest, &amp; sweetest,
                &amp; fullest American voice. We grant as true all that you claim for yourself. And
                you gain steadily among us new readers &amp; lovers.</p>
            
            <p>If you care at all for what I have written it would certainly be a pleasure to hear
                this from yourself. If you do not care for it you will know 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01486.007.jpg" type="recto"/> that I wished to do better than I
                did.</p>

            <p>My fixed residence is 50 Wellington Road, <lb/> Dublin, <lb/>Ireland.</p>
            
            <p>My work there is that of Professor of English Literature in the University of Dublin.
                We have lately had a good public lecture in Dublin from a Fellow of Trinity College
                on your poems—R. Y. Tyrrell a man who knows Greek poetry very well, &amp; who
                finds it does not interfere with his regard for yours. If the lecture should at any
                time be published 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01486.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
                I shall send you a copy.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>I am,</salute>
                <salute>dear Sir,</salute>
                <salute>Very truly yours</salute>
                <signed>Edward Dowden.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>