<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00888">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Lewis K. Brown, 15 August 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00888</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">133-135</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Lewis K. Brown, 15 August 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-08-15">August 15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Brown, Lewis K.">Lewis K. Brown</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-18">added TEI id</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-08-15">August 15 1863</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Lewy, your letter of August 10 came safe, &amp; was glad to hear all about you, &amp; the way you are spending the time&#8212;Lew, you must be having first rate times out there&#8212;well you need something to make up what you have suffered&#8212;You speak of being used well out there&#8212;Lewy, I feel as if I could love any one that uses you well, &amp; does you a kindness&#8212;but what kind of heart must that man have that would treat otherwise, or say any thing insulting, to a crippled young soldier, hurt in fighting for this union &amp; flag? (Well I should say damned little man or heart in the business)&#8212;</p>
            <p>Should you meet any such, you must not mind them, dear comrade, &amp; not allow your feelings to be hurt by such loafers&#8212;(I agree with you that a rebel in the southern army is much more respectable than a northern copperhead.) Dear son, when I read about your agreeable visit of a week, &amp; how much you enjoyed yourself, I felt as much gratified as though I had enjoyed it myself&#8212;&amp; I was truly thankful to hear that your leg is still doing well, &amp; on the gain&#8212;you must not mind its being slowly, dear son, if it only goes forward instead of backward, &amp; you must try to be very careful of your eating &amp; drinking &amp;c., not indulge in any excesses, &amp; not eat too much flummery, but generally plain food, for that is always best, &amp; it helps along so much.</p> 
            <p>Lewy, I believe I wrote you an acc't of the presentation to Dr Bliss&#8212;he is now off north for three weeks&#8212;Dr Butler<ptr target="loc.00888_n1"/> (ward D) is in charge&#8212;some of the doctors &amp; wardmasters have been drafted&#8212;poor Johnny Mahay<ptr target="loc.00888_n2"/> is not in very good spirits&#8212;he was to have an operation performed before Bliss went, but he went off &amp; did not do it&#8212;Johnny is pretty low some days&#8212;Things in ward K are pretty much the same&#8212;they had some improvem'ts in the Hospital, new sinks, much better, &amp; the grounds in front &amp; between the wards nicely laid out in flowers &amp; grass plots &amp;c.&#8212;but, Lew, it has been awful hot in the wards the past two weeks, the roofs burnt like fire&#8212;</p>
            <p>There is no particular war news&#8212;they are having batches of conscripts now every day in the Army&#8212;Meade is down on the upper Rappahannock &amp; fords, &amp; around Warrenton&#8212;Lee stretches down toward Gordonsville, they say his head quarters is there&#8212;folks are all looking toward Charleston&#8212;if we could only succeed there, I don't know what secesh would do&#8212;the ground seems to be slipping more &amp; more from under their feet&#8212;Lew, the <hi rend="italic">Union</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="italic">American Flag</hi> must conquer, it is destiny&#8212;it may be long, or it may be short, but that will be the result&#8212;but O what precious lives have been lost by tens of thousands in the struggle already&#8212;</p>
            <p>Lew, you speak in your letter how you would like to see me&#8212;well, my darling, I wonder if there is not somebody who would be gratified to see you, &amp; always will be wherever he is&#8212;Dear comrade, I was highly pleased at your telling me in your letter about your folks' place, the house &amp; land &amp; all the items&#8212;you say I must excuse you for writing so much foolishness&#8212;nothing of the kind&#8212;My darling boy, when you write to me, you must write without ceremony, I like to hear every little thing about yourself &amp; your affairs&#8212;you need never care how you write to me, Lewy, if you will only&#8212;I never think about literary perfection in letters either, it is the <hi rend="italic">man</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="italic">feeling</hi>&#8212;Lewy, I am feeling pretty well, but the sun affects me a little, aching &amp; fulness in the head&#8212;a good many have been sun-struck here the last two weeks&#8212;I keep shady through the middle of the day lately&#8212;Well, my dear boy, I have scribbled away any thing, for I wanted to write you to-day &amp; now I must switch off&#8212;good by, my darling comrade, for the present, &amp; I pray God to bless you now &amp; always.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt.</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Write when you feel like it, Lewy, don't hurry&#8212;address still care Major Hapgood, paymaster U S A, cor 15th &amp; F st Washington D C.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
