<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04059">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 26 March 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="gt">Grace Thomas</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04059</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">179&#8211;180</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 26 March 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-03-26" xml:id="dat1">March 26, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#gt">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-02" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">112 Madison Ave.</name>
                    <date when="1879-03-26" rend="right">March 26, '79.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>It seems quite a long while since I wrote, &#38; a <hi rend="italic">very long</hi> while since you wrote.<ptr target="n0259"/> I am beginning to turn my thoughts Philadelphia-wards that we may have some weeks near you before we set out on fresh wanderings across the sea; and though I feel quite cheery about them, I look eagerly forward to the time beyond that when we have a fixed, final nest of our own again, where we can welcome you just when and as you please. Whichever side the Atlantic it is, you will come surely? for you belong to the one country as much as to the other. And I shall always feel that I do too. I take back with me a deep and hearty love for America&#8212;I came indeed with a good deal of that, but what I take back is different&#8212;stronger, more real. I went over to see friends in Brooklyn yesterday, &#38; it was more lovely than I can tell you on the Ferry&#8212;in fact, it was just your poem, "Crossing Brooklyn Ferry". Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> still painting away <hi rend="italic">con amore</hi>, &#38; making good progress. I met Joaquin Miller<ptr target="n0412"/> at the Bigelows last week, &#38; he was very pleasant (which isn't always the case) and said some very good things to me. Thursday we are going to lunch with Mrs. Albert Brown&#8212;perhaps you may have heard of her as Bessie Griffiths. She was a Southern lady who, when she was about 18, freed all her slaves &#38; left herself penniless. On Sunday we take tea at Prof. Rood's of Columbia College. Kate Hillard<ptr target="n0302"/> we often see &#38; have lively chats with. We meet also &#38; see a good deal of General Edward Lee<ptr target="n3008"/>&#8212;a fine soldierly looking man, &#38; I believe he distinguished himself in the war &#38; was afterwards sent to organize the new Territory of Wyoming, &#38; was the first governor. I wish very much that if you or your brother knew him or know anything about him, you would tell me&#8212;for reasons that I will tell you by &#38; bye. Bee<ptr target="n0260"/> is seeing a great deal of the educated coloured people at Boston&#8212;was at the meeting of a literary club&#8212;the only white among 20 or 30 coloured ladies&#8212;likes them much.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>Write soon, dear Friend. Meanwhile, best love &#38; good-bye.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>No letters from England this long while.</p>
                    
                    <p>Please give friendly greetings from me to your brother &#38; sister.</p>
                </postscript>  
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
