<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00395">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 1 January 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>

               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00395</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">19-21</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 1 January 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-01-01">January 1, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-12-22">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2006-11-21">added rend="doubleunderline" attribute to encoding</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
               <opener>
                  <dateline rend="right">
                     <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                     <date when="1863-01-01">Jan. 1st 1863</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear brother Walt,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>"Happy New Year" Walt, to you, is the wish and greeting of your Mother and brothers and sister in Brooklyn, and Hattie too says to send Happy new Year for her too to Uncle Walt. I received the letter that you wrote me in due time and yesterday Mother received one from you<ptr target="loc.00395_n1"/>  I wrote to you two letters<ptr target="loc.00395_n2"/> and directed [them] to the "Delevan House, cor. of Pennsylvania and West Ninth Streets.["]<ptr target="loc.00395_n3"/> Dear Walt, what hours of trouble you must of past till you found George  Mother and Mat each had a "good cry" yesterday in reading of how you had to get along, and I myself could hardly keep the water from my face  If you had only been coming home they say, and lost your money, twould have been no matter  but to loose it when you did not know how much you might need it on Georges account, must have made you felt miserable indeed.<ptr target="loc.00395_n4"/> And then the damnable conduct of those "big bugs" (I believe the biggest bugs are ["]tumble turds") that you speak about must have made you feel doubly provoked.<ptr target="loc.00395_n5"/> But the most trying scene of all must have been your sight in front of the Hospital tent, not knowing how severely George was wounded. I should think that it would almost have been too much for you.<ptr target="loc.00395_n6"/> But thank God, it has all come out right, and George was not much hurt.</p>
               <p>I have written George, somewhat urging him to quit the army.<ptr target="loc.00395_n7"/> I think that it is the duty of all of us to urge this upon him, I honestly think that he has done enough and run risk enough for any one man. And too there is no judgement used in putting the old regiments in battle, they just keep throwing them in as long as there is a man left. If I belonged to one I am sure that it would look to me just as if they were bound to kill every man as long as the number of the Reg. was represented Walt do see and talk this matter over with him  Speak with him of Mother, who is getting old very old, and if anything should happen [to] him I am quite sure she could not survive it  Even now I can see the effect of the weeks worry that she has already had.  Certainly no one could find any fault with him, or talk of him other than the bravest of the brave if he should resign to-morrow. And another thing I certanly do not see how this immense risk and sacrifice of life is doing any good at all, it looks very much to me as if we were slowly but surely drifting towards mediation or something worse. Walt, I beg of you, do not neglect to see George and put this thing in its strongest light. Just think for a moment of the number of suckers that are gaining all the real benefits of the war (if that is not wicked to say) and think of George and thousands of others running all the risk while they are drawing all the pay. Think of Dick Butt<ptr target="loc.00395_n8"/> and the thousand [other?] sneaks that we know. If he wont resign see if there is no possible way in which he can be removed for a while at least from his present place to one of less danger. Dear Walt I honestly think that he is carrying the life of our Mother, dear dear Mother with his own, and therefore I say tis our <hi rend="italic">duty</hi>
                  <ptr target="loc.00395_n9"/> to urge him to resign and his <hi rend="italic">duty</hi>
                  <ptr target="loc.00395_n10"/> to do it. Again and again let me say that if possible accomplish it<ptr target="loc.00395_n11"/>
               </p>
               <p>Friday 2nd. I intended to mail this to you yesterday but not having a stamp and not being able to get one could'nt do it. I have just taken dinner with Mat, Mother and Sis. on "Turkey." Knowing the locality you can imagine the whole performance to a niceity. I only wish that you and George had been with us, then the thing would have been complete. Mother is pretty well, but shows the effects of her anxiety about George, I think, quite plainly. On New Years Eve old Mr Turner<ptr target="loc.00395_n12"/> next door, died, quite suddenly I believe. The old man I saw out but a few days since  Otherwise I beleve things are about as usual.  How about you Walt, what are you trying to get to do. How about <hi rend="italic">Money</hi>. If you get hard pushed let me know and I will try and raise you some. I am going along as usual, earning about half time with a "constant" prospect of doing better. Of course if you can poultice any thing so as to draw a little money out of it why do so, but dont be discouraged if you cant. I would rather see you and George come home to-gether than any amt of Green-backs. I understand that our old friend Bill Hart<ptr target="loc.00395_n13"/> is on here, wounded in the battle of Fredricksburg&#8212;, quite badly, but will recover. Mother sends her dearest love also Mat, ditto the rest of us. Write me at once and let me know how you are getting along. I was much, very much interested by your letters and want it repeated. Good bye dear Brother</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>Yours very truly J.</signed>
               </closer>
            
            <postscript>
               <p>Mother had a letter from Heyde to-day  Han is quite well. Mary writes that Fanny is married<ptr target="loc.00395_n14"/>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
