<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00427">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 22 October 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00427</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">80-82</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 22 October 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-22">October 22, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1863-10-22">Oct 22nd 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This morning I mail with this a letter to you from Mother and also a letter to George from Mother. I suppose Mother has told you fully abt Andrew. My own opinion is that he will not recover, that he cannot last long. However I think that it is owning more to the circumstances that surround him than to his disease. There is no use trying to disguise the matter, Andrew is very unfortunately situated in regard to his home. His wife, I guess is not one of the doing kind, and posessed with rather an ugly high temper.<ptr target="loc.00427_n1"/> His disease of course makes Andrew fretful and discouraged, and instead of soothing and nursing him Nancy does the reverse. As to his disease I really think that had I the same disease that I could recover from it.<ptr target="loc.00427_n2"/> However I dont know. I sincerely wish that you would come hom for a short time anyway. I think that you could do Andrew a great deal of good  In the letter<ptr target="loc.00427_n3"/> that Mother received yesterday from you, you speak abt my having been reduced in pay. I am sorry Mother wrote you abt it for it only worries you without doing any good, and another thing it is not like you think in regard to cutting down my wages. I was working for the two boards of Commissioners, one at $40 and the other at $50 per month, and I have got all the work for one board finished (the one at $40) [and?] as the Sal. of the office I hold for the Permanent board (that of Map clerk at $50) is put down in their annual appropriation at $50 why of course I have to get along with it for the present. It is not the meanness<ptr target="loc.00427_n4"/> or anything of that kind of anybody and they would pay me more if they could and will probably in a short time. I shall get some appointment again from the old board I have no doubt, and soon too. As to the worry part, I never think of that  A man with a wife like I have got cant worry even if he wanted to. Give yourself no thought abt my worring. Something that I have got entirely past.<ptr target="loc.00427_n5"/> I have every reason to think that the Commissioners (both boards) think well of me, and I know that Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00427_n6"/> will ever do everything in his power for me, and I undoubtedly in a short time shall be getting more.</p>
            <p>In regard to the Pacific R. R.<ptr target="loc.00427_n7"/> I am real obliged to you. I learned this morning that our friend J. W. Adams<ptr target="loc.00427_n8"/> was appointed chief and I've no doubt but I could get a place at once on it, yet I think that in the end I will make more by staying where I am but its rather pleasant to have that to fall back on. I wish you would write me  Ruggles<ptr target="loc.00427_n9"/> sends his regards.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
