<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00768">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 5 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00768</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">97&#8211;98</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 5 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-05">May 5, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-09-04">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-16">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-05">Tuesday May 5th '63.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter came safe, and was very welcome, &amp; always will be&#8212;Mother, I am sorry about your rheumatism&#8212;If it still continues, I think it would be well for me to write a line to Mrs. Piercy,<ptr target="loc.00768_n1"/> &amp; get Jeff to stop with it, so that you could take the baths again, as I am sure they are very beneficial&#8212;Dear mother, you write me, or Jeff must in the next letter, how you are getting along, whether it is any better, or worse&#8212;I want to know.</p>
            <p>Mother, about George's fund in the bank, I hope by all means you can scratch along so as to leave $250 there&#8212;I am so anxious that our family should have a little ranch, even if it is the meanest kind, off somewhere that you can call your own, &amp; that would do for Ed, &amp;c.&#8212;it might be a real dependence, &amp; comfort&#8212;and may-be for George as much as any one. I mean to come home one of these days, and get the acre or ½ acre somewhere out in some by-place on Long Island, &amp; build it, you see if I dont. About Hannah,<ptr target="loc.00768_n2"/> dear mother, I hardly know what advice to give you&#8212;from what I know at present, I cant tell what course to pursue. I want Han to come home, from the bottom of my heart. Then there are other thoughts &amp; considerations that come up. Dear mother, I cannot advise, but shall acquiesce in any thing that is settled upon, &amp; try to help.</p>
            <p>The condition of things here in the Hospitals is getting pretty bad&#8212;the wounded from the battles around Fredericksburgh are coming up in large numbers.<ptr target="loc.00768_n3"/> It is very sad to see them. I have written to Mr. Lane, asking him to get his friends to forward me what they think proper&#8212;but somehow I feel delicate about sending such requests, after all.<ptr target="loc.00768_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>I have almost made up my mind to do what I can personally, &amp; not seek assistance from others.</p>
            <p>Dear Mother, I have not received any letter from George. I write to him &amp; send papers to Winchester. Mother, while I have been writing this, a very large number of southern prisoners, I should think 1000 at least, has past up Pennsylvania avenue, under a strong guard. I went out in the street, close to them, to look at them. Poor fellows, many of them mere lads&#8212;it brought the tears, they seemed our own flesh &amp; blood too, some wounded, all miserable in clothing, all in dirt &amp; tatters&#8212;many of them fine young men. Mother, I cannot tell you how I feel to see these prisoners marched [<hi rend="italic">incomplete</hi>]</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
