<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00452">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 21 January 1869</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00452</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">134-136</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 21 January 1869</title>
               <date when="1869-01-21">January 21, 1869</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
                  <date when="1869-01-21">Jan 21st 1869</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Tis a long, long time since I have written you, and I am somewhat ashamed of it I assure you&#8212;but somehow I cannot seem to get time&#8212;and so day after day passes without writing. When I was at home I expected to be able to come to Washington to see you but matters turned out so&#8212;combined with Mats poor health at the time, that I could'nt make it out.</p>
            <p>You have learned, of course, through Mother of our safe arrival in St. Louis  We at first put up at Barnums Hotel<ptr target="loc.00452_n1"/> but the place was inconvenient and price very high so I have hired a large room (abt. 25' X 20' by 16 high)  we have a large stove in it, two beds and have our meals served from the Restaurant in the basement&#8212;the room is directly opposite the office<ptr target="loc.00452_n2"/> and altogether quite pleasant&#8212;yet of course we should prefer to keep house&#8212;and shall do so if Mattie gets well enough&#8212;I think Mat is getting better fast. Her cough is very much less&#8212;she is gaining in flesh and is much stronger&#8212;she goes out with me on the work almost every day that it is pleasant and enjoys it hugely. The children go to school&#8212;quite away off too&#8212;so that they take the cars that run past the door and within a block or so of the school. They are both very healthy and when night comes are just as tired as they can be what with their ride in the car&#8212;their studies and play  Both of them grow fast&#8212;Hattie inde[e]d is quite a large girl.</p>
            <p>The works are going along pretty well although just at this moment we are in ill-luck consequent upon the river having risen and overflowed our cofferdam and thereby stopped progress on the river work.<ptr target="loc.00452_n3"/> I have just come down from there and found the water slowly falling and I hope in a few days&#8212;by Sunday next&#8212;to commence again&#8212;this is the part of the works that we expected would be difficult and we have got along with them better than we had a right to expect. For the last three weeks the river has been just on the verge of overflowing us&#8212;the consequence was that we worked hard to crowd the work and fight the water to keep it out of the dam&#8212;the foundations are from 25 to 30 feet under the surface of the water in the river and I felt it would make bad work to be drowned out  It would (the river) go up to within just a few inches of the top of the dam some days and then fall a few inchs&#8212;this style of worry and excitement has had rather a bad effect on me as I have for some two weeks had a pretty bad diarrhea&#8212;but since the matter is settled I am getting better of it&#8212;and shall undoubtedly be all right in a few days now.</p>
            <p>I had a letter from Davis<ptr target="loc.00452_n4"/> to day who is now in Brooklyn&#8212;he says he took dinner on Sunday with Mother and George&#8212;that they were well and that George was getting along quite fast with his Portland Avenue house  Davis thinks of coming back to St. Louis <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Washington&#8212;if he does you will see him and he will give you an idea of what we are attempting to do here&#8212;I wish, dear Walt, that you could come out and see for yourself tho  'twould do us lots of good&#8212;cant you ring in on one of the R. Road examinat[ion] excursions<ptr target="loc.00452_n5"/> and come as far as St Louis  I think it would do you lots of good to come west for awhile just to see how big 'tis getting</p>
            <p>How goes things with you Walt? Will you be able to retain your sit under the new come ins?<ptr target="loc.00452_n6"/> Do you write anything for publications now adays.<ptr target="loc.00452_n7"/> Tis so long since I have heard from you directly that I suppose you have had quite a good dea[l] published that I have not seen.</p>
            <p>Mattie and the children send love&#8212;when you can, scribble us a line&#8212;tis a good day when we get a letter from any of you  Do you hear much about Han,  poor girl I think of her often if I say but little. she has a hard lot of it.<ptr target="loc.00452_n8"/> Give my love to all mutual friends in Washington&#8212;particularly the O'Connors.<ptr target="loc.00452_n9"/>
            </p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionately your brother Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
