<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00818">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 19 April 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00818</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">210&#8211;211</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 19 April 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-04-19">April 19, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2009-09-04">updated annotations according to new style guidelines</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-03">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-03">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1864-04-19">Tuesday noon April 19 '64</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I havn't heard any news from home now in more than a week, I hope you are well, dear Mother, &amp; all the rest too&#8212;there is nothing new or different with me&#8212;I can only write you the same old story about going to the hospitals &amp;c &amp;c.&#8212;I have not heard any thing since from George&#8212;have you heard any thing further?<ptr target="loc.00818_n1"/> I have writ to him, to Annapolis&#8212;We are having it pretty warm here to-day, after a long spell of rain storms, but the last two or three days very fine&#8212;Mother, I suppose you got my letter of last Tuesday, 12th&#8212;</p>
            <p>I went down to the Capitol the nights of the debate on the expulsion of Mr Long<ptr target="loc.00818_n2"/> last week&#8212;they had night sessions, very late&#8212;I like to go to the House of Representatives at night, it is the most magnificent hall, so rich &amp; large, &amp; lighter at night than it is days, &amp; still not a light visible, it comes through the glass roof&#8212;but the speaking &amp; ability of the members is nearly always on a low scale, it is very curious &amp; melancholy to see such a rate of talent there, such tremendous times as these&#8212;I should say about the same range of genius as our old friend Dr Swalm,<ptr target="loc.00818_n3"/> just about&#8212;you may think I am joking, but I am not, Mother&#8212;I am speaking in perfect earnest&#8212;the Capitol grows upon one in time, especially as they have got the great figure on top of it now, &amp; you can see it very well, it is a great bronze figure, the Genius of Liberty<ptr target="loc.00818_n4"/> I suppose&#8212;it looks wonderful toward sundown, I love to go down &amp; look at it, the sun when it is nearly down shines on the headpiece &amp; it dazzles &amp; glistens like a big star, it looks quite curious&#8212;</p>
            <p>Well, Mother, we have commenced on another summer, &amp; what it will bring forth who can tell?&#8212;the campaign of this summer is expected here to be more active &amp; severe than any yet&#8212;As I told you in a former letter Grant is determined to bend every thing to take Richmond &amp; break up the banditti of scoundrels that have stuck themselves up there as a "government"&#8212;he is in earnest about it, his whole soul &amp; all his thoughts night &amp; day are upon it&#8212;he is probably the most in earnest of any man in command or in the government either&#8212;that's something, ain't it, Mother&#8212;&amp; they are bending every thing to fight for their last chance&#8212;calling in their forces from southwest &amp;c&#8212;Dear Mother, give my love to dear brother Jeff &amp; Mat &amp; all&#8212;I write this in my room, 6th st&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
