<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05101">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 14 February
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05101</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 14 February 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-02-14" xml:id="dat1">February 14, 1882</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-09" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-06" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-05" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-30" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-11-07" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01021_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">'82</note>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">29 Lange Strasse</name>
                        <name type="place">Dresden</name>
                        <date when="1882-02-14" rend="right">Tuesday Feb 14</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Whitman</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>So you have had a visit from the Aesthete!<ptr target="loc.05101_n1"/> I was
                    interested in the report you sent me. I know O.W. slightly&#8212;met him once or
                    twice when I was in Trinity College.<ptr target="loc.05101_n2"/> His presence
                    and talk exercised an extraordinary fascination on me. I felt as if I would have
                    done anything for him. But his poetry, then and now, seems to me to be entirely
                    worthless&#8212;dead and artificial&#8212;not even good singing. You may have
                    come across the poems of another Trinity man, and also a lover of
                    yours&#8212;William Wilkins.<ptr target="loc.05101_n3"/> Wilkins <del
                        type="overstrike">is</del> has only a limited range and he's not always
                    sincere &#38; is often affected&#8212;but I think there is real dash and life
                    about him and that a page of him is worth <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                        facs="loc_af.01022_large.jpg" type="verso"/> all Oscar Wilde's poetry put
                        <unclear reason="gap" cert="high" resp="#ss">together.</unclear> How absurd
                    too, to say that Tennyson has cut himself off from the spirit of his time and
                    that not he, but the Aesthetes are at the "heart of the nation"! Tennyson with
                    his glorious battle-ballads, history, humor, is read in every household in
                    England. The world of the Aesthetes is only, after all, London fashionable
                    "society"&#8212;a large and important world no doubt, but not the heart of
                    England, by any manner of means.</p>
                <p>I sent you a 'Kottabos' yesterday with 'Calvin Harlowe' in it&#8212;a slightly
                    amended version.<ptr target="loc.05101_n4"/> I enclose herewith a page of my
                    translation of the Leaves of Grass&#8212;you needn't <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                        facs="loc_af.01023_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <unclear reason="gap" cert="high" resp="#ss">save</unclear> it as I don't want
                    it again. I am studying Luther's translation of the Bible a good deal with
                    reference to this translation. It is grand strong idiomatic German, not the
                    milk-and-water, romantified stuff they put into books nowadays. Germany at
                    present is suffering under an unprecedented plague of mediocrity&#8212;in all
                    branches of imaginative art. Dry bones everywhere&#8212;everything scientific,
                    psychological, faultless, barren&#8212;and they are delighted with it all, and
                    firmly believe themselves to be leading an active spiritual existence. Wagner is
                    the only man that is really alive among them. It is difficult to understand how
                    they can admire him as they do and then <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                        facs="loc_af.01024_large.jpg" type="verso"/>sit down with such perfect
                    complacency <unclear reason="gap" cert="high" resp="#ss">to</unclear> their
                    anatomical philosophy and pedagogic novels and the studies of historical costume
                    which they call paintings. Well, if I was to unburden all my mind on this weary
                    subject I should go on till&#8212;till things got better, I suppose; and there
                    are no signs of that as yet.</p>
                <p>I have come across two charming American girls, with their mother, who are living
                    here now. They are studying, one to be a professional singer, the other a
                    player&#8212;have real genius I think. My wife knows them well too. They are the
                    first Americans I have met who seemed to me at all native growths, and not
                    spoiled Europeans.</p>
                <p>I see the 'Critic' of N. York has given very high praise to my Encheiridion.<ptr
                        target="loc.05101_n5"/> It is selling pretty well I hear, better then I had
                    expected. I see Jeff Davis has written a history of the war.<ptr
                        target="loc.05101_n6"/> Ought to be valuable for a student. I will try and
                    get hold of it.</p>
                <p>Hope you keep well.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Yours always</salute>
                    <signed>T W Rolleston.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="enclosure">

                <lg type="poem">
                    <head type="main-authorial">&#8212;BEGINNENDE.<ptr target="loc.05101_n7"
                    />&#8212;</head>
                    <l>Wie f&#252;r sie auf der Erde gesorgt wird, die von Zeit zu Zeit
                        erschienen,</l>
                    <l>Wie lieb und furchtbar sie der Erde sind,</l>
                    <l>Wie sie f&#252;r sich ebensowohl als f&#252;r irgend einen Andern sich gelten
                        lassen,&#8212;welch' ein Paradoxon ihr Zeitalter scheint,</l>
                    <l>Wie ihnen die Leute gegenstimmen, doch sie nicht kennen,</l>
                    <l>Wie zu allen Zeiten in ihrem Schicksal etwas Unerbittliches liegt,</l>
                    <l>Wie alle Zeiten die Gegenst&#228;nde ihres Schmeichelns und ihres Lohns
                        &#252;bel w&#228;hlen,</l>
                    <l>Und wie derselbe unerbittliche Preis noch immer f&#252;r dieselbe gro&#223;e
                        Erwerbung bezahlt werden mu&#223;.</l>
                </lg>


                <lg type="poem">
                    <head type="main-authorial">&#8212;AN DIE STAATEN&#8212;</head>
                    <l>An die Staaten, oder an irgend einen Staat, oder an irgend eine Stadt
                        derselben&#8212;</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Widersteht viel, gehorcht wenig.</hi></l>
                    <l>Einmal blinder Gehorsam, einmal v&#246;llig unterjocht,</l>
                    <l>Einmal v&#246;llig unterjocht, gewinnt kein Volk, kein Staat, keine Stadt der
                        Erde seine Freiheit wieder.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="poem">
                    <head type="main-authorial">&#8212;ZU REISEN DURCH DIE STAATEN&#8212;</head>
                    <l>Zu Reisen durch die Staaten brechen wir auf,</l>
                    <l>(Ja, durch die Welt, von diesen Liedern getrieben,</l>
                    <l>Fortan nach jedem Lande, jedem Meer hinsegelnd)</l>
                    <l>Wir, bereitwillig Alle zu lehren, von Allen zu lernen, Alle zu lieben.</l>
                    <l>Wir haben die Jahreszeiten beobachtet, wie sie sich spenden, und
                        weiterziehen,</l>
                    <l>Und wir haben gesagt,&#8212;Warum sollte nicht ein Mann oder ein Weib so viel
                        als die Jahreszeiten wirken, so viel als sie aus sich hervorstr&#246;men
                        lassen?</l>
                    <l>Wir wohnen eine Weile in jeder Stadt,</l>
                    <l>Durch Kanada ziehen wir, und durch das Nordost,<ptr target="loc.05101_n8"/>
                        das ungeheure Thal des Mississippi und die s&#252;dlichen Staaten,</l>
                    <l>Mit jedem Staat auf gleiche Weise unterreden wir,</l>
                    <l>Wir stellen uns selbst auf die Jrobe, and forden M&#228;nner u. Weiber zu'
                        H&#246;ren auf,</l>
                    <l>Wir sagen uns, Gedenke, erschrecke nicht, sei, offen, verk&#252;nde den
                        K&#246;rper und die Seele,</l>
                    <l>Wohne eine Weile und zieh' dann weiter, reich/frei sei Dein Wesen, und
                        ma&#223;voll, sei keusch, sei magnetisch,</l>
                    <l>Und dann kann das was Du aus Dir hervorstr&#246;men l&#228;&#223;est wie die
                        Jahreszeiten wiederkehren,</l>
                    <l>Und sein was die Jahreszeiten sind.</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
