<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?> 

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05145">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 24 November 1882</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
        <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
        <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
          <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
          <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
          <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
          Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
        <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>loc.05145</idno>
        <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
          <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
          <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
          <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
            the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
            law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express
            written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for
            Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">209&#8211;210</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
        <bibl>
          <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
          <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 24 November 1882</title>
          <date cert="high" when="1882-11-24" xml:id="dat1">November 24, 1882</date>
          <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <person role="sender">
          <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
        </person>
        <person role="recipient">
          <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
        </person>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
      <change when="2014-06-02" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
      <change when="2014-03-24" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
      <change when="2014-02-19" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
      <change when="2013-12-08" who="#ss">encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text type="letter">
    <body>
      <opener>
        <dateline>
          <name type="place">Keats Corner <lb/>Well Rd., Hampstead, London</name>
          <date when="1882-11-24">Nov. 24, '82.</date>
        </dateline>
        <salute>Dearest Friend:</salute>
      </opener>
      <p>You have long ere this, I hope, received Herby's letter telling of the safe arrival of the
        precious copy of "Specimen Days," with the portraits: it makes me very proud. Your father
        had a fine face too&#8212;there is something in it that takes hold of me &#38; that seems to
        be a kind of natural background or substratum to the radiant sweetness of that other sacred
        &#38; beloved face completing your parentage. I like heartily too the new portraits of you:
        they are all wanted as different aspects: but the two that remain my favourites are the
        portrait taken about 30 without coat of any kind, and the one you sent me in '69&#8212;next
        to those I love these two latest&#8212;&#38; in some respects better, because they are the
        Walt I saw &#38; had such happy hours with. The second copy of book &#38; my lending one,
        has come safe&#8212;too&#8212;and the card that told of your attack of illness, &#38; the
        welcome news of your recovery in the Paper; &#38; I have been fretting with impatience at my
        own dumbness&#8212;but tied to as many hours a day writing as I could possibly manage, at my
        little book now (last night)&#8212;finished, all but proofs, so that I can take my pleasure
        in "Specimen Days" at last; but before doing that must have a few words with you, dearest
        Friend. First a gossip. Do you remember Maggie Lesley? She came to see us on her way to
        Paris, where she is working all alone &#38; very earnestly to get through training as an
        artist&#8212;then going to start in a studio of her own in Philadelphia. She, like my
        mother's sister, are to me fine, lovable samples of American women&#8212;in whom, I mean, I
        detect, like the distinctive aroma of a flower, something special&#8212;that is
        American&#8212;a decisive new quality to old-world perceptions. Herby is working away still
        chiefly at the Consuelo picture&#8212;has got a very beautiful model to-day sitting to him.
        His summer work was down in Warwickshire, making sketches&#8212;&#38; very charming ones
        they are, of George Eliot's native scenes&#8212;one of a garden-nook&#8212;up steep, old,
        worn stone steps bordered with flowers that is enticing&#8212;it will make a lovely
        background for a figure picture.&#8212;Giddy's voice is growing in richness &#38;
        strength&#8212;&#38; she works with all her heart, hoping one day to be a real artist
        vocally&#8212;in church &#38; oratorio music. She will not have power or dramatic ability
        for opera&#8212;nor can I wish that she had; there are so many thorns with the roses in that
        path. I fear you will be a loser by Bogne's bankruptcy. Did I tell you that among our
        friends one of your warmest admirers is Henry Holmes, the great violinist (equal [to] Joachim
        some think&#8212;we among them). Per. &#38; wife &#38; little grandson all well. My love to
        brother &#38; sister &#38; to Hattie [&amp;] Jessie. Good-bye, dear Walt. I hope to write more &#38;
        better soon.</p>
      <closer>
        <signed rend="right">Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
      </closer>
      <postscript>
        <p>Greetings to the Staffords.</p>
      </postscript>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
