<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00759">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Martha Whitman, 2&#8211;4 January 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00759</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">62-63</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Martha Whitman, 2&#8211;4 January 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-01-02">January 2&#8211;4, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.  </orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Martha">Martha Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-05">Proofread</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-12">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <div1 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington,</name>
                  <date when="1863-01-02">Friday morning, Jan. 2, 1863.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear sister,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You have heard of my fortunes and misfortunes of course, (through my letters to mother and Jeff,) since I left home, that Tuesday afternoon. But I thought I would write a few lines to you, as it is a comfort to write home, even if I have nothing particular to say. Well, dear sister, I hope you are well and hearty, and that little sis keeps as well as she always had, when I left home, so far. Dear little plague, how I would like to have her with me, for one day. I can fancy I see her, and hear her talk. Jeff must have got a note from me about a letter I have written to the <hi rend="italic">Eagle</hi>
               <ptr target="loc.00759_n1"/>&#8212;you may be sure you will get letters enough from me, for I have little else to do at present. Since I laid my eyes on dear brother George, and saw him alive and well&#8212;and since I have spent a week in camp, down there opposite Fredericks-burgh, and seen what well men and sick men, and mangled men endure&#8212;it seems to me I can be satisfied and happy henceforward if I can get one meal a day, and know that mother and all are in good health, and especially if I can only be with you again, and have some little steady paying occupation in N. Y. or Brooklyn.</p>
            <p>I am writing this in the office of Major Hapgood, way up in the top of a big high house, corner of 15th and F. street&#8212;there is a splendid view, away down south, of the Potomac river, and across to the Georgetown side, and the grounds and houses of Washington spread out beneath my high point of view. The weather is perfect&#8212;I have had that in my favor ever since leaving home&#8212;yesterday and to-day it is bright, and plenty warm enough. The poor soldiers are continually coming in from the hospitals, &amp;c. to get their pay&#8212;some of them waiting for it, to go home. They climb up here, quite exhausted, and then find it is no good, for there is no money to pay them&#8212;there are two or three paymasters desks in this room, and the scenes of disappointment are quite affecting. Here they wait in Washington, perhaps week after [week], wretched and heart sick&#8212;this is the greatest place of delays and puttings off, and no finding the clue to any thing&#8212;this building is the paymaster general's quarters, and the crowds on the walk and corner, of poor sick, pale, tattered soldiers, are awful&#8212;many of them day after day, disappointed and tired out. Well, Mat, I will suspend my letter for the present, and go out through the city&#8212;I have a couple of poor fellows in the Hospital to visit also.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div1>
         
         <div1 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <dateline rend="right">
               <date when="1863-01-03">Saturday evening, Jan 3d.</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>I write this in the place where I have my lodging room, 394 L street, 4th door above 14th street. A friend of mine, William D. O'Connor,<ptr target="loc.00759_n2"/> has two apartments, on the 3d floor, very ordinarily furnished, for which he pays the <hi rend="italic">extra</hi> ordinary price of $25 a month. I have a werry little bedroom on the 2d floor&#8212;Mr. &amp; Mrs. O'Connor and their little girl have all gone out "down town" for an hour or two, to make some Saturday evening purchases, and I am left in possession of the premises&#8212;so I sit by the fire, and scribble more of my letter. I have not heard any thing from dear brother George since I left the camp last Sunday morning, 28th Dec. I wrote to him on Tuesday last&#8212;I wish to get to him the two blue woolen shirts Jeff sent, as they would come very acceptable to him&#8212;and will try to do it yet. I think of sending them by mail, if the postage is not more than $1.</p>
            <p>Yesterday I went out to the Campbell Hospital to see a couple of Brooklyn boys, of the 51st. They knew I was in Washington, and sent me a note, to come and see them. O my dear sister, how your heart would ache to go through the rows of wounded young men, as I did&#8212;and stopt to speak a comforting word to them. There were about 100 in one long room, just a long shed neatly whitewashed inside. One young man was very much prostrated, and groaning with pain. I stopt and tried to comfort him. He was very sick. I found he had not had any medical attention since he was brought there&#8212;among so many he had been overlooked. So I sent for the doctor, and he made an examination of him&#8212;the doctor behaved very well&#8212;seemed to be anxious to do right&#8212;said that the young man would recover&#8212;he had been brought pretty low with diarroeha, and now had bronchitis, but not so serious as to be dangerous. I talked to him some time&#8212;he seemed to have entirely give up, and lost heart&#8212;he had not a cent of money&#8212;not a friend or acquaintance&#8212;I wrote a letter from him to his sister&#8212;his name is John A. Holmes,<ptr target="loc.00759_n3"/> Campbello, Plymouth county, Mass. I gave him a little change I had&#8212;he said he would like to buy a drink of milk, when the woman came through with milk. Trifling as this was, he was overcome and began to cry. Then there were many, many others. I mention the one, as a specimen. My Brooklyn boys were John Lowery, shot at Fredericksburgh, and lost his left forearm, and Amos H. Vliet<ptr target="loc.00759_n4"/>&#8212;Jeff knows the latter&#8212;he has his feet frozen, and is doing well. The 100 are in a ward, (6.)&#8212;and there are, I should think, eight or ten or twelve such wards in the Campbell Hospital&#8212;indeed a real village. Then there are some 38 more Hospitals here in Washington, some of them much larger.</p>
         </div1>
         
         <div1 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <dateline rend="right">
               <date when="1863-01-04">Sunday forenoon, Jan 4, '63.</date>
            </dateline>
            <p>Mat, I hope and trust dear mother and all are well, and every thing goes on good home. The envelope I send, Jeff or any of you can keep for direction, or use it when wanted to write to me. As near as I can tell, the army at Falmouth remains the same.</p>
            <p>Dear sister, good bye.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt.</signed>
            </closer>
         
            <postscript>
               <p>I send my love to Andrew and Jesse and Eddy and all&#8212;What distressing news this is of the loss of the Monitor<ptr target="loc.00759_n5"/>&#8212;</p>
            </postscript>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
