<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

   <TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03062">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 20 July 1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03062</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 20 July 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-07-20" xml:id="dat1">July 20, 1882</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-07" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-05" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-11-18" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03062.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.</name> 
                    <date when="1882-07-20" rend="right">July 20, 1882.</date>                    
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I just have your postal of the 19th, announcing the first edition out and gone in a day! Hooray!
                Come on, Vice Society!</p>
            <p>I am rejoiced. Rees Welsh &#38; Co ought to have printed more, but no matter. If they manage right now, they can secure 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03062.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                a prodigious sale. The main thing is not to be afraid, but to face persecution. The thunderstorm mounts <hi rend= "underline">against</hi> the wind.</p>
            <p>Comstock is here, probably merely on Post Office business, he being a special agent. If he is moving against your book, I shall hear of it. But the Department is in his way, as he will 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03062.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                find. He ought to be pitched out of the public service. It is a disgrace to the Government that they should employ this vile maggot bred from carrion&#8212;this rat of the cloaca&#8212;this lump of devil's-dung. I just want a square chance&#8212;a clear sight&#8212;to embalm him in a letter. Properly shown up, he would be 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03062.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                bounced.</p>
            <p>I have a bad dose in preparation for Tobey. There has been some delay, work presses me so much, together with the load of the dog day weather, and I have been really quite ill for a week with a severe cold. I wish I could go North for a while to recover.</p>
            <p>I got the <hi rend="underline">Press</hi> you sent with the Rev. Mr. Morrow's remarks, which 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03062.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                I had already seen in the <hi rend= "underline">Tribune</hi>. He is a pearl among clergymen, and I feel grateful to him. I heard a story once how the brilliant Douglas Jerrold astonished an evening party in London by a constant fire of <hi rend= "underline">jeu de mots</hi> for hours, which continued until 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03062.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                every person in the room, man or woman, had been the subject of a jest or epigram, always splendid and nearly always tart. Finally, when the admired wit was leaving, every eye fixed upon him, every ear bent to hear whatever he might utter, 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03062.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                Charles Knight, the historian, whose sweetness of nature made him loved by all, standing near the door, said to him with a smile, "You've said something this evening about everyone here except me, Douglas; have you nothing to say about me?" "Yes," replied Jerrold, tenderly pressing his hand as he went 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03062.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                away, "Good Knight"! I feel like imitating this wit, and saying, not in parting but in welcome, to our new friend, "Good Morrow."</p>
            <p>I have an immensely cordial letter from Dr. Channing, who says he is going to write to you.</p>
            <p>Send me one of the new edition when you can.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Faithfully,</salute>
                <signed rend="right">W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03062.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="left">see notes July 29 1888 | also July 30</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03062.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
