<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00774">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 22 June 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00774</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">110-111</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 22 June 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-06-22">June 22, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-20">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-23">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-06-22">Monday morning June 22 '63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Jeff's letter came informing me of the birth of the little girl,<ptr target="loc.00774_n1"/> &amp; that Matty was feeling pretty well, so far. I hope it will continue&#8212;Dear sister, I should much like to come home &amp; see you &amp; the little one, I am sure from Jeff's description it is a noble babe, &amp; as to its being a girl it is all the better. (I am not sure but the Whitman breed gives better women than men.)</p>
            <p>Well, mother, we are generally anticipating a lively time here or in the neighborhood,<ptr target="loc.00774_n2"/> as it is probable Lee is feeling about to strike a blow on Washington, or perhaps right into it&#8212;&amp; as Lee is no fool, it is perhaps possible he may give us a good shake&#8212;he is not very far off&#8212;yesterday was a fight to the southwest of here all day, we heard the cannons nearly all day&#8212;the wounded are arriving in small squads every day, mostly cavalry, a great many Ohio men&#8212;they send off to-day from the Washington hospitals a great many to New York, Philadelphia, &amp;c. all who are able, to make room, which looks ominous&#8212;indeed it is pretty certain that there is to be some severe fighting, may be a great battle again, the pending week&#8212;I am getting so callous that it hardly arouses me at all&#8212;I fancy I should take it very quietly if I found myself in the midst of a desperate conflict here in Washington.</p>
            <p>Mother, I have nothing particular to write about&#8212;I see &amp; hear nothing but new &amp; old cases of my poor suffering boys in Hospitals, &amp; I dare say you have had enough of such things&#8212;I have not missed a day at Hospital I think for more than three weeks&#8212;I get more &amp; more wound round&#8212;poor young men&#8212;there are some cases that would literally sink &amp; give up, if I did not pass a portion of the time with them&#8212;I have quite made up my mind about the lecturing &amp;c project&#8212;I have no doubt it will succeed well enough, the way I shall put it in operation&#8212;you know, mother, it is to raise funds to enable me to continue my Hospital ministrations, on a more free handed scale&#8212;As to the Sanitary Commissions &amp; the like, I am sick of them all, &amp; would not accept any of their berths&#8212;you ought to see the way the men as they lie helpless in bed turn away their faces from the sight of these Agents, Chaplains &amp;c. (<hi rend="italic">hirelings</hi> as Elias Hicks<ptr target="loc.00774_n3"/> would call them&#8212;they seem to me always a set of foxes &amp; wolves)&#8212;they get well paid, &amp; are always incompetent &amp; disagreeable&#8212;As I told you before the only good fellows I have met are the Christian Commissioners&#8212;they go everywhere &amp; receive no pay<ptr target="loc.00774_n4"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Dear, dear mother, I want much to see you &amp; dear Matty too, I send you both [my] best love, &amp; Jeff too&#8212;the pictures came&#8212;I have not heard from George nor Han. I write a day earlier than usual.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>We here think Vicksburgh is ours<ptr target="loc.00774_n5"/>&#8212;the probability is that it has capitulated&#8212;&amp; there has been no general assault&#8212;can't tell yet whether the 51st went there&#8212;we are having very fine weather here to-day&#8212;rained last night.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
