<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05694">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 27 March
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05694</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 27 March 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-03-27" xml:id="dat1">March 27, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-25" who="#nhg">added images, updated transcription</change>
            <change when="2014-11-17" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-07" who="#no">checked, italicized words, added missing line</change>
            <change when="2014-07-23" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded and annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03280.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes Jan 18th 1889</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Providence, R.I.</name>
                    <date when="1883-03-27">March 27, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:<!--<ptr target="n2002"/>--></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your gratifying letter of the 25th instant was received last evening.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05694_n1"/>--> I return the proof herewith. The only corrections I have
                seen to make are&#8212;</p>

            <p>I. Striking out the quotation marks from the declaration of Novalis, which I think
                was without the quotation marks in the Tribune. I never meant to attribute <hi
                    rend="underline">those words</hi>&#8212;"the body is the temple of the Holy
                Ghost"&#8212;to Novalis,<!--<ptr target="n3087"/>--> but only to indicate in that phrase
                the sense of what he says. The <hi rend="underline">phrase</hi> is St. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03280.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Paul's (I
                Corinthians, Chap. VI, verse 19) and I think it happily expresses, in epigrammatic
                form, what Novalis says very grandly, at length, in one of his "Fragments." When I get
                back to Washington, I will get the German book out of the Congressional Library (it
                has never been translated) and send you a version of some of his splendid sentences;
                and when I collect my letters into a pamphlet, as I still mean to (much work and
                    Jeannie's<!--<ptr target="loc.05693_n4"/>--> illness having prevented) I think I shall
                put in a note to the passage about Novalis, giving these sentences, lest some one
                should accuse me of having made the bull of attributing to von Hardenberg what
                belongs to Paul.<!--<ptr target="loc.05694_n2"/>--></p>

            <p>II. "The poet, using <hi rend="underline">nuptial</hi>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03280.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                imagery, as Isaiah, as Ezekiel," etc. I have changed
                this to <hi rend="underline">sexual</hi> imagery, which is truer to the fact as regards
                Isaiah and Ezekiel. The word "nuptial" was not well chosen originally.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05694_n3"/>--></p>

            <p>III. I have put in a row of stars (x x x x) to indicate a break in the extracts. You
                can strike them out, if you choose, for I don't stick on them, but they seem
                justified.</p>

            <p>That is all. The extracts pleased me greatly. They never seemed less <hi rend="underline">mine</hi> than when I
                read them in this proof, nor ever before so powerful. If ever lightning went into
                sentences, it is these&#8212;although I say it, as shouldn't! That <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03280.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                letter did good to <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi>, and I hope so much of it as is given here (in Bucke's book) will continue to do good. Dick Spofford<!--<ptr
                    target="n3088"/>--> told me Oliver Stevens<!--<ptr target="upa.00201_n2"/>--> felt
                "perfectly withered" when he read it. Apropos, he told me that his wife, Harriet
                Prescott Spofford,<!--<ptr target="nyp.00486_n5"/>--> says always and everywhere, that you
                are the only poet that ever lived, who has done justice to women.</p>

            <p>I have drawn a mark and made a ? beside the passage in which Bucke<!--<ptr target="n0119"
                />--> eulogizes me, just to make you consider it. I read it with deep mental
                acknowledgments to him, but not without some misgivings. Still, it is his tribute,
                and it is not for me to make objections. I only wish to consider <hi rend="underline"
                    >your</hi> interests, 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03280.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                and should deprecate the introduction of any express
                statement, which might challenge successful attack by our enemies. I doubt the truth
                of the statement that I am "a scholar."<!--<ptr target="loc.05694_n4"/>--> Alas! I am not,
                and have had many a moment of bitter sorrow because I am not&#8212;because I have
                never had the chance to be more than a somewhat omniverous and desultory reader. I
                am afraid, too, that the Doctor overstates my proficiency in Elizabethan letters. I
                have had some new insights, some novel views of those books; no more. However, you
                must judge of the effect of the passage. As I read it, my main thought was whether it
                would do good or harm, and I am still in dubiety on this question.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03280.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I am glad I am to have a revise, for there is one brief correction I want to make,
                being afraid to let the passage stand as I have it. It is where I mention Bacon as
                loving to ride at night, uncovered, that he might feel "the spirit of the universe
                upon his brow." This is from an old note of mine, which I forgot to ascribe to its
                source, and am unable to verify, though I cannot see how I could have misstated the
                matter in my notation. The nearest I can come to it is Aubrey's gossip that he loved
                to ride, uncovered, <hi rend="underline">in the spring rains</hi>, that he might feel
                upon him "the universal spirit of the world"&#8212;a magnificent anecdote, I think,
                and 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03280.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                quite in keeping with the Shakespeare ideal (isn't it?), but not quite like my
                version; and I must alter the latter accordingly, for we are going to run a sweet
                gauntlet of criticism, and must not be laid open any more than can be helped.</p>

            <p>Shouldn't wonder if the book, and especially my share in it, would make an enormous
                    row!<!--<ptr target="loc.05694_n5"/>--></p>

            <p>The title page is very handsome, and the Lucretian motto delights my soul. I only
                wish a good <hi rend="underline">prose</hi> translation of the lines (Munro's would do) could be slipped in
                    <hi rend="underline">somewhere</hi> in the book, for probably it is better to have
                the Latin alone on the title-page. I have no doubt, as you suggest, that I shall
                like the book typographically and every other way.<!--<ptr target="loc.05693_n2"/>--></p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03280.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>Today is the day set for Heywood's trial,<!--<ptr target="n3086"/>--> and cold shivers run
                over me as I think of it. I can't help some sympathy for the devilish fool, despite
                the mischief he is likely to do us. Dr. Channing<!--<ptr target="loc.00945_n5"/>--> and I
                have concocted a move toward getting a <hi rend="underline">nolle pros</hi>, though
                with small hope of success. In case of conviction, I mean to attempt, with Ashton's
                help, to get him promptly pardoned, which will break the force of the finding, and
                paralyze Comstock<!--<ptr target="nyp.00457_n2"/>--> in his designs against your book.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05694_n5"/>--> I am horribly anxious. Heywood is a stupendous jackass,
                and has contrived to render almost nugatory the clean victory we won by the Tribune
                letters. It is too bad.<!--<ptr target="loc.05694_n6"/>--></p>

            <p>More anon. I am glad you keep well.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed>W D O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
