<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05077">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 29 January
                    [1881]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05077</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 29 January [1881]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1881-01-29" xml:id="dat1">January 29, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-09-15">checked transcription against images</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-07" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-06-06" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-04-17" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-04-16" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-24" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-03-17" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-27" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.00987_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1881-01-29">Saturday. Jan 29.</date>
                    <name type="place">Glasshouse <lb/>Shinrone <lb/>Kings County <lb/>Ireland.</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend and Master</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>You see I am now back in my own country.<ptr target="n1027"/> I had no idea that I
                would be so soon. I am staying, with my wife (I have been married about 18 months)
                at my father's house. We shall be here for some months now. There is great
                excitement in the country, but I think no likelihood of any serious disturbances.
                The people know the strength of England too well. I think the Land League<ptr
                    target="loc.05077_n6"/> is slowly losing its influence here, and it deserves to.
                There never was an agitation conducted towards a more useful end or by worse means
                than this. From the very beginning the leaders of the people encouraged them to
                maintain <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.00988_large.jpg" type="verso"/> their
                organization by secret outrage and personal intimidation. There is not the slightest
                doubt that this was so. Their words may not have been arraignable by law, (though in
                many cases they were so) but they were such as their hearers could give but one
                interpretation to. "If a man takes a farm from which another has been evicted" says
                Mr. Dillon, "I don't think his cattle will prosper very much."<ptr
                    target="loc.05077_n1"/> And they don't, for in hundreds of cases these cattle
                have had wooden balls struck over with nails administered to them, have been driven
                over precipices, hamstrung, their eyes picked out. There is little violence just
                now, because the Land League is so all-powerful, and murder or violence is so
                certain to follow a breach of its rules, that no one ventures to transgress them.
                The speakers have in general terms condemned assassination in the sort of language
                which one would use to reprove excessive zeal, but they have never interfered <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.00989_large.jpg" type="recto"/> by word or deed
                to prevent any individual crime which was known to be intended, or condemned with
                energy any individual murder. There are 150 persons now whose lives would not be
                safe for one hour but for police protection, and no Land Leaguer will say one word
                to save them. I entirely agree with them in thinking that it is allowable of the
                tenants to repudiate unjust rents, and I would have thrown myself heart and soul
                into this movement if it were not founded upon crime of the most degrading and
                brutal kind. But as it is, I must say I think the Government are quite justified in
                bringing in their Protection Bill,<ptr target="loc.05077_n4"/> &amp; the League has
                itself to blame for making that Bill necessary. I think too that once it receives a
                straight and severe blow its tyranny will be utterly broken, for it has largely
                ruled by terror and I do not believe that it has endeared itself to the people.</p>
            <p>Scribner has not taken 'Calvin Harlowe.'<ptr target="loc.05077_n2"/> They might have
                done so if they had read it, but I suppose they don't read all the poetry they
                receive. Well for them, no doubt. You did <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc_af.00990_large.jpg" type="verso"/>not say anything about my
                translation of Epictetus which I sent you. I should like to know how you liked it. I
                am writing a preface for it now &amp; will try then &amp; find a publisher. I read news
                of the States with great interest. General Garfield seems a very good sort of man.
                What a puzzling question that is about the Chinese.<ptr target="loc.05077_n3"/> I
                don't think it will get solved by any laws or treaties. I see your expected essay on
                the English poets of this century has never appeared.<ptr target="loc.05077_n5"/>
                Was the announcement a mistake?</p>
            <p>Will you kindly send me a copy of the last edition of the "Leaves of Grass." I want
                it as a present for a friend, so don't write my name in the beginning.<ptr
                    target="loc.05077_n7"/> Indeed the friend is my wife&#8212;so on second thoughts
                I would be glad, &amp; so would she, if you would write 'Edith Rolleston' in it. I'll
                send the 5 dollars as soon as I can get into some town. Please send to this
                address.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours always</salute>
                <signed rend="right">T W H Rolleston</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
