<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05144">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 29 October
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05144</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 29 October 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-10-29" xml:id="dat1">October 29, 1882</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-10" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-05-30" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-04-29" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-20" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-13" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-12-09" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01035_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">'82</note>
                    <date when="1882-10-29">October 29</date>
                    <name type="place">29 Lange Strasse <lb/>Dresden</name>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>'Specimen Days' safely arrived, a really beautiful book externally.<ptr
                    target="n1027"/> Many, many thanks for the gift. I have been looking through it
                and find much that I had not seen anywhere before. I see you have put in your letter
                about the Russian translation, to Lee.<ptr target="loc.05144_n2"/> Did I tell
                you&#8212;(or was it in the letter that went astray?) that Lee has got an
                appointment in England which will take up all his time <add rend="unmarked"
                    place="supralinear">except in vacations,</add> for the present at any rate? I
                haven't heard from him now for months, though I wrote twice. I know he meant to go
                into Servia and Bosnia early this year &#38; hope he hasn't got into any trouble
                there&#8212;he &#38; a friend had a rather narrow escape for <choice>
                    <orig>there</orig>
                    <reg>their</reg>
                </choice> lives in those parts year before last. He is a great enthusiast for
                Panslavism, but brigands wouldn't respect that. My translation I hope to get <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01036_large.jpg" type="verso"/>finished by
                Spring. When it approaches completion I will lecture on it in the Literarischer
                    Verein<ptr target="loc.05119_n3"/> &#38; see if I cannot induce any of the
                members of it to join me in preparing it for the press, revising, etc. Or do you
                know, by correspondence or otherwise, any competent German with whom you could put
                me in communication? Not yet however; it is best, I think, that I should have it all
                turned into literal effective German, the sense of leading words penetrated, etc.
                before we go at it together. It will much facilitate the work.</p>
            <p>To find one who will really cooperate with energy in giving a faithful presentment of
                your book will be difficult, for German literature (and art and all mental products)
                of this day is cramped by formalities and proprieties to an inconceivable
                extent&#8212;far more so than in England. Art in all branches is thought of as a
                technique&#8212;anything like strong individuality is despised&#8212;or if it
                happens to escape that fate is overtaken by a still worse one, in being lauded as if
                it were a piece of correct conventionalism like everything else. <add
                    rend="insertion" place="supralinear">&#8212;I have known this with the L of
                    G.</add> This is the tone among those who take the lead in aesthetic matters,
                but there is a silent mass in the background whom I reckon on.</p>
            <p>Picture of you with the moth is the most perfect visible type of <choice>
                    <orig>yr</orig>
                    <reg>your</reg>
                </choice> looks I could imagine.<ptr target="loc.05144_n3"/></p>
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">T W Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
