<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01818">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 30 December
               1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
               Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.01818</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in
                  the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                  copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce
                  the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals
                  for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
               <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 30 December 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-12-30">December 30, 1864</date>
               <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                  Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n4992">William D. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2015-06-14" who="#ss">annotated</change>
         <change who="#kmp" when="2015-05-14">blessed</change>
         <change who="#nhg" when="2015-01-28">adjusted image names, corrected</change>
         <change who="#ak" when="2015-01-16">added images, corrected transcriptions, removed
            biblStruct</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2011-10-27">changed archive id</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-14">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-17">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03021.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         <opener rend="right">
            <dateline>
               <name type="place">Washington, D.C.,</name>
               <date when="1864-12-30">December 30, 1864.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have been constantly hoping to have you here again and now begin to see something more
            than a glimmer of fruition. Ashton<ptr target="loc.01818_n2"/> has spoken (at my
            instigation) to Mr Otto<ptr target="nyp.00196_n2"/> the Assistant Secretary of the
            Department of the Interior in your behalf, and Mr Otto says that if you will write a
            letter of application to the Secretary of the Interior, he will endeavor to put you
               in.<ptr target="loc.01818_n3"/></p>
         <p>Now, dear Walt, do this without delay. The object of your writing the letter is to get a
            specimen of your hand. Pick out, then, a good pen and write as fairly as you can a
            letter formally applying for a clerkship. Then enclose a copy of this <pb
               xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03021.002.jpg" type="verso"/>letter to Ashton, so that he
            can follow it in to the Secretary. The <hi rend="underline">first</hi> letter you will,
            of course, mail to the Secretary direct.</p>
         <p>Do this as soon as you can. We shall fetch it this time. I have every confidence that
            you will get a good and an easy berth, a regular income, &amp;c, leaving you time to
            attend to the soldiers, to your poems, &amp;c,&#8212;in a word, what Archimedes wanted,
            a place on which to rest the lever.</p>
         <p>I shall wait anxiously to hear that you have sent on the letters. I have been thinking
            of you constantly for months and have been doing everything I could to secure you a
            foothold here. For a long time, deceived (I must think) by Swinton's<ptr
               target="tex.00153_n4"/> pretensions to influence and by his profuse promises, I hoped
            to get you either one of the New York State Agency <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
               facs="loc.03021.003.jpg" type="recto"/>Assistantships or the place of an Assistant
            Librarian in the Congress Library (the latter would be really a sinecure if the right
            one was got).<ptr target="loc.01818_n4"/> But who follows Swinton follows a
            will-of-the-wisp and though I followed him remorselessly, every blessed day for several
            weeks, and gave him neither rest nor peace, as the saying is, I got nothing except
            promises. Since I gave him up, I have been badgering Ashton, who is a man of another
            sort, as what he has done shows. The difficulty was to get the right thing. He secured
            me some little time ago a place in the Post Office for you, but I declined it, because I
            thought it was not the proper place for you. I think a desk in the Interior would be
            first rate.</p>
         <p>I told Ashton there was nothing I would not do for him if he would carry this affair to
            a safe conclusion. He has been very <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03021.004.jpg"
               type="verso"/>good and anxious in your behalf. He would have given you a desk in his
            own office if a vacancy had occurred as expected.</p>
         <p>Don't forget to do as I tell you immediately.</p>
         <p>I never answered your letter of September 11th, but, dear Walt, I always think of you,
            though I write so seldom and so badly. You are never forgotten. I read your poems often,
            I get their meaning more and more, I stand up for them and you, I expound, define,
            defend, vindicate, justify them and you with all the heart and head I have whenever
            occasion demands.</p>
         <p>I got the Times with your long letter about the Hospital experiences, which I read with
            a swelling heart and wet eyes. It was very great and touching to me. I think I could
            mount the tribune for you on that and speak <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
               facs="loc.03021.005.jpg" type="recto"/>speech which jets fire and drops tears. Only
            it filled me with infinite regrets that there is not a book from you, embodying these
            rich and sad experiences. It would be sure of immortality. No history of our times would
            ever be written without it, if written with that wealth of living details you could
            crowd into it. Indeed, it would itself be history.</p>
         <p>I saw your letter about the prisoners. It was as just as powerful. I have been hearing
            for a fortnight past that it is the Secretary of War's "policy" which prevents exchange,
            and if this is true, I pray from my heart of hearts that it never may be forgotten
            against him. Reddest murder is white to an act like this and its folly is equal to its
            crime. It would <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03021.006.jpg" type="verso"/>be a
            demonism of another kind indeed than the Southerners', yet as bad, perhaps worse,
            because sprung from calculation rather than hatred.</p>
         <p>Such things make one sicken of the world.</p>
         <p>I write this letter at intervals between the press of office work, which has driven upon
            me in spasms today, but pretty severely when it did come. Any incoherences in it, you
            may refer to the obfusticated state which such hurryings have induced in me.</p>
         <p>Farewell, dear Walt. I hope to hear from you very soon. We are all tolerably well at
            home. Eldridge<ptr target="loc.00943_n2"/> comes every evening. We often talk of you. On
            Christmas, you were wanted to make the dinner at home perfect. We all spoke of you. On
            Thanksgiving <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03021.007.jpg" type="recto"/>it was the
            same. At dinner that day, I said "I wish"&#8212;and stopped. "What?"&#8212;said
               Nelly.<ptr target="loc.01818_n5"/> "<hi rend="underline">I</hi> know," chirped little
            Jeannie, "he wishes Walt was here." Which was true&#8212;that <hi rend="underline"
               >was</hi> the unuttered wish.</p>
         <p>Let me hear soon.</p>
         <closer rend="right">
            <salute>Your loving</salute>
            <signed>W D O'Connor.</signed>
            <salute>Walt Whitman, Esq.</salute>
         </closer>
         <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03021.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
