<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04085">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Elisa Seaman Leggett to Walt Whitman, 9 October
                    1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Elisa Seaman Leggett</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04085</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Thomas Donaldson</author>
                        <title xml:id="td">Walt Whitman the Man</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Francis P. Harper</publisher>
                            <date when="1896">1896</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">239&#8211;242</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Elisa Seaman Leggett</author>
                    <title>Elisa Seaman Leggett to Walt Whitman, 9 October 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-10-09" xml:id="dat1">October 9, 1880</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Leggett, Elisa Seaman">Elisa Seaman Leggett</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-26" who="#nhg">updated biblStruct</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-01-23" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-07" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <!-- "crl's" (Courtney's} date is missing [ej] -->
            <change when="2013-02-08" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">169 East Elizabeth Street, Detroit,</name>
                    <date when="1880-10-09" rend="right">October 9, 1880.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Mr. W. Whitman.</salute>
                <salute><hi rend="italic">Dear Friend:</hi></salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Do you know it seems very much out of tune to say Mr. to Walt Whitman?<ptr target="n1017"/> and the good
                old Quaker dignity of addressing one by name alone, I like. I hope you are in good
                health this lovely day of October. I feel lonely in October since William Cullen
                Bryant died. Always in this month I used to write to him, just that I might be ahead
                in my congratulations upon his birthday. I remember the sweet October days in
                Roslyn, when he and his wife would come over to Hillside, on some soft, dreamy
                afternoon in the Indian summer; perhaps with a small basket with nice lunch in it
                and a book, "The Berkshire Jubilee," and he would climb up the hill and get into the
                woods, always stopping upon the brow of the hill back of the barn, just under a
                famous great butternut tree, and, turning, take a look upon the harbor and far away
                Long Island Sound, the Red Mill hid among the willows, the lake under the close
                Harbor hill, and the busy village. Bryant always loved just this view of the bay.
                Well, I won't talk now of Bryant, although, when I used to write him from here, I
                would say: "The month of October I give to memories of Roslyn."</p>

            <p>And where are you now to-day? We felt sorry not to have you come to us. All the
                summer the chair stood for you on our piazza. It stands there yet, with its broad
                arms waiting for you. All summer the old willows swayed and rippled, and spoke the
                "various language."<ptr target="n3034"/>  All summer thousands of sparrows came home at early twilight and
                talked ever so much, and scolded some, and nestled in the great ivy on the east wall
                of our home, and Walt Whitman came not to sit beside us. Well, we all felt sorry.
                When I say all, I mean three generations, a goodly company of old and young, down to
                the babe of a few days old. It may be the baby felt sorry. If it don't now, it will
                when it learns of our disappointment, for its mother did. My son<ptr target="n3035"/> sent me your
                picture last week from New York, the one sitting on the rocks, by Sarony. I don't
                know when it was taken, but it looks younger than the one he sent me three years
                ago&#8212;the one with the large necktie. Did you get the story I wrote you about
                your "Leaves of Grass"? When the book came back to me, the picture had been taken
                out. I meant to have asked you, while talking of Roslyn, if you were ever there? Oh!
                it is so charming in autumn. My husband has just bought me the "Prayer of Columbus,"
                by Walt Whitman. I had never read it before. Why he thought I would be especially
                interested was this: I believe it would be good to have a universal holyday, and I
                like to talk about Columbus to my children, and like to stimulate them to feel that
                the advent of Columbus to the New World would be a grand day to select&#8212;not his
                birthday, but the day on which he fell on his knees and thanked God for the
                longed-for reality&#8212;the truth his soul had believed in. One child says:
                "Mother, don't you think that the landing of 'The Pilgrim Fathers' was more noble,
                more than the birth of America as a Nation?" I answer: "The thought of Columbus was
                for the world; the thought of the others, freedom for a theory. Columbus opened the
                flood-gates and behold! now the growing Brotherhood of Man." On the 14th day of this
                month I shall pass the day with my family and a few friends, to read and talk about
                Columbus and about the far away holyday. I have four children in Heidelberg
                (Germany). The eldest grandson writes: "Grandma, in 1892, it will be the 400th
                anniversary of Columbus and of America. Shall we start then?" I say: "No, dear. I'm
                going to have a little tea party here this year, on the 14th day of October, just to
                celebrate in advance, for when one gets to be sixty-five, we don't count twelve
                years&#8212;to wait. One wants to go to work and start a point." I always remember
                just a <hi rend="italic">small</hi> event that has occurred in my life. When we came
                into Detroit, fifteen years ago, there was no place in the streets for a drink of
                water&#8212;no old-fashioned pumps, and no new-fashioned fountains. I knew three
                editors of daily papers. I said: "It is no wonder that dogs go mad in Detroit. They
                must run down to the river before they can get a drink. And it's no wonder that the
                beer saloons flourish, for not even a little boy or poor laboring man can get a cup
                of cold water." So I talked in season and out to everybody, thinking I might touch
                the hem of some garment, and virtue would go out from it. So, after a year or more,
                one morning, there came a nice editorial, advocating fountains, such as they had in
                Philadelphia: and the City Fathers were moved, and now we have all we want. So now I
                am going to talk to everybody about Columbus day, and who knows but that some day
                the world will clasp hands and sing songs of jubilee in concert, and honor itself by
                a recognition of the event.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I am yours truly,</salute>
                <signed>Elisa Seaman Leggett.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
