<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00672">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Hannah Whitman Heyde to Walt Whitman, November
                    1881</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.00672</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>


                <bibl>
                    <title>Hannah Whitman Heyde to Walt Whitman, November 1881</title>
                    <author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
                    <date cert="low" when="1881-11" xml:id="dat1">November 1881</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Hannah Louisa Whitman Heyde Papers, 1853&#8211;1892, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Hannah">Hannah Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-04-07">corrected orgName</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-06" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-20" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-02-20" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2014-01-14" who="#ej">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.00672.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1881-11">Sunday Evening <choice>
                            <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                            <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice></date><note resp="#ww" type="editorial" place="top right">'81</note>
                </dateline>
                <salute/>Dearest Brother</opener>

            <p>Your Book came last night, I was just delighted I prize it greatly. I shall always
                keep this one&#8212;every single one of the others are gone, the last one you sent
                Charlie also &amp; he lent them to his friends, and <choice>
                    <sic>thats</sic>
                    <corr>that's</corr>
                </choice> the last of them,&#8212;. I said last night that this one does not go out
                of this house under any consideration as long as I live.</p>
            <p>Dont you think its got up finely,&#8212;I do.</p>
            <p>It will be <choice>
                    <sic>sucessful</sic><corr>successful</corr></choice>, many speak of it, here. We looked it over all the evening, Charlie taking
                it, then I. he read aloud (appreciatively) the Song of Myself. I wanted to read the
                Ox Tamer and others I liked. There is something so touching or
                affecting <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.00672.002.jpg" type="verso"/>in the words,
                or title, Sobbing of the Bells, (you know you sent to Boston Globe), we were so taken
                with &amp; glad to get read &amp;c the rest of the poem. Charlie
                sits here reading your book, he says this book is <choice>
                    <sic>electrick</sic><corr>electric</corr></choice>. You cant <choice>
                    <sic>immagine</sic>
                    <corr>imagine</corr>
                </choice> Walt how many speak of you to me. I believe every body under the sun knows
                of you even persons that live far back in the Country. the other day a Lady friend
                Mrs Barney called that lives back among the Richmond hills away from any village among other things
                she spoke of a full length picture of you having been painted for a German Club out West, all have
                something to say of you that is pleasant for me to hear.</p>

            <p>Some want to see me Walt <choice>
                    <sic>Whitmans</sic><corr>Whitman's</corr></choice>, sister I have not begun to put on airs yet, but I <choice>
                    <sic>dont</sic>
                    <corr>don't</corr>
                </choice> know but I shall soon</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.00672.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I was pleased with Mr Luce a Wisconsin Editor that called some months since, he has
                sent us several of his papers, most all speak of you, I <choice>
                    <sic>dont</sic>
                    <corr>don't</corr>
                </choice> know that you would care for it, but I will send you the first one.</p>
            <p>Mrs Abbott (an old very intelligent friend that we had not seen for twelve years,
                used to live here) called yesterday, she wanted your new book should purchase it
                here if she could, or wait till she arrived in Boston,&#8212;I said I would tell you
                that she wanted you very much to visit her at their farm among the mountains spoke
                of many things she would do for you if you would come I told her you had promised to
                come here some time.</p>
            <p>Walt I am ashamed I did not write last Spring when you sent me that money. <hi
                    rend="underline">You</hi> understand how much I do appreciate it,&#8212;. For a
                day or two I could only think how <hi rend="underline">good</hi> you was.&#8212;And
                then I never in all my life <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.00672.004.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>had money that done me so much good. I have some of it yet. I
                saved to finish out a dress I wanted for this Winter, this dress will be all that I
                shall need. I <choice>
                    <sic>dont</sic>
                    <corr>don't</corr>
                </choice> know whatever I should do without you Walt, in many ways always some
                pleasant <choice><abbr>supprise</abbr><expan>surprise</expan></choice>, a paper or magazine letter something or other, all so pleasant to get.
                Life would be dull without you.</p> 
            <p>That West Hill letter. I think perhaps I know more of those places you
                describe than the rest of the family, so to me it was <hi rend="underline">more than <choice>
                        <abbr>interresting</abbr>
                        <expan>interesting</expan>
                    </choice></hi> something to keep. Charlie wrote a pleasant letter to Dr Bucke
                Canada got a kind letter in reply, spoke of you &amp; he taking dinner together in
                New York, but the best was that you was pretty well Your Nov 1<hi rend="superscript"
                    >st</hi> letter too said you was well as usual, I am so glad, after all the work
                and worry you must have had. But <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.00672.005.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>sometimes we take long walks in the country, we went to day, a mile
                or so.</p>
            <p>Charlie has been sketching some this summer out Williston 18 or 20 miles from here we
                drove out there two weeks ago, the country was beautiful I liked the ride <hi
                    rend="underline">ever</hi> so much.</p>
            <p>he has sent his Williston picture West, he thinks it sold, he will know soon. He sold
                one there previous for &#36;75, has just now sold a small one &#36;16.&#8212;he has
                some prospects. We have ups &amp; downs, like every body. He sold more years ago,
                than late years. I think his pictures much better now, people here follow the
                fashion, buy foreign pictures</p>
            <p>I am well, I feel better than I did last summer, I worry less if things go crossways.&#8212;dear dear brother I hope to live long enough to see you again, I want you to come
                here more than I can say</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.00672.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>What a lovely time you must have had in Boston, Walt, socially I mean. your long
                letter was delightful to get, told me so much your dinner at Emersons and all the
                rest. I remember I thought you was good to think of me. How many good friends you
                have, it was all just <choice><orig>splended</orig><reg>splendid</reg></choice></p>
            <p>I like Dr Bucke, I feel flattered to be ever so little like Mrs Bucke</p>
            <p>The Burlington Free Press says you are going to Europe this fall. there is no truth
                in it, is there. I noticed your <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="medium">long</unclear> poem, Song of the Banner at Daybreak, in Free Press,
                a while ago.</p>
            <p>With me dear Bother every thing goes much the same, new neighbors about us, with one
                exception Gen Henry, I liked the old ones best</p>
            <p>I run in Mrs Griswolds, one of our neighbor's a good <choice>
                    <sic>dead</sic><corr>deal</corr></choice>, she very often speaks of you.</p>
            <p>if you should build that little house Walt you used to speak of, I shant forget that
                old invitation I am sorry its so late I cant write to Lou, I wanted to, so she would
                write to me ever so much love to you dear Walt &amp; George and Lou, and Eddy. I
                very very often think of him</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>good night</salute>
                <signed>Han</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
