<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01921">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Hiram Sholes to Walt Whitman, 8 June
                    1867</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Hiram Sholes</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01921</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Sholes, Hiram</author>
                    <title>Hiram Sholes to Walt Whitman, 8 June 1867</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1867-06-08" xml:id="dat1">June 8, 1867</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Sholes, Hiram">Hiram Sholes</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2011-08-01" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-28" who="#al">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-09" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01921.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">Albany</name>,
                    <date when="1867-06-08">June, 8th, 1867</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours of May 30th was received some time since and I take great pleasure in writing to you again, and in giving you some of the particular in regard to my health, limb situation, &amp;c</p>

            <p>My health at present is very good—better than at any time since I left the army for I had considerable <choice><orig>sickness</orig><reg>sickness</reg></choice> during the first two years after coming home</p>

            <p>My limb has never troubled me of any account 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01921.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                have worn my artificial nearly all the time since the winter of –'64.</p>

            <p>About one year an half ago I went to work in the "State Lunatic asylum" as an attendant, worked there some eight months and was taken sick, the physician told me it was caused by being confined <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr></choice> much, and so I left. I then went to Rhode Island where I had some relatives, last fall I came to albany and when the Legislature convened, obtained a position as watchman—it lasted about three months.</p>

            <p>This summer they are having a State – Convention I had a promise 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01921.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                of doorkeeper but they managed it so that I was unable to obtain it. It seems that the President of the Convention instead of appointing the doorkeepers by himself gave the <choice><sic>delagates</sic><corr>delegates</corr></choice> of each Judicial Dist a choice of their <choice><sic>apointment</sic><corr>appointment</corr></choice> (these being about one appointment to each dist) the <choice><sic>Secratary</sic><corr>Secretary</corr></choice> of the Convention appointed a man from Oswego Co. as clerk (which being in my dist) threw me out of my position as doortender. I do not know what I shall go to doing now, perhaps something may turn up after a while.</p>

            <p>I was glad to learn that Lewis had so good a situation
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01921.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                I was <choice><sic>verry</sic><corr>very</corr></choice> neglectful in my <choice><sic>correspondance</sic><corr>correspondence</corr></choice> with him and I am ashamed of not writing to him also to Joe Harris but I have one good excuse and that is, as you will <choice><sic>verry</sic><corr>very</corr></choice> readily see, a poor writer. During the time that I was in the Hospital in Washington I formed some acquaintances <choice><orig>than</orig><reg>that</reg></choice> I can never forget indeed I have thought of them often Mrs Wright, &amp; Hanly. <choice><orig>Misses</orig><reg>Misses</reg></choice> Martin &amp; Lowell and some others were the best women I ever saw and I wish them all the <choice><sic>hapiness</sic> <corr>happiness</corr></choice> and prosperity <choice><sic>imagineable</sic><corr>imaginable</corr></choice>, there are other ladies to be sure that I feel under many obligations 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01921.005.jpg" type="verso"/> 
               
               too, but to these <choice><sic>especialy</sic><corr>especially</corr></choice>. To you, Joe Harris, &amp; Dr. <choice><orig>Bliss</orig><reg>Bliss</reg></choice> I feel deep gratitude more than I can ever repay.</p>



            <p>The information that you sent me about some of the comrades was surprising Tobias the <choice><orig>dresser</orig><reg>dresser</reg></choice> that was killed. I have often thought of him and wondered if he came out of the war. I saw Tom Sawyer in N.Y. three years ago.</p>

            <p><unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#br">Cute</unclear> I think has done remarkably well may he still flourish and perhaps we may yet hear of him as an ornament to the State in which he now so nobly <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="6" unit="chars"/>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01921.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                I will now draw this to a close, and may I hear from you again soon. I am a poor writer and cannot furnish anything <choice><sic>verry</sic><corr>very</corr></choice> interesting to you to read only so far as my own self is concerned</p>

            <p>Remember me to all of my acquaintances and if any of them have any ill will on account of my not writing let them lay it to my inabilities instead of my inclination</p>

            <p>Waiting to hear from you again dear friend allow me to subscribe myself</p>

            <closer rend="right">
                <salute>Your humble Friend</salute>
                <signed>Hiram Sholes</signed>                
            </closer>
        </body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01921.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01921.007.jpg" type="verso"/>
    </text>

</TEI>