<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00942">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 24 November 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00942</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 24 November 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-11-24">November 24, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">edited annotation on O'Connor</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-02">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">added encoding for page breaks</change>
         
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="loc.00942.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">No. 400 L St.</name>
                  <date when="1863-11-24">Nov. 24 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mrs. Cooper and Mr. Eldridge left yesterday morning as they intended, and as you see by this I did not go.<ptr target="loc.00942_n1"/> I hardly think that you did either, so I will venture to send to you.</p>
            <p>I have some news to tell you. Mr. Howells came home with his wife last Saturday from New York.<ptr target="loc.00942_n2"/> He has decided not to go to Idaho, and does not know yet what he will do. But he says he shall have no trouble in making it all right with the Government. About the other matter I do not know any more. I agree <pb facs="loc.00942.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00942.003.jpg" type="recto"/>with you Walt, that in time he must see right through those people, &amp; if it were not for the suffering it causes his wife, I should by all means say, let him go there, see them, be with them and live it out. Perhaps it is the only thing to do any way. Time will prove that.</p>
            <p>How I long to see you. Are you going to be here by Thursday, Thanksgiving! I wish I knew, for I would get a good big turkey and we would have a jolly time.</p>
            <p>I miss Mrs. C. very much. By the way, when you return to Washington if it is not too much <pb facs="loc.00942.004.jpg" type="recto"/>out of your way, will you stop at Mrs. Cooper's and get a small parcel she is to have ready for me? It will save the expressage, and if you can do so without too much trouble I shall be very glad. She wants you to stop very much, and you would have a good time, &amp; see Mr. &amp; Mrs. Louis her brother &amp; sister both of whom are great admirers of yours.</p>
            <p>I enjoyed your letter very much, did I tell you so in my note? I am better of my cough, which has been very bad, and I shall do well I have no doubt, but I get very tired of being <hi rend="italic">half</hi>
               <pb facs="loc.00942.005.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00942.006.jpg" type="recto"/> well, I would like to be in perfect health like you&#8212;how splendid it is! You ought to do grand things with such a grand body.</p>
            <p>I am sorry to hear such poor accounts of your brother Andrew&#8212;I hoped you would find him better. But for your mother's good health and vigor I rejoice with you.</p>
            <p>It must be a compensation for all to see her so nobly bearing up. You are rich indeed in having such a noble, grand mother. I hope I shall know her sometime, also your sister Martha &amp; all. Are they going to let you name the baby California? She is a <pb facs="loc.00942.007.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00942.008.jpg" type="recto"/>fine baby, I am sure. Your boys there will hold on to you till the last minute I know, and how they will miss you. I quite envy you the Opera, I wish I were there with you for a week to go around. Would we not have some good times? I am sure we would.</p>
            <p>Have you seen Mrs. Price any more?<ptr target="loc.00942_n3"/> I hope you will, for I know she counted so much on seeing you.</p>
            <p>Last Sunday we were out walking &amp; met the Count, the first time since you left.<ptr target="loc.00942_n4"/> He immediately asked for you, &amp; I told him where you were&#8212;he asked if you <pb facs="loc.00942.009.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00942.010.jpg" type="recto"/>were coming back etc. &amp; when I told him that I had heard &amp; should write you, he said "My Gott, I did not know that he was such a poet, tell him so, I have been trying every where to find him to tell him myself." So you see. He said tell him he must write more poems.</p>
            <p>I wish that you were back here in your old room for my sake, for I miss you &amp; shall.</p>
            <p>I should have gone to the Hospital today if it had not rained, and I shall go to-morrow I think, rain or shine. I could not very well while Mrs. Cooper was here, for we kept <pb facs="loc.00942.011.jpg" type="verso"/>
               <pb facs="loc.00942.012.jpg" type="recto"/>thinking that every day would be here last here.</p>
            <p>I count upon your return, and on our all being together much, very much this winter, and on some good talks, &amp; good times reading your Drum Taps. You must publish that book.</p>
            <p>William very often wishes for your return and wants to see you.<ptr target="loc.00942_n5"/>
            </p>
            <p>Good bye.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With love from us all. Your friend</salute>
               <signed>Nelly O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="loc.00942.013.jpg" type="verso"/>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
