<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05148">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 27
                    September 1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05148</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 27 September 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-09-27" xml:id="dat1">September 27, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H.
                        Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-31" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-07-10" who="#ss">images added</change>
            <change when="2014-04-29" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-05" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-02-18" who="#kc">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-12-12" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01041.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1883-09-27" rend="right">Sept. 27th.</date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right"><hi rend="underline">28 Terrassen Ufer</hi>.
                        Dresden</name>
                </dateline>
                <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">'83</note>
                <salute>My dear Master</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got your post card last Tuesday morning.<ptr target="n1027"/> I had not written for
                some time because I waited till I had something to say about the essay on the <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr>
                    <expan>Leaves of Grass</expan>
                </choice> I was preparing for delivery here. They had promised me an earlier date
                for it, but could not, in the end, find one till the 25th Sept. last, the day I got
                your card on. It (i.e. the lecture) was delivered before the Dresden Literary
                Society, consisting mostly of Professors &#38; savants of all kinds.<ptr
                    target="loc.05119_n3"/> No one knew anything, or anything beyond the name, of
                you, except Dr. Doehn, the author of a history of American Literature I told you
                    of.<ptr target="loc.05148_n1"/> He spoke on my essay, and took the usual line of
                intelligent and book-learned persons, thus&#8212;"He is a poet by God's 
                grace&#8212;but that is all" (and it isn't much, according to Dr. D.) "He is wanting
                in two indispensable requisites for a <hi rend= "underline">great</hi> writer. (1) Knowledge&#8212;(2) Form."
                As to the absence of knowledge, I can only conjecture that he meant that your poems
                would not be regarded as historical studies, like Schillers 'Tell' &amp;c. Two others
                spoke&#8212;one a Dr. Hohlfeld, a man of much genuine thoughtfulness. He merely
                pointed out some philosophical parallels between things I had said, and passages of
                Schiller &#38; Schleiermacher. A third speaker said a few words which showed that he
                understood my drift&#8212;among other things he said what I had reported about you
                reminded him of Wordsworth. Now this was really remarkable, for I had always held
                that Wordsworth was the true predecessor of the <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr>
                    <expan>Leaves of Grass</expan>
                </choice> &#38; on asking Edward Dowden<!--<ptr target="n0199"/>--> once about this, he fully
                confirmed what I had thought. ("Wordsworth is calculated to lead a courageous,
                though not a timid, person <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01042_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.01043_large.jpg" type="recto"/>up to W.W.")<ptr
                    target="loc.05148_n2"/> Yet in writing my essay, I had no thought of him, nor
                had mentioned him.&#8212;Now it so happens that another English friend here has,
                about a year ago, delivered a lecture before the same Literary <choice>
                    <abbr>Soc.</abbr>
                    <expan>Society</expan>
                </choice> on Wordsworth. And we mean now to publish both lectures together with a
                short preface showing in what direction the connection between you &#38; Wordsworth is
                to be looked for. I will send you some copies as soon as this appears, which will be
                without delay. As to my translation of the <choice>
                    <abbr>L. of G.</abbr>
                    <expan>Leaves of Grass</expan>
                </choice> I am now ready to cooperate with any competent German, i.e. I have got a
                good way in the actual rendering, &amp; see how it is to be done, &amp;c. &#38; all I want
                is a colleague to push on the work energetically with. But nothing of the kind has
                as yet turned up (although intelligent &#38; more or less sympathetic readers in
                sufficient number.) Now do you know anyone whom you could put in connection with
                me? It does not strike me as needful that he should live in this town. We could
                easily arrange some system of work, through the post, &amp; meet if necessary some
                time? Perhaps my essay when published may lead to something. I got Dr. Bucke's
                    book.<ptr target="loc.05148_n3"/> He was kind enough to send me a copy (I hope
                my letter of acknowledgment did not fail to reach him). I think it will be of the
                greatest service for all time (giving permanent expression to facts of great
                interest &amp; importance, but the theoretic part of it not going deep enough.) I will
                send him my essay when it appears.</p>
            <p>Nothing more to say now. Very glad to hear that you keep well.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours always</salute>
                <signed rend="right"><hi rend="underline">T. W. Rolleston</hi></signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_af.01044_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
