<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01900">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Annie Tolman Smith to Walt Whitman, 24 September 1877</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Annie Tolman Smith</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01900</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>Annie Tolman Smith</author>
    <title>Annie Tolman Smith to Walt Whitman, 24 September 1877</title>  
    <date cert="high" when="1877-09-24" xml:id="dat1">September 24, 1877</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 15 Reel 9</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
              
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Tolman Smith, Annie">Annie Tolman Smith</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2013-12-10" who="#nhg">added annotation pointers</change>
            <change when="2013-10-03" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-07" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-06" who="#js">corrected opener</change>
            <change when="2012-03-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-05" who="#al">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-01-27" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01900.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington,</name>
                    <date when="1877-09-24">Sept. 24th 1877</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Mr. Whitman;</salute>
                <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>My desire to address you springs from a question addressed me by a member of my class in literature.<!-- <ptr target="n0843"/> --></p>
            <p>What do you think of Walt Whitman?</p>
            <p>Up to that moment I had read only a single one of your poems "The two mysteries" which moved me by its subtlety and beauty. Soon after the question, which I was not prepared to answer, came comments in a British Review to the effect that Americans did not
            
                     
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01900.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            know their poets when they had them, instancing our slow appreciation of yourself&#8212;put me upon the determination to know your works, but I have only been able to secure a volume of Leaves of Grass, which I understand are your earlier poems&#8212;</p>
            <p>I should feel that my addressing you was an insult, if I could pretend not to have been moved by these. You seemed to me as near the divine secret of Nature, as most poets have been to her external graces and to have restored almost the virginal force, and vividness to language. But as true poems, are


            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01900.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            not like mosaics to be admired in bits, I have sought to discern the distinctive idea which informs and controls the expression in these</p>
            <p>I feel its presence, but am conscious that I do not define it, nor am I able to get at your idea of poetical form which seems to me as essential an element in poetry, as lines of beauty are in the plastic arts. Many expressions in your poems pain me because many things which seem to me sacred, because natural, are profaned by the utterance. I have long been enamored of the poetry of the past, but lately find myself longing to come into sympathy with the poetry of the present, and
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01900.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            most of all, as a teacher, I desire to know the truth of all art. Should you pardoning my presumption, and my candor, be kind enough to explain the points to which I have referred, I should consider myself highly favored.</p>
            <p>I do not know which is most likely to reconcile you to the liberty I have taken, the accompanying letter,<!-- <ptr target="loc.01900_n1"/> --> or the recollection of your own words&#8212;"Stranger if you passing meet me, and desire to speak to me&#8212;why should you not speak to me?"</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Respectfully Yours</salute>
                <signed>A. Tolman Smith,</signed>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>506–5th <!-- two hashmarks below the superscript -NNK --> St. N.W.</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Washington, D.C</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01900.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01900.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>