<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00762">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 6 February 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00762</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">71-72</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 6 February 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-02-06">February 6, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-05">Proofed</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-12">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington,</name>
                  <date when="1863-02-06">Friday noon, February 6, 1863.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Jeff must have got a letter<ptr target="loc.00762_n1"/> from me yesterday, containing George's last letter.<ptr target="loc.00762_n2"/> The news of your sickness, and the strange silence of Han made me feel somewhat gloomy. I wrote to George yesterday, conveying the news&#8212;and to-day I have sent him another letter, with much more comfortable news, for I was so glad to hear from Han, (her letter, enclosed in Jeff's, received this morning) that I wrote him right away, and sent Han's letter.<ptr target="loc.00762_n3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mother, I am quite in hopes George will get a furlough&#8212;may-be my expectations are unfounded, but I almost count on it.<ptr target="loc.00762_n4"/> I am so glad this morning to hear you are no worse, but changed for the better&#8212;and dear sister Mat too, and sissy, I am so glad to think they are recovering.<ptr target="loc.00762_n5"/> Jeff's enclosure of $10 through Mr. Lane,<ptr target="loc.00762_n6"/> from the young engineers, for the soldiers in hospitals, the most needy cases, came safe of course&#8212;I shall acknowledge it to Mr. Lane to-morrow. Mother, I have written so much about hospitals, that I will not write any in this letter.</p>
            <p>We have had bad weather enough here lately to most make up for the delightful weather we had for five weeks after I came from home.</p>
            <p>Mother, I do hope you will be careful, and not get any relapse&#8212;and hope you will go on improving. Do you then think of getting new apartments, after the 1st of May? I suppose Jeff has settled about the lot<ptr target="loc.00762_n7"/>&#8212;it seems to me first rate as an investment&#8212;the kind of house to build is quite a consideration, (if any house,) I should build <hi rend="italic">a regular Irish shanty</hi> myself, two rooms, and an end shed&#8212;I think that's luxury enough, since I have been down in the army.</p>
            <p>Well, mother, I believe I will not fill out the sheet this time, as I want to go down without delay to the P. O. and send George's letter, and this one.</p>
            <p>Good bye, dear mother,</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
