<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00426">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 15 October 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00426</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">79-80</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 15 October 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-15">October 15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1863-10-15">Oct 15th 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mother received a letter from you yesterday<ptr target="loc.00426_n1"/>  I got one the day before.<ptr target="loc.00426_n2"/> Mother did not let me see her letter<ptr target="loc.00426_n3"/> but Mat says that she understands that you say that you think about coming home. I hope dear Walt, that you <hi rend="italic">will</hi> come and that soon  I think if you should come just now you might be able to do Andrew considerable good  He is in a very bad way and I really fear, under the present circumstances that he will not last long. Dear Walt I wish that I could do something more for Andrew, but I have to work all the time, almost day and night and another thing I think he would be guided more by your advice than any one elses  That damed infernal robber the doctor<ptr target="loc.00426_n4"/> that he has been with (Andrew has paid him $95 and been getting worse all the time) told Andrew yesterday that he must not come there again till he brought him $45 more. Only think of it. The infernal son of a bitch. I would like to hang him for a thousand years, ten times a second. I dont care anything about it for the good that I think that he could do Andrew but that he Andrew thinks that perhaps if he could pay him $45 he could do something for him. The very fact that the scoundrel wants the money in advance is enough  Dear Walt do come home if only for a short time  And unless you come quite soon you certainly will never see Andrew alive.<ptr target="loc.00426_n5"/> Will you write me at once if you can come.</p>
            <p>Mother Mat and Sis are all suffering from bad colds, Mother particularly I think is failing rapidly. I do so wish that I could see you and have a good talk abt family affairs  I am in an awful hurry or would write more. To day I have to go through the whole line of conduit</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
