<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00425">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 8 October 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>

               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00425</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">78-79</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 8 October 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-08">October 8, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-31">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2006-11-21">added table to first paragraph for monetary information</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
                  <date when="1863-03-21">Oct. 8th/63</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Walt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I yesterday wrote you<ptr target="loc.00425_n1"/> enclosing the $10 from Mr Kirkwood<ptr target="loc.00425_n2"/> for the use of the "sogers"  The enclosed $8 is contributed thus
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>$5</cell>
                     <cell>by Moses Lane<ptr target="loc.00425_n3"/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>$2</cell>
                  <cell>"  J. D. Martin<ptr target="loc.00425_n4"/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>"1</cell>
                  <cell>"  Henry Carlow<ptr target="loc.00425_n5"/>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>In my yesterdays letter I said something about the acknowledgement of the moneys  I fear that I did not express myself so that you could understand me  I do not want to get the credit of sending money that I dont send,&#8212;I want to show your letters to those that contribute so that they may see that all the money they give me is duly sent and appropriated and as I proposed this regular contribution I dont like to have them know that I am the first one to back out, but as I said yesterday I think that whatever I possibly can do I ought to do for Andrew, that whatever I can give ought to be given to him. Andrew is in a bad fix, he is hardly able to get around and has no money  Mat sends him at least one good meal a day. He generally comes and spends an hour or two at the house. I had quite a talk with Dr Ruggles<ptr target="loc.00425_n6"/> yesterday about him. The Dr says that had he gone to the interior when he first advised him to in the summer he would have stood a fair chance of getting well, but that now he thinks that it is more than wicked to take his money and make beleive to cure him for in his opinion that is almost impossible  I think that it is about so. It makes one feel rather bad when you think of it dont it  Ruggles says that his lungs are much diseased. I wish that you could come home for a short time and see Andrew  Mother and the rest are quite well. This morning mother is not quite so well,&#8212;a bad cold&#8212;yesterday Jess was sick all day&#8212;there is no doubt Walt in my mind but that Mother is doing injury both to herself and Jess by her economy  they do not have enough <hi rend="italic">good</hi> things to eat, and they are both of the age that they require it. I have spoken of it till I have tired and it dont accomplish any-thing. I wish you was at home to give a little advice now and then.</p>
            <p>Walt I often think of you wonder what you are about and how you get along. Do you have any employment there. You must often meet Brooklyn people there  I understand that they liked your letter at the Times. Twas superior to the Brooklyn one I'm sure.<ptr target="loc.00425_n7"/>
            </p>
            <p>Walt let me hear from you&#8212;a letter that I can show Lane &amp;c  They like to read your letters  Mattie and the babies are well and send their love. Ruggles always tells me to remember him to you. Probasco<ptr target="loc.00425_n8"/> complains that he has not heard from you since he sent you some money, fears that it did not reach you  I will write again soon</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Thos J. Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
