<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00788">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 8 September 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00788</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">143-146</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 8 September 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-09-08">September 8, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-27">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-26">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  <date when="1863-09-08">September 8 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wrote to Jeff Sunday last that his letters sent Sept 3d containing your letter &amp; $5 from Mr Lane had miscarried&#8212;this morning when I came down to Major Hapgood's office I found it on my table, so it is all right&#8212;singular where it has been all this while as I see the post mark on it is Brooklyn Sept 3 as Jeff said<ptr target="loc.00788_n1"/>&#8212;Mother, what to do about Andrew I hardly know&#8212;as it is I feel about as much pity for you as I do for my poor brother Andrew, for I know you will worry yourself about him all the time&#8212;I was in hopes it was only the trouble about the voice &amp;c but I see I was mistaken, &amp; it is probably worse&#8212;I know you &amp; Jeff &amp; Mat will do all you can&#8212;&amp; will have patience with all (it is not only the sick who are poorly off, but their friends&#8212;but it is best to have the greatest forbearance, &amp; do &amp; give &amp;c whatever one can&#8212;but you know that, &amp; practice it too, dear mother)<ptr target="loc.00788_n2"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, if I had the means, O how cheerfully I would give them, whether they availed any thing for Andrew or not&#8212;yet I have long made up my mind that money does not amount to so much, at least not so very much, in serious cases of sickness&#8212;it is judgment, both in the person himself, &amp; in those he has to do with&#8212;&amp; good heart is every thing&#8212;(Mother, you remember Theodore Gould,<ptr target="loc.00788_n3"/> how he has stuck it out, though sickness &amp; death has had hold of him as you may say for fifteen years)&#8212;but any how I hope we will all do what we can for Andrew&#8212;Mother, I think I must try to come home for a month&#8212;I have not given up my project of lecturing, I spoke about before,<ptr target="loc.00788_n4"/> but shall put it in practice yet, I feel clear it will succeed enough. (I wish I had some of the money already, it would be satisfaction to me to contribute something to Andrew's necessities, for he must have bread)&#8212;I will write to you of course before I come&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, I hope you will live better&#8212;Jeff tells me you &amp; Jess &amp; Ed live on poor stuff, you are so economical<ptr target="loc.00788_n5"/>&#8212;Mother, you mustn't do so, as long as you have a cent&#8212;I hope you will at least four or five times a week have a steak of beef or mutton, or something substantial for dinner&#8212;I have one good meal of that kind every day, or at least five or six days out of the seven&#8212;but for breakfast I never have any thing but a cup of tea &amp; some bread or crackers, (first rate tea though with milk &amp; good white sugar)&#8212;well I find it is hearty enough&#8212;more than half the time I never eat any thing after dinner, &amp; when I do it is only a cracker &amp; cup of tea&#8212;Mother, I hope you will not stint yourselves&#8212;as to using George's money for your &amp; Jess's &amp; Ed's needful living expenses, I know George would be mad &amp; hurt in his feelings, if he thought you was afraid to&#8212;Mother, now have a comfortable time as much as you can, &amp; get a steak occasionally, won't you?</p>
            <p>I suppose Mat got her letter last Saturday, I sent it Friday&#8212;O I was so pleased that Jeff was not drawn,<ptr target="loc.00788_n6"/> &amp; I know how Mat must have felt too, &amp; you too&#8212;I have no idea the government will try to draft again, whatever happens&#8212;they have carried their point, but have not made much out of it&#8212;O how the conscripts &amp; substitutes are deserting down in front, &amp; on their way there&#8212;you don't hear any thing about it, but it is incredible&#8212;they don't allow it to get in the papers&#8212;Mother, I was so glad to get your letter, you must write again&#8212;can't you write to-morrow, so I can get it Friday or Saturday?&#8212;you know though you wrote more than a week ago I did not get it till this morning&#8212;I wish Jeff to write too, as often as he can&#8212;mother, I was gratified to hear you went up among the soldiers<ptr target="loc.00788_n7"/>&#8212;they are rude in appearance, but they know what is decent, and it pleases them much to have folks, even old women, take an interest &amp; come among them&#8212;mother, you must go again, &amp; take [Hat]&#8212;Well, dear mother, I must close&#8212;I am first rate in health, so much better than a month &amp; two mo's ago&#8212;my hand has entirely healed&#8212;I go to hospital every day, or night&#8212;I believe no men ever loved each other as I &amp; some of these poor wounded, sick &amp; dying men love each other&#8212;good bye, dearest mother, for present&#8212;</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
