<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00397">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 6 February 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00397</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">24-26</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 6 February 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-02-06">February 6, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-01-06">Proofed</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>
                  <date when="1863-02-06">Feb. 6th 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mr Lane<ptr target="loc.00397_n1"/> handed me the enclosed $11 to be sent to you for the soldiers</p>
            <p>$10. Contributed by Hill &amp; Newman<ptr target="loc.00397_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>$1.        "      "  Henry Carlow<ptr target="loc.00397_n3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr Lane thinks your last letter to me was a clincher.<ptr target="loc.00397_n4"/> Newman, of the above firm was in the office and upon finding out what we were doing promised to give $10. Mr Lane, thinking perhaps that by sending the money immediately might save a life or at least help to do it, advanced the money and wished me to write you to-day.</p>
            <p>Mother and Mat are getting along with their colds but Sis is not so well to day. She seems to have more colds and her head is almost stopped up</p>
            <p>Poor little toad  I often wish that I could take it for her, however she gets along with it quite well and is not more cross than the law allows for a little one that has such a cold. If mother could be persuaded to let the scrubbing of the lower entry alone for a few days she would recover, but I believe that she is too much afraid of Mrs Brown,<ptr target="loc.00397_n5"/> for this morning, and it was one of those cold rainy ones, she went to work and scrubbed as usual. I think they all have had the worst colds that I know of. How do [you] get along about your appointment, does it come and will it. Do you hear from George. What do you think about Han?, the lot, and matters in general.<ptr target="loc.00397_n6"/> I think Walt, that mother has showed her age more within the last three or four weeks than I ever knew her to before</p>
            <p>Everything is just the same with me. I am getting along quite well, and if Mr Lane holds his position I shall eventually be all right. I think I shall be able to carry through my little "real estate" scheme without much trouble, and I think it is a good one.<ptr target="loc.00397_n7"/> at least I must try, for I am "in" and I suppose I shall not be a true Whitman if I dont get dis-heartened, however I do not feel at all so just now. On the "<hi rend="italic">contrary quite the revarse</hi>"  You must write oftener, home, particulay Mr Lane. He likes much to hear from [you], every letter is productive of good, of course I mean those speaking of the manner of your visits to the Hospitals. Walt, you must be doing more <hi rend="italic">real good</hi> than the whole sanitary Commission put to-gether<ptr target="loc.00397_n8"/>  Mr Lane, in conversation with a gentleman in the office, said yesterday that we ought [to] raise money enough to keep a 100 Walt Whitmans, support them and pay them, (if they could be found.) and by that means take the rough edge off the War. Tis indeed true. I am thankfull that you are there. Somehow I feel that as if George, God bless him, was a little safer while you are so near him and while you are doing so much good. Oh how I wish that he could come home now, without running any more risk, and for myself, I think that he ought to. If they go to consolidating the regiments I sincerely hope that by some accident, he may be left out.<ptr target="loc.00397_n9"/> I really feel worried on mothers account. I know that if anything should happen [to] him that she could not stand it. However I suppose we must get along the best we can.</p>
            <p>With the exception of the colds, we are all in jolly good health  Mother has taken breakfasts dinner and supper I guess, with Mat and I ever since you went away. We call her up in the morning and if it is <hi rend="italic">very cold</hi> I go down and make her fire while she works and eats breakfast with us. Then Ed comes along just as I leave and Jess is generally getting up when I go home to dinner. so we live. all send love to you</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Affectionately your brother Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
