<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01961">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 7
                    February 1872</title>

                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01961</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="shueller">Herbert M. Schueller and Robert L.
                    Peters</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Symonds, John Addington</author>
                    <title>John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 7 February 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-02-07" xml:id="dat1">February 7, 1872</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Symonds, John Addington">John Addington Symonds</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-26" who="#al">Made Ken's corrections</change>
            <change when="2011-05-02" who="#al">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-03-18" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01961.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place"/>
                    <date when="1872-02-07"/>Feb: 7. 1872.</dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter found me today. This is my permanent address. I live here in a large old
                house wh.
                
                belonged to my father—a house on a hill among trees looking down upon Bristol
                with its docks &amp; churches—a picturesque labyrinth of masts &amp; spires
                &amp; houseroofs.</p>
            <p>Your letter gave me the keenest pleasure I have felt for a long time. I had not
                exactly expected to hear from you. Yet I felt that if you liked my poem you would
                write. So I was beginning to dread that I had struck some quite wrong
                chord—that perhaps I had seemed to you to have arrogantly confounded your own
                fine thought &amp; pure feeling with the baser metal of my own nature. What you say
                has reassured me and has solaced me nearly as much as if I had seen the face &amp;
                touched the hand of you—my Master!</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01961.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>For many years I have been attempting to express in verse some of the forms of what
                in a note to Democratic Vistas (as also in a blade of Calamus) you call
                "adhesiveness." I have traced passionate friendship through Greece, Rome, the
                medieval &amp; the modern world, &amp; I  have now a large body of poems written but
                not published. In these I trust the spirit of the Past is faithfully set forth as
                far as my abilities allow.</p>
            <p>It was while engaged upon this work (years ago now) that I first read Leaves of
                Grass. The man who spoke to me from that Book impressed me in in every way most
                profoundly &amp; unalterably; but especially did I then learn confidently to believe
                that the Comradeship, wh. I conceived as on a par with the Sexual feeling for depth
                &amp; strength &amp; purity &amp; capability of all good, was real—not a
                delusion of <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01961.003.jpg" type="verso"/> distorted
                passions, a dream of the Past, a scholar's fancy—but a strong &amp; vital bond
                of man to man.</p>
            <p>Yet even then how hard I found it—brought up in English feudalism, educated at
                an aristocratic public School (Harrow) and an over refined University
                (Oxford)—to winnow from my own emotions &amp; from my conception of the ideal
                friend, all husks of affectations &amp; aberrations &amp; to be a simple human
                being. <hi rend="italic">You</hi> cannot tell quite how hard this was, &amp; how you
                helped me.</p>
            <p>I have pored for continuous hours over the pages of Calamus (as I used to pore over
                the pages of Plato), longing to hear you speak, <hi rend="italic">burning</hi>  for a
                revelation of your more developed meaning, panting to ask—is this <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01961.004.jpg" type="verso"/> what you would
                indicate?—Are then the free men of your lands really so pure &amp; loving
                &amp; noble &amp; generous &amp; sincere? Most of all did I desire to hear from you
                own lip —or from your
                pen—some story of athletic friendship from wh. to learn the truth. Yet I dared
                not to address you or dreamed that the thoughts of a student could abide the
                inevitable shafts of your searching intuition.</p>
            <p>Shall I ever be permitted to question you &amp; learn from you?</p>
            <p>What the love of man for man has been in the Past I think I know. What it is
                 now, I know also—alas! What
                you say it can &amp; shall be I dimly discern in your Poems. But this hardly
                satisfies me—so desirous am I of learning what you teach. <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01961.005.jpg" type="recto"/> Some day,
                perhaps—in some form, I know not what, but in your own chosen form—you
                will tell me more about the Love of Friends! Till then I wait. Meanwhile you have
                told me more than anyone beside.—</p>
            <p>I have been led to write too much about myself, presuming on what you said, that you
                should like to know me better.</p>
            <p>It will give me sincere pleasure to receive a copy of your book from you. I am
                grateful to you for purposing to give me so great a gift. Will you complete the
                benefit by sending me a portrait of yourself?—</p>
            <p>It is good to hear that your work does not deny you leisure. Work with an ample
                margin of freedom is the best thing for man; but I cannot believe in the modern
                Gospel of Work &amp; no <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01961.006.jpg" type="verso"/> leisure. This ends in a Science of Human Mechanics.—</p>
            <p>When I am free enough from home duties, I hope to be for America, on a tour with my
                wife. Then I shall request to be permitted to pay respect to you in
                person.—</p>
            <p>That you may know my face I enclose 2 portraits. The little girl in one of them is my
                youngest child.</p>

           <closer rend="right">
                <salute>I am your ever grateful &amp; indebted</salute>
                <signed>John Addington Symonds</signed>
            </closer>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01961.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01961.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            

        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>