<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05678">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 17 March
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05678</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                        <editor>Sculley Bradley</editor>
                        <title xml:id="wwwc">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">354&#8211;56</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 17 March 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-03-17" xml:id="dat1">March 17, 1883</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D.">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-10-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <!--date of check by bbb not included-->
            <change when="2014-07-23" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded and annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Providence, R.I.</name>
                    <date when="1883-03-17">March 17, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:<!--<ptr target="n2002"/>--></salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I just have your letter of the 16th instant.<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n1"/>--> What must
                be, must; and of course if the printer wants it so, but mainly because you request
                it, I accede to the names of books being left as they were set, and not italicized,
                though I must say the italicizing of such titles has a great artistic charm for me,
                and I like to reserve quotation marks strictly for quoted matter.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05678_n2"/>--></p>

            <p>About the other thing&#8212;the paragraphic breaks&#8212;I am a good deal more
                reluctant. I wish I might be indulged in this. The composition is so
                fiery&#8212;moves on so&#8212;so sweeps the reader along "like a rushing mighty
                    wind"<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n3"/>--> that he needs no paragraphing aid to buoy up
                interest; and besides the proposed paragraphs really break this rushing continuity
                and hurt the effect: the paragraphs in the pamphlet being only put at changes of
                phase in the subject. In one portion of the pamphlet as reset, I am settled that the
                proposed paragraphing would be simply horrible: I mean the long enumeration of the
                great books. It becomes ponderous if broken up into paragraphs, and is saved by the
                rush from sentence to sentence, without pause.</p>

            <p>I think, Walt, that the paragraphs in both the Introductory and the G.G.P., had
                better be let remain as I have fixed them, and I hope the printer will concede this.
                Don't you know that it is a printer's vice&#8212;quite modern, too&#8212;to break up
                everything into scrappy paragraphs, with subheadings, &#38;c.? The effect of my
                second letter in your behalf&#8212;the reply to Chadwick<!--<ptr target="nyp.00443_n2"
                />-->&#8212;was seriously marred by this sub-captioning, and I wrote a letter to
                Whitelaw Reid<!--<ptr target="n0500"/>--> begging him not to do it any more to any other of
                my communications. The modern French books are often seriously injured by this
                excessive paragraphing, which gives an indescribable staccato, dislocated, jerky,
                hop-skip-and-jump effect to compositions full of intrinsic sobriety. I love better
                the grand old Aldine manners of the books of former days.<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n4"
                />--></p>

            <p>I hope, therefore, my paragraphing may be permitted by the benignant printer.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05678_n5"/>--></p>

            <p>I was horrified to learn that my footnote about Lowell<!--<ptr target="n1026"/>--> was set
                as per copy. It is surprising that Bucke<!--<ptr target="n0119"/>--> should have taken the
                liberty of altering words for which I am responsible.<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n6"/>-->
                The note, I guess, will have to stand as it is, for I am at the disadvantage of
                having left my annotated copy of the pamphlet at Washington, and cannot now
                precisely remember the phrasing of the note. It began something like&#8212;"'Sad
                pleasure,' because mingled (or words to this effect) with the sense of an act of
                signal meanness." The note, you see, explained the paradox of the phrase, "sad
                pleasure," and then kicked Lowell all around his os coccyx with the concise energy
                of that good animal, the mule. I am sorry it is altered, but it will do as it
                stands, and I cannot supply the original until I get back to Washington. But Bucke
                ought to have been ashamed to have done such a thing. Stupid in him, too.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05678_n7"/>--></p>

            <p><hi rend="italic">Do</hi> let me have a revise. I will return it instanter. My name
                is Promptness.<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n8"/>--> Good printer-man, thou, too, be not
                obdurate, but grant me a revise!<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n9"/>--></p>

            <p>I hope when the book comes out that you can arrange that I may have some copies at
                wholesale prices. I can put some where they will do good to all concerned.</p>

            <p>Have you seen the last edition of Dana's Household Book of Poetry? It is really
                cheering. The section entitled Poems of Nature has for an epigraph the whole of your
                "O vast rondure swimming in space"&#8212;a conspicuous honor, of course, and several
                of your poems appear in the body of the collection. This is significant. There has
                been a change.<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n10"/>--></p>

            <p>I am rummaging my memory for an epigraph for the appendix, as you requested. Nothing
                has turned up yet, but something will.</p>

            <p>I never was so taken with anything as with Bucke's epigraph from Lucretius.<!--<ptr
                    target="loc.05693_n2"/>--> I hope to heaven that he has not abandoned it. It should
                appear in Latin on the title page, with a translation in English <hi rend="italic">prose</hi> set in
                brackets [ ] directly under it. It is ineffably felicitous and apropos. Even the
                "barbaric yawp" is tallied by the Latin words describing the poetic style of
                Empedocles. It is a big thing.<!--<ptr target="loc.05678_n11"/>--></p>

            <p>I write with a dreadful pen and bad ink. The day is bad here, windy, dusty, raw,
                bleak, a genuine St. Patrick's.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed>W. D. O'Connor</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
