<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02188">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 21 July 1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ef">Ed Folsom</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02188</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 21 July 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-07-21" xml:id="dat1">July 21, 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box 10, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc> 
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Herbert" ref="n0262">Herbert Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-22" who="#ef">blessed</change>
            <change when="2015-07-22" who="#nhg">corrected correspondent note</change>
            <change when="2015-05-26" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-01" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-02" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-24" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02188.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">12 Well Road</name>
                        <name type="place">Hampstead.</name>
                        <date when="1885-07-21">July 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, 1885.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear old Walt</salute>
                </opener>

                <p> A wish has suddenly and quite spontaneously sprung up in England amongst your
                    readers to in some part pay off the debt owed every poet &amp; especially to you. I hope
                    that you may see your way to letting this little bud blossom. I shall proceed no
                    further in this until I hear from you: trusting that you will not deprive
                    England of this honour. </p>
                <p> I could not well write to you before as the scheme was so sudden and
                    spontaneous. </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02188.03_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

                <p> I think that you will like Wedmore,<ptr target="loc.02188_n1"/> he is coming to
                    call upon you in September. Wedmore is about the best critical writer in London
                    and quite the best of his kind. Although precise and neat his mind moves with
                    freedom as a candid mind should. Our friend is somewhat of a butterfly though I
                    have always found a staunch friend in Wedmore, in short I like him. </p>
                <p> I fear me that you do not take such pleasure in Glendale<ptr target="loc.02188_n3"/> as you did in Kirkwood
                    I do not hear of your being there much. I am sorry Ruthie has married so
                        young,<ptr target="loc.02188_n2"/> it means a long hard life probably in the
                    country. Her mother too has no one to help her. My mother's health is but sadly,
                    but it is <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02188.02_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    wonderful what she manages to do, continuing always to think and work for
                    others, herself last. My sister's voice is developing and her art is beginning
                    to be admired.<ptr target="n0890"/> I am in excellent health and spirits. My
                    picture in this year's Royal Academy was a good deal noticed, and has done my
                    reputation good: in fact I am getting on my feet, slowly. I am rather hankering
                    after a studio right down in the city amongst men: From a business point of view
                    it is fatal not be central, and besides I love the Strand, Oh! how you would
                    too, sort of human Delaware river. </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>With best love</salute>
                    <signed>Herbert H Gilchrist.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02188.04_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <!--Pasted to back of letter-->
                <head><handShift rend="printed"/>THE ANTHEN&#198;UM</head>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/> N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 3011, <date when="1885-07-11"><hi
                            rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 11, '85</date>
                </p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/> A <hi rend="smallcaps">subscription</hi> list is being formed in England with a
                    view to presenting a free-will offering to the American poet Walt Whitman. The
                    poet is in his sixty-seventh year, and has since his enforced retirement some
                    years ago from official work in Washington, owing to an attack of paralysis,
                    maintained himself precariously by the sale of his works in poetry and prose,
                    and by occasional contributions to magazines. Mr. Herbert H. Gilchrist, 12, Well
                    Road, Hampstead, acts as honorary and corresponding secretary to this scheme;
                    Mr. Rossetti,<ptr target="n0522"/> 5, Endsleigh Gardens, Euston Square, as
                    treasurer. </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
