<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04211">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 2 August 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04211</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">183&#8211;185</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 2 August 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-08-02" xml:id="dat1">August 2, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
  
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-19" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-01-27" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Lower Shincliffe</name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Durham</name>
                    <date when="1879-08-02" rend="right">August 2d, '79.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I am sitting in my room with my dear little grandson, the sweetest little fellow you ever saw, asleep beside me.<ptr target="n0259"/> Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> and Norah<ptr target="n3006"/> (my <choice><abbr>3d</abbr><expan>third</expan></choice> daughter) are gone into Durham to do some shopping. Bee is up in London on her way to Berne in Switzerland, where she has finally decided to complete her medical studies. Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> is, I think, staying with Eustace Conway<ptr target="n3007"/> at Hammersmith just now. He has been spending a week at Brighton with Edward Carpenter<ptr target="n0141b"/> &#38; his family&#8212;but I will leave him to tell his own news. We are lodging in this little village with its red-tiled roofs &#38; gray stone walls, lying among wooded hills, corn fields, meadows, and collieries on the banks of the Weir, for the sake of being near Percy &#38; his wife. He is superintending here the erection of some kilns for making the peculiar kind of basic firebricks needed in his dephosphorization process. Durham Cathedral, which was mainly built soon after the Norman conquest, is in sight, crowning a wooded hill that rises abruptly from the river-side. It looks as solid, majestic, venerable as the rocks &#38; hills&#8212;the interior is of wonderful grandeur &#38; beauty. When you enter one of these cathedrals you are tempted to say architecture is a lost art with us moderns so far as sublimity is concerned&#8212;except in vast engineering works. You would not dignify the Weir with the name of a river in America&#8212;it is no bigger than Timber Creek&#8212;but it winds about so capriciously through the picturesque little city as to make almost an island of the hill on which the castle &#38; cathedral stand &#38; to need three great solid stone bridges within a quarter of a mile of each other, &#38; with its steep wooded sides carrying nature right into the heart of the old town. But the rainy season (we have scarcely seen the sun since we have been in England &#38; I believe it is the same in France &#38; Italy) and the great depression in trade, especially the coal &#38; iron, which chiefly concerns this district, seem to cast a gloom over everything. There are whole rows of colliers' cottages in this village empty. Where they go to no one knows, but as soon as the collieries reopen they will all reappear. We often meet Colliers returning from work&#8212;they look as if they had just emerged from Hades, poor fellows&#8212;their faces black as soot&#8212;their lean, bowed legs bare&#8212;I believe the mines are hot here; they work with little on&#8212;but they are really the cleanest of all workmen, as they take a bath every night on their return before supping. The speech here is almost like a foreign tongue to any one from the south or middle of England. I wonder if you have yet read Dr. Bucke's book.<ptr target="loc.04211_n1"/> It is about the only thing I have read since my return. It suggests deeply interesting trains of thought.</p>
            
            <p>I wonder if you are at Camden, taking your daily trips across the ferry &#38; strolls up Chestnut St. I hardly realized till I left it how dearly I love America&#8212;great sunny land of hope and progress&#8212;or how my whole life has been enriched with the human intercourse I had there. Give my love to those of our friends whom you know &#38; tell them not to forget us. I have had a long letter from Emma Lazarus.<ptr target="n1052"/> I suppose Hattie<ptr target="n0911"/> and Jessie<ptr target="n1055"/> are spending their holidays at Camden &#38; that Hattie has pretty well done with school. We have been chiefly busy with needlework since we came&#8212;preparing dear Bee for Berne. I miss her sadly&#8212;had quite hoped we should have all been together at Paris this winter&#8212;but it seems the course is much longer &#38; more arduous [there]. We spent a week in Edinburgh before we came on here. It is by far the most beautiful city I have ever seen. The journey between it and Berwick-on-Tweed lies through the richest &#38; best cultivated farm land in Britain&#8212;the sea sparkling on one side of us &#38; these fertile fields dotted with splendid flocks &#38; herds&#8212;with large comfortable-looking farmhouses, &#38; here &#38; there an old castle; it was singularly enjoyable. How I have wished everywhere that you were with us to share the sight&#8212;and the best is that you would return home more than ever proud &#38; rejoicing in America. It is a land where humanity is having, and is going to have, such chances as never before. Giddy sends her love. Mine also &#38; to your brother &#38; sister. Good-bye, dear Friend.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="center">A. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Please write soon; I am longing for a letter.</p>
                </postscript>    
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
