<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04212">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 5 December 1879</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>                    
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04212</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">187&#8211;189</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 5 December 1879</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1879-12-05" xml:id="dat1">December 5, 1879</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-13" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-09-19" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-02-22" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-01-26" who="#ab">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">1 Elm Villas, Elm Row, Heath St.</name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Hampstead,</name>
                    <date when="1879-12-05" rend="right"><choice><abbr>Dec.</abbr><expan>December</expan></choice> 5, '79,</date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">London, England.<ptr target="n0259"/></name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>You could not easily realize the strong emotion with which I read your last note and traced on the little map<ptr target="loc.31103_n1"/>&#8212;a most precious possession which I would not part with for the whole world&#8212;all your journeyings&#8212;both in youth &#38; now. Mingled emotions! for I cannot but feel anxious about your health, &#38; if I didn't know it was very naught to ask you questions, should beg you [to] tell me in what way your health has failed&#8212;whether it is the rheumatic &#38; neuralgic affection that troubled you the last spring we were in Philadelphia, or whether the fatigues &#38; excitements &#38; the very enjoyments &#38; full life, &#38; burst of prophetic joy, as it were, had proved too great a strain. But you have accomplished another thing, that had to be done in your life &#38; I exult with you&#8212;have seen the vast magnificent theatre, the free, unfettered conditions whereon humanity will enact a new drama, with the parts all so differently cast! the rest&#8212;the moving spirit of it all&#8212;hints of this, at least&#8212;flashes, glimpses, I find in your greatest poems. But, dear Friend, I think humanity moves forward [slowly] even under splendid conditions&#8212;you must give it a century or two instead of 50 years&#8212;before at least the crowning glories of a corresponding literature &#38; art will develope themselves&#8212;Nature has got plenty of time before her, &#38; obstinately refuses to be hurried; witness her dealings with the mere rocks &#38; stones.</p>
            
            <p>Bee<ptr target="n0260"/> is at Berne, working away merrily, rejoicing in the really splendid advantage for medical study there open to her. She mastered German so as to be able to speak &#38; understand it&#8212;lectures &#38; all&#8212;with ease during the two months at Wiesbaden &#38; she has found a thoroughly comfortable home with some excellent, intelligent ladies who are fond of her &#38; see to her bodily welfare in every possible way. I have my dear little grandson with me here&#8212;as engaging a little toddler as the sun ever shone upon&#8212;so affectionate &#38; sweet-tempered &#38; bright. I wish I could see him sitting on your knee. You will certainly have to come to us as soon as ever we have a comfortable home, won't you? Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> is well &#38; as rosy as ever. She &#38; Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> send their love. I have seen Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/>&#8212;he was full of enquiries &#38; affectionate interest in all that concerns you&#8212;&#38; loth we were to break off our conversation &#38; hurry back&#8212;but Hampstead, the pleasantest &#38; prettiest of all our suburbs, is terribly inaccessible &#38; cuts us off a good deal from the intercourse with old friends I had looked forward to. It is on the top of a high hill (as high as the top of St. Pauls), &#38; looks down on one side over the great city with its canopy of smoke, &#38; on the other over a wide, pleasant stretch of green &#38; fertile Middlesex&#8212;has moreover pleasant lanes, solid old houses, shaded by big elms, &#38; other picturesque features &#38; such an abundance of keen, fresh air this cold weather too! We sigh for the warmth of an American house indoors often &#38; for American sunshine out of doors. Rossetti has a beautiful little group of children growing up around him&#8212;I think the eldest girl will grow up a real beauty &#38; the boy too is a noble little fellow. I meet numbers so delighted to hear about you. I believe Addington Symonds<ptr target="n0615"/> is preparing a book which treats largely of your Poems.</p>
           
            <p>Glad to hear that Brother &#38; Sister &#38; nieces are all well. I wish I could write to some of them, but what with needlework, an avalanche of letters, the care of my dear little man&#8212;the re-editing of my husband's life of Blake,<ptr target="loc.04045_n2"/> to which there will be a considerable addition of letters newly come to light, I hardly know which way to turn. Per.<ptr target="n2000"/> &#38; my nephew &#38; the "Process" have made a great stride forward. Won two important law suits at Berlin, where the Bessemer ring &#38; Krupp at their head were trying to oust them of their patent rights. Also it is practically making good way in England. So by &#38; bye the money will begin to flow in, I suppose&#8212;but has not done so yet.</p>
            
            <p>I trust, dearest Friend, this will find you safe &#38; fairly well again at Camden, with plenty of great, happy thoughts to brood over for the winter.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Love from us all. Good-bye.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
