<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00439">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 4 June 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00439</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">111-112</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman to Walt Whitman, 4 June 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-06-04">June 4, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2012-10-22">revised third annotation</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-09">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn, N. Y.,</name>
                  <date when="1865-06-04">June 4th 1865</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mother sent you a letter yesterday<ptr target="loc.00439_n1"/>&#8212;and a few moments afterward received one from you&#8212;Mother is getting quite around again&#8212;although I think she fails considerably&#8212;she is always quite bad mornings&#8212;it takes her some time before she can get around much  When I got home last night Mat told me that during the afternoon Mother came up stairs crying as if her heart would break all on account of that lazy baggage Ed&#8212;Mother cant do anything with him&#8212;he wont wait on himself hardly and wont do the least thing for her&#8212;I think he is the most infernal lazy and the most ugly human being I ever met&#8212;unless something can be done he certainly will shorten Mothers life by years&#8212;I cant express the amount of work that he causes her&#8212;and the excitement and worriment he causes her every moment of her life</p>
            <p>I told Mother last night that if he could be boarded, somewhere that I would take her, that she should have a good room to herself and that Mat and I would do and provide for her in all respects as long as she lived and that she need not do another thing in the way of work, except for her amusement besides I would pay part of Ed's board  She seemed to feel that if it could be done she would like it much&#8212;I sincerely wish that some arrangement could be made&#8212;for I greatly fear that Mother will not live long if she has to go on in this way&#8212;Walt wont you think over the matter and write me what you think could be done in the matter&#8212;</p>
            <p>If it wouldnt be too much trouble I wish you would write a letter to the young ones that sent you the money through Lane<ptr target="loc.00439_n2"/>&#8212;they are all awfully disappointed&#8212;they are all little girls of 8 and 12 years old (some even younger) and have been speculating what they should do with the letter&#8212;which one it would be directed to &amp;c&#8212;at last they settled it by agreeing that each one should have the letter for a week at a time in regular order&#8212;they have called to see Mr Lane several times to see if it had been received&#8212;They of course are too young to know that the great point was to give it and of course look for the praise that is usually bestowed. Did Lane explain to you that they were the children of the people that sent you money last winter a year ago&#8212;Durkee's, Crany, Lanes &amp;c &amp;c<ptr target="loc.00439_n3"/>  they remembered hearing your letters read to their fathers and mothers, and heard a great deal of talk about the great good you could do with even a few dollars  This fair they got up entirely among themselves and resolved in solumn conclave (after voting down resolutions to give to the Sanitary Com. Christian Com, &amp;c &amp;c) to send the money to you to be spent &amp;c  Mattie and the children are very well&#8212;I am writing this at the office with Hattie at my side&#8212;she wants to send a kiss to Uncle Walt</p>
            <p>We do not hear from George  I wonder why he don't write&#8212;I wish he would&#8212;Mother gets very down hearted&#8212;and a letter cheers her up wonderfully&#8212;you must write her as often as you can too&#8212;</p>
            <p>all send their love</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>affectionately Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
