<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00798">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 13 October 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00798</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">165-166</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 13 October 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-10-13">October 13, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#nhg" when="2014-02-16">corrected orgName, typo in annotations</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">modified for full citation</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-31">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-26">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington </name>
                  <date when="1863-10-13">Oct 13 | 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dearest mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>[Nothing] particular new with me. I am well &amp; hearty&#8212;think a good deal about home. Mother, I so much want to see you, even if only for a couple of weeks&#8212;for I feel I must return here &amp; continue my hospital operations. They are so much needed, although one can do only such a little in comparison, amid these thousands. Then I desire much to see Andrew.<ptr target="loc.00798_n1"/> I wonder if I could cheer him up any&#8212;does he get any good from that treatment with the baths, &amp;c. Mother, I suppose you have your hands full with Nancy's poor little children, &amp; one worry &amp; another (when one gets old little things bother a great deal). Mother, I go down every day looking for a letter from you or Jeff&#8212;I had two from Jeff latter part of the week.<ptr target="loc.00798_n2"/> I want to see Jeff much. I wonder why he didn't send me the Union with my letter in.<ptr target="loc.00798_n3"/> I am disappointed at not getting it. I sent Han [a] N Y Times with my last letter, &amp; one to George too. Have you heard any thing from George or Han?</p> 
            <p>There is a new lot of wounded now again.<ptr target="loc.00798_n4"/> They have been arriving, sick &amp; wounded, for three days&#8212;First long strings of ambulances with the sick. But yesterday many with bad &amp; bloody wounds, poor fellows. I thought I was cooler &amp; more used to it, but the sight of some of them brought tears into my eyes&#8212;Mother, I had the good luck yesterday to do quite a great deal of good&#8212;I had provided a lot of nourishing things for the men, but for another quarter&#8212;but I had them where I could use them immediately for these new wounded as they came in faint &amp; hungry, &amp; fagged out with a long rough journey, all dirty &amp; torn, &amp; many pale as ashes, &amp; all bloody&#8212;I distributed all my stores, gave partly to the nurses I knew that were just taking charge of them&#8212;&amp; as many as I could I fed myself&#8212;Then besides I found a lot of oyster soup handy, &amp; I procured it all at once&#8212;Mother, it is the most pitiful sight I think when first the men are brought in&#8212;I have to bustle round, to keep from crying&#8212;they are such rugged young men&#8212;all these just arrived are cavalry men&#8212;Our troops got the worst of it, but fought like devils. Our men engaged were Kilpatrick's<ptr target="loc.00798_n5"/> cavalry. They were in the rear as part of Meade's retreat&#8212;&amp; the reb cavalry cut in between &amp; cut them off &amp; [attacked] them &amp; shelled them terribly. But Kilpatrick brought them out mostly&#8212;this was last Sunday.</p>
            <p>Mother, I will try to come home before long, if only for six or eight days. I wish to see you, &amp; Andrew&#8212;I wish to see the young ones &amp; Mat. You must write. I am about moving,<ptr target="loc.00798_n6"/> I have been hunting for a room to-day&#8212;I shall write next how I succeed. Good by for present, dear mother.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
