<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00772">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 26 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00772</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">104-106</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 26 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-26">May 26, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-21">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-19">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington,</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-26">Tuesday forenoon, | May 26th 1863.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got a long letter from George, dated near Lancaster, Kentucky, May 15th<ptr target="loc.00772_n1"/>&#8212;he seems to be well &amp; in good spirits, says he gets some letters from me &amp; papers too&#8212;At the time he wrote, the 51st was doing provost duty at Lancaster, but would not probably remain so very long&#8212;seem to be moving toward southeast Kentucky&#8212;had a good camp, &amp; good times generally. LeGendre<ptr target="loc.00772_n2"/> is colonel&#8212;Gen. Ferrero<ptr target="loc.00772_n3"/> has left the service&#8212;Col. Potter<ptr target="loc.00772_n4"/> (now Brig. Gen.) is in Cincinnati&#8212;Capt. Sims<ptr target="loc.00772_n5"/> &amp;c are all well&#8212;George describes Kentucky as a very fine country&#8212;says the people are about half &amp; half, secesh &amp; union. This is the longest letter I have yet rec'd from George. Did he write you one about the same time? Mother, I have not rec'd any word from home in over a week&#8212;the last letter I had from Mr. Lane was about 12 days ago, sending me $10 for the soldiers, (5 from Mr. Kirkwood<ptr target="loc.00772_n6"/> &amp; 5 from Conklin Brush.)<ptr target="loc.00772_n7"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mother dear, I should like to hear from Martha, I wish Jeff would write me about it<ptr target="loc.00772_n8"/>&#8212;has Andrew gone? &amp; how is your wrist &amp; arm, mother&#8212;We have had some very hot weather here&#8212;I don't know what I should have done without the thin grey coat you sent&#8212;you don't know how good it does, &amp; looks too&#8212;I wore it three days, &amp; carried a fan &amp; an umbrella, (quite a Japanee)&#8212;most every body here carries an umbrella, on acc't of the sun&#8212;yesterday &amp; to-day however have been quite cool, east wind&#8212;Mother, the shirts were a real godsend, they do first rate, I like the fancy Marseilles collar &amp; wristbands&#8212;</p>
            <p>Mother, how are you getting along&#8212;I suppose just the same as ever&#8212;I suppose Jess &amp; Ed are just the same as ever&#8212;when you write, you tell me all about every thing, &amp; the Browns,<ptr target="loc.00772_n9"/> &amp; the neighborhood generally. Mother, is George's trunk home &amp; of no use, there? I wish I had it here, as I must have a trunk&#8212;but do not wish you to send it, until I send you word&#8212;I suppose my letter never appeared in the Eagle,<ptr target="loc.00772_n10"/> well I shall send them no more, as I think likely they hate to put in any thing which may celebrate me a little, even though it is just the thing they want for their paper &amp; readers. They altered the other letter on that account, very meanly. I shall probably have letters in the N. Y. Times &amp; perhaps other papers in about a week<ptr target="loc.00772_n11"/>&#8212;Mother, I have been pretty active in hospitals for the past two weeks, somewhere every day or night&#8212;I have written you so much about cases &amp;c I will not write you any more, on that subject this time&#8212;O the sad, sad things I see, the noble young men with legs &amp; arms taken off&#8212;the deaths&#8212;the sick weakness, sicker than death, that some endure, after amputations&#8212;(there is a great difference, some make little of it, others lie after it for days, just flickering alive, &amp; O so deathly weak &amp; sick)&#8212;I go this afternoon to Campbell Hospital, out a couple of miles.</p>
            <p>Mother, I should like to have Jeff send me 20 of the large sized portraits &amp; as many of the standing figure, do them up flat. I think every day about Martha. Mother, have you heard any further about Han? Good bye for the present, dearest mother.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
