<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05529">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 10 June
                    [1882]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05529</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 10 June 1882</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1882-06-10" xml:id="dat1">June 10, 1882</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H.">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-08-25" who="#bbb">checked</change>
            <change when="2014-07-09" who="#ss">transcribed, encoded, annotated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_af.01025_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">1882</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1882-06-10" rend="right">June 10th</date>
                    <name type="place">29 Lange Strasse</name>
                    <name type="place">Dresden</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Whitman<ptr target="n1027"/></salute>
            </opener>  
            <p>I learn to day to my great surprise that the Philistines are down on you again about
                the Children of Adam.<ptr target="loc.05529_n1"/> What purblind asses! But there's
                no use in irritating oneself with thinking about it&#8212;only somehow every new
                instance of human folly and cant strikes one as something unexpected and
                bewildering; as if one hadn't had plenty of occasion to get accustomed to anything
                or everything in that line. I am sure it will do you more good than harm in the end.
                I am, sometime soon, to read something on the Leaves of Grass before a German
                audience, a 'Literary Club,' in Dresden.<ptr target="loc.05529_n2"/> This will
                perhaps <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_af.01026_large.jpg" type="verso"/>lead to my
                finding a collaborateur for the translation&#8212;said translation owing to press of
                other business has not been very rigorously pursued lately, but after this month I
                shall take off my coat to it again. You
                    received some M.S.? A great event has lately happened in our home. I have
                become the father of a vigorous boy&#8212;our first-born; now some ten days old.<ptr
                    target="loc.05529_n3"/> "Ay, madam&#8212;it is common" but nevertheless it seems
                particular to me, naturally; and is altogether an enlivening and wonderful fact to
                us.</p>
            <p>What fearful doings in Ireland lately!<ptr target="loc.05529_n4"/> I have a
                recantation to make to you on that subject. I remember once writing to you that Home
                Rule, or Separation, was in my <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_af.01027_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>opinion a chimerical &amp; undesirable scheme for Ireland. Yet then,
                and always, that was the cause that had my affection &amp; interest&#8212;only I saw
                such obstacles in the way, &amp; foresaw such dangers to liberty if it were realized,
                that I could not go with it. Now all that has changed itself in my mind. I recognize
                now the deepseated expression of a national will in the movement. I see that the
                English can <hi rend="underline">never</hi> govern us, &#38; do worst when they mean
                best. And I see that the conflicts and miseries which I still believe to be
                inevitable on the fulfilment of the idea, will only be the (necessary) preludes
                towards a grander liberty and nationality than is at all within our reach now. I
                always abominated the English, and it is <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc_af.01028_large.jpg" type="verso"/>a great relief to me to find that I
                can support, with the feeling that I am doing right, the cause that I always
                sympathized with in my heart.&#8212;One thing is certain&#8212;these wretched
                outrages will cease instantly when Ireland has a government of her own. And that she
                will surely have, and I believe before long. If we only had arms we'd have a try
                when England gets into difficulties about this Egyptian business. (So unspeakably
                shameful to her, and <hi rend="underline">more</hi> so to France).<ptr
                    target="loc.05529_n5"/> But I expect it will be "constitutional" measures for
                some time yet. Nothing perhaps does us more harm than your dynamite party in
                    America.<ptr target="loc.05529_n6"/></p>
            <p>I hope you are well &#38; strong now, &#38; that you'll be well defended in your own
                country against this last outrage.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours always</salute>
                <signed>T W Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
