<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="man.00056">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William Taylor to Walt Whitman, 9 June 1880</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William Taylor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>man.00056</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William Taylor</author>
                    <title>William Taylor to Walt Whitman, 9 June 1880</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1880-06-09" xml:id="dat1">June 9, 1880</date>
                    <idno type="callno">GB 133 Eng 1170/1/1/28</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="man">Charles Sixsmith Collection at the John Rylands Library, University of Manchester</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Taylor, William">William Taylor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-05-26" who="#nhg">revised for final check</change>
            <change when="2014-03-30" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-03-15" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-01" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-10-24" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2013-09-26" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-06-10" who="#crl">Transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="man_ej.00165_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">Woodstown, <choice><abbr>N.J.</abbr><expan>New Jersey</expan></choice></name>
                        <date when="1880-06-09">6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <choice><abbr>mo.</abbr><expan>month</expan></choice> 9, 1880</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Walt Whitman</salute>
                    <salute>Dear Friend &amp; Guide&#8212;</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I was about to make another effort to find you,<ptr target="n3018"/> to talk over the project I wanted
                    your advice about (the Foreign Newspaper correspondence) when lo! to-day I
                    notice a few lines in the <choice><abbr>N.Y.</abbr><expan>New York</expan></choice> <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> to say you were
                    in <hi rend="underline">Canada</hi> (not Camden) and intended to remain North some
                    time: then that you intended traveling to the Far South. Thinking the <hi
                        rend="underline">Register</hi> would not be as likely as a letter to catch
                    you, in these flittings, I have enclosed proofs of pieces I mentioned to you
                    recently.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="man_ej.00229_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <p>If you get time for composition in your Summer pilgrimages, and have anything you
                    think it worth while to say to us "Farmers", I would be glad to have the same.
                    As such things must help your income to some extent&#8212;please write with the
                    piece the amount,&#8212;and I will forward <choice>
                        <abbr>chk</abbr>
                        <expan>check</expan></choice>. Don't hesitate, please, to set a price, for I am only too happy to in
                    some way to be an instrument in handing forth your Thought. Have you the Lecture
                    on Elias Hicks<ptr target="n0301"/> in such shape that you can &#38; will deliver it before an
                    assemblage. When you return, and can come to see me, &#38; visit awhile, think I
                    can get a <hi rend="underline">paying</hi> audience to our large Hall to hear
                    &#38; see you. And we being Hicksite Friends, the lecture on Hicks would be the
                    theme of greatest interest. Think over this, please, and try to favor us with
                    delivery of this Lecture on Hicks.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="man_ej.00230_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p>Well the Chicago Convention has ended &#38; politics must have a lull of
                    reaction, till the tongues of the talkers have a rest. The Greenbacks meet
                    to-day; and soon the Democrats, to make Presidential ticket.</p>
                <p>The clatter &#38; chatter of "patriots" will be soon like unending "Sound of
                    revelry by night."&#8212;till they get their offices secure! Then "the
                    Country'll be Safe".</p>
                <p>I spoke in the paper something favorable to Blaine,<ptr target="n1015"/> gave a sketch of this
                    Editor-politician, and a portrait. Sent copy to the Senator, and there was a
                    prompt <choice>
                        <sic>responce</sic>
                        <corr>response</corr>
                    </choice> of the White <choice>
                        <orig>Plume</orig>
                        <reg>Plumed</reg>
                    </choice> Knight, Blaine sending me a very pleasant letter of thanks. He seems a
                    people's favorite&#8212;but the politicians&#8212;such as Conkling<ptr target="n1016"/>&#8212;are
                    jealous.</p>
                <p>But how far below the Calm, Clear Atmosphere of <hi rend="underline">Contemplation</hi> and Soul <hi rend="underline">Repose</hi>&#8212;that you know&#8212;is this jarring discord&#8212;Politics!</p>
                        
                    
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="man_ej.00167_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <p>Tennyson,<ptr target="n0625"/> in his last poem "De Profundis" shows that his inclination is to become the <hi rend="underline">mystic</hi> in his riper years. So it is with the author of "Adam Bede" (she reported Married lately), her "Theophrastus Such" I have just been reading<ptr target="n1014"/>&#8212;filled with "wise Laws."</p>    
                    
                <p>What has become of that excellent &#38; very handsome <hi rend="underline">Radical Review</hi>? I have first few <choice>
                        
                        <abbr>Nos.</abbr>
                        <expan>Numbers</expan>
                    </choice> Then it stopped coming&#8212;Failed? The best magazine sketch I had
                    seen in any periodical, was the critical biography &#38; essay of&#8212;<hi
                        rend="underline">Walt Whitman</hi> in its Pages. My copy was loaned round,
                    till I fear it is lost. Hope you have a copy. If not I will try to secure one
                    for you. The review article about yourself was fair &#38; just</p>
                <p>&#8212;If this letter ever overtakes such a traveler as you are, I will hope to
                    get a line in reply&#8212;if time &#38; inclination permit.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Fraternally <choice>
                            <abbr>Yrs.</abbr>
                            <expan>Yours</expan>
                        </choice></salute>
                    <signed>W<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi>
                    Taylor</signed></closer>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="man_ej.00168_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <head type="main-authorial" rend="center"><handShift rend="printed"/>WALT WHITMAN.</head>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>In this column we give, from the Phila. <hi rend="italic">Press</hi>, a letter
                    from Dr. Bucke that, in justice to our Good Gray Poet, should be widely
                    circulated. Scribblers are too prone to attack every man or woman who exhibits
                    the least originality,&#8212;with about the same reason that the crows display
                    in pecking to death one of their kind happening to have a white feather or other
                    peculiarity unlike the persecutors themselves. Intolerance of religious belief
                    has the same petty and malignant origin,&#8212;I am better and holier than
                    thou, so go to, and be damned to everlasting torments!</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We have known Walt Whitman the poet, and found him ever gentlemanly in demeanor,
                    cleanly in habits and careful in his dress&#8212;not flaunting a red, open
                    shirt, and wearing a tarpaulin hat as has been asserted by <choice>
                        <sic>him</sic>
                        <corr>his</corr>
                    </choice> enemies. Even in his younger days, there is the best of evidence that
                    his habits were correct, and his conversation ennobling&#8212;as became one to
                    whom was entrusted by his Creator the sacred fire of genius. If he had been
                    ill-dressed and low-minded, it is hardly probable that the beloved poet, William
                    Cullen Bryant, should have made young Whitman his bosom companion. Often the two
                    youthful poets, while engaged in New York or Brooklyn printing offices, before
                    or after working hours met to take long walks together, so that by sweet
                    converse amid the beauties of nature, there might be satisfied that longing each
                    possessed for the poetic and prophetic afflatus, to unravel the <choice>
                        <sic>mystires</sic>
                        <corr>mysteries</corr>
                    </choice> of Life or Death.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>When Walt Whitman began writing his peculiarly original poems, one of the first
                    to give cordial recognition and praise was the philosopher Emerson. Charles
                    Sumner, too, gave Whitman, unasked, the warmest commendation, as writer of the
                    grandest dirge upon the lamented Lincoln ever composed. We have evidence, as
                    well, that our New Jersey poet is a profound thinker upon religious and moral
                    themes. One of his very latest compositions is a lecture upon Elias Hicks, one
                    the great lights of modern Quakerism. But to hear some ignorant fellows talk
                    about Walt Whitman, one would think him a nasty and eccentric old lunatic;
                    instead of the quiet gentleman and the poet and thinker that he is.</p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>W<hi rend="smallcaps">ALT</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">HITMAN</hi>.&#8212;Dr. Bucke writes thus to the Phila. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Press</hi> of late date:</p>
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"Your report in to-day's paper of Colonel Ingersoll's Tuesday evening lecture,
                        on "What Shall I Do to be Saved?" is interspersed every second or third
                        paragraph with "Amen from Walt Whitman," the poet's name appearing in this
                        manner in the long report and introduction some eight or ten times. It was
                        at my invitation that Mr. Whitman went to the lecture, and I sat at his side
                        throughout its delivery. He neither uttered the "Amen" which the reporter
                        puts so often in his mouth, nor once made any sign whatever, either by voice
                        or hand, of approval or disapproval, but maintained his usual
                        undemonstrative manner throughout. The "Amens" were uttered by a person
                        immediately to the left of Mr. Whitman; the mistake was therefore a natural
                        one.</p>
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>While I am about it, would you give me room to correct "The Genesis of Walt
                        Whitman" in <hi rend="italic">Appleton's Journal</hi>&#8212;not the
                        malignance and falsehood of the
                        whole article, but a small specimen brick. The <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal</hi> speaks of Walt Whitman as habitually wearing, while living
                        in New York, a red flannel shirt, a blouse and a tarpaulin hat. It doesn't
                        seem to me to matter if he did; but the fact is, he never in his life donned
                        either of those articles. Whitman always dressed about the same as he does
                        now.</p>
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Another: Not long since the <hi rend="italic">Inquirer</hi> of this city
                        published a lengthy article on cremation, giving interviews with prominent
                        men and their views on the subject&#8212;among the rest a long string
                        purporting to come from Walt Whitman. A day or two after the poet received a
                        letter from the author of the article, saying that as he had been pressed for
                        time he had taken the liberty to manufacture and print a set of opinions for
                        Walt Whitman without consulting him&#8212;and hoped to be excused!</p>
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Then one more: I am informed that an elderly, full-bearded, gray haired artist
                        has for years been frequenting the barrooms and hotels of this city, his
                        chums introducing him to strangers as "Walt Whitman," he being always ready
                        to take a drink in that character!</p>
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>You might say that such mistakes and "roasts" are not very important, and, at
                        all events, get rectified in time. But they don't&#8212;not by any means&#8212;always; <hi rend="italic">they often make so-called history.</hi>
                        Walt Whitman himself laughs at them as merely amusing, but they are very
                        painful to his friends, who are more in number and warmer than perhaps is
                        generally suspected, and, as one of these, I write you this letter, which I
                        hope you will have the kindness to insert."</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <p><handShift rend="printed"/>In justice to the Phila. <hi rend="italic">Inquirer</hi>, we must state
                        that this excellent newspaper had nothing to do with getting up the bogus
                        interview with Walt Whitman recently about "Cremation" (mentioned elsewhere)
                        except that with other matter it was purchased from the reporter and printed
                        upon faith. The intemperate scribbler who got up, "out of his own head," the
                        so-called interview, had become a slave of rum, and was fast sinking from an
                        honored position on the reportorial staff of the newspaper. Since the hoax
                        was printed this reporter has died from effects of his dissipation.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="man_ej.00169_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="man_ej.00170_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>



</TEI>
