<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00667">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Elisa Seaman Leggett to Walt Whitman, 19 December
                    1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Elisa Seaman Leggett</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00667</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Thomas Donaldson</author> 
                        <title xml:id="td">Walt Whitman the Man</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Francis P. Harper</publisher>
                            <date when="1896">1896</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">246&#8211;248</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Elisa Seaman Leggett</author>
                    <title>Elisa Seaman Leggett to Walt Whitman, 19 December 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-12-19" xml:id="dat1">December 19, 1882</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of this manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Leggett, Elisa Seaman">Elisa Seaman Leggett</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-06-03" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-24" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-02-19" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-12-12" who="#ss">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place" rend="right">Detroit,</name>
                        <date when="1882-12-19" rend="right">December 19, 1882.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dear Friend:</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I feel so drawn to send you a Christmas greeting. I hear from Percy that you are
                    in better health than you were during the summer. I hope you may constantly
                    improve. I read a medical article once, which said: "If a person has had poor
                    health through middle life and has struggled on so as to reach his sixty-second
                    year, the probability is that he will live through the next twenty years in very
                    comfortable condition." I trust this may prove a truth in your life. I don't
                    know if I think it a fine wish, to hope for length of days for those we love or
                    not, but somehow it seems as though the later days of an earnest soul are the
                    ripest fruit of all the seasons&#8212;well-conditioned. So I look upon the life
                    of a person in healthy mind, from the time we call middle age to the years of
                    eighty or more, as the most helpful to humanity and oftenest the most serene
                    and richest to the person himself. So let me wish you a good long life, full of
                    comfort, full of gifts to the world. Did you receive an invitation to the
                    wedding of my daughter, Blanche, on the 14th of June last? I said to her:
                    "Choose who you like to come;" and she said: "Oh, I would be so glad to have
                    Walt Whitman! He seems so much like one of our family." I send you her picture,
                    that you may think of the child who feels like a sister to you. This was our
                    baby, and she has left her home for one in Chicago. We were never before
                    separated. It is a trial. So often I think of the days of my youth, amid the
                    calm content of Quaker society, so beautiful. The home where often four
                    generations in one family lived, a bit of the farm given to a child at his
                    coming of age, and the marriage of youths scarcely separating families. Until I
                    came to Michigan, thirty years ago, all my surroundings were among Friends,
                    twelve years at Roslyn and Friends meeting at Wesbury. Did you ever attend a
                    silent meeting? If not, do go some day to Philadelphia and feel its solemnity.
                    The last I was at was at Race Street. The early hour was silent; then George
                    Truman said a few words that seemed to fall like seed in the prepared soil. A
                    cat came into the meeting and took its place beside the speaker. It all seemed
                    right. Everything seemed so harmonious, that the quiet movements of any domestic
                    animal would have created no surprise. Tears came into my children's eyes. After
                    meeting I asked them why? They could not tell, only it was "so sweet, so
                    solemn." I will tell you a story about Percy's mother, when she was a little
                    child, seven years old. A baby had been born while she was at school. It was
                    dead. I took it into a quiet room, made it look pretty, and put a few flowers
                    about it. It looked not much different from a doll. I had often wondered if a
                    child had naturally a fear of death, of being alone with the dead. When Minnie
                    came home, I said: "Would you like to look at the pretty baby?" She touched the
                    hand and face and kissed the face, and wanted to hold it in her arms. I laid it
                    in her lap, and said: "Be careful." There was an instinct that forbade her to
                    hold it up, and she did not want to give it up. I said: "Would you like to stay
                    and keep it a while?" "Yes." Then I left her alone and stood outside, thinking
                    she might lift it. In a few minutes she called, and asked me "to take it." I
                    asked, "Why?" "Oh, it was so still, it made her feel so strange! She did not
                    want to be alone, if mamma would stay." Then I wondered if it was the silence, so
                    powerful is it, in its messages. So I feel the silences in the meetings of
                    Friends. I can't tell why, there is a solemnity that finds its way through the
                    soul.</p>
                <p>I am my friend with kindest regards,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute rend="center">Yours truly,</salute>
                    <signed rend="right">Elisa S. Leggett.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
