<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyh.00004">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Elisa Seaman Leggett to Walt Whitman, 22 June 1881</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Elisa Seaman Leggett</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kc">Kirsten Clawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nyh.00004</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Thomas Donaldson</author>
                        <title xml:id="td">Walt Whitman the Man</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Francis P. Harper</publisher>
                            <date when="1896">1896</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">242&#8211;246</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Elisa Seaman Leggett</author>
                    <title>Elisa Seaman Leggett to Walt Whitman, 22 June 1881</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-06-22" xml:id="dat1">June 22, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="nyh">New York Historical Society</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Leggett, Elisa Seaman">Elisa Seaman Leggett</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-04-24" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2014-02-04" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-01-23" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-19" who="#kc">Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Detroit,</name>
                    <date when="1881-06-22" rend="right">June 22, 1881.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>DEAR FRIEND:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Let me thank you for papers sent, which gave me great pleasure.<!--<ptr target="n1017"/>--></p>

            <p>I wonder if you know anything about Sojourner Truth, an old <choice>
                    <orig>col'd</orig>
                    <reg>colored</reg>
            </choice> woman, known to be 100 years of age.<!--<ptr target="n3057"/>--> She remembers the soldiers of our
                Revolutionary War, going to see them and their wounded legs; tells
                incidents, when she was a "pretty big girl," of the events of the Revolution. Her
                father's mother was a squaw. Sojourner was a slave in New York State, on the Hudson,
                until she was forty years. After her freedom she became a seeker for the truth;
                hence she gave up her slave name of Isabella and took the one she has, saying "she
                would be a sojourner on the earth, seeking for truth." She is a majestic, tall, thin
                person, with an eye fevery at times, at others, tender and pitiful. She can neither
                read or write, but she has a powerful voice and, like her eye, at times, sweet, and
                filled with human love. Soon after her emancipation, she heard of Matthias. Do you
                remember him, in New York? You were a little boy then, but he represented
                himself as Christ, and a follower of his called himself John the Baptist. There was
                a "Kingdom of Heaven" established up the North River, with many disciples.
                Sojourner's imagination was fired by this, and she thought she had found the truth,
                lived among them and discovered great sins and corruption. A sudden death came in
                the "Kingdom" and Matthias was arrested. Sojourner knew him to be innocent, took
                care of him in prison, testified as to his innocence,&#8212;a long story,&#8212;but
                she got him clear. Then she got on Long Island, and after a while joined the
                Adventists at Northampton, <choice>
                    <abbr>Mass.</abbr><expan>Massachusetts</expan></choice>, saw their mistakes, and threw herself into a servant of truth, meant to
                help the Lord. She worked in the anti-slavery cause; was intimate
                with Garrison,<!--<ptr target="n3058"/>--> Phillips,<!--<ptr target="n3059"/>--> <choice><orig>Gerritt</orig><reg>Gerrit</reg></choice> Smith,<!--<ptr target="n3060"/>--> and Lucretia Mott;<!--<ptr target="n3061"/>--> was well known and
                honored in the houses of all these; worked in the woman's cause, and was a hard
                worker in the war; went to Washington and saw President Lincoln, had a good talk
                with him, told him "she had come to help him." He said: "Go and teach your race
                the meaning of liberty." Stayed there a year working. Then she went to a water cure
                to study the laws of health. She has lectured in all of our Northern States and many
                of the Middle ones; in every good cause, and on temperance, in our
                political campaigns she has been most efficient; she spent one winter
                with Theodore Tilton,<!--<ptr target="uva.00366_n2"/>--> and knew the Beechers well, old Lyman Beecher<!--<ptr target="duk.00586_n17"/>--> and Mrs. Stowe<!--<ptr target="n3062"/>-->
                as well; she has been upon the platform with our best men and women, and
                knew them intimately, Theodore Parker<!--<ptr target="n0463"/>-->  and all who worked in reform causes; she
                will not have the Bible read to her except by children; and says: "If it was
                the Word of God he will make it plain to her." She talks with God as though he was
                beside her, and asks him many questions, sometimes advises a little. She
                don't see anything useful in the new translation of the New
                Testament; says that the history belongs to past ages. We have
                outgrown the history, but the truths that Christ gave can't die. Thinks there ought
                to be Scriptures written of what God has done ever since the times of the early
                creation and Moses&#8212;Scriptures telling of railroads, and telephones and the
                Atlantic cable. She sees God in a steam engine and electricity. Well, I have
                told you all this, just to tell you of an anecdote connected with yourself. In 1864
                she visited me in Detroit. I used to read your "Leaves of Grass" to my children. It
                has formed a large part of their education. Once with my back to the door
                entering the parlor, in a large chair, my children before me on the sofa, I noticed
                while I read they looked up. I said: "Pay attention, or I can't read to you." So
                they were quiet, and I continued. Presently I was surprised to hear Sojourner, in a
                loud voice, exclaim, "Who wrote that?" I turned, and there in the doorway she
                stood, her tall figure, with a white turban on her head, her figure and every
                feature full of expression. Immediately, she added: "Never mind the man's
                name. It was God who wrote it. He chose the man to give his message." After that I
                often read it to her. Her great brain accepts the highest truths. She is here
                now. I took her last week to hear a lecture upon Raphael's School of Athens. The
                teacher talked of the old philosophers, Plato, Socrates, and others.
                Sojourner gave great attention, occasionally uttering, when something was
                explained: "Eh, who said it? <choice>
                    <orig>'Tis</orig>
                    <reg>It is</reg>
                </choice> God, <choice>
                    <orig>'Tis</orig>
                    <reg>It is</reg>
                </choice> God! How good, how simple!" I wonder if you care for all this. She
                is still marvelous. Mr. <choice><orig>Iver</orig><reg>Ives</reg></choice> and his son, Percy,<ptr target="nyh.00004_n1"/> the little fellow that loves
                you so well, are both painting her portrait. If I can get a photo, I will send you
                one.</p>

            <p>Last year Sojourner went to Kansas and worked faithfully among the refugees, and
                lectures yet. Her concern now is to emancipate the minds of people from the
                old superstitions of religious teaching and that the Kingdom of God is in the
                hearts of his children, and telling the people to save their labor about sending
                missionaries to the heathen, but to take care of the heathen in our own country. Her
                voice is still powerful.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I am, with sincere good will, your friend,</salute>
                <signed>ELISA SEAMAN LEGGETT.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
