<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00182">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Thomas P. Sawyer, 27 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00182</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">106-107</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Thomas P. Sawyer, 27 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-27">May 27, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Sawyer, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Sawyer</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-20">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-19">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Washington,</name>
                  <date when="1863-05-27">May 27, 1863.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I sit down to rattle off in haste a few lines to you. I do not know what is the reason I have been favored with nary a word from you, to let me know whether you are alive &amp; well&#8212;that is, if you are so, which I pray to God you are. My thoughts are with you often enough, &amp; I make reckoning when we shall one day be together again&#8212;yet how useless it is to make calculations for the future. Still a fellow will.</p>
            <p>Tom, I wrote you one letter April 21st, &amp; then another April 26th. The first one must have gone all right, as a letter was received by me April 28th,<ptr target="nyp.00182_n1"/> (very pretty written)&#8212;but I have not heard whether you got my second letter. I enclosed in it an envelope with my address on, in hopes you would write to me.</p>
            <p>Well, dear brother, the great battle between Hooker &amp; Lee came off, &amp; what a battle it was&#8212;without any decisive results again, though at the cost of so many brave men's lives &amp; limbs&#8212;it seems too dreadful, that such bloody contests, without settling any thing, should go on. The hospitals here are filled with the wounded, I think the worst cases &amp; the plentiest of any fighting yet. Was you in the fight? I have made inquiries of two of the 11th Mass. here in hospital, but they could not tell me about you for certain.</p>
            <p>Lewy Brown<ptr target="nyp.00182_n2"/> seems to be getting along pretty well. I hope he will be up &amp; around before long&#8212;he is a good boy, &amp; has my love, &amp; when he is discharged, I should feel it a comfort to share with Lewy whatever I might have&#8212;&amp; indeed if I ever have the means, he shall never want.</p>
            <p>Dr. Bliss<ptr target="nyp.00182_n3"/> was removed from Armory &amp; put for a few days in the Old Capitol prison&#8212;there is now some talk however of his going back to Armory. There is no particular change in my affairs here&#8212;I just about manage to pay my way, with newspaper correspondence &amp;c. Tom, I believe I shall have to lay pipe for some office, clerkship, or something&#8212;</p>
            <p>We had awful hot weather here three or four days ago&#8212;O how the grease run off of me&#8212;I invested in an umbrella &amp; fan&#8212;it must have been gay<ptr target="nyp.00182_n4"/> down there about Falmouth&#8212;didn't you want some <hi rend="italic">ice cream</hi> about last Sunday?</p>
            <p>My dearest comrade, I cannot, though I attempt it, put in a letter the feelings of my heart&#8212;I suppose my letters sound strange &amp; unusual to you as it is, but as I am only expressing the truth in them, I do not trouble myself on that account. As I intimated before, I do not expect you to return for me the same degree of love I have for you.</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
