<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00180">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Thomas P. Sawyer, 21 April 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00180</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">90&#8211;93</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Thomas P. Sawyer, 21 April 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-04-21">April 21, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Sawyer, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Sawyer</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-08-31">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-16">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <p>Tom,<ptr target="nyp.00180_n3"/> I thought I would write you a few words, and take chances of its getting to you&#8212;though there is great excitement now about the Army of the Potomac,<ptr target="nyp.00180_n4"/> no passes allowed, mails held over, &amp;c. &amp;c.&#8212;still I thought I would write, and take chances.</p> 
            <p>There is nothing very special here about Washington&#8212;they seem to be shoving troops off from here now all the time, in small or large bodies&#8212;the convalescents are doing guard duty &amp;c in the Hospitals&#8212;even the old regiments doing patrol, &amp; provost, are sent off. So I suppose something is up. Tom, I was at Armory last evening, saw Lewy Brown,<ptr target="nyp.00180_n5"/> sat with him a good while, he was very cheerful, told me how he laid out to do, when he got well enough to go from hospital, (which he expects soon), says he intends to go home to Maryland, go to school, and learn to write better, and learn a little bookkeeping, &amp;c.&#8212;so that he can be fit for some light employment. Lew is so good, so affectionate&#8212;when I came away, he reached up his face, I put my arm around him, and we gave each other a long kiss, half a minute long. We talked about you while I was there. I saw Hiram<ptr target="nyp.00180_n6"/> but did not speak to him. He lay pale and pretty sick, sound asleep. I could not help stopping before I came away, and looking at him&#8212;it was pitiful to see him, so pale, sound asleep&#8212;Poor Hiram&#8212;he is a good boy&#8212;he gets no better. Johnny Mahay<ptr target="nyp.00180_n7"/> does not get any better, in Ward E. He is going to have an operation performed on him by Dr. Bliss.<ptr target="nyp.00180_n8"/> Tom, I do not know who you was most intimate with in the Hospital, or I would write you about them.</p>
            <p>As to me, there is nothing new with me, or my affairs. I manage to pay my way here in Washington, what I make writing letters for the New York papers, &amp;c. When I stopped here, last January, on my return from Falmouth, I thought I would stop only a few days, before returning to New York, and see if I could not get some berth, clerkship or something&#8212;but I have not pushed strong enough&#8212;have not got anything&#8212;and I don't know as I could be satisfied with the life of a clerk in the departments anyhow. So I have hung along here ever since. I guess I enjoy a kind of vagabond life any how. I go around some, nights, when the spirit moves me, sometimes to the gay places, just to see the sights. Tom, I wish you was here. Somehow I don't find the comrade that suits me to a dot&#8212;and I won't have any other, not for good.</p>
            <p>Well, Tom, the war news is not lovely, is it? We feel disappointed here about Charleston<ptr target="nyp.00180_n9"/>&#8212;I felt as blue about it as anybody. I was so in hopes they would take the conceit out of that gassy city. It seems to me always as if Charleston has done the biggest business of blowing &amp; mischief, on a small capital of industry or manliness, of any city the world ever knew. But for all our bad success at Charleston, and even if we fail for a while elsewhere, I believe this Union will conquer in the end, as sure as there's a God in heaven. This country can't be broken up by Jeff Davis, &amp; all his damned crew. Tom, I sometimes feel as if I didn't want to live&#8212;life would have no charm for me, if this country should fail after all, and be reduced to take a third rate position, to be domineered over by England &amp; France &amp; the haughty nations of Europe &amp;c and we unable to help ourselves. But I have no thought that will ever be, this country I hope would spend her last drop of blood, and last dollar, rather than submit to such humiliation.</p>
            <p>O I hope Hooker<ptr target="nyp.00180_n10"/> will have good success in his plans, whatever they may be. We have been foiled so often in our plans, it seems as though it was too much. And our noble Army of the Potomac, so brave, so capable, so full of good men, I really believe they are this day the best in the world. God grant Hooker may have success, and his brave boys may at last achieve the victory they deserve. O how much I think about them though. I suppose that does no good. Tom, you tell the boys of your company there is an old pirate up in Washington, with the white wool growing all down his neck&#8212;an old comrade who thinks about you &amp; them every day, for all he don't know them, and will probably never see them, but thinks about them as comrades &amp; younger brothers of his, just the same.<ptr target="nyp.00180_n11"/>
            </p>
            <p>These lines may never reach you, as it is talked here that the Army of the Potomac is in for a real fighting march, at last, may be something desperate, it may continue some time when it once begins. Tom, I thought I would write you a few words, hoping they might reach you. Dear comrade, you must not forget me, for I never shall you. My love you have in life or death forever. I don't know how you feel about it, but it is the wish of my heart to have your friendship, and also that if you should come safe out of this war, we should come together again in some place where we could make our living, and be true comrades and never be separated while life lasts&#8212;and take Lew Brown too, and never separate from him. Or if things are not so to be&#8212;if you get these lines, my dear, darling comrade, and any thing should go wrong, so that we do not meet again, here on earth, it seems to me, (the way I feel now,) that my soul could never be entirely happy, even in the world to come, without you, dear comrade.<ptr target="nyp.00180_n12"/> And if it is God's will, I hope we shall yet meet, as I say, if you feel as I do about it&#8212;and if [it] is destined that we shall not, you have my love none the less, whatever should keep you from me, no matter how many years. God bless you, Tom, and preserve you through the perils of the fight.</p>
         <p>Good bye, my darling comrade, my dear darling brother, for so I will call you, and wish you to call me the same.<ptr target="nyp.00180_n100"/>
         </p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
