<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00223">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">A. Van Rensellaer to Walt Whitman, 30 July
                    1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>A. Van Rensellaer</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kp">Ken Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="km">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00223</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>A. Van Rensellaer</author>
               <title>A. Van Rensellaer to Walt Whitman, 30 July
                    1865</title>
               <date when="1865-07-30">July 30, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Oscar Lion Papers, 1914&#8211;1955, New York Public Library, New York, N.Y. A photostat reproduction of the manuscript is held in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection of the Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Van Rensellaer, A.">A. Van Rensellaer</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2011-09-14">updated sourceDesc and revisionDesc</change>
         <change who="#kp" when="2011-09-13">updated transcription based on consultation of photostat at University of Chicago</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2011-08-31">updated Oscar Lion info</change>
         <change who="#km" when="2011-09-13">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-11">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-17">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>            
         
                <opener rend="right">
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">New York,</name>
                        <date when="1865-07-30">July 30, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>                
            <p>Looking over a file of papers in the reading room I saw a paragraph about your
                    dismissal from the Interior Department, and as I once read your book, I am moved
                    to express my feelings in the matter. The act strikes me as pretty mean but
                    quite of a piece with Harlan's<ptr target="nyp.00223_n1"/> character. As I
                    see you are in the Atty Gen'l's office I will call on you when I come to W. in a
                    few days and tell you <hi rend="italic">in confidence</hi> a little transaction
                    I once had with Harlan, long time ago, which will show you what kind of chap he
                    is. I read your book when it first came out and though I must admit a good deal
                    of it was blind to me, I saw considerable which struck me as first class, though
                    I don't pretend to much judgment in such matters. Anyhow I didn't see anything
                    worse in what Harlan makes so much of than what is in old Bill Shakespeare and
                    the Bible, and dashed in pretty thick too. Some folks are more squeamish than
                    me, though.&#8212;Perhaps you might like to hear something Mr. Lincoln once said
                    of you, which you probably never heard of. It wasn't much to say, but the way he
                    said it struck me a good deal. It was in the winter time, I think in '64 I went
                    up to the White House with a friend of mine, an M. C., who had some business
                    with the President. He had gone out, so we didn't stop, but coming down stairs,
                    quite near the door we met the President coming in and we stept back into the
                    East Room and stood near the front windows, where my friends had a confab with
                    him. It didn't last more than three or four minutes, but there was something
                    about a letter which my friend had handed the President, and Mr Lincoln had read
                    it and was holding it in his hand like one thinking it over, and looking out of
                    the window when you went by, quite slow, with your hands in the breastpockets of
                    your overcoat and a sizeable felt hat on your head pretty well up, just as I
                    have often seen you on Broadway. Mr. Lincoln asked who you were, or something
                    like that. I spoke up and said, mentioning your name and that you had written
                    "Leaves of Grass," etc. Mr. Lincoln didn't say anything but took a good long
                    look till you were quite gone by. Then he says&#8212;(I cant give you his way of
                    saying it, but it was quite emphatic, and odd), "Well," he says, "<hi rend="italic">he</hi> looks like a <hi rend="italic">man</hi>." He said it
                    pretty loud but in a sort of absent way and with the emphasis on the words I
                    have underscored. He didn't say any more but began to talk again about the
                    letter and in a minute or so, we went off. Seeing your name just now in the
                    paper put me in mind of it it and I thought it was an item you might like to
                    know. It was the only time I spoke to Mr. Lincoln though I saw him often.</p>                
            <p>I expect to be in Washington on my way down South in a few days and will take the
                    freedom of giving you a call. Please don't mention my <hi rend="italic">name</hi> in connection with what I write about Harlan. I'll explain why
                    when I see you and you will see the reason for not spreading it round.</p>                
            <closer rend="right">
                    <salute>With respect, &amp;c., truly yours,</salute>
                    <signed>A. Van Rensallaer.</signed>
                </closer>            
                 
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
