<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00187">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Moses Lane (?), 13 (?) March 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="lh">Luke Hollis</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00187</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">201&#8211;202</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Moses Lane (?), 13 (?) March 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-03-13">March 13, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Lane, Moses">Moses Lane</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-16">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#lh" when="2009-09-02">proofed and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-10-03">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear friend,<ptr target="nyp.00187_n2"/>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I rec'd this morning your additional contribution of $5 for the wounded &amp; sick. The same am't from you was also duly &amp; thankfully received last month. It is some time since I have written you.<ptr target="nyp.00187_n3"/> I have lately been down to front a second time through the field hospitals&#8212;they are breaking them up &amp; sending the bad cases up here. I suppose preparatory to some movement of course. Among the sick diarrhea &amp; rheumatism are prevalent. Many of the cases of the latter suffer fearfully. I am writing this in hospital as I am watching here to-night over a bad case.</p>
            <p>(Describe scene.)<ptr target="nyp.00187_n4"/>
            </p>
            <p>With me here things are about the same. I have first-rate health &amp; strength. My hospital ministrations are very fascinating with all of their sadness. The wounded &amp; sick get incredibly near to one. Poor young men, they respond so affectionately to kindness &amp; magnetism.<ptr target="nyp.00187_n5"/>
            </p>
            <p>I suppose you hear of Grant's plan to improve enormously the communication between here &amp; the southwest by rail &amp;c. so that he can transport the army by immense trains hither &amp; yon at short notice. They say he has staked all on taking Richmond within three months. God prosper him.</p>
            <p>Our Virginia Army is in prime condition. This I know from personal observation. All its defeats &amp; slaughters have only hardened it, &amp; made it an army of fighters. I believe Grant realizes in his secret heart that it is the clear superior in fibre &amp; soul of his Western Army, but of course he would not say so.</p>
         <p>Dear friend, the sick are coming in here now from front pretty freely. I have need of means additional&#8212;The new sick &amp; wounded generally come in without a cent. I give aid of all kinds, sometimes little sums of money. You have been generous &amp; regular in your aid, &amp; I cannot call on you for any thing more than you are doing, but I would like you to cast around among your friends, show them this note, &amp; tell them the case&#8212;see if you could raise among them some 20 or $25 the ensuing week, if possible, for it is for a sacred object.<ptr target="nyp.00187_n100"/>
         </p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
