<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00163">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Charles H. Harris to Walt Whitman, 30 May 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Charles H. Harris</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="lh">Luke Hollis</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00163</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">150&#8211;151</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Charles H. Harris</author>
               <title>Charles H. Harris to Walt Whitman, 30 May 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-05-30">May 30, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Harris, Charles H.">Charles H. Harris</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#lh" when="2009-08-28">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-07">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> </opener>
         <p>Dear Uncle As i<ptr target="nyp.00163_n100"/> shal now clame you four you remain as dear to me as mi one [relation] Wal Uncle i got home all lonely only i was mity tiard whin i arrived i ni Brattelboro but i am fuly wal Reasted now as four mi wound i dont think it is as wal as it was whin i left Washington but i think it will be all rite after a while  Charles Dunkler get home all rite also he sens his love to you</p>
            <p>Oh Uncle i wish you ware hear in old Vermont with me  we wod have some late old times fishing a mong the green mountains that what master  Wal Uncle i soppose that you like on the old court Register now as ever  oh the boys must think a good deal of you i wish i had see you now i most Pay the wine it seames lonesome hear without you but Nevr mind i woant be long before i shal be whare i Can see you once mour i told mi folks about you thay think thr soldier Boys out to think a grate Deal of you</p>
            <p>whin i arived in Brattleboro i found mi folks all wal i tel you whot theay was very glat to se mi and also the <hi rend="italic">Girls</hi>&#8212;oh Pleas giv mi love to Miss Howard<ptr target="nyp.00163_n2"/> and also to dear Carter<ptr target="nyp.00163_n3"/> also to Miss Gregg<ptr target="nyp.00163_n4"/>, wont you</p>
            <p>about mi Photograph i will send it to you in mi next letter Wal Uncle i have no moare now to write this time Ples giv mi love to all mi [ac]quainize frinds i will Close now by saying good By Dear Uncle wishing to hear from you son   From year Ever tru young friend</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Ples Excuse all mistakes an Bad Writing Also Excuse mi shoart letter this tim an i will try and Do Better in my next</salute>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
