<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00185">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Ellen M. O'Connor, 15 November 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00185</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">182-184</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Ellen M. O'Connor, 15 November 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-11-15">November 15, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M.">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-07">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-01">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-30">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Brooklyn </name>
                  <date when="1863-11-15">November 15 1863</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Nelly</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I have received your letter, also Charles Eldridge's &amp; Mrs Cooper's. Nelly, I hope this will find you better of your cold, &amp; that you &amp; all the rest are well &amp; [in] good spirits.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n100"/> Tell Mrs Cooper I heartily accept her invitation to visit at Philadelphia, &amp; if I can work it so I will come gladly.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n2"/> I think about you all, &amp; frequently. I have told my mother &amp; sister about you all. I send my love to William. I feel that I have never had a better friend, &amp; that no truer nor warmer heart beats. Tell Charles Eldridge too I send him my love. I regret his not likely meeting me in New York to go around together. But, Charley, we will have it yet, dear comrade. I received the letters you sent under envelope. For all &amp; sundry, &amp; the year's most valuable kindness, from you three, what can I say, more than that I am sure I appreciate it.
Nelly, I had a pleasant trip that Monday from the start, &amp; all through&#8212;clear &amp; cool &amp; no dust&#8212;I got home about 8 in evening&#8212;was up bright &amp; early to the polls next morning &amp;c. How well the election went in this state, you know.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n3"/> Here Brooklyn gave a stunning union vote, the biggest ever dreamed of here&#8212;Mayor, assemblymen, judges, all elected. Nelly, I am writing this from my room at my mother's house. It is Sunday afternoon, dripping &amp; rainy, the air thick &amp; warm, &amp; the sky lowering. My poor brother Andrew is very ill. It is not likely he can live. His voice is quite gone. Still he moves about &amp; is here all the time during the day. My sister Martha is untiring, feeding &amp; nursing him. Of her children, little Hattie is well&#8212;the new baby is immense, &amp; I take to her in proportion. I want her to be called California. She is fully worthy the name. She is large, calm, not pretty but something ahead of that, full of latent fire in the eyes (which are grey) &amp; a complete success every way. Mother is very well &amp; active &amp; cheerful&#8212;she still does her own light housework, &amp; keeps up handsomely under her surroundings of domestic pressure&#8212;one case of sickness &amp; its accompanying irritability&#8212;two of grown helplessness<ptr target="nyp.00185_n4"/>&#8212;&amp; the two little children, very much with her, &amp; one of them unsurpassed in volatility &amp; restlessness&#8212;Nelly, I have thought before that the real &amp; best bravery is to be discovered somewhere else than in the bravery of war, &amp; beyond the heroisms of men. My brother Jeff is well&#8212;he is a noble young man &amp; one to love.</p>
            <p>I find my New York boys the same gay-hearted, joyous fellows, full of friendship &amp; determined to have pleasure. We have been together quite a good deal. They have given me little supper parties, men only, with drinking &amp;c. Of course we have great times. I have been several times to the Opera &amp; to French theatre. The opera here, Maretzek's troupe,<ptr target="nyp.00185_n5"/> is very fine. Medori, soprano, is pretty near perfection&#8212;Mazzoleni, tenor, ditto&#8212;Biachi, base, ditto. Miss Kellogg is also good. The pieces were Lucrezia, Sonnambula, &amp;c.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n6"/>
            </p>
            <p>Nelly, I have seen Charles Howells.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n7"/> He is well&#8212;apparently indeed better than he was in Washington (in health I mean). I have been at the place, 15 Charles street. In the parlor is hung up a large blue placard "Headquarters of the Pantarchy" in white letters. I did not stop to dinner, although I was prest hard. I saw a man named Newbold.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n8"/> Charles Howells is cheerful. We had quite a walk. He told me he was doing well in a business point of view, had made more while in New York than his salary would have been in Idaho. I did not see Mr nor Mrs Andrews.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n9"/> I did not make any demonstration upon Charles, except what was probably significant enough during the course of his flourishing &amp; somewhat elaborated statement of the Pantarchian scheme which I listened to in dead silence, broken only by one or two running questions of a very brief &amp; dry character. Charles was full of friendship &amp; our interview was one in which he imprest me more agreeably than ever before. Surely he is a good man. The impression I received (maybe casual) is that he is partially absorbed there, his own yearning &amp; eager nature supplying the fuel of the flame, but that he is really shrewd at bottom, &amp; may prove more able to pick his way through the humbugs of the world than we were thinking.</p>
            <p>Nelly, I have seen Mrs Price, but not to have much true &amp; friendly talk, as there were many present. She is much <hi rend="italic">less</hi> well than I expected&#8212;has a hacking cough. She preserves the same quiet cheerful way&#8212;&amp; her daughters&#8212;dear girls&#8212;<hi rend="italic">they are all friends</hi>, to prize &amp; love deeply.</p>
            <p>Nelly, if you go down to Armory Square&#8212;or if Mrs Howells should, (&amp; if you feel well, &amp; like going, I much wish you would very soon) please find if Pleasant Borley<ptr target="nyp.00185_n10"/> is living, he is in bed 40 in Ward A&#8212;tell him I am coming back soon, (or tell Miss Gregg,<ptr target="nyp.00185_n11"/> for him)&#8212;Also see James S Stilwell<ptr target="nyp.00185_n12"/> in Ward C, &amp; Thomas Carson<ptr target="nyp.00185_n13"/> in same ward&#8212;also Lewis K Brown<ptr target="nyp.00185_n14"/> in Ward K, (I have sent him a long letter)&#8212;also Oscar Cunningham<ptr target="nyp.00185_n15"/> in Ward K&#8212;also tell Mrs Doolittle<ptr target="nyp.00185_n16"/> in Ward B, I want to see the boys there. I shall probably stay five or six days longer. I count on our all being together again. My head &amp; hearing &amp;c. are better yesterday &amp; to-day than for two weeks&#8212;sometimes have been rather disagreeable. Well, Nelly, I will now bid you good bye for present, my truly dear friend, &amp; good bye to the rest, &amp; God bless you all.<ptr target="nyp.00185_n17"/>
            </p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
