<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00130">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman   to Walter Whitman, Sr. and Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 18(?)-28 February 1848</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00130</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
                  <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                  <title xml:id="dbw">Dear Brother Walt: The Letters of Thomas Jefferson Whitman</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kent, Ohio</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Kent State University Press</publisher>
                     <date>1984</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">3-4</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman   to Walter Whitman, Sr. and Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 18(?)-28 February 1848</title>
               <date when="1864-02-18">February 18(?)-28, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walter Sr.">Walter Whitman, Sr.</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-02">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
               <opener>
                  <dateline rend="right">
                     <name type="place">[New Orleans,</name>
                     <date when="1848-02-18">February 18(?)-28, 1848]<ptr target="nyp.00130_n100"/>
               </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>[Dear Parents,]</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>...<ptr target="nyp.00130_n2"/> Our captain though[t] he would run the risk and save the time (it takes some time longer to go through the canal) so he got a flat-boat and took out some of the freight, and we started to go over the falls.<ptr target="nyp.00130_n3"/> Father can judge how fast we went, when I tell him it is a fall of twenty feet, within a space of three miles. And what is most dangerous, the bottom is covered with very large rock which leave a very small channel for the boat. When you get about the middle there is a large rock in this channel, and one on each side of it, the one on the right side is a little distance from the one in the middle, just room enough for a boat to pass through. So you have to take a very sudden turn, or the boat is smashed all to peices. It happened we got off with a little bump on each rock, we should not have got that (for we had the best pilots that could be found) but one wheel would not work. The fun of the whole thing was, the <hi rend="italic">fright</hi> we all had, some of the passengers went to bed, others walked the cabin floor, looking as gloomy as if they were going to be hung. Altho I was frightened a good deal, it was not so much as some of the <hi rend="italic">men</hi> were. If the boat had sunk we were within a few feet of the shore, but I dont think we could have got there, the current was so swift.</p>
               <p>Mother, you have no idea of the splendor and the comfort of these western river steam-boats. The cabin is on the deck, and state rooms on each side of it, their are two beds in each room. The greatest of all these splendors is the eating (you know I always did love eating) department. Every thing you would find in the Astor house in New York, You find on these boats.</p>
               <p>I will give you a little description of the way we live on board. For breakfast we have: coffee, tea, ham and eggs, beef steak, sausages hot cakes, with plenty of good bread sugar &amp;c &amp;c. For dinner: roast beef d[itt]o mutton d[itt]o veal boiled ham roast turkey d[itt]o goose with pie and puddings and for supper every thing that is good to eat.<ptr target="nyp.00130_n4"/>...</p>
               <p>Saturday noon  Last night we had a very hard storm, it rained hard and blew harder. We expect to get as far as Cairo to night on the Mississipi river. Nothing has occurred since yesterday of importance</p>
               <p>Sunday night. We have arrived at last, at New Orleans we came in on Friday night about ten o'clock. Saturday  Walter found a board in Poydrass st cor St Charles</p>
               <p>You must dirrect your letters thus, Walter Whitman, New Orleans, La. Saturday it was a drizzely rainy day.</p>
               <p>I hope[e] they dont have many of them</p>
               <p>Monday. Yesterday was quite warm. I saw a good many peach trees in blossom to day. Walter will get the first number of his out on Sunday next.</p>
               <p>Dear Mother I must bid you good bye for a little while. I will write to you again pretty soon.</p>
               <p>Dear Father I will write to you also pretty soon  until then good bye one and all</p>
               <closer rend="right">
                  <signed>Jefferson Whitman</signed>
               </closer>
            
            <postscript>
               <p>Dear Mother, write often</p>
            </postscript>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
