<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00175">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Herman Storms to Walt Whitman, 11 January 1865</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Herman Storms</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00175</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">196</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Herman Storms</author>
               <title>Herman Storms to Walt Whitman, 11 January 1865</title>
               <date when="1865-01-11">January 11, 1865</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Storms, Herman">Herman Storms</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2010-04-01">proofread</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-31">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-12">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-18">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear friend Walter</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>it is with the greatest of pleasure that I<ptr target="nyp.00175_n100"/> sit down to write to you in answer to the letter you sent me as it is some time since I heard from you, I am happy to inform you we are all well at present and sincerely hope this will find you the same  young Walt Whitman is well and hearty out of doors almost all day long rideing down Hill with his little sled he will be 7 years old if he lives till spring  he is much pleased with the Card you sent him he chose the dark one it is a good one your boy is smart to learn he has never been to school as the school is about 2 miles off but he can read right smart.</p>
            <p>my Father &amp; Mother are smart considering their age they are still keeping House.
George has been out here since last May he is stout he has done considerable work for me and we have had some nice rides going to the Political meetings last fall and we have elected our Man and I hope and pray he will with Gods help settle this trouble before long<ptr target="nyp.00175_n2"/>.</p>
            <p>Walter I am sorry to inform you that I never got the paper you sent me and I think you better come out here yourself and give us the particulars yourself we would be very happy to see you, we all send our best respects to you and all your friends.</p>
            <p>you will see my pen and ink are both poor and myself a poor writer&#8212;so I will close by wishing you a happy New Year from your true friend</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
