<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00138">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas P. Sawyer to Walt Whitman, 26 April 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas P. Sawyer</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00138</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cl">Calamus Lovers: Walt Whitman's Working-Class Camerados</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1987</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">74&#8211;75</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas P. Sawyer</author>
               <title>Thomas P. Sawyer to Walt Whitman, 26 April 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-04-26">April 26, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Sawyer, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Sawyer</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-08-31">proofed and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline> </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>As you have given me permission I<ptr target="nyp.00138_n100"/> have taken the liberty to address you as above, and I assure you I fully reciprocate your friendship as expressed in your letter and it will afford me great pleasure to meet you after the war will have terminated or sooner if circumstances will permit.</p>
            <p>I am much pleased that Lewy<ptr target="nyp.00138_n2"/> is so cheerful and happy, and I trust he will be successful in his hopes and desires and be prosperous and happy and enjoy life to a good old age. I am sorry very sorry that Hiram has not improved.<ptr target="nyp.00138_n3"/> I was in hopes that ere this he would be sufficiently recovered to go Home and I sincerly hope that it will not be long until he can do so. It is [my] sincere wish that Johny Makey<ptr target="nyp.00138_n4"/> will survive the operation and ultimately recover. I hope you will be more fortunate and procure a good berth, and be ever prosperous. We in the Army feel our reserves at Charleston and Vicksburg very deeply as yet we have not had a chance to strike a blow in our vicinity but as you say that time is near at hand and I hope we will be successful at any rate we will do out utmost and endeavor to give the Rebels the biggest thrashing they have yet received. Let the Government Officials in Washington mind their own biz. let Hooker<ptr target="nyp.00138_n5"/> alone and the Army of the Potomac will be triuimphant but as long as they will continue to interfere with our Gen[era]ls arrangements, dictate to him when he shall move, and when he shall halt, just so long will the Army of the Potomac be of little avail. It is composed of good material, and all ready for a forward movement. then let Hooker have the reins, and he will soon drive the Rebs to Richmond and far beyond it.</p>
            <p>Yes my dear Brother, You have my friendship as fully as you can desire, and I hope we will meet again.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Having nothing more of importance to communicate, I will conclude with my best wishes for your health and happiness and believe me to be</salute>
               <salute>Yours sincerly,</salute>
               <signed>Thos P. Sawyer</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
