<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00139">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Justus F. Boyd to Walt Whitman, 14 May 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Justus F. Boyd</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00139</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">112&#8211;113</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Justus F. Boyd</author>
               <title>Justus F. Boyd to Walt Whitman, 14 May 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-05-14">May 14, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Boyd, Justus F.">Justus F. Boyd</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-08-21">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline rend="right"> </dateline>
               <salute>Mr. Whitman Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Here I<ptr target="nyp.00139_n100"/> am seated at the desk pen in hand once more writing a few lines to you. I guess I dont write so you can read it or else I direct wrong or else you do. there is something the matter anyway for I have written this makes four letters and I have sent word to you once by Fred Euler  But I havent re'cd a line from you since I got home  I am going to send this one and if I dont receive an Ans in about a week I shall write one more &amp; direct to Brooklin N.Y. but I shall look for one this time sure. I am in a store yet I dont know how long I shall stay I havnt made any bargain&#8212;yet how long I shall stay. I may not stay more than a week and I may stay all summer</p>
            <p>I am not able to work on the farm yet and I dont know as I shall ever be able  I am still takeing medison  I am getting about sick of living on medison all the time but I suppose I must if I live at all but enough of this  I would like to take a walk down Pennsylvania Avenue this pleasant afternoon  we would have a good time if there was any such thing and I guess there is I would like to be back in Washington now   (I dont mean in the Hospital) though I got all of that I want for much as six months but there is no use wishing I suppos for it wont do me any good to wish I shall have to close for there has some customers just come in  Now please write as soon as you receive this In[stan]t</p>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
