<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00160">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Rodney R. Worster to Walt Whitman, 28 March 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Rodney R. Worster</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00160</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">229&#8211;230</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Rodney R. Worster</author>
               <title>Rodney R. Worster to Walt Whitman, 28 March 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-03-28">March 28, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Worster, Rodney R.">Rodney R. Worster</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-04">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2009-08-31">updated annotations according to new correspondence sytlesheet guidelines</change>
         <change who="#jc" when="2009-08-31">deleted empty notes from encoding; Worster does not appear in the annotations database as of yet</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-14">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Friend Walt</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>You may be somewhat surprised to hear from me but I<ptr target="nyp.00160_n100"/> have not forgotten you although you have lost sight of me  I am one of Uncle Sams Boys going the whole Hog for Union &amp; The Constitution as it was. I belong to the 133rd NY V[olunteer]s &amp; Bully Boys are we  we have seen some service where Rebel shot &amp; shell flew some at the Battle of Bisland we bore our part &amp; I believe acquired ourselves manfully some of our brave fellows fell there. we were also at the siege &amp; capture of Port Hudson where our Col was wounded &amp; many of our men were killed in fact it would take me to long &amp; ocupy to much space this time to tell you one half the places or the adventures we have passed through since we left Gotham suffice it to say that we are at present doing garison Duty here Bonet Carra is situated on the banks of the Missisippi about 35 miles above New Orleans our Dutys are light barely enough for healthy exercise the camp right on the bank of the River, the air pure &amp; wholesome. I dont know that there are any here with whom you are personally acquainted we are A compound mixture of all sorts Stage Drivers Policemen Hotel &amp; Steam Boat runners Old Sports in hard luck Dry goods Clerks &amp; Broken Down merchants all mixed together &amp; on the most friendly terms with each other we have all sorts of sports Ball play being the favorite we are havin A jimnasium built in which we may break our necks if we like on the whole we pass the
time pleasantly enough with now &amp; then A twinge of Home sickness but it all comes in the Prrogramme &amp; we take it as it comes I am &amp; have been with slight exceptions in good Health plenty to eat comfortable clothing what more need I ask but I am tired of the war &amp; wish it was over but I fear that I shall tire your patience will close by subscribing vour sincere Friend</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Rodney R. Worster Co C 133rd Reg. NY VS New Orleans or else where Please direct as above</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
