<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00181">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Thomas P. Sawyer, 26 April 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00181</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                  <editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                  <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                     <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961&#8211;1977</date>
                     <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="page">93&#8211;94</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Walt Whitman</author>
               <title>Walt Whitman to Thomas P. Sawyer, 26 April 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-04-26">April 26, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection, New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Sawyer, Thomas P.">Thomas P. Sawyer</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-08-31">proofread and edited</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-09-16">added main TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-30">added TEI header structure w/o IDs and titles; added minimal TEI markup</change>
         <change who="#ao" when="2008-07-29">pulled transcription from Primary Source Media</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
        
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear comrade,<ptr target="nyp.00181_n100"/>
            </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have not heard from you for some time, Lewy Brown has received two letters from you, &amp; Walter<ptr target="nyp.00181_n3"/> in Ward E has received one three weeks ago. I wrote you a letter about a week ago, which I hope you have received. I was sorry you did not come up to my room to get the shirt &amp; other things you promised to accept from me and take when you went away. I got them all ready, a good strong blue shirt, a pair of drawers &amp; socks, and it would have been a satisfaction to me if you had accepted them. I should have often thought now Tom may be wearing around his body something from <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, &amp; that it might contribute to your comfort, down there in camp on picket, or sleeping in your tent.</p>
            <p>Lewy Brown and Hiram are about the same. I saw Lewy &amp; sat with him last evening. I go to see him almost every evening. He sets up a little in the chair, during the middle of the day&#8212;his foot is doing pretty well. There is quite a time at Armory about Dr. Bliss<ptr target="nyp.00181_n4"/>&#8212;some say he is under arrest for defrauding the government. There is a new surgeon in charge&#8212;I have not seen him. In Ward K there is a new surgeon, Dr. Rose.<ptr target="nyp.00181_n5"/> There is quite a change, with men &amp; doctors, going and coming.</p>
            <p>Well, Tom, how did you stand the gay old rain storm of Thursday &amp; Friday last?<ptr target="nyp.00181_n6"/> It rained here enough to wet hell itself, and swamp the fires. But yesterday &amp; to-day here have been fine. The talk here previously was all about Hooker's advance&#8212;we expected a big fight, on the jump&#8212;but of course the storm has laid an injunction on that for some days.</p>
            <p>Yet I suppose Hooker must move soon, &amp; that there will be fighting and lots of marches and skirmishes, &amp;c before the summer is through. O my dear comrade &amp; brother, I hope it will prove your good luck to come safe through all the engagements &amp; marches of this war, &amp; that we shall meet again, not to part. I hope this letter will find you in good health &amp; spirits.</p>
            <p>Tom, I will not write a long yarn at present. I guess I have not made out much of a letter, anyhow at present, but I will let it go, whatever it is, hoping it may please you, coming from old wooly-neck, who loves you. You must let that make up for all deficiencies now and to come. Not a day passes, nor a night but I think of you. Now, my dearest comrade, I will bid you <hi rend="italic">so long</hi>, &amp; hope God will put it in your heart to bear toward me a little at least of the feeling I have about you. If it is only a quarter as much I shall be satisfied.</p>
            <p>Your faithful friend &amp; brother,</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Walt</signed>
            </closer>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>Tom, it is now about 9 o'clock, a fine moonlight night. I am going to close this up, and then scud out for a walk to the post office. Good by again, &amp; God bless you, dear brother.</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
