<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00224">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">William E. Babcock to Walt Whitman, 25 December 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>William E. Babcock</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
               
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>nyp.00226</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>William E. Babcock</author>
               <title>William E. Babcock to Walt Whitman, 25 December 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-12-25">December 25, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="nyp">Berg Collection at the New York Public Library</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Babcock, William E.">William E. Babcock</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-13">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#jw" when="2009-09-10">Transcription revision</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb facs="nyp.00226.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
         
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <name type="place">Camp 51st N.YVV <lb/>Near Petersburg Va</name>
               <date when="1864-12-24">December 15th 1864</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Friend Walt,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Your kind letter came to hand in due time.<ptr target="nyp.00226_n100"/> And as this is Christmas night and I alone in my Shanty will improve it in writing You althouth there is not much new to write Yet I will make the Endeavor. I have been away all day as this is a day that all Niggers Should be free. and haveing an invitiation out to Eat roast Turkey of course excepted it and had a verry nice time yet I think had I been in <pb facs="nyp.00226.002.jpg" type="verso"/>New York or Brooklyn that I would enjoyed My-Self much better and Shall be glad to get back there once more as a citizen for to go there on a leave of absence is only an agrivation as the time is always So Short that one cannot heardly turn before he has to come back</p>
         <p>I Suppose that you have heard that we have a new Colonel Commissioned in our regt. who is none other than Capt. McKiben Bronets Brig. Genl. And I heard that there had been a Commisson issued as Lt. Col. to Some out Sider, I don't know how true it is, Yet I think it is a Shame to run over all of our Officers that are now Priosners of War <pb facs="nyp.00226.003.jpg" type="recto"/> Who have Served and fought in the regiment Since the Orginization and for my part I Shall resign if what I hear is true. So You need not be Surprised if You hear that Your humble Servant has put in his Unconditional Surrender, and retires to Private life</p>
         <p>We have Sent Your Brother Georges large Trunk home to Your Mothers Address by Express So if you have not already received it You Can look out for it</p>
         <p>Hopeing to hear from you Soon</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I remain</salute>
            <salute>Yours &amp;c</salute>
            <signed>WE Babcock <lb/>1st Lieut Comdr Co<gap reason="illegible"/> 
               <lb/>51st NYV</signed>
         </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
