<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="owu.00002">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Martha Whitman to Walt Whitman, 21&#8211;23 December
                    1863</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Martha Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                        Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>owu.00002</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Martha Whitman</author>
                    <title>Martha Whitman to Walt Whitman, 21&#8211;23 December 1863</title>
                    <date cert="high" notBefore="1863-12-21" notAfter="1863-12-23" xml:id="dat1">December 21&#8211;23, 1863</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="owu">The Bayley-Whitman Collection, Ohio Wesleyan University,
                        Delaware, OH</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Martha">Martha Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient" xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-01-28" who="#kmp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2015-01-22" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-01-15" who="#ak">added annotations</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2010-12-17" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-05" who="#vs">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="owu.00002.001.jpg" type="recto"/>


            <note type="editorial" place="left" resp="#ww">Sister Matty</note>

            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">      
                    <date when="1863-12-21">Monday Dec 21/63</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Brother Walt</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have just received a letter from you<ptr target="owu.00002_n2"/> and as I am rocking the baby<ptr target="owu.00002_n3"/> I thought I would
                answer it but you will <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nhg">have
                    to take</unclear> it written with pencil I feel a little annoyed that Jeff
                should have written you about Jess although it was an <choice><orig>aweful</orig><reg>awful</reg></choice> scene and I do not want
                to witness another for I must say I never was so frightened in my life I cannot
                write you the particulars it would take so long he commenced at Hattie because she
                pushed a chair it was not what she done for he wanted a chance all day to have a
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#el">muss</unclear> with
                    some one he
                flew at Hattie uttering a terrible oath I protected her and told him to let her
                alone she had done no harm then he said 'I would not hurt the child no indeed but
                you D_ old B_ you have been picking at me all day and I will soon put an end to you
                he flew right <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="owu.00002.002.jpg" type="verso"/> towards
                me he looked just like a madman and what he would have done if your mother had not
                interfered the Lord only knows I still thought I would not let him see I was <choice>
                    <orig>affraid</orig>
                    <reg>afraid</reg>
                </choice> and I told him he better try it if he dare to when he flew at me again and
                said he did not mean to hurt me but now he Be D_ if he would'nt knock my brains out
                such a D_ fool as I was hadn't right to live I managed to get out of the basement<ptr target="owu.00002_n4"/>
                but it was a long time before I could get up stairs when Jeff came home I told him
                about it and he was very much excited and was going downstairs but I <choice>
                    <orig>beged</orig>
                    <reg>begged</reg>
                </choice> of him to stay you know Dear Brother how Impulsive Jeff is but come to the
                point I dont think Jeff would do a rash act any quicker than I or you would he is <choice>
                    <orig>naturrally</orig>
                    <reg>naturally</reg>
                </choice> so good and kind my back <choice><orig>achued</orig><reg>ached</reg></choice> two or three days and it made Jeff very
                angry I do not have Jess up in my room any more he has not rocked the baby since
                that Friday<ptr target="owu.00002_n5"/> he is very ugly and irritable he sleeps till late every afternoon Mother
                feels very bad that I wont have him up stairs because it deprives her the pleasure of
                spending most of her time with me and especially her evenings<ptr target="owu.00002_n6"/> but <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="owu.00002.003.jpg" type="recto"/> he has such ugly
                spells that I am <choice><orig>affraid</orig><reg>afraid</reg></choice> of him last week he got angry at Hattie twice and made
                terrible threats and this conduct is nothing new only he used to confine it to your
                mother I have often seen him take up a chair to throw at her but we must submit to
                it and try to bear with him I think sometimes it is very hard for mother to have so
                much trouble she feels it more now than ever before but I can never consent to have
                him in my room again I think Poor Dear Andrews death has shocked him very much<ptr target="owu.00002_n7"/> I
                think just as much of him now as I ever did but he has taken such a dislike to
                Hattie that I am <choice>
                    <orig>affraid</orig>
                    <reg>afraid</reg>
                </choice> to have him up stairs he sometimes says if he could be where there was no
                young ones he would get his senses but you must not think any thing of what Jeff
                said about shooting him for you must know he wouldn't do any thing of the kind</p>

            <p>Well Dear Brother I dont know as there is any news to write about we are here about
                the same as when you left<ptr target="owu.00002_n8"/> only we miss Andrew coming around every day Jimmy has been
                very sick he has had the Gastric fever but is better now, when I think about Andrews
                family it makes <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="owu.00002.004.jpg" type="verso"/> me
                feel very bad they are so utterly <choice>
                    <orig>distitute</orig>
                    <reg>destitute</reg>
                </choice> Mother sent them 50 cts last Thursday and afterwards I thought I would go <choice>
                    <orig>arround</orig>
                    <reg>around</reg>
                </choice> and see Jimmy I took him a chicken he said he thought he would get well
                now, he liked chicken I asked Nancy if she had things to eat she said yes I knew by
                her manner it was not so and come to question her she had nothing but a crust of
                bread I gave her a Dollar it was all the money I had and I sent her <choice>
                    <orig>arround</orig>
                    <reg>around</reg>
                </choice> a large basket of Provisions when Jeff came home I told him about it he
                went <choice>
                    <orig>arround</orig>
                    <reg>around</reg>
                </choice> to see Nancy intending to give her some money but Milgate<ptr target="owu.00002_n9"/> had just been
                there and gave her &#36;30.00&#8212;he raffled off Andrews tools at 25 cts a chance
                it came in first rate and this morning Cornell<ptr target="owu.00002_n10"/> sent for Nancy and told her he would
                buy her a sewing Machine but she will never make out much as she is in the street
                most all day I feel very sorry for her her case is <choice>
                    <orig>aweful</orig>
                    <reg>awful</reg>
                </choice> she is going to have another child<ptr target="owu.00002_n11"/> and it seems as if the creature cant do
                much but it seems as if the Lord always provides for the Widow and I feel confident
                that He will provide for her Mr Rodgers lost his wife very suddenly last week you
                know him he lives in this street and Jenny Ward<ptr target="owu.00002_n13"/> has lost her husband he died to his
                fathers went over there to see his doctor last Friday week and died the following
                Monday Jenny was here the night he died she said she expected him over the next day
                you know he has been sick a long time he was found dead in his chair. We are very  
                lonesome here Jeff has gone away again he is now at Albany<ptr target="owu.00002_n14"/> I expect him home Friday
                Dear Brother I commenced this letter Monday and I am finishing it today Wednesday
                Mother has just received a letter from you and she said she could not put Jess in
                the Asylum that it would be time enough when she was dead that she could not stand
                it to see <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#el">him</unclear> go he
                does not seem any worse than he has been and <choice><orig>untill</orig><reg>until</reg></choice> matters get worse I dont think
                you could <choice><orig>pursuade</orig><reg>persuade</reg></choice> her to send him Well Dear Brother you see I am rather crowding
                things on this page and I shall have to stop I have been trying to plan some way to
                send you a mince pie I made 17 large <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#nhg" cert="low">ones</unclear> and they are splendid
                if you could get a pass I think it would pay to come home and I will make you some
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> cakes just think about it I sometimes wonder if we
                will ever live together again and have George home going to work every day like he
                used to Wouldn't it be pleasant now I think I have told you all the news but I must
                not finish without saying something about my two little darlings Hattie is about as
                mischievous as ever a great deal of company for me now Jeff is away she is better
                than when you was home and little California I think is just about cunning enough she is
                fatter than ever and when I think about them both I flatter myself that I have got
                about the nicest prettiest little creatures that can be found any where. Now Dear
                Brother I will close and if you will write me again I will answer.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Your affectionate
                    sister</salute>
                <signed>Mattie</signed>
            </closer>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
