<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="pri.00013">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William D. Rossetti, 3
                    December 1867</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>pri.00013</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth
                    Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author><editor>Edwin Haviland Miller</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Correspondence</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>New York University Press</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1961" notAfter="1977">1961–1977</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">352–354</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to William D. Rossetti, 3 December 1867</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1867-12-03" xml:id="dat1">December 3, 1867</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="prc">Manuscripts Division, Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, Princeton University Library </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Rossetti, William M.">William M. Rossetti</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-02" who="#al">Made Ken's changes</change>
            <change when="2010-12-17" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-06" who="#zk">encoded</change>
            <change when="2010-08-20" who="#ec">extracted transcription from Major Authors
                cd</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington</name>, <date when="1867-12-03" rend="right">December 3, 1867</date>. </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Mr. Rossetti:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have just received, &amp; have considered your letter of November 17. In order that
                there be the frankest understanding with respect to my position, I hasten to write
                you that the authorization in my letter of November 1st to Mr. Conway, for you, to
                make verbal alterations, substitute words, &amp;c. was meant to be construed as an
                answer to the case presented in Mr. Conway's letter of October 12.<ptr target="pri.00013_n1"/> Mr. Conway stated the case of a volume of selections in which it had been
                decided that the poems reprinted in London should appear verbatim, &amp; asking my
                authority to change certain words in the Preface to first edition of poems,
                    &amp;c.<ptr target="pri.00013_n2"/>
            </p>

            <p>I will be candid with you, &amp; say I had not the slightest idea of applying my
                authorization to a reprint of the full volume of my poems. As such a volume was not
                proposed, &amp; as your courteous &amp; honorable course &amp; attitude called &amp;
                call for no niggardly or hesitating response from me, I penned that authorization,
                &amp; did not feel to set limits to it. But abstractly &amp; standing alone, &amp;
                not read in connection with Mr. C's letter of October 12, I see now it is far too
                loose, &amp; needs distinct guarding.</p>

            <p>I cannot &amp; will not consent of my own volition, to countenance an expurgated
                edition of my pieces. I have steadily refused to do so under seductive offers, here
                in my own country, &amp; must not do so in another country.</p>

            <p>I feel it due to myself to write you explicitly thus, my dear Mr. Rossetti, though it
                may seem harsh &amp; perhaps ungenerous. Yet I rely on you to absolve me, sooner or
                later. Could you see Mr. Conway's letter of October 12, you would, I think, more
                fully comprehend the integrity of my explanation.</p>

            <p>I have to add that the points made in that letter in relation to the proposed
                reprint, as originally designed, exactly correspond with those, on the same subject,
                in your own late letter—&amp; that the kind &amp; appreciative tone of both
                letters is in the highest degree gratifying, &amp; is most cordially &amp;
                affectionately responded to by me—&amp; that the fault of sending so loose an
                authorization has surely been, to a large degree, my own.</p>

            <p>And now, my friend, having set myself right on that matter, I proceed to say, on the
                other hand, for you, &amp; for Mr. Hotten, that if, before the arrival of this
                letter, you have practically invested in, &amp; accomplished, or partially
                accomplished, any plan, even contrary to this letter, I do not expect you to abandon
                it, at loss of outlay, &amp;c. but shall <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> consider
                you blameless if you let it go on, &amp; be carried out, as you may have arranged.
                It is the question of the authorization of an expurgated edition proceeding from me,
                that deepest engages me. The facts of the different ways, one way or another way, in
                which the book may appear in England, out of influences not under the shelter of my
                umbrage, are of much less importance to me. After making the foregoing explanation,
                I shall, I think, accept kindly whatever happens. For I feel, indeed know, that I am
                in the hands of a friend, &amp; that my pieces will receive that truest, brightest
                of light &amp; perception coming from love. In that, all other &amp; lesser
                requisites become pale.</p>

            <p>It would be better, in any Introduction, to make no allusion to me, as authorizing,
                or not prohibiting, &amp;c.</p>

            <p>The whole affair is somewhat mixed—&amp; I write offhand<ptr target="pri.00013_n3"/> to catch to-morrow's New York steamer. But I guess you will
                pick out my meaning. Perhaps, indeed, Mr. Hotten has preferred to go on after the
                original plan—which, if so, saves all trouble.</p>

            <p>I have to add that I only wish you could know how deeply the beautiful personal tone
                &amp; passages of your letter of November 17, have penetrated and touched me.<ptr target="pri.00013_n4"/>
                It is such things that go to our hearts, and reward us, &amp; make up for all else,
                for years. Permit me to offer you my friendship.</p>

            <p>I sent you hence Nov. 23d<ptr target="pri.00013_n5"/> a
                letter, through Mr. Conway. Also a copy of Mr. Burroughs's <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, Mr. O'Connor's pamphlet, &amp; some papers containing criticisms on
                    <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. Also, later, a prose article of mine
                named <hi rend="italic">Democracy</hi>, in a magazine.</p>

            <p>Let me know how the work goes on, what shape it takes, &amp;c. Finally I charge you
                to construe all I have written, through my declared &amp; fervid realization of your
                goodness toward me, nobleness of intention, &amp;, I am fain to hope, personal, as,
                surely, literary &amp; moral sympathy &amp; attachment. And so, for the present,
                Farewell.</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>