<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00012">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">T. F. Macdonald to Walt Whitman, 17 November
                    1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>T. F. Macdonald</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="am">Alicia Meyer</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00012</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>T.F. Macdonald</author>
                    <title>T.F. Macdonald to Walt Whitman, 17 November 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-11-17" xml:id="dat1">November 17, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Macdonald, T. F.">T. F. Macdonald</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-07-31" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-03-06" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2014-01-21" who="#ss">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-11-26" who="#am">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00025_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes Jul 21 1889</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">S.S. "Anchoria" <lb/>Anchor Line <lb/>New York</name>
                    <date when="1883-11-17"><choice>
                            <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                            <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>./<choice><abbr>83</abbr>
                            <expan>1883</expan>
                        </choice></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Poet,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have been home and back again since I called upon you in Philadelphia last month. I
                often think of you and wish I could stay near you, that I might see and speak to you
                sometimes, however, I often read your poems and as Shelley has said, "Poetry is the
                record of the greatest happiest moments, of our greatest and best minds." Therefore
                in reading your book I feel that I have that which is greatest in you, but the heart

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr_kc.00026_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            will often rebel against the most logical conclusion, and thus with me I would like
                to be near you sometimes. I have only one other friend who has the same power over
                me, and that is he of whom I told you in Halifax. I was rather amused (when I told
                some of my friends at home that I had seen you), at the ideas they seemed to have of
                my object in calling on you. Some thought it was simply because you were a great
                man, and they gave me addresses of several well known men in Literature &amp;c.
                however, I told them

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_kc.00027_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

            these other men were not Walt Whitman and that the only others I would have crossed
                the Atlantic to see would have been <hi rend="underline">Emerson</hi> and <hi
                    rend="underline">Thoreau</hi> both of whom are very dear to me.</p>
            <p>You may have forgotten all about me: indeed it would be surprising to find it
                otherwise; but it was not that you should know me, that I came, no&#8212;I both <hi
                    rend="underline">knew &amp; loved</hi> you before, but I wanted to see &amp;
                speak to you. It might have been my friend as well as myself who called but I had
                the opportunity.</p>
            <p>I send you a book, that a friend in Glasgow, who is greatly taken with your "Leaves
                of Grass" asked me to send to you or take. I cannot very well leave my ship just
                now so I post it to you, he would have liked to have sent a more valuable

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="syr_kc.00028_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            book but he cannot afford it. I thought it very kind of him, I know he is a dear
                soft hearted fellow, and a splendid critic of English Literature. I will be here for
                8 days, and I would like very much to know if you are well.</p>
            <p>I am glad to be able to tell you that your number of readers in Scotland is
                greatly increased. They are beginning to understand your teaching much better</p>
            <p>I heard that Swinbourne
                ranks you third of living men. <hi rend="underline">Victor Hugo</hi> I know is his
                great hero.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Wish best wishes</salute>
                <salute>Yours affectionately,</salute>
                <signed>T. F. Macdonald</signed>
                <signed>(Surgeon S.S. Anchoria)</signed>
                <salute>Walt Whitman</salute>
                <salute>Philadelphia</salute>
            </closer>
         
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
