<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00019">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Allen Upward to Walt Whitman, 12 March 1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Allen Upward</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00019</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Allen Upward</author>
                    <title>Allen Upward to Walt Whitman, 12 March 1884</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1884-03-12" xml:id="dat1">March 12, 1884</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Upward, Allen" ref="n4996">Allen Upward</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-02-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-02-07" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2015-01-25" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-01-14" who="#ak">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00057_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <salute>O Walt!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Take this Calamus leaf at the hands of him thou hast sought for.<ptr target="syr.00019_n1"/></p>
            <p>Lo! I am he.</p>
            <p> What shall I say, or how shall I utter the radiant feelings that gush from my heart
                at the magical words thou hast sung to the unknown? like as the waters at Moses
                command gushed out form the rock in the desert. </p>
            <p> Long had I wandered alone in the earth nor met with a friend or a lover. And wonder
                not that my tongue now stutters and falters, for never before have I been allowed to
                express my love to a living soul. And none can comprehend the extent of my ecstasy who
                hath not passed like Dante from hell to the light.</p>
            <p>'Twas at midnight and we lay alone (remember thy words) when first we met, and O the
                flush of <choice><abbr>o'erwhelming</abbr><expan>overwhelming</expan></choice> joy that shot through my heart and set my pulses throbbing
                with a wild exaltation that hath not faded away.</p>
            <p> I need not demand thy love, for that has been given. I have embraced thee and thou
                hast returned my embrace. Utterly thine am I and thou art mine own, and no one in
                all the world is like to us twain. Nor need I repeat again what thou hast depicted,
                nor add my silver words to thine of redeemed gold.</p>
            <p> O thou hast not written in vain! Well didst thou know an echo would somewhere be
                found, fearing only (didst thou not fear?) that it would not reach thine ears in the
                day of thy sojourn here. </p>
            <p> But now thou wantest myself. Then listen, brother &amp; lover. Let me unroll the
                extensive panorama of my own personality. </p>
            <p> 1. </p>
            <p> First for the account of its growth up till now (for it has not and never will have
                done growing): At 14 I was a freethinker, at 15 a Buddhist, at 16 a Mohammedan, at
                17 a follower of Carlyle,<ptr target="n0139"/> at 18 a Darwinian,<ptr target="n3075"
                /> at 19 a sceptic and almost materialist, at 20 a human universalist: these are
                but rough landmarks. I have been an atheist and a pantheist. I have been a Stoic and
                an Epicurean, a follower of Plato, and of Diogenes. I have been an admirer of the
                man Jesus and of the Struggle for Existence, an idealist and a materialist, a
                misanthrope and a philanthropist. I have been a Liberal and a Radical, a Socialist
                and an Anarchist. And I am still all these and much moreover. </p>
            <p> I glory in my mutability and my vast receptivity; I glory in having no unalterable
                opinions. I glory in my invincible supremacy over prejudice, my superb contempt for
                custom. Finality is the only thing that is impossible to me. The only idea I fight
                against is the idea of fixed principles: against the possession of such I revolt and
                stand on my guard, for I know that, as necessary as is its perfect poise to the
                magnet, unswerving endeavor coupled with inexhaustible liberty is the only price of
                Truth. </p>
            <p> I have pondered on Life &amp; Death &amp; the Universe more than anyone else that is
                alive: but now I am no more troubled about them. If I am to be immortal, it does
                not trouble me; and if I am to be annihilated, that does not trouble me. For I have
                so diminished the separateness of my identity that I have already partly <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr_kc.00058_large.jpg" type="verso"/> ceased to exist,
                and I have so transfused my essence with the Universe round me that while it lasts I
                cannot be altogether annihilated. </p>
            <p> I have accepted the Universe. Wherefore it has come to pass that I am as Godlike as
                God is, for God cannot cause anything to happen that I have not agreed to and willed
                beforehand. </p>
            <p> Also, I laugh at the smallness of this little earth; with thumb at the North Pole
                and finger at South Pole I can grasp it and pinch it together. And the solar
                system is absurd in mine eyes, the sun and all his planets are so small. </p>
            <p> (A word is written on externals.) </p>
            <p> Although I am not of thine in birth, yet that may be perhaps be forgiven, for what
                is a country, or what is a world, in the depths of the All? And is even Identity or
                Separation so beautiful as Nothing or Cohesion? And anyway can Sentiment stand in
                the place of Truth? </p>
            <p> Easy to me was thy paradox. I answer it by this riddle of mine own, for thee to
                read: The segment is as circular as the circle, but it is not half so beautiful. </p>
            <p> 2 </p>
            <p> Love alone is my master, to him I succumb and surrender. He is the author of all my
                suffering, but he hath redeemed my soul. (And alas! for the blasphemous scruples of
                prudish harlots, I have not seen the loving entire of thee; only thine English
                presentment reached me last week,&#8212;selected too by a mild, well-meaning soul who
                "admits" thy "boundless self-assertion" a "serious fault."&#8212;For me, who love
                thee, thou canst not assert thyself enough.) </p>
            <p> Love is my lord and king and only god, and yet I know not what it is to be
                loved,&#8212;did not, let me say, till I met thyself. For when I was but fifteen I
                loved in vain, loved with a holy, yearning, obstinate love, loved a being too weak
                for me to reproach. Pardon me that the flesh-wielded pen returns with a sad delight
                to the thought of bygone loves. And O how joyfully now can I look again at the
                sorrowful, sorrowful times I have left behind. </p>
            <p> I assure thee that from that time to the present there has never elapsed one moment
                in which I would not have welcomed death. I assure thee that when I was but
                seventeen I bore poison constantly about with me, meditating the example of
                    Chatterton.<ptr target="syr.00019_n2"/> I assure thee that when Carlyle died I
                almost shed tears, I, who since my childhood have never wept. </p>
            <p> I assure that I wrote letters at midnight to an imaginary friend! To him I said
                thus: "I feel a large fountain of love running waste in my heart, &amp; I want someone to
                partake of it; I thirst for someone to love and to be loved by. And will a merciful
                God let me thirst in vain for ever? Surely not. O my friend, mayst thou never feel
                such heaviness of heart as I sometimes feel." (O wherefore did I not meet thee then?)
                And elsewhere I wrote: "O could our souls together climb above this realm of earthly
                clods and soar aloft like demigods, To watch the travail-throes of Time!" All these
                were meant for thee, and more I need not now extract. </p>
            <p> Hast thou had experience such as I speak of? Hast thou known what it is to live
                unloved? </p>
            <p> With parents whose affection is no boon to me (for without it be accompanied by
                understanding, what is such affection better, after all, than the beast's?), with
                relations not even friendly, without a single lover, or friend, or intimate or
                companion. </p>
            <p> Such is the curse of the Truth-seeker; but the Universe is his reward. </p>
            <p> And I had steeled my heart to desertion, and they that marked me said: "This mortal
                has never loved, a selfish satirical cynic is he, whose heart is only a palpitating
                stone." Yet knew I that somewhere, far in the Universe, there dwelt a spirit in pure
                accord <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_kc.00059_large.jpg" type="recto"/> with mine,
                strong &amp; weak &amp; high &amp; tender &amp; large &amp; true. </p>
            <p> Now dost thou know as much, perhaps more of me than I know of myself, for these
                blunt words to thee will be subtle directions. (And of what account are words except
                for the impression produced? And no words ever yet produced quite the same
                impression on two different personalities.) </p>
            <p> And if thou wouldst enquire of evil qualities and vices, I have all thine evil
                qualities and vices, but I do not acknowledge them to be evil nor vicious. (I have
                expunged the word "SIN" from my writings.) And I take pleasure in what men would
                call my personal defects for I can, standing by as it were an outsider, perceive
                them working together to influence my identity for good. </p>
            <p> And if though wouldst know me, as I write, even to the innermost core, go forth at
                night and gaze for a silent hour into the mighty deeps of the far-off stars. </p>
            <p> 3 </p>
            <p> My soul and heart has thou seen, and now my mental directions. </p>
            <p> I am a singer or writer of verses or perhaps,&#8212;but I do not yet appraise
                myself. I have written plays, comedy &amp; tragedy, allegory, satire and biting
                political pieces, a few of them printed! also a multitude of sonnets, with other pieces 
            serious &amp; pleasant, too numerous to be mentioned.</p>
            <p> I have written prose treatises on the constitution of the Universe and contributions in
                several comic papers. </p>
            <p> I am an orator and a demagogue (I prefer the name demagogue for myself), I have
                delivered speeches on behalf of freethought &amp; democracy. I have gone, a Saxon,
                among the embittered children of Erin,<ptr target="syr.00019_n3"/> and they will not
                report unfavourably of me. </p>
            <p> Nor am I less thine equal on account of my years. I hold that youth has its own high
                wisdom, that it is fully as wise as age. For youth can be easiest touched &amp;
                taught &amp; won &amp; converted. </p>
            <p> 4 </p>
            <p> On externals. </p>
            <p> Here I have recently come as a clerk in a government office. But meanwhile I
                secretly prepare myself for the task of aiding this people to reject the yoke of my
                own (I do not mean by bloodshed.) This though wilt surely deem a not unworthy
                object. Yet for its better advancement I have to play the part of a genteel
                citizen,&#8212;part repugnant! Such am I known, a respectable, good young man, with
                perhaps a taste for rhyme, a radical too, and tainted, alas! with some slight touch
                of freethought! </p>
            <p> Yet to no two persons am I known quite the same, and there is not one who has seen
                one tenth part of what I am showing thee. (For I have not succeeded in publishing
                aught yet, though even now I am trying.) </p>
            <p> Here too my fate of unfortunate love has followed me still, for thou art an ocean
                away. Now if thou wilt summon me, I will take courage and leave all I have, although
                without a penny I reach thy side (for I am not rich). But without thy word I dare
                not <choice>
                    <sic>forestal</sic>
                    <corr>forestall</corr>
                </choice> the course of events. Nor dare I summon thee here, for it is my place to
                go to thee. And if it were possible, I know <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00060_large.jpg" type="verso"/> thou wouldst come. </p>
            <p> Yet it shall come to pass somehow, soon or late. I must behold thee. And not so much
                to listen or talk, as to grasp thine own warm strong right hand, and take a long
                look down thine eyes! </p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <p> This is the Calamus leaf which the Englishman Allen Upward (Upward, ought I not to
                be proud of the name?) plucked from the soil of his inmost bosom to send to Walt
                Whitman the American, poet, brother and lover. </p>
            <closer>
                <dateline>
                    <address><addrLine>From 11 Great Charles Street, Dublin, Ireland.</addrLine></address>
                    <date when="1884-03-12">Written on the 12th March, 1884.</date>
                </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>WALT<ptr target="syr.00019_n4"/> See, I kiss this, am I too bold?</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
