<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00018">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 7 August
                    1884</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ef">Ed Folsom</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00018</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas W. H. Rolleston</author>
                    <title>Thomas W. H. Rolleston to Walt Whitman, 7 August 1884</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1884-08-07" xml:id="dat1">August 7, 1884</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rolleston, Thomas W. H." ref="n1027">Thomas W. H. Rolleston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-07" who="#ef">blessed</change>
            <change when="2015-03-27" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-02-14" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-12-19" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00053_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top">see notes Feb 8 1889</note>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1884-08-07">August 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                        <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="infralinear">'84</note></date>
                    <name type="place">28 Terrassen Ufer. Dresden</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Walt&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I write to tell you how things are going now about the translation, &amp;c. It is nearly through its last stage. Our way of working
                is this. First I translated all I am going to give as well as I could out of my own
                unassisted resources and handed over the <choice><abbr>M.S.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> to my colleague. He then read it
                over carefully with the English text &amp; made such notes &amp; corrections as occurred
                to him. Then he handed the notes &amp; <choice><abbr>M.S.</abbr><expan>manuscript</expan></choice> back to me. All this is now done, &amp; at
                present I spend the evening in reading a portion of the <choice><abbr>transl.</abbr><expan>translation</expan></choice> with his notes,
                &amp; considering all carefully&#8212;next morning I visit my colleague &amp; we go over what
                I prepared the previous night, weighing every sentence; and give final shape to
                the translation. In the afternoon I write out for the printer what we have done in
                the morning. I have now ready for print the Song of Myself, Starting from Paumanok,
                I Sing the Body Electric, Song of the Open Road, Brooklyn Ferry, and a
                dozen or so of the shorter poems. We were at work this morning on 'Salut au Monde.'</p>
                <p>As to publishing, I am trying to get a Dresden <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00054_large.jpg" type="verso"/> man, Heinrich Minden, to take it
                upon commission. He is now away in <choice><orig>Moskow</orig><reg>Moscow</reg></choice>, on business, but returns in a few days. I
                have written to broach the matter. Curious fact illustrative of rule in Russia&#8212;I
                wanted to send Minden my <choice><abbr>transl.</abbr><expan>translation</expan></choice> of 'Starting from Paumanok,' with my preface to
                the work and Freiligrath's<ptr target="n0248"/> article from the Allg. Zeitung. But
                they told me at his office that if I ever wished to see these things again I had
                better not despatch them&#8212;as this highly revolutionary or explosive literature
                would assuredly be confiscated on the frontier by the Russian police! So I left them
                in the office, where I suppose they will label them 'dangerous,' and put them on an
                upper shelf till Minden comes back. </p>
            <p> The German colleague I alluded to is not a partner in the strict sense &amp; takes
                no part in the publication of the work, nor has legal responsibility for it. His
                name is Gustav Adolf Israel<ptr target="syr.00018_n1"/>&#8212;he is master for
                German literature in a school here&#8212;I have known him for long, &amp; knowing his
                capacities engaged him for a fixed sum of money to revise my <choice><abbr>M.S.S.</abbr><expan>manuscripts</expan></choice>. You must not let
                his name be known&#8212;it would have serious consequences for him if he were known to
                have taken any part in the production <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="syr_kc.00055_large.jpg" type="recto"/> of the <choice><abbr>L. of G</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice>. No one supposes
                that the book will be much of a success, financially speaking. A bookseller told me
                the other day that no one reads poetry now in Germany, or buys it, except to give
                pretty books as presents to young ladies on their confirmation. But then as a
                leading critical organ here, anent my lecture, asserted that the <choice><abbr>L. of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice> are not
                poetry, perhaps there is a chance for them! I have not gone into detailed criticism
                in my preface&#8212;said that if anyone didn't see his way to calling the book 'poetry,'
                he might call it by any other earthly name he liked, if he would only begin to
                listen to it. Gave a sketch of your life, in which I have corrected some mistakes I
                made in my lecture, &amp; gave your letter, i.e. the portion you wrote for this
                purpose. I mean to give the English text, but not on alternate
                pages&#8212;underneath, in smaller type, on the bottom &#8531;rd of the page, so as to
                give the idea that it is there for reference, making the German rendering the main
                thing, as it should be for German readers. But this is a good deal dependent on the
                publisher &amp; his opinion. We are thinking of leaving Germany about the middle of
                September. My address then will be Glasshouse, Shinrone, Ireland. This <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="syr_kc.00056_large.jpg" type="verso"/> indeed is always
                sure to find me. </p>
            <p>I shall be glad to get among my own people again, &amp; to have a bit of a holiday
                too, for I have been working pretty hard all this summer. I hope you are well and
                prospering. </p>
            <p> As soon as there is further definite news about the <choice><abbr>L. of G.</abbr><expan>Leaves of Grass</expan></choice> translation I'll let
                you know&#8212;meantime goodbye. </p>
            <closer>
                <signed>T. W. Rolleston.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
