<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00023">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 23 March
                    1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00023</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 23 March 1886</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1886-03-23" xml:id="dat1">March 23, 1886</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-23" who="#nhg">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-07-16" who="#ss">added _n6</change>
            <change when="2015-07-12" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-07-01" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-16" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-11-21" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-24" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>    

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes March 24 1889</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00078.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>
                    <name type="place">Life Saving Service</name>
                    <date when="1886-03-23">March 23, 1886.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p> It is a perfect shame I have not written you for so long, but I have been <choice><sic>wofully</sic><corr>woefully></corr></choice>
                lame and ill, and with a mind so weak and wandering that most of the time I have
                been actually unable to write.<ptr target="syr.00023_n1"/> I now begin to feel a
                little better as the spring advances, though still greatly crippled. </p>
            <p> I got your letter of last January (22d) and your card of Feb. 3rd from Elkton,<ptr
                    target="syr.00023_n2"/> telling <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr_kc.00079.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> of your lecturing, at which proof of your activity I greatly
                rejoiced. I saw in the <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> today that you are to give
                your Lincoln lecture in Philadelphia.<ptr target="loc.01337_n2"/>
            </p>   
            <p> I wonder if Dr. Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> got off. I had a letter from him some
                time ago telling me he expected to go, but have not since heard from him. </p>
            <p> C.W.E.<ptr target="syr.00023_n8"/> and I were intensely amused at your "amiable clerk with a pen behind his
                ear," as applied to Stedman's book.<ptr target="syr.00023_n3"/> The hit is palpable,
                like Hamlet's lunge. </p>
            <p> I am glad I sent you Nencioni's article.<ptr target="syr.00023_n4"/> We are after
                it, hot foot, for I judge that <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_kc.00080.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> it must be fine. I made an effort to get it here, but could not
                find, however, where in Italy the <hi rend="underline">Nuova Antologia</hi> is
                published, though probably it is Florence or Milan. Kennedy<ptr target="n3039"/>
                promises to help find the <hi rend="underline">locale</hi>. </p>
            <p> It pleases me greatly to hear that your eyes are all right, or nearly so. Do take
                care of them, and beware of draughts&#8212;so grateful, but so pernicious. Dr.
                Bigelow, our greatest physician in Boston of old time,<ptr target="syr.00023_n5"/>
                used to say that the back of the neck was more vulnerable than the heel of Achilles,
                when exposed to a draught, and he always put up his coat collar when he got into an
                omnibus or horse-car. </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="syr_kc.00081.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p> I heard yesterday that John Burroughs<ptr target="n0129"/> is coming down here. I
                shall be glad to see him, though I owe him a grudge for his late proposition to
                murder all the sparrows. This gives points to Herod, and is worse than the slaughter
                of the innocents, because they were Jew babies and had objectionable little hook
                noses. </p>
            <p> The winter has been infernal here since January, and March is not much better. I
                hope the Spring, just beginning to open, may put new life into you. </p>
            <p> Glad to hear of the English "offering," which I wish was much more.<ptr
                    target="loc.02186_n1"/> I wish we could get up a boom on your books. That McKay
                is a poor publisher. </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="syr_kc.00082.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p> Wonders will never cease, and after all <hi rend="underline">Houghton</hi> consented
                to publish my little work "Hamlet's Note-Book," a copy of which I hope to send you
                in a few days.<ptr target="syr.00023_n6"/> Everyone else refused it. The prejudice
                against the Baconians is amazing. The last publisher to whom I offered it (Coombes,
                of New York) although I proposed to pay the cost of manufacture, wrote in reply that
                he would undertake it, push it with energy, and do everything for it in his power,
                if I would only consent that his imprint should not appear on the title page!!! I
                never answered his letter. </p>
            <p> Write when you feel like <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="syr_kc.00083.jpg" type="verso"
                /> it, and let me know if anything happens.<ptr target="syr.00023_n7"/></p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Always faithfully</salute>
                <signed>W.D. O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
