<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00145">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Helen S. Cunningham to Walt Whitman, 9 May 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Helen S. Cunningham</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
               <persName xml:id="lh">Luke Hollis</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>tex.00145</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">131&#8211;132</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Helen S. Cunningham</author>
               <title>Helen S. Cunningham to Walt Whitman, 9 May 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-05-09">May 9, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="tex">Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Cunningham, Helen S.">Helen S. Cunningham</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#jw" when="2009-09-10">Transcription revision</change>
         <change who="#lh" when="2009-09-04">updated annotations to new style guidelines</change>
         <change who="#ss" when="2009-09-02">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-07">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Mr. Walt Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I<ptr target="tex.00145_n100"/> will address you a short time through the medium of the pen  I am thankfull I have the privelige of doing so that I may tell you in part how gratefull we are to you for your kindness to one so dear to us as Oscar is  I feel as if you was his true friend<ptr target="tex.00145_n2"/>. I am glad you feel an interest in him while he is sick and among strangers.  I recd your letter of the 5 inst [This letter is currently lost], the evening of the 7. We had been apprised of Oscars loss by a lady by the name of Hatch which I think was very kind of her  oh with what a throbing heart did I open your letter  I was fearfull it contained worse news. the loss of a limb is bad enough but how much worse we would have felt had not his life been spared but poor fellow he must have sufered almost everything but death in the last year. he never has told us realy how bad he was yet we knew he was suffering verry much all the time or he would have got along faster than he did and I have long thought it would be necessary to amputate his limb before he would get well.</p>
            <p>We are all rejoiced to hear you speak in such favorable terms of his recovery yet we feel he is not out of danger  I believe God will answer our prayers and restore him to health and friends and more is our daily prayer, may the good God be with him and strengthen him in this his affliction&#8212;</p>
            <p>if you and Oscar both think I had better not come I suppose I will have to stay at home. I felt as though it was my duty to go to him for he is one of the dearest brothers ever was given to a sister. Father &amp; Mother send many thanks &amp; kind wishes to you  they can never forget you for your kindness to Oscar and if ever in any way they could repay your they will do it. we will ever feel gratefull to you for what you have been to him&#8212;tell Oscar we are all well &amp; simpathise with him in all his trouble &amp; that I will write tomorrow or next day. I wrote him last friday. we will espect to hear from him this week again and you will tell us just how he is getting along  do not conceal his suffering from us any more  I do hope he may gain strength very fast and think he will if the disease had not worked up in his body. Please write to us as often as convenient and you will greatly oblige</p>
            <closer rend="right"/>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
