<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00125">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">John J. Barker to Walt Whitman, 19 June 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>John J. Barker</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>tex.00125</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">109-110</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>John J. Barker</author>
               <title>John J. Barker to Walt Whitman, 19 June 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-06-19">June 19, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="tex">Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Barker, John J.">John J. Barker</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-08-20">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2008-07-30">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-11">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <salute>Dear friend</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>i<ptr target="tex.00125_n100"/> resevd your leter this morning an was very glad to here from you  i am driven a team for the regment i have every faver i ask. i go whare i pleas and when i pleas Capten sais he will do all in his power to get mee in as a recruten officer if i get that i will be just whare i want to bee  Carter is the Col he is all the man that hoald the same command that they first held thar has bin a change in all the officers in the regment  lutennent Col melten<ptr target="tex.00125_n2"/> is in command of the regment  Col Carter<ptr target="tex.00125_n3"/> is often brgider genral  genral Carter is ctin mager general wee think they will be promoted Capten Skaggs<ptr target="tex.00125_n4"/> did may the 19 at stan-foard by A Psenter that was ordley sargent of Co E is now Captan he is Jest like a privet and as study as a Jug JC sebrig<ptr target="tex.00125_n5"/> is fist lutenent B B Jones<ptr target="tex.00125_n6"/> is a lutenent brother william<ptr target="tex.00125_n7"/> is ordly</p>
            <p>1 hve got sound an well an as stout as ever i have bin at home twice since i roat to you i cudent stay long for the rebels pickets was in site just acrous the river an our pickets on this side i wish you could be with mee i have moar fun than a litel i am singel all a long the road from mill springs to stanfoard whare i make a trip ever 7 or 8 days   i go in two miles of hoam when i go to millsprings our boys are all in good sirrets and egger to fight since rot to you wee went acrous the river an had skermis of about 4 ours an driv the bac seven miles wee returned in good order our los was 6 kild an 30 wound Capten Carrens morrtly   I but is geten beter lutenen will Coff wounded 5 companys of our regmet is at millsprings an 5 here they will return today they 70 prisners yesterd give my big respc to all inquiren friends tell mis isral an mis low howdy for me ma god bles you good by</p>
            <closer rend="right"/>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
