<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00143">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Alonzo S. Bush to Walt Whitman, 7 March 1864</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Alonzo S. Bush</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="jw">Joshua Ware</persName>
               <persName xml:id="br">Bev Rilett</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>tex.00143</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="db">Drum Beats:  Walt Whitman's Civil War Boy Lovers</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1989</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">129-130</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Alonzo S. Bush</author>
               <title>Alonzo S. Bush to Walt Whitman, 7 March 1864</title>
               <date when="1864-03-07">March 7, 1864</date>
               <orgName xml:id="tex">Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Bush, Alonzo S.">Alonzo S. Bush</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2010-04-15">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#jw" when="2009-09-10">Transcription revision</change>
         <change who="#br" when="2009-09-02">proofed and edited</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-07">annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-14">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener> 
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Friend Walter</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Your kind favor of 22nd [This letter is currently lost] came to hand all O.K. and I<ptr target="tex.00143_n100"/> was glad to here from you and the Hospital Boys and learn that you ware getting along fine. I should like to have been out to the front withe you and seen the old army of Potomac once more for cince we left them we have had no fight or skirmish in that line every thing is dul down here. You say you have had some hard weather of late. We experienced some of it I dare say&#8212;</p>
            <p>I am glad to know that the boys had such good quarters this winter and hope that they may be able to whip the rebs in the coming contest. I was much pleased to here that Lewis Brown had recovered so much as to go out on pass. tell him to go slow and all will be well in the out come. And tell him that I still look for his &amp; Benedict's photographs. Bartlett's I have.<ptr target="tex.00143_n2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Friend Walt there is nothing of importance or interest going on here and camp. Life is pretty lazy at this time we are rejocing at the timely arrival of sweet spring once more Winter has come &amp; gone, and solders begin to feell happy. the weather is tolarable fine at this presant time and the trees begin to bud and the Bird to sing. it will be a beautiful place down here in a few weeks.</p>
            <p>There is a large dance house and pleasure garden a bout 1/ 4 from here they are fixing it up for the summer. So you must com down when it gets in full blast a boat will play between here &amp; Washington so it will be handy and I shall expect many of the Boys to come. John Strain is in pretty good Health but his leg has never been of much service to him cince he is expecting his discharge at this time he will get it<ptr target="tex.00143_n3"/>. I would like to have some of the contents of the black Balt at this time </p>
            <p>I gave that note to Larr and he was muched pleased to here from you, and will reply to it in person. They both wish to be remembered to you and the boys of Hospital. Please to remember me to Miss Lowell<ptr target="tex.00143_n4"/> Brown<ptr target="tex.00143_n5"/>, Benedict, Bartlett, &amp; Chas Cate<ptr target="tex.00143_n6"/>&#8212;also to all others of my acquain[tance]&#8212;and dont forget to reserve a due portion for you self  I will now close Hoping to Here from you soon, good By</p>
            
            <closer rend="right"/>
         
         <postscript>
            <p>To Walt, I wish to know if you can get aa Photograph taken from the Negitive of mine if so inform me, also of Price as I wish to send for a doz more  if it can be done I will send you the money for to have them taken&#8212;as soon as we are paid I will send you</p>
         </postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
