<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="upa.00216">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 17 June 1881</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="no">Natalie O'Neal</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>upa.00216</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>           
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 17 June 1881</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1881-06-17" xml:id="dat1">June 17, 1881</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="upa">Walt Whitman Collection, 1842&#8211;1957, Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-11-22" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-07" who="#ak">corrected transcription and encoding</change>
            <change when="2014-10-28" who="#no">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="upa_nhg.00005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <date when="1881-06-17">June 17/81</date>
                    <name type="place">4 Manor Place. Edinburgh <lb/>Scotland</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dearest friend,</salute>
             </opener>

            <p>"Bumble-bees &#38; Bird Music" safe to hand this morning&#8212;does me good&#8212;makes me feel exactly as if I were with you in the flesh enjoying it       all&#8212;dear America! I never saw here&#8212;thousands&#8212;swarms of bumblebees&#8212;on the contrary they seem always in ones &#38; two&#8212;&#38; half a dozen at a time would be quite surprising. Your robin is not the <choice><orig>sam</orig><reg>same</reg></choice> as ours either &#38; is really they tell me a kind of 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="upa_nhg.00006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                thrush. Ours is the plumpest little roly poly of a bird&#8212;fat saucy, fierce &#38; bold&#8212;his breast a much brighter red too. I am wondering whether this was written from Glenfield&#8212;whether you have found a "creek" there, or are back at "Timber Creek". I had a pain too in reading it&#8212;suddenly remembered your birthday&#8212;that it was past &#38; I had not written one word&#8212;not just put my hand in yours as I would fain always do on that day. I am so very sorry. I was then (when I should have written&#8212;middle of May 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="upa_nhg.00007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                just preparing &#38; starting on my journey to the north&#8212;first to Redear on the Yorkshire coast to stay with Percy &#38; his wife &#38; the dear little son in a cottage within a yard or two of the beach&#8212;the North Sea rolling up on broad smooth sands there, but with treacherous reefs just beyond on which there were <gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="chars"/> wrecks last winter. I enjoyed everything&#8212;the being with Norah (who is like one of my own) &#38; the dearest jolliest little man digging &#38; playing happily in the sands&#8212;&#38; the wonderful colours &#38; sweet odors of the sea&#8212;everything is <unclear resp="#no" cert="medium" reason="illegible">best</unclear> 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="upa_nhg.00008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                except the keenness of the wind which made my breathing worse&#8212;&#38; the absence of dear Per himself who was all the time busy over his fierce furnaces &amp;c in Sheffield. And now I am with Beatrice &#38; needn't tell you what a pleasure that is. She looks rather pale, but seems otherwise strong &#38; hearty, &#38; to have her heart in her work as much as ever&#8212;gaining more confidence in herself, too, which was what she most needed. Much liked by her patients&#8212;you know what a grand old place Edinburgh is amid its rugged hills &#38; the beautiful broad firth 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="upa_nhg.00010_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                of which one gets fine glimpses at the end of many of the streets. And then the wonderful grey old houses almost as high &#38; massive as the hills (but I fear, too, full of most ancient dirt, &#38; crammed with a poor, dirty, ragged looking population)&#8212;And the castle on its wooded height in the very midst&#8212;&#38; the great cavern below that runs through the city &#38; has many bridges over it. Drink is the giant evil of the city as of the north generally&#8212;Such a sensible rugged healthy looking people too! how can they give themselves up to the mean &#38; ugly demon. It must be that the scanty amount of sunshine gives a great craving for
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="upa_nhg.00009_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                the bottled fire. They seem even fonder even than we English of their dogs&#8212;take them into Church in country places &#38; here into the cars where there are generally two or three faithful shaggy fellows uneasily wriggling in &#38; out to avoid getting their poor little toes trodden on.&#8212;How about England dearest friend? Do your thoughts turn that way? I have an old friend coming for a week or two at the beginning of August&#8212;after that a sunny bed-room ready &#38; waiting for you&#8212;as long as ever you will stay with us. Love to your brother &#38; sister &#38; to Mrs. Marvin &#38; John Burroughs &#38; to Hattie &#38; Jessie &#38; most of all to yourself. If Per were here he would return your friendly message. Bees best love. I send a line of Herbs that you may see how well they are getting on without me.</p>
            

            <closer>
                <signed>A. G.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript><p>I am to remain here till the end of July. Mrs. Rossetti has twins. 5 children now.</p></postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
