<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="wcu.00001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman to Mary Elizabeth Whitman, 19 March 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Ted Genoways</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2009</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>wcu.00001</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman to Mary Elizabeth Whitman, 19 March 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-03-19">March 19, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="wcu">Hunter Library at Western Carolina University</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Mary Elizabeth">Mary Elizabeth Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2009-08-20">copied plain from Walt WhitmanQR; encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Near Newbern N.C.</name>
                  <date when="1862-03-19">March 19th 1862</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Hearing that a mail leaves here today I have only time to write a few lines to let
you know that I am well and hearty. Tell Han we have given the rebels another licking
and won a splendid victory. I went through the fight and did not get a scratch although
the balls rained around me for over two hours, and several of our boys were struck
down close to my side. We left Roanoke Island March 11th and landed about sixteen
miles below Newbern (which is, or was a city of some 6,000 inhabitants) on the 13th
and took up the line of march. After marching 8 or 10 miles through the woods, a halt
was ordered as it was getting dark and we passed rather an uncomfortable night as it
rained pretty hard and our blankets soon got soaked through. We got up at daylight
on the morning of the 14th, marched 4 or 5 miles, when we came upon the enemy in
strong forces behind breastworks as usual. We marched up under a terrible fire, formed
line of battle, and at it we went. The enemy were posted in an almost impregnable
position, but after 3 hours hard fighting (during which time our boys had crept nearer
and nearer to the enemy's works) the rebels ran and the day was ours. Our regiment
suffered pretty bad, we had only about 651 men when we went into the fight, and lost
about 100 in killed and wounded, among whom was some of my intimate friends. One
young fellow (named Bob Smith, Orderly Sergeant Co. 13) was shot through the heart,
he lived in Portland Ave. near Mother. Among the badly wounded is our Lieutenant
Colonel R. B. Potter, shot through the side. I asked him at the time if he was hurt, he
said nothing to speak of (and did not give up for an hour after that). After the fight I
found our Major LeGendre lying in the mud, a ball had struck him in the back of the
neck and passed out through his cheek. I took off the blanket that I had strapped to
my back, laid him on it, got some help and carried him about a quarter of a mile to a
tent where he now lies in a very critical condition. We had one captain, one lieutenant,
3 orderly sergeants, our Chaplain, and 16 or 18 privates killed. Lieutenant Carrington
had a leg taken off. He was by my side when he was struck and was an intimate friend
of mine. Two other lieutenants were shot through the leg. I don't know what our total
loss is but should think about 450 killed and wounded.<ptr target="wcu.00001_n1"/> I think the enemy lost about
the same number. The battle was on each side of a railroad leading into the city and
we knew they carried off a good many of their killed and wounded in cars. Immediately
after the fight a front of our force started in pursuit, but the rebels had set fire
to a bridge which crosses a river about .9 of a mile wide. Our troops finally crossed in
a boat and found the city nearly deserted and fired in 3 or 4 places. The fires did not
do much damage however and most of our troops are now quartered there. Our regiment
marched slowly up to the river and as our boys were about lived out we spread
our blankets on the ground and passed the night there. We are now encamped on the
banks of the river about 2 miles from the city and we have things very comfortable.
We will probably stay here for some time. The enemy had tremendous advantages
over us and as they had more men engaged than we had, they ought to have cut us
to pieces as they have spent months and months fortifying and getting ready for us.
After we were landed from the ships, our gunboats went up and drove the rebels out
of 4 or 5 splendid short batteries so that our victory is complete. We have taken quite
a number of canon, and to day a part of our force leaves here to take another small
city lying on the coast. The last letter I received from home was dated February 19th
and I have had none from you since I left Annapolis. I wrote you soon after our fight
at Roanoke. Did you get the letter? Write immediately please.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. W. Whitman <lb/>Direct 2nd Brigade Burnside Expedition Newbern N.C.</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
