<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="yal.00089">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Alonzo S. Bush to Walt Whitman, 22 December 1863</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Alonzo S. Bush</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="tj">Tim Jackson</persName>
               <persName xml:id="vs">Vanessa Steinroetter</persName>
               <persName xml:id="nk">Nick Krauter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>yal.00089</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor>Charley Shively</editor>
                  <title xml:id="cl">Calamus Lovers: Walt Whitman's Working-Class Camerados</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gay Sunshine Press</publisher>
                     <date>1987</date>
                     <biblScope type="page">81-82</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>
               <author>Alonzo S. Bush</author>
               <title>Alonzo S. Bush to Walt Whitman, 22 December 1863</title>
               <date when="1863-12-22">December 22, 1863</date>
               <orgName xml:id="yal">Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Bush, Alonzo S.">Alonzo S. Bush</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2010-04-09">proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#tj" when="2009-09-03">proofread and modified</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-27">proofread and edited annotations</change>
         <change who="#vs" when="2009-08-06">added annotations</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#nk" when="2007-06-14">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right"/>
               <salute>Friend Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
         <p>Sir I<ptr target="yal.00089_n100"/> am happy to announce the arrival of Your Kind and verry wellcom Epistel and I can assure you that the contents ware persued with all the pleasure immaginable. I am glad to Know that you are once more in the hotbed City of Washington So that you can go often and See that Friend of ours at Armory Square, L[ewis] K. B[rown].<ptr target="yal.00089_n2"/> The fellow that went down on your BK, both So often with me. I wished that I could See him this evening and go in the Ward Master's Room and have Some fun for he is a gay boy. I am very Sorry indeed to here that after laying So long that he is about to loose his leg, it is to bad, but I Suppose that the Lords will must be done and We must submit. Walter I Suppose that you had a nice time while at Home. I am glad to report that I enjoyed my Self finely and had a gay time. Generaly I am now paying up for the good times I had at Armory Square &amp; at Home. Just immagin that you see me at the dead Hour of night Standing picket on the Potomac looking to see how things are going on and pick up Deserters  it is amusing to See how Sly they are in getting over  they come on rafts logs &amp; any thing that will bear there weight with oars muffled and as still as possible. And you may guess that they are Some what suppriz[ed] on landing to find an escort of the first Ind Cav waiting to See them Safe to Washington. We have caught over a hundred in the last 2 months. They all Seam to be flush with money and that goes to Show they are Sub[stitutes.] They come for money &amp; not country. We have verry good Quarters and plenty of Grub. Our Shantys are of Logs and are very comfort[able.] Our Horses can not be beat for they are fat and in Splend[id] Condition our Stables are made of pine boughs and covered With Straw which turns rain and snow very well considering</p>
            <p>When off duty the boys enjoy them selves by Horse racing &amp; Hunting Game is very plenty down Here ducks Quail Squirl &amp; fox are the chief ones Coons &amp; opoposms are als[o] humerous. We have a good pack of Hounds now and are training our Horses for a grand fox Hunt on the  25th of this month  I wish you and Some of the boys ware here to take a hand, as there will be fun, that you may depend on. I have been waiting for a comission Ever cince I came Here but as yet I have not Seen it. I expected to be in Washington before this on my way Home to get my rights, if I dont get it I will not come to Washington till the latter part of Jan or the first of Feb&#8212;and when I do come I will be sure to give you a call. I want you to give my best wishes to the Lady Nurse of Ward K also to W[ard] M[aster] Cate, Brown, Billy Clements, Miss Felton<ptr target="yal.00089_n3"/> &amp; all the rest...</p>
            <p>Please to tell them each &amp; every one that I would like to write to them all but am So Situated that I can not but will call on them the first time I come up. Tell Miss Lowell that her kindness to the Solders undr her charge While I was there I never Shall forget and that I often think of the games we used to play Tell Miss Felton that I never will forget theWatter cooler of Ward P. and as there are some of my Friends that I have omited on account of names I hope you will as[k] Pardon in my behalf. tell Brown to remember me to Joseph of the Starr.</p>
            <p>Johny Strain my companion wishes to be remembred to all I am sorry to inform you that He met with another misfortune after he got Here he was thrown from his Horse and had his arm broken but is getting along very well at presant. My Love &amp; best Wishes to all I will close Hoping to Here from you soon.</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <salute>I remain your True Friend,</salute>
               <signed>Alonzo Bush</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
