<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="yal.00378">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Abby H. Price to Walt Whitman, [25 March 1867]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Abby Price</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2010</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>yal.00378</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted:
<persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Abby H. Price</author>
                    <title>Abby Price to Walt Whitman, [25 March 1867]</title>                    
                    <date cert="medium" when="1867-03-25" xml:id="dat1">March 25, 1867</date>
                    <idno type="callno">YCAL MSS 220</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="yal">Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book
                        and Manuscript Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Price, Abby H.">Abby H. Price</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-02" who="#al">Made Ken's corrections</change>
            <change when="2011-03-03" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-11-15" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="yal.00378.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <name type="place" rend="center">279 E. 55th st.</name>
                <salute>My dear Walt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your welcome letter was duly received for which accept many thanks.</p>
            
            <p>I write now in great haste to ask your assistance in behalf of Our Ruffle
                Manufacture and if you succeed in doing what we ask, or in getting it done I am
                authorised to offer you a 1000 dollar check as soon as it is done! think of <hi rend="underline">that</hi>. It is only a simple act of justice that we ask 
                either</p>
            <p>The committee have just <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#br">revised</unclear> the law concerning the "internal Revenue tax and "articles of
                clothing made by sewing from materials already having <choice><orig>payed</orig><reg>paid</reg></choice> tax are exempted we thought our goods came under that head and rejoiced
                greatly but the Assesor says <hi rend="underline">not</hi> so 
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="yal.00378.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            Our Manufacture bring <hi rend="underline">trimmings</hi> to clothing and not
                clothing. Now <choice>
                    <orig>altho</orig>
                    <reg>although</reg>
                </choice> we got the article patented and have tried in vain to defend the patent
                and put down infringers by law. The article is made in secret by unprincipled
                parties who do not pay any revenue tax at all, as they make no returns to the
                Internal Revenue Office, but are Jews working in a very underhanded way. Still we
                have to compete in the market with their manufacture. Our company always making
                fair returns each month and paying so large a proportion of the profit as tax, that
                in order to sell as low as those who evade the law, has left us very little scarcely
                enough to encourage 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="yal.00378.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                the manufacture at all. The tax on my part the last year was quite as much as I
                received—</p>
            
            <p>Well, what we want is to have them the ruffles <hi rend="underline">exempted</hi> by
                the <hi rend="underline">Committee</hi>
                before Congress adjourns either as parts of articles of clothing made by sewing or
                as a special article. They have exempted "step ladders" and several other things
                which I forget now.</p>
            
            <p>You might ask it as "<hi rend="underline">parts</hi> of articles of clothing such as
                shirt bosoms, <hi rend="double-underline">ruffles</hi>, &amp;c. made by <hi rend="underline">sewing</hi> and of materials already paying tax" (shirt bosoms are in the law mentioned as
                exempted, and I think they will easily put in <hi rend="underline">ruffles</hi> if
                you can hurry up and get at 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="yal.00378.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                them soon enough.</p>
            <p>You see Harland right away and tell him about it and find out who the Committee are. and I guess if
                you have time enough you can get it done and I shall have the fun of sending you the
                check! In haste to get it in to-night</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours ever</salute>
                <signed>A H Price</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript rend="margin-left">
                <p>The $1000 is to pay you for a <hi rend="underline">big</hi> effort and the trustees told me this
                    morning they would gladly pay it you</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>